<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible translation="English Standard Version" revision="2025-02-02" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
<book title="2 Peter" num="61">
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001001"/>
  <chapter num="1">
    <heading>Greeting</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Simeon<note nid="n61001001.1"/> Peter, a servant<note nid="n61001001.2"/> and apostle of Jesus Christ,
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-paragraph/>To those who have obtained <crossref let="a" cid="c61001001.1"/>a faith of equal standing with ours <crossref let="b" cid="c61001001.2"/>by the righteousness of our <crossref let="c" cid="c61001001.3"/>God and Savior Jesus Christ:
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001002"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="d" cid="c61001002.1"/>May grace and peace be multiplied to you <crossref let="e" cid="c61001002.2"/>in the knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001003"/>
    <heading>Confirm Your Calling and Election</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3">His divine power has granted to us all things that pertain to life and godliness, through the knowledge of him <crossref let="f" cid="c61001003.1"/>who called us to<note nid="n61001003.1"/> his own glory and excellence,<note nid="n61001003.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001004"/>
    <verse num="4">by which he has granted to us his precious and very great promises, so that through them you may become <crossref let="g" cid="c61001004.1"/>partakers of the divine nature, <crossref let="h" cid="c61001004.2"/>having escaped from the corruption that is in the world because of sinful desire.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001005"/>
    <verse num="5">For this very reason, make every effort to supplement your faith <crossref let="i" cid="c61001005.1"/>with virtue,<note nid="n61001005.1"/> and virtue <crossref let="j" cid="c61001005.2"/>with knowledge,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001006"/>
    <verse num="6">and knowledge with self-control, and self-control <crossref let="k" cid="c61001006.1"/>with steadfastness, and steadfastness with godliness,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001007"/>
    <verse num="7">and godliness <crossref let="l" cid="c61001007.1"/>with brotherly affection, and brotherly affection <crossref let="m" cid="c61001007.2"/>with love.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001008"/>
    <verse num="8">For if these qualities<note nid="n61001008.1"/> are yours and are increasing, they keep you from being ineffective or <crossref let="n" cid="c61001008.1"/>unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001009"/>
    <verse num="9">For whoever lacks these qualities is so nearsighted that he <crossref let="o" cid="c61001009.1"/>is blind, having forgotten that he was <crossref let="p" cid="c61001009.2"/>cleansed from his former sins.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001010"/>
    <verse num="10">Therefore, brothers,<note nid="n61001010.1"/> be all the more diligent to confirm your calling and <crossref let="q" cid="c61001010.1"/>election, for if you practice these qualities <crossref let="r" cid="c61001010.2"/>you will never fall.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001011"/>
    <verse num="11">For in this way there will be richly provided for you <crossref let="s" cid="c61001011.1"/>an entrance into the eternal kingdom of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">Therefore I intend <crossref let="t" cid="c61001012.1"/>always to remind you of these qualities, though you know them and are established in <crossref let="u" cid="c61001012.2"/>the truth that you have.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001013"/>
    <verse num="13">I think it right, as long as I am in this <crossref let="v" cid="c61001013.1"/>body,<note nid="n61001013.1"/> <crossref let="w" cid="c61001013.2"/>to stir you up by way of reminder,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001014"/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="x" cid="c61001014.1"/>since I know that the putting off of my body will be soon, <crossref let="y" cid="c61001014.2"/>as our Lord Jesus Christ made clear to me.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001015"/>
    <verse num="15">And I will make every effort so that after my departure you may be able at any time to recall these things.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001016"/>
    <heading>Christ&apos;s Glory and the Prophetic Word</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">For we did not follow <crossref let="z" cid="c61001016.1"/>cleverly devised <crossref let="a" cid="c61001016.2"/>myths when we made known to you <crossref let="b" cid="c61001016.3"/>the power and <crossref let="c" cid="c61001016.4"/>coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, but <crossref let="d" cid="c61001016.5"/>we were eyewitnesses of his majesty.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001017"/>
    <verse num="17">For when he received honor and glory from God the Father, and the voice was borne to him by the Majestic Glory, <crossref let="e" cid="c61001017.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="61001017.1" from="61001017.1" to="61001017.2"/>This is my beloved Son,<note nid="n61001017.1"/> with whom I am well pleased,<q class="end-double" qid="61001017.2" from="61001017.1" to="61001017.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001018"/>
    <verse num="18">we ourselves heard this very voice borne from heaven, for we were with him on <crossref let="f" cid="c61001018.1"/>the holy mountain.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001019"/>
    <verse num="19">And <crossref let="g" cid="c61001019.1"/>we have the prophetic word more fully confirmed, to which you will do well to pay attention <crossref let="h" cid="c61001019.2"/>as to a lamp shining in a dark place, until <crossref let="i" cid="c61001019.3"/>the day <crossref let="j" cid="c61001019.4"/>dawns and the morning star rises in your hearts,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001020"/>
    <verse num="20">knowing this first of all, that no prophecy of Scripture comes from someone&apos;s own interpretation.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61001021"/>
    <verse num="21">For <crossref let="k" cid="c61001021.1"/>no prophecy was ever produced by the will of man, but men spoke from God <crossref let="l" cid="c61001021.2"/>as they were carried along by the Holy Spirit.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002001"/>
  <chapter num="2">
    <heading>False Prophets and Teachers</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">But <crossref let="m" cid="c61002001.1"/>false prophets also arose among the people, <crossref let="n" cid="c61002001.2"/>just as there will be false teachers among you, who will <crossref let="o" cid="c61002001.3"/>secretly bring in destructive heresies, even denying the Master <crossref let="p" cid="c61002001.4"/>who bought them, bringing upon themselves swift destruction.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002002"/>
    <verse num="2">And many will follow their sensuality, and because of them the way of truth <crossref let="q" cid="c61002002.1"/>will be blasphemed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002003"/>
    <verse num="3">And <crossref let="r" cid="c61002003.1"/>in their greed they will exploit you <crossref let="s" cid="c61002003.2"/>with false words. <crossref let="t" cid="c61002003.3"/>Their condemnation from long ago is not idle, and their destruction is not asleep.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">For if God did not spare <crossref let="u" cid="c61002004.1"/>angels when they sinned, but <crossref let="v" cid="c61002004.2"/>cast them into hell<note nid="n61002004.1"/> and committed them to chains<note nid="n61002004.2"/> of gloomy darkness <crossref let="w" cid="c61002004.3"/>to be kept until the judgment;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002005"/>
    <verse num="5">if he did not spare the ancient world, but <crossref let="x" cid="c61002005.1"/>preserved Noah, a herald of righteousness, with seven others, when he brought <crossref let="y" cid="c61002005.2"/>a flood upon the world of the ungodly;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002006"/>
    <verse num="6">if by <crossref let="z" cid="c61002006.1"/>turning the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah to ashes he condemned them to extinction, <crossref let="a" cid="c61002006.2"/>making them an example of <crossref let="b" cid="c61002006.3"/>what is going to happen to the ungodly;<note nid="n61002006.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002007"/>
    <verse num="7">and <crossref let="c" cid="c61002007.1"/>if he rescued righteous Lot, greatly distressed by the sensual conduct of the wicked</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002008"/>
    <verse num="8">(for as that righteous man lived among them day after day, <crossref let="d" cid="c61002008.1"/>he was tormenting his righteous soul over their lawless deeds that he saw and heard);</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002009"/>
    <verse num="9">then <crossref let="e" cid="c61002009.1"/>the Lord knows how to rescue the godly from trials,<note nid="n61002009.1"/> and to keep the unrighteous under punishment until the day of judgment,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002010"/>
    <verse num="10">and especially <crossref let="f" cid="c61002010.1"/>those who indulge<note nid="n61002010.1"/> in the lust of defiling passion and <crossref let="g" cid="c61002010.2"/>despise authority.
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-paragraph/>Bold and willful, they do not tremble <crossref let="g" cid="c61002010.3"/>as they blaspheme the glorious ones,
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="h" cid="c61002011.1"/>whereas angels, though greater in might and power, do not pronounce a blasphemous judgment against them before the Lord.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="i" cid="c61002012.1"/>But these, like irrational animals, <crossref let="j" cid="c61002012.2"/>creatures of instinct, born to be caught and destroyed, blaspheming about matters of which they are ignorant, will also be destroyed in their destruction,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002013"/>
    <verse num="13">suffering wrong as <crossref let="k" cid="c61002013.1"/>the wage for their wrongdoing. They count it pleasure <crossref let="l" cid="c61002013.2"/>to revel in the daytime. They are blots and blemishes, reveling in their deceptions,<note nid="n61002013.1"/> while <crossref let="m" cid="c61002013.3"/>they feast with you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002014"/>
    <verse num="14">They have eyes full of adultery,<note nid="n61002014.1"/> <crossref let="n" cid="c61002014.1"/>insatiable for sin. They entice unsteady souls. They have hearts <crossref let="o" cid="c61002014.2"/>trained in greed. <crossref let="p" cid="c61002014.3"/>Accursed children!</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002015"/>
    <verse num="15">Forsaking the right way, <crossref let="q" cid="c61002015.1"/>they have gone astray. They have followed <crossref let="r" cid="c61002015.2"/>the way of Balaam, the son of Beor, who loved <crossref let="s" cid="c61002015.3"/>gain from wrongdoing,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002016"/>
    <verse num="16">but was rebuked for his own transgression; <crossref let="t" cid="c61002016.1"/>a speechless donkey spoke with human voice and restrained the prophet&apos;s madness.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002017"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="u" cid="c61002017.1"/>These are waterless springs and mists driven by a storm. <crossref let="v" cid="c61002017.2"/>For them the gloom of utter darkness has been reserved.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002018"/>
    <verse num="18">For, <crossref let="w" cid="c61002018.1"/>speaking loud boasts of folly, they entice by sensual passions of the flesh those who are barely <crossref let="x" cid="c61002018.2"/>escaping from those who live in error.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002019"/>
    <verse num="19">They promise them <crossref let="y" cid="c61002019.1"/>freedom, <crossref let="z" cid="c61002019.2"/>but they themselves are slaves<note nid="n61002019.1"/> of corruption. For whatever overcomes a person, to that he is enslaved.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002020"/>
    <verse num="20">For if, <crossref let="a" cid="c61002020.1"/>after they have escaped the defilements of the world <crossref let="b" cid="c61002020.2"/>through the knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ, they are again entangled in them and overcome, <crossref let="c" cid="c61002020.3"/>the last state has become worse for them than the first.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002021"/>
    <verse num="21">For <crossref let="d" cid="c61002021.1"/>it would have been better for them never to have known the way of righteousness than after knowing it to turn back from <crossref let="e" cid="c61002021.2"/>the holy commandment delivered to them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61002022"/>
    <verse num="22">What the true proverb says has happened to them: <q class="begin-double" qid="61002022.1" from="61002022.1" to="61002022.2"/>The <crossref let="f" cid="c61002022.1"/>dog returns to its own vomit, and the sow, after washing herself, returns to wallow in the mire.<q class="end-double" qid="61002022.2" from="61002022.1" to="61002022.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003001"/>
  <chapter num="3">
    <heading>The Day of the Lord Will Come</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">This is now the second letter that I am writing to you, beloved. In both of them <crossref let="g" cid="c61003001.1"/>I am stirring up your sincere mind by way of reminder,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="h" cid="c61003002.1"/>that you should remember the predictions of <crossref let="i" cid="c61003002.2"/>the holy prophets and the commandment of the Lord and Savior through your apostles,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003003"/>
    <verse num="3">knowing this first of all, that scoffers will come <crossref let="j" cid="c61003003.1"/>in the last days with scoffing, <crossref let="k" cid="c61003003.2"/>following their own sinful desires.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="l" cid="c61003004.1"/>They will say, <q class="begin-double" qid="61003004.1" from="61003004.1" to="61003004.2"/>Where is the promise of <crossref let="m" cid="c61003004.2"/>his coming? For ever since the fathers fell asleep, all things are continuing as they were from the beginning of creation.<q class="end-double" qid="61003004.2" from="61003004.1" to="61003004.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003005"/>
    <verse num="5">For they deliberately overlook this fact, that the heavens existed long ago, and the earth <crossref let="n" cid="c61003005.1"/>was formed out of water and through water <crossref let="o" cid="c61003005.2"/>by the word of God,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003006"/>
    <verse num="6">and that by means of these the world that then existed <crossref let="p" cid="c61003006.1"/>was deluged with water and <crossref let="q" cid="c61003006.2"/>perished.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003007"/>
    <verse num="7">But by the same word <crossref let="r" cid="c61003007.1"/>the heavens and earth that now exist are stored up for fire, being kept until the day of judgment and <crossref let="s" cid="c61003007.2"/>destruction of the ungodly.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">But do not overlook this one fact, beloved, that with the Lord one day is as a thousand years, and <crossref let="t" cid="c61003008.1"/>a thousand years as one day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="u" cid="c61003009.1"/>The Lord is not slow to fulfill his promise <crossref let="v" cid="c61003009.2"/>as some count slowness, but <crossref let="w" cid="c61003009.3"/>is patient toward you,<note nid="n61003009.1"/> <crossref let="x" cid="c61003009.4"/>not wishing that any should perish, but <crossref let="y" cid="c61003009.5"/>that all should reach repentance.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003010"/>
    <verse num="10">But <crossref let="z" cid="c61003010.1"/>the day of the Lord will come like a thief, and then <crossref let="a" cid="c61003010.2"/>the heavens will pass away with a roar, and <crossref let="b" cid="c61003010.3"/>the heavenly bodies<note nid="n61003010.1"/> will be burned up and dissolved, and the earth and the works that are done on it will be exposed.<note nid="n61003010.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11">Since all these things are thus to be dissolved, <crossref let="c" cid="c61003011.1"/>what sort of people ought you to be in lives of holiness and godliness,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="d" cid="c61003012.1"/>waiting for and hastening the coming of the day of God, because of which the heavens will be set on fire and dissolved, and <crossref let="e" cid="c61003012.2"/>the heavenly bodies will melt as they burn!</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003013"/>
    <verse num="13">But according to his promise we are waiting for <crossref let="f" cid="c61003013.1"/>new heavens and a new earth <crossref let="g" cid="c61003013.2"/>in which righteousness dwells.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003014"/>
    <heading>Final Words</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="h" cid="c61003014.1"/>Therefore, beloved, since you are waiting for these, be diligent to be found by him <crossref let="i" cid="c61003014.2"/>without spot or <crossref let="j" cid="c61003014.3"/>blemish, and <crossref let="k" cid="c61003014.4"/>at peace.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003015"/>
    <verse num="15">And count <crossref let="l" cid="c61003015.1"/>the patience of our Lord as salvation, just as <crossref let="m" cid="c61003015.2"/>our beloved brother Paul also wrote to you <crossref let="n" cid="c61003015.3"/>according to the wisdom given him,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003016"/>
    <verse num="16">as he does in all his letters when he speaks in them of these matters. <crossref let="o" cid="c61003016.1"/>There are some things in them that are hard to understand, which the ignorant and unstable twist to their own destruction, <crossref let="p" cid="c61003016.2"/>as they do the other Scriptures.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003017"/>
    <verse num="17">You therefore, beloved, <crossref let="q" cid="c61003017.1"/>knowing this beforehand, <crossref let="r" cid="c61003017.2"/>take care that you are not carried away with the error of lawless people and lose your own stability.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v61003018"/>
    <verse num="18">But <crossref let="s" cid="c61003018.1"/>grow in the grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. <crossref let="t" cid="c61003018.2"/>To him be the glory both now and to the day of <crossref let="u" cid="c61003018.3"/>eternity. Amen.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
</book>
</crossway-bible>
