<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible translation="English Standard Version" revision="2018-3-26" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
<book title="Esther" num="72">
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.a"/>
  <chapter num="0">
    <heading>Mordecai&apos;s Dream</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1a"><deutero><note nid="n72000001a.1"/> In the second year when Artaxerxes the Great was reigning, on the first day of Nisan, Mordecai son of Jair, son of Shimei, son of Kish, of the tribe of Benjamin, had a dream.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.b"/>
    <verse num="1b"><deutero>He was a Jew, dwelling in the city of Susa, a great man, serving in the court of the king.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.c"/>
    <verse num="1c"><deutero>He was one of the captives whom King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon had brought from Jerusalem with King Jeconiah of Judea. And this was his dream:</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.d"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1d"><deutero>Behold, noise and confusion, thunders and earthquake, tumult upon the earth!</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.e"/>
    <verse num="1e"><deutero>And behold, two great dragons came forward, both ready to fight, and they roared terribly.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.f"/>
    <verse num="1f"><deutero>And at their roaring every nation prepared for war, to fight against the nation of the righteous.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.g"/>
    <verse num="1g"><deutero>And behold, a day of darkness and gloom, tribulation and distress, affliction and great tumult upon the earth!</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.h"/>
    <verse num="1h"><deutero>And the whole righteous nation was troubled; they feared the evils that threatened themselves and were ready to perish.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.i"/>
    <verse num="1i"><deutero>Then they cried to God; and from their cry, as though from a tiny spring, there came a great river, with abundant water;</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.k"/>
    <verse num="1k"><deutero>light came, and the sun rose, and the lowly were exalted and consumed those held in honor.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.l"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1l"><deutero>Mordecai saw in this dream what God had determined to do, and after he awoke he had it on his mind and sought all day to understand it in every detail.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.m"/>
    <heading>Plot against the King</heading>
    <verse num="1m"><deutero><note nid="n72000001m.1"/> Now Mordecai took his rest in the courtyard with Gabatha and Tharra, the two eunuchs of the king who kept watch in the courtyard.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.n"/>
    <verse num="1n"><deutero>He overheard their conversation and inquired into their purposes and learned that they were preparing to lay hands upon King Artaxerxes; and he informed the king concerning them.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.o"/>
    <verse num="1o"><deutero>Then the king examined the two eunuchs, and when they confessed they were led to execution.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.p"/>
    <verse num="1p"><deutero>The king made a permanent record of these things, and Mordecai wrote an account of them.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.q"/>
    <verse num="1q"><deutero>And the king ordered Mordecai to serve in the court and rewarded him for these things.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72000001.r"/>
    <verse num="1r"><deutero>But Haman son of Hamadathos, a Bougean, was in great honor with the king, and he sought to injure Mordecai and his people because of the two eunuchs of the king.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001001"/>
  <chapter num="1">
    <heading>The King&apos;s Banquets</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Now in the days of Ahasuerus, the Ahasuerus who reigned <crossref let="a" cid="c72001001.1"/>from India to Ethiopia over <crossref let="b" cid="c72001001.2"/>127 provinces,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001002"/>
    <verse num="2">in those days when King Ahasuerus <crossref let="c" cid="c72001002.1"/>sat on his royal throne in <crossref let="d" cid="c72001002.2"/>Susa, the citadel,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001003"/>
    <verse num="3">in the third year of his reign <crossref let="e" cid="c72001003.1"/>he gave a feast for all his officials and servants. The army of Persia and Media and the nobles and governors of the provinces were before him,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001004"/>
    <verse num="4">while he showed the riches of his royal glory and the splendor and pomp of his greatness for many days, 180 days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001005"/>
    <verse num="5">And when these days were completed, the king gave for all the people present in Susa the citadel, both great and small, a feast lasting for seven days in the court of <crossref let="f" cid="c72001005.1"/>the garden of the king&apos;s palace.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001006"/>
    <verse num="6">There were white cotton curtains and violet hangings fastened with cords of fine linen and purple to silver rods<note nid="n72001006.1"/> and marble pillars, and also <crossref let="g" cid="c72001006.1"/>couches of gold and silver on a mosaic pavement of porphyry, marble, mother-of-pearl, and precious stones.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001007"/>
    <verse num="7">Drinks were served in golden vessels, vessels of different kinds, and the royal wine was lavished according to the bounty of the king.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001008"/>
    <verse num="8">And drinking was according to this edict: <q class="begin-double" qid="72001008.1" from="72001008.1" to="72001008.2"/>There is no compulsion.<q class="end-double" qid="72001008.2" from="72001008.1" to="72001008.2"/> For the king had given orders to all the staff of his palace to do as each man desired.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001009"/>
    <verse num="9">Queen Vashti also gave a feast for the women in the palace that belonged to King Ahasuerus.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001010"/>
    <heading>Queen Vashti&apos;s Refusal</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">On the seventh day, <crossref let="h" cid="c72001010.1"/>when the heart of the king was merry with wine, he commanded Mehuman, Biztha, <crossref let="i" cid="c72001010.2"/>Harbona, <crossref let="j" cid="c72001010.3"/>Bigtha and Abagtha, Zethar and Carkas, the seven eunuchs who served in the presence of King Ahasuerus,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001011"/>
    <verse num="11">to bring Queen Vashti before the king with <crossref let="k" cid="c72001011.1"/>her royal crown,<note nid="n72001011.1"/> in order to show the peoples and the princes her beauty, for she was lovely to look at.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001012"/>
    <verse num="12">But Queen Vashti refused to come at the king&apos;s command delivered by the eunuchs. At this the king became enraged, and his anger burned within him.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">Then the king said to <crossref let="l" cid="c72001013.1"/>the wise men <crossref let="m" cid="c72001013.2"/>who knew the times (for this was the king&apos;s procedure toward all who were versed in law and judgment,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001014"/>
    <verse num="14">the men next to him being Carshena, Shethar, Admatha, Tarshish, Meres, Marsena, and <crossref let="n" cid="c72001014.1"/>Memucan, <crossref let="o" cid="c72001014.2"/>the seven princes of Persia and Media, <crossref let="p" cid="c72001014.3"/>who saw the king&apos;s face, and sat first in the kingdom):</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001015"/>
    <verse num="15"><q class="begin-double" qid="72001015.1" from="72001015.1" to="72001015.2"/>According to the law, what is to be done to Queen Vashti, because she has not performed the command of King Ahasuerus delivered by the eunuchs?<q class="end-double" qid="72001015.2" from="72001015.1" to="72001015.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001016"/>
    <verse num="16">Then Memucan said in the presence of the king and the officials, <q class="begin-double" qid="72001016.1" from="72001016.1" to="72001020.1"/>Not only against the king has Queen Vashti done wrong, but also against all the officials and all the peoples who are in all the provinces of King Ahasuerus.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001017"/>
    <verse num="17">For the queen&apos;s behavior will be made known to all women, causing them to look at their husbands with contempt,<note nid="n72001017.1"/> since they will say, <q class="begin-single" qid="72001017.1" from="72001017.1" to="72001017.2"/>King Ahasuerus commanded Queen Vashti to be brought before him, and she did not come.<q class="end-single" qid="72001017.2" from="72001017.1" to="72001017.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001018"/>
    <verse num="18">This very day the noble women of Persia and Media who have heard of the queen&apos;s behavior will say the same to all the king&apos;s officials, and there will be contempt and wrath in plenty.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001019"/>
    <verse num="19">If it please the king, let a royal order go out from him, and let it be written among the laws of the Persians and the Medes so <crossref let="q" cid="c72001019.1"/>that it may not be repealed, that Vashti is never again to come before King Ahasuerus. And let the king give her royal position to another who is better than she.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001020"/>
    <verse num="20">So when the decree made by the king is proclaimed throughout all his kingdom, for it is vast, <crossref let="r" cid="c72001020.1"/>all women will give honor to their husbands, high and low alike.<q class="end-double" qid="72001020.1" from="72001016.1" to="72001020.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001021"/>
    <verse num="21">This advice pleased the king and the princes, and the king did as Memucan proposed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72001022"/>
    <verse num="22">He sent letters to all the royal provinces, <crossref let="s" cid="c72001022.1"/>to every province in its own script and to every people in its own language, that every man be master in his own household and speak according to the language of his people.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002001"/>
  <chapter num="2">
    <heading>Esther Chosen Queen</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">After these things, <crossref let="t" cid="c72002001.1"/>when the anger of King Ahasuerus had abated, he remembered Vashti <crossref let="u" cid="c72002001.2"/>and what she had done and what had been decreed against her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002002"/>
    <verse num="2">Then the king&apos;s young men who attended him said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72002002.1" from="72002002.1" to="72002004.1"/>Let beautiful young virgins be sought out for the king.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002003"/>
    <verse num="3">And let the king appoint officers in all the provinces of his kingdom to gather all the beautiful young virgins to the harem in Susa the citadel, under custody of <crossref let="v" cid="c72002003.1"/>Hegai, the king&apos;s eunuch, who is in charge of the women. <crossref let="w" cid="c72002003.2"/>Let their cosmetics be given them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002004"/>
    <verse num="4">And let the young woman who pleases the king<note nid="n72002004.1"/> be queen instead of Vashti.<q class="end-double" qid="72002004.1" from="72002002.1" to="72002004.1"/> This pleased the king, and he did so.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002005"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5">Now there was a Jew in Susa the citadel whose name was <crossref let="x" cid="c72002005.1"/>Mordecai, the son of Jair, son of Shimei, son of Kish, a Benjaminite,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="y" cid="c72002006.1"/>who had been carried away from Jerusalem among the captives carried away with Jeconiah king of Judah, whom Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon had carried away.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002007"/>
    <verse num="7">He was bringing up Hadassah, that is Esther, <crossref let="z" cid="c72002007.1"/>the daughter of his uncle, for she had neither father nor mother. The young woman had a beautiful figure and was lovely to look at, and when her father and her mother died, Mordecai took her as his own daughter.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002008"/>
    <verse num="8">So when the king&apos;s order and his edict were proclaimed, and <crossref let="a" cid="c72002008.1"/>when many young women were gathered in Susa the citadel in custody of <crossref let="b" cid="c72002008.2"/>Hegai, Esther also was taken into the king&apos;s palace and put in custody of Hegai, who had charge of the women.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002009"/>
    <verse num="9">And the young woman pleased him and won his favor. And he quickly provided her <crossref let="c" cid="c72002009.1"/>with her cosmetics and her portion of food, and with seven chosen young women from the king&apos;s palace, and advanced her and her young women to the best place in the harem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="d" cid="c72002010.1"/>Esther had not made known her people or kindred, for Mordecai had commanded her not to make it known.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002011"/>
    <verse num="11">And every day Mordecai walked in front of the court of the harem to learn how Esther was and what was happening to her.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">Now when the turn came for each young woman to go in to King Ahasuerus, after being twelve months under the regulations for the women, since this was the regular period of their beautifying, six months with oil of myrrh and six months with spices and ointments for women&emdash;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002013"/>
    <verse num="13">when the young woman went in to the king in this way, she was given whatever she desired to take with her from the harem to the king&apos;s palace.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002014"/>
    <verse num="14">In the evening she would go in, and in the morning she would return to the second harem in custody of Shaashgaz, the king&apos;s eunuch, who was in charge of the concubines. She would not go in to the king again, unless the king delighted in her and she was summoned by name.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">When the turn came for Esther <crossref let="e" cid="c72002015.1"/>the daughter of Abihail the uncle of Mordecai, who had taken her as his own daughter, to go in to the king, she asked for nothing except what <crossref let="f" cid="c72002015.2"/>Hegai the king&apos;s eunuch, who had charge of the women, advised. Now Esther was winning favor in the eyes of all who saw her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002016"/>
    <verse num="16">And when Esther was taken to King Ahasuerus, into his royal palace, in the tenth month, which is the month of Tebeth, in the seventh year of his reign,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002017"/>
    <verse num="17">the king loved Esther more than all the women, and she won grace and favor in his sight more than all the virgins, so that he set <crossref let="g" cid="c72002017.1"/>the royal crown<note nid="n72002017.1"/> on her head and made her queen instead of Vashti.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002018"/>
    <verse num="18">Then the king <crossref let="h" cid="c72002018.1"/>gave a great feast for all his officials and servants; it was Esther&apos;s feast. He also granted a remission of taxes to the provinces and gave gifts with royal generosity.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002019"/>
    <heading>Mordecai Discovers a Plot</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19">Now when the virgins were gathered together <crossref let="i" cid="c72002019.1"/>the second time, Mordecai was sitting <crossref let="j" cid="c72002019.2"/>at the king&apos;s gate.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="k" cid="c72002020.1"/>Esther had not made known her kindred or her people, as Mordecai had commanded her, for Esther obeyed Mordecai just <crossref let="l" cid="c72002020.2"/>as when she was brought up by him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002021"/>
    <verse num="21">In those days, as Mordecai was sitting at the king&apos;s gate, <crossref let="m" cid="c72002021.1"/>Bigthan and <crossref let="n" cid="c72002021.2"/>Teresh, two of the king&apos;s eunuchs, who guarded the threshold, became angry and sought to lay hands on King Ahasuerus.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002022"/>
    <verse num="22">And this came to the knowledge of Mordecai, <crossref let="o" cid="c72002022.1"/>and he told it to Queen Esther, and Esther told the king in the name of Mordecai.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72002023"/>
    <verse num="23">When the affair was investigated and found to be so, the men were both hanged on the gallows.<note nid="n72002023.1"/> And it was recorded in <crossref let="p" cid="c72002023.1"/>the book of the chronicles in the presence of the king.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003001"/>
  <chapter num="3">
    <heading>Haman Plots Against the Jews</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">After these things King Ahasuerus <crossref let="q" cid="c72003001.1"/>promoted Haman <crossref let="r" cid="c72003001.2"/>the Agagite, the son of Hammedatha, <crossref let="s" cid="c72003001.3"/>and advanced him and set his throne above all the officials who were with him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003002"/>
    <verse num="2">And all the king&apos;s servants who were at the king&apos;s gate bowed down and paid homage to Haman, for the king had so commanded concerning him. <crossref let="t" cid="c72003002.1"/>But Mordecai did not bow down or pay homage.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003003"/>
    <verse num="3">Then the king&apos;s servants who were <crossref let="u" cid="c72003003.1"/>at the king&apos;s gate said to Mordecai, <q class="begin-double" qid="72003003.1" from="72003003.1" to="72003003.2"/>Why do you transgress <crossref let="v" cid="c72003003.2"/>the king&apos;s command?<q class="end-double" qid="72003003.2" from="72003003.1" to="72003003.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003004"/>
    <verse num="4">And when they spoke to him day after day and he would not listen to them, they told Haman, in order to see whether Mordecai&apos;s words would stand, for he had told them that he was a Jew.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003005"/>
    <verse num="5">And when Haman saw that <crossref let="t" cid="c72003005.1"/>Mordecai did not bow down or pay homage to him, Haman was <crossref let="w" cid="c72003005.2"/>filled with fury.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003006"/>
    <verse num="6">But he disdained<note nid="n72003006.1"/> to lay hands on Mordecai alone. So, as they had made known to him the people of Mordecai, Haman sought to destroy<note nid="n72003006.2"/> all the Jews, the people of Mordecai, throughout the whole kingdom of Ahasuerus.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">In the first month, which is the month of Nisan, in the twelfth year of King Ahasuerus, <crossref let="x" cid="c72003007.1"/>they cast Pur (that is, they cast lots) before Haman day after day; and they cast it month after month till the twelfth month, which is <crossref let="y" cid="c72003007.2"/>the month of Adar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003008"/>
    <verse num="8">Then Haman said to King Ahasuerus, <q class="begin-double" qid="72003008.1" from="72003008.1" to="72003009.1"/>There is a certain people scattered abroad and dispersed among the peoples in all the provinces of your kingdom. <crossref let="z" cid="c72003008.1"/>Their laws are different from those of every other people, and they do not keep the king&apos;s laws, so that it is not to the king&apos;s profit to tolerate them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003009"/>
    <verse num="9">If it please the king, let it be decreed that they be destroyed, and I will pay 10,000 talents<note nid="n72003009.1"/> of silver into the hands of those who have charge of the king&apos;s business, that they may put it into the king&apos;s treasuries.<q class="end-double" qid="72003009.1" from="72003008.1" to="72003009.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="a" cid="c72003010.1"/>So the king took his signet ring from his hand and gave it to Haman <crossref let="b" cid="c72003010.2"/>the Agagite, the son of Hammedatha, <crossref let="c" cid="c72003010.3"/>the enemy of the Jews.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003011"/>
    <verse num="11">And the king said to Haman, <q class="begin-double" qid="72003011.1" from="72003011.1" to="72003011.2"/>The money is given to you, the people also, to do with them as it seems good to you.<q class="end-double" qid="72003011.2" from="72003011.1" to="72003011.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="d" cid="c72003012.1"/>Then the king&apos;s scribes were summoned on the thirteenth day of the first month, and an edict, according to all that Haman commanded, was written to the king&apos;s <crossref let="e" cid="c72003012.2"/>satraps and to the governors over all the provinces and to the officials of all the peoples, <crossref let="f" cid="c72003012.3"/>to every province in its own script and every people in its own language. It was written <crossref let="g" cid="c72003012.4"/>in the name of King Ahasuerus <crossref let="h" cid="c72003012.5"/>and sealed with the king&apos;s signet ring.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003013"/>
    <verse num="13">Letters were sent <crossref let="i" cid="c72003013.1"/>by couriers to all the king&apos;s provinces with instruction <crossref let="j" cid="c72003013.2"/>to destroy, to kill, and to annihilate all Jews, young and old, women and children, <crossref let="k" cid="c72003013.3"/>in one day, the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, which is the month of Adar, <crossref let="l" cid="c72003013.4"/>and to plunder their goods.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003013.a"/>
    <heading>The King&apos;s Letter</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13a"><deutero><note nid="n72003013a.1"/> This is a copy of the letter: <q class="begin-double" qid="72003013a.1" from="72003013a.1" to="72003013g.1"/>The great king, Artaxerxes, to the rulers of the 127 lands from India to Ethiopia and to the governors under them, writes thus:</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003013.b"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13b"><deutero><q class="continue-double" qid="72003013b.1" from="72003013a.1" to="72003013g.1"/>Having become ruler of many nations and master of the whole world, not elated with presumption of authority but always acting reasonably and with kindness, I have determined to settle the lives of my subjects in lasting tranquility and, in order to make my kingdom peaceable and open to travel throughout all its extent, to reestablish the peace that all people desire.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003013.c"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13c"><deutero><q class="continue-double" qid="72003013c.1" from="72003013a.1" to="72003013g.1"/>When I asked my counselors how this might be accomplished, Haman, who excels among us in sound judgment and is distinguished for his unchanging good will and steadfast fidelity and has attained the second place in the kingdom,</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003013.d"/>
    <verse num="13d"><deutero>pointed out to us that among all the tribes in the world there is scattered a certain hostile people who have laws contrary to those of every nation and continually disregard the ordinances of the kings, so that the unifying of the kingdom that we honorably intend cannot be brought about.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003013.e"/>
    <verse num="13e"><deutero>We understand that this nation, and it alone, stands constantly in opposition to all, perversely following a strange manner of life and laws and is ill disposed to our government, doing all the harm they can so that our kingdom may not attain stability.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003013.f"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13f"><deutero><q class="continue-double" qid="72003013f.1" from="72003013a.1" to="72003013g.1"/>Therefore we have decreed that those indicated to you in the letters of Haman, who is in charge of affairs and is our second father, shall all, with their wives and children, be utterly destroyed by the sword of their enemies, without pity or mercy, on the fourteenth day of the twelfth month, Adar, of this present year,</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003013.g"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13g"><deutero>so that those who have long been and are now hostile may in one day go down in violence to Hades and leave our government completely secure and untroubled hereafter.<q class="end-double" qid="72003013g.1" from="72003013a.1" to="72003013g.1"/></deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="m" cid="c72003014.1"/>A copy of the document was to be issued as a decree in every province by proclamation to all the peoples to be ready for that day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72003015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="i" cid="c72003015.1"/>The couriers went out hurriedly by order of the king, and the decree was issued in Susa the citadel. And the king and Haman sat down to drink, <crossref let="n" cid="c72003015.2"/>but the city of Susa was thrown into confusion.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004001"/>
  <chapter num="4">
    <heading>Esther Agrees to Help the Jews</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">When Mordecai learned all that had been done, Mordecai tore his clothes <crossref let="o" cid="c72004001.1"/>and put on sackcloth and ashes, and went out into the midst of the city, and he cried out with a loud and bitter cry.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004002"/>
    <verse num="2">He went up to the entrance of the king&apos;s gate, for no one was allowed to enter the king&apos;s gate clothed in sackcloth.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004003"/>
    <verse num="3">And in every province, wherever the king&apos;s command and his decree reached, there was great mourning among the Jews, <crossref let="p" cid="c72004003.1"/>with fasting and weeping and lamenting, and many of them <crossref let="q" cid="c72004003.2"/>lay in sackcloth and ashes.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">When Esther&apos;s young women and her eunuchs came and told her, the queen was deeply distressed. She sent garments to clothe Mordecai, so that he might take off his sackcloth, but he would not accept them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004005"/>
    <verse num="5">Then Esther called for Hathach, one of the king&apos;s eunuchs, who had been appointed to attend her, and ordered him to go to Mordecai to learn what this was and why it was.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004006"/>
    <verse num="6">Hathach went out to Mordecai in the open square of the city in front of the king&apos;s gate,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004007"/>
    <verse num="7">and Mordecai told him all that had happened to him, <crossref let="r" cid="c72004007.1"/>and the exact sum of money that Haman had promised to pay into the king&apos;s treasuries for the destruction of the Jews.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004008"/>
    <verse num="8">Mordecai also gave him <crossref let="s" cid="c72004008.1"/>a copy of the written decree issued in Susa for their destruction,<note nid="n72004008.1"/> that he might show it to Esther and explain it to her and command her to go to the king to beg his favor and plead with him<note nid="n72004008.2"/> on behalf of her people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004008.a"/>
    <verse num="8a"><deutero><q class="begin-double" qid="72004008a.1" from="72004008a.1" to="72004008a.2"/>Remembering the days of your lowliness, when you were cared for by me, because Haman, who is next to the king, spoke against us for our destruction. Ask the Lord and speak to the king concerning us and deliver us from death.<q class="end-double" qid="72004008a.2" from="72004008a.1" to="72004008a.2"/></deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004009"/>
    <verse num="9">And Hathach went and told Esther what Mordecai had said.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004010"/>
    <verse num="10">Then Esther spoke to Hathach and commanded him to go to Mordecai and say,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004011"/>
    <verse num="11"><q class="begin-double" qid="72004011.1" from="72004011.1" to="72004011.2"/>All the king&apos;s servants and the people of the king&apos;s provinces know that if any man or woman goes to the king inside <crossref let="t" cid="c72004011.1"/>the inner court without being called, <crossref let="u" cid="c72004011.2"/>there is but one law&emdash;to be put to death, except the one <crossref let="v" cid="c72004011.3"/>to whom the king holds out the golden scepter so that he may live. But as for me, I have not been called to come in to the king these thirty days.<q class="end-double" qid="72004011.2" from="72004011.1" to="72004011.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">And they told Mordecai what Esther had said.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004013"/>
    <verse num="13">Then Mordecai told them to reply to Esther, <q class="begin-double" qid="72004013.1" from="72004013.1" to="72004014.1"/>Do not think to yourself that in the king&apos;s palace you will escape any more than all the other Jews.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004014"/>
    <verse num="14">For if you keep silent at this time, relief and deliverance will rise for the Jews from another place, but you and your father&apos;s house will perish. And who knows whether you have not come to the kingdom for such a time as this?<q class="end-double" qid="72004014.1" from="72004013.1" to="72004014.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004015"/>
    <verse num="15">Then Esther told them to reply to Mordecai,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004016"/>
    <verse num="16"><q class="begin-double" qid="72004016.1" from="72004016.1" to="72004016.2"/>Go, gather all the Jews to be found in Susa, and hold a fast on my behalf, and do not eat or drink for <crossref let="w" cid="c72004016.1"/>three days, night or day. I and my young women will also fast as you do. Then I will go to the king, though it is against the law, <crossref let="x" cid="c72004016.2"/>and if I perish, I perish.<q class="end-double" qid="72004016.2" from="72004016.1" to="72004016.2"/><note nid="n72004016.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017"/>
    <verse num="17">Mordecai then went away and did everything as Esther had ordered him.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.a"/>
    <heading><deutero>Mordecai&apos;s Prayer</deutero></heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17a"><deutero><note nid="n72004017a.1"/> Then Mordecai<note nid="n72004017a.2"/> prayed to the Lord, calling to remembrance all the works of the Lord. He said:</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.b"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17b"><deutero><q class="begin-double" qid="72004017b.1" from="72004017b.1" to="72004017k.1"/>O Lord, Lord, King who rules over all things, for the universe is in your power and there is no one who can oppose you when it is your will to save Israel.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.c"/>
    <verse num="17c"><deutero>For you have made heaven and earth and every wonderful thing in it under heaven,</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.d"/>
    <verse num="17d"><deutero>and you are Lord of all, and there is no one who can resist you, the Lord.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.e"/>
    <verse num="17e"><deutero>You know all things; you know, O Lord, that it was not in insolence or pride or for any love of glory that I did this and refused to bow down to this proud Haman.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.f"/>
    <verse num="17f"><deutero>For I would have been willing to kiss the soles of his feet, to save Israel!</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.g"/>
    <verse num="17g"><deutero>But I did this that I might not set the glory of man above the glory of God, and I will not bow down to anyone but you, my Lord; and I will not do these things in pride.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.h"/>
    <verse num="17h"><deutero>And now, O Lord God and King, God of Abraham, spare your people; for they are looking to annihilate us, and they desire to destroy the inheritance that has been yours from the beginning.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.i"/>
    <verse num="17i"><deutero>Do not neglect your portion, which you redeemed for yourself out of the land of Egypt.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.k"/>
    <verse num="17k"><deutero>Hear my prayer and have mercy upon your allotment and turn our mourning into feasting, that we may live and sing praise to your name, O Lord; do not destroy the mouth of those who praise you.<q class="end-double" qid="72004017k.1" from="72004017b.1" to="72004017k.1"/></deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.l"/>
    <verse num="17l"><deutero>And all Israel cried out mightily, for their death was before their eyes.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.m"/>
    <heading>Esther&apos;s Prayer</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17m"><deutero><note nid="n72004017m.1"/> And Esther the queen, seized with deathly anxiety, fled to the Lord;</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.n"/>
    <verse num="17n"><deutero>she took off her splendid apparel and put on the garments of distress and mourning, and instead of costly perfumes she covered her head with ashes and dung, and she utterly humbled her body and every part that she loved to adorn she covered with her tangled hair.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.o"/>
    <verse num="17o"><deutero>And she prayed to the Lord God of Israel and said:
    <end-paragraph/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <q class="begin-double" qid="72004017o.1" from="72004017o.1" to="72004017ee.1"/>O my Lord, you only are our King; help me, who am alone and have no helper but you,
    </deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.p"/>
    <verse num="17p"><deutero>for my danger is in my hand.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.q"/>
    <verse num="17q"><deutero>Ever since I was born I have heard in the tribe of my family that you, O Lord, took Israel out of all the nations and our fathers from among all their ancestors for an everlasting inheritance and that you did for them all that you promised.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.r"/>
    <verse num="17r"><deutero>And now we have sinned before you, and you have given us into the hands of our enemies,</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.s"/>
    <verse num="17s"><deutero>because we glorified their gods. You are righteous, O Lord!</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.t"/>
    <verse num="17t"><deutero>And now they were not satisfied that we are in bitter slavery, but they have covenanted with their idols</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.u"/>
    <verse num="17u"><deutero>to abolish what your mouth has ordained and to destroy your inheritance, to stop the mouths of those who praise you and to quench your altar and the glory of your house,</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.v"/>
    <verse num="17v"><deutero>to open the mouth of the nations for the praise of vain idols and to magnify forever a mortal king.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.w"/>
    <verse num="17w"><deutero>O Lord, do not surrender your scepter to what has no being; and do not let them mock at our downfall; but turn their plan against them and make an example of the man who began this against us.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.x"/>
    <verse num="17x"><deutero>Remember, O Lord; make yourself known in this time of our affliction and give me courage, O King of the gods and Master of all dominion!</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.y"/>
    <verse num="17y"><deutero>Put eloquent speech in my mouth before the lion and turn his heart to hate the man who is fighting against us, so that there may be an end of him and those who agree with him.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.z"/>
    <verse num="17z"><deutero>But save us by your hand and help me, who am alone and have no helper but you, O Lord.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.aa"/>
    <verse num="17aa"><deutero>You have knowledge of all things; and you know that I hate the splendor of the wicked and abhor the bed of the uncircumcised and of any alien.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.bb"/>
    <verse num="17bb"><deutero>You know my necessity—that I abhor the sign of my proud position, which is upon my head on the days when I appear in public. I abhor it like a menstrual rag, and I do not wear it on the days when I am at leisure.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.cc"/>
    <verse num="17cc"><deutero>And your servant has not eaten at Haman’s table, and I have not honored the king’s feast or drunk the wine of the libations.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.dd"/>
    <verse num="17dd"><deutero>Your servant has had no joy since the day that I was brought here until now, except in you, O Lord God of Abraham.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72004017.ee"/>
    <verse num="17ee"><deutero>O God, whose might is over all, hear the voice of the despairing and save us from the hands of evildoers. And save me from my fear!<q class="end-double" qid="72004017ee.1" from="72004017o.1" to="72004017ee.1"/></deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005001"/>
  <chapter num="5">
    <heading>Esther Prepares a Banquet</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="y" cid="c72005001.1"/>On the third day Esther put on her royal robes and stood in <crossref let="z" cid="c72005001.2"/>the inner court of the king&apos;s palace, in front of the king&apos;s quarters, while the king was sitting on his royal throne inside the throne room opposite the entrance to the palace.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002"/>
    <verse num="2">And when the king saw Queen Esther standing in the court, <crossref let="a" cid="c72005002.1"/>she won favor in his sight, <crossref let="b" cid="c72005002.2"/>and he held out to Esther the golden scepter that was in his hand. Then Esther approached and touched the tip of the scepter.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.a"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <heading>Esther Received by the King</heading>
    <verse num="2a"><deutero><note nid="n72005002a.1"/> And it happened on the third day, when she finished praying, she took off the garments of service and put on her glory.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.b"/>
    <verse num="2b"><deutero>Then, majestically adorned, after invoking the aid of the all-seeing God and Savior, she took her two maids with her,</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.c"/>
    <verse num="2c"><deutero>leaning daintily on one,</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.d"/>
    <verse num="2d"><deutero>while the other followed carrying her train.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.e"/>
    <verse num="2e"><deutero>She was radiant with perfect beauty, and she looked happy, as if beloved, but her heart was frozen with fear.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.f"/>
    <verse num="2f"><deutero>When she had gone through all the doors, she stood before the king. He was seated on his royal throne, clothed in the full array of his majesty, all covered with gold and precious stones. And he was most terrifying.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.g"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="2g"><deutero>Lifting his face, flushed with splendor, he looked at her in fierce anger. And the queen faltered and turned pale and faint and collapsed upon the head of the maid who went before her.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.h"/>
    <verse num="2h"><deutero>Then God changed the spirit of the king to gentleness, and in alarm he sprang from his throne and took her in his arms until she came to herself. And he comforted her with soothing words and said to her,</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.i"/>
    <verse num="2i"><deutero><q class="begin-double" qid="72005002i.1" from="72005002i.1" to="72005002k.1"/>What is it, Esther? I am your brother. Take courage;</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.k"/>
    <verse num="2k"><deutero>you shall not die, for our law applies only to the common person. Come near.<q class="end-double" qid="72005002k.1" from="72005002i.1" to="72005002k.1"/></deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.l"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="2l"><deutero>Then he raised the golden rod and touched it to her neck;</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.m"/>
    <verse num="2m"><deutero>and he embraced her and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72005002m.1" from="72005002m.1" to="72005002m.2"/>Speak to me.<q class="end-double" qid="72005002m.2" from="72005002m.1" to="72005002m.2"/></deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.n"/>
    <verse num="2n"><deutero>And she said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="72005002n.1" from="72005002n.1" to="72005002o.1"/>I saw you, my lord, like an angel of God, and my heart was shaken with fear at your glory.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.o"/>
    <verse num="2o"><deutero>For you are wonderful, my lord, and your face is full of grace.<q class="end-double" qid="72005002o.1" from="72005002n.1" to="72005002o.1"/></deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.p"/>
    <verse num="2p"><deutero>But as she was speaking, she fell fainting.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005002.q"/>
    <verse num="2q"><deutero>And the king was agitated, and all his servants sought to comfort her.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005003"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3">And the king said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="72005003.1" from="72005003.1" to="72005003.2"/>What is it, Queen Esther? What is your request? It shall be given you, even <crossref let="c" cid="c72005003.1"/>to the half of my kingdom.<q class="end-double" qid="72005003.2" from="72005003.1" to="72005003.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005004"/>
    <verse num="4">And Esther said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72005004.1" from="72005004.1" to="72005004.2"/>If it please the king,<note nid="n72005004.1"/> let the king and Haman come today to a feast that I have prepared for the king.<q class="end-double" qid="72005004.2" from="72005004.1" to="72005004.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005005"/>
    <verse num="5">Then the king said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72005005.1" from="72005005.1" to="72005005.2"/>Bring Haman quickly, so that we may do as Esther has asked.<q class="end-double" qid="72005005.2" from="72005005.1" to="72005005.2"/> So the king and Haman came to the feast that Esther had prepared.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="d" cid="c72005006.1"/>And as they were drinking wine after the feast, the king said to Esther, <crossref let="e" cid="c72005006.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="72005006.1" from="72005006.1" to="72005006.2"/>What is your wish? It shall be granted you. And what is your request? <crossref let="c" cid="c72005006.3"/>Even to the half of my kingdom, it shall be fulfilled.<q class="end-double" qid="72005006.2" from="72005006.1" to="72005006.2"/><note nid="n72005006.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005007"/>
    <verse num="7">Then Esther answered, <q class="begin-double" qid="72005007.1" from="72005007.1" to="72005008.1"/>My wish and my request is:</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="f" cid="c72005008.1"/>If I have found favor in the sight of the king, and if it please the king<note nid="n72005008.1"/> to grant my wish and fulfill my request, let the king and Haman come to <crossref let="g" cid="c72005008.2"/>the feast that I will prepare for them, and tomorrow I will do as the king has said.<q class="end-double" qid="72005008.1" from="72005007.1" to="72005008.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005009"/>
    <heading>Haman Plans to Hang Mordecai</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9">And Haman went out that day <crossref let="h" cid="c72005009.1"/>joyful and glad of heart. But when Haman saw Mordecai <crossref let="i" cid="c72005009.2"/>in the king&apos;s gate, <crossref let="j" cid="c72005009.3"/>that he neither rose nor trembled before him, he was filled with wrath against Mordecai.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005010"/>
    <verse num="10">Nevertheless, Haman restrained himself and went home, and he sent and brought his friends and <crossref let="k" cid="c72005010.1"/>his wife Zeresh.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005011"/>
    <verse num="11">And Haman recounted to them the splendor of his riches, <crossref let="l" cid="c72005011.1"/>the number of his sons, all the promotions with which <crossref let="m" cid="c72005011.2"/>the king had honored him, and how he had advanced him above the officials and the servants of the king.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005012"/>
    <verse num="12">Then Haman said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72005012.1" from="72005012.1" to="72005013.1"/>Even Queen Esther let no one but me come with the king to the feast she prepared. And tomorrow also I am invited by her together with the king.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005013"/>
    <verse num="13">Yet all this is worth nothing to me, so long as I see Mordecai the Jew sitting <crossref let="i" cid="c72005013.1"/>at the king&apos;s gate.<q class="end-double" qid="72005013.1" from="72005012.1" to="72005013.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72005014"/>
    <verse num="14">Then <crossref let="k" cid="c72005014.1"/>his wife Zeresh and all his friends said to him, <crossref let="n" cid="c72005014.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="72005014.1" from="72005014.1" to="72005014.2"/>Let a gallows<note nid="n72005014.1"/> fifty cubits<note nid="n72005014.2"/> high be made, and in the morning tell the king to have Mordecai hanged upon it. Then go joyfully with the king to the feast.<q class="end-double" qid="72005014.2" from="72005014.1" to="72005014.2"/> This idea pleased Haman, and he had the gallows made.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006001"/>
  <chapter num="6">
    <heading>The King Honors Mordecai</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">On that night the king could not sleep. And he gave orders to bring <crossref let="o" cid="c72006001.1"/>the book of memorable deeds, the chronicles, and they were read before the king.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006002"/>
    <verse num="2">And it was found written how <crossref let="p" cid="c72006002.1"/>Mordecai had told about <crossref let="q" cid="c72006002.2"/>Bigthana<note nid="n72006002.1"/> and <crossref let="r" cid="c72006002.3"/>Teresh, two of the king&apos;s eunuchs, who guarded the threshold, and who had sought to lay hands on King Ahasuerus.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006003"/>
    <verse num="3">And the king said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72006003.1" from="72006003.1" to="72006003.2"/>What honor or distinction has been bestowed on Mordecai for this?<q class="end-double" qid="72006003.2" from="72006003.1" to="72006003.2"/> The king&apos;s young men who attended him said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72006003.3" from="72006003.3" to="72006003.4"/>Nothing has been done for him.<q class="end-double" qid="72006003.4" from="72006003.3" to="72006003.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006004"/>
    <verse num="4">And the king said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72006004.1" from="72006004.1" to="72006004.2"/>Who is in the court?<q class="end-double" qid="72006004.2" from="72006004.1" to="72006004.2"/> Now Haman had just entered <crossref let="s" cid="c72006004.1"/>the outer court of the king&apos;s palace to speak to the king about having Mordecai hanged on <crossref let="t" cid="c72006004.2"/>the gallows<note nid="n72006004.1"/> that he had prepared for him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006005"/>
    <verse num="5">And the king&apos;s young men told him, <q class="begin-double" qid="72006005.1" from="72006005.1" to="72006005.2"/>Haman is there, standing in the court.<q class="end-double" qid="72006005.2" from="72006005.1" to="72006005.2"/> And the king said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72006005.3" from="72006005.3" to="72006005.4"/>Let him come in.<q class="end-double" qid="72006005.4" from="72006005.3" to="72006005.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006006"/>
    <verse num="6">So Haman came in, and the king said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="72006006.1" from="72006006.1" to="72006006.2"/>What should be done to the man <crossref let="u" cid="c72006006.1"/>whom the king delights to honor?<q class="end-double" qid="72006006.2" from="72006006.1" to="72006006.2"/> And Haman said to himself, <q class="begin-double" qid="72006006.3" from="72006006.3" to="72006006.4"/>Whom would the king delight to honor more than me?<q class="end-double" qid="72006006.4" from="72006006.3" to="72006006.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006007"/>
    <verse num="7">And Haman said to the king, <q class="begin-double" qid="72006007.1" from="72006007.1" to="72006009.3"/>For the man whom the king delights to honor,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006008"/>
    <verse num="8">let royal robes be brought, which the king has worn, <crossref let="v" cid="c72006008.1"/>and the horse that the king has ridden, and on whose head <crossref let="w" cid="c72006008.2"/>a royal crown<note nid="n72006008.1"/> is set.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006009"/>
    <verse num="9">And let the robes and the horse be handed over to one of the king&apos;s most noble officials. Let them dress the man whom the king delights to honor, and let them lead him on the horse through the square of the city, <crossref let="x" cid="c72006009.1"/>proclaiming before him: <q class="begin-single" qid="72006009.1" from="72006009.1" to="72006009.2"/>Thus shall it be done to the man whom the king delights to honor.<q class="end-single" qid="72006009.2" from="72006009.1" to="72006009.2"/><q class="end-double" qid="72006009.3" from="72006007.1" to="72006009.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006010"/>
    <verse num="10">Then the king said to Haman, <q class="begin-double" qid="72006010.1" from="72006010.1" to="72006010.2"/>Hurry; take the robes and the horse, as you have said, and do so to Mordecai the Jew, who sits <crossref let="y" cid="c72006010.1"/>at the king&apos;s gate. Leave out nothing that you have mentioned.<q class="end-double" qid="72006010.2" from="72006010.1" to="72006010.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006011"/>
    <verse num="11">So Haman took the robes and the horse, and he dressed Mordecai and led him through the square of the city, proclaiming before him, <q class="begin-double" qid="72006011.1" from="72006011.1" to="72006011.2"/>Thus shall it be done to the man whom the king delights to honor.<q class="end-double" qid="72006011.2" from="72006011.1" to="72006011.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">Then Mordecai returned to the king&apos;s gate. But Haman hurried to his house, mourning <crossref let="z" cid="c72006012.1"/>and with his head covered.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006013"/>
    <verse num="13">And Haman told <crossref let="a" cid="c72006013.1"/>his wife Zeresh and all his friends everything that had happened to him. Then his wise men and his wife Zeresh said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="72006013.1" from="72006013.1" to="72006013.2"/>If Mordecai, before whom you have begun to fall, is of the Jewish people, you will not overcome him but will surely fall before him.<q class="end-double" qid="72006013.2" from="72006013.1" to="72006013.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72006014"/>
    <heading>Esther Reveals Haman&apos;s Plot</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14">While they were yet talking with him, the king&apos;s eunuchs arrived and hurried to bring Haman <crossref let="b" cid="c72006014.1"/>to the feast that Esther had prepared.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72007001"/>
  <chapter num="7">
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">So the king and Haman went in to feast with Queen Esther.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72007002"/>
    <verse num="2">And on the second day, as they were drinking wine after the feast, the king again said to Esther, <crossref let="c" cid="c72007002.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="72007002.1" from="72007002.1" to="72007002.2"/>What is your wish, Queen Esther? It shall be granted you. And what is your request? <crossref let="d" cid="c72007002.2"/>Even to the half of my kingdom, it shall be fulfilled.<q class="end-double" qid="72007002.2" from="72007002.1" to="72007002.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72007003"/>
    <verse num="3">Then Queen Esther answered, <crossref let="e" cid="c72007003.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="72007003.1" from="72007003.1" to="72007004.1"/>If I have found favor in your sight, O king, and if it please the king, let my life be granted me for my wish, and my people for my request.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72007004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="f" cid="c72007004.1"/>For we have been sold, I and my people, <crossref let="g" cid="c72007004.2"/>to be destroyed, to be killed, and to be annihilated. If we had been sold merely as slaves, men and women, I would have been silent, for our affliction is not to be compared with the loss to the king.<q class="end-double" qid="72007004.1" from="72007003.1" to="72007004.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72007005"/>
    <verse num="5">Then King Ahasuerus said to Queen Esther, <q class="begin-double" qid="72007005.1" from="72007005.1" to="72007005.2"/>Who is he, and where is he, who has dared<note nid="n72007005.1"/> to do this?<q class="end-double" qid="72007005.2" from="72007005.1" to="72007005.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72007006"/>
    <verse num="6">And Esther said, <crossref let="h" cid="c72007006.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="72007006.1" from="72007006.1" to="72007006.2"/>A foe and enemy! This wicked Haman!<q class="end-double" qid="72007006.2" from="72007006.1" to="72007006.2"/> Then Haman was terrified before the king and the queen.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72007007"/>
    <heading>Haman Is Hanged</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">And the king arose in his wrath from the wine-drinking and went into <crossref let="i" cid="c72007007.1"/>the palace garden, but Haman stayed to beg for his life from Queen Esther, for he saw that harm was determined against him by the king.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72007008"/>
    <verse num="8">And the king returned from <crossref let="i" cid="c72007008.1"/>the palace garden to the place where they were drinking wine, as Haman was falling on <crossref let="j" cid="c72007008.2"/>the couch where Esther was. And the king said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72007008.1" from="72007008.1" to="72007008.2"/>Will he even assault the queen in my presence, in my own house?<q class="end-double" qid="72007008.2" from="72007008.1" to="72007008.2"/> As the word left the mouth of the king, they covered Haman&apos;s face.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72007009"/>
    <verse num="9">Then <crossref let="k" cid="c72007009.1"/>Harbona, one of the eunuchs in attendance on the king, said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72007009.1" from="72007009.1" to="72007009.2"/>Moreover, <crossref let="l" cid="c72007009.2"/>the gallows<note nid="n72007009.1"/> that Haman has prepared for Mordecai, <crossref let="m" cid="c72007009.3"/>whose word saved the king, is standing at Haman&apos;s house, fifty cubits<note nid="n72007009.2"/> high.<q class="end-double" qid="72007009.2" from="72007009.1" to="72007009.2"/> And the king said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72007009.3" from="72007009.3" to="72007009.4"/>Hang him on that.<q class="end-double" qid="72007009.4" from="72007009.3" to="72007009.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72007010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="n" cid="c72007010.1"/>So they hanged Haman on the gallows that he had prepared for Mordecai. <crossref let="o" cid="c72007010.2"/>Then the wrath of the king abated.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008001"/>
  <chapter num="8">
    <heading>Esther Saves the Jews</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">On that day King Ahasuerus gave to Queen Esther the house of Haman, <crossref let="h" cid="c72008001.1"/>the enemy of the Jews. And Mordecai came before the king, for Esther had told <crossref let="p" cid="c72008001.2"/>what he was to her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="q" cid="c72008002.1"/>And the king took off his signet ring, which he had taken from Haman, and gave it to Mordecai. And Esther set Mordecai over the house of Haman.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008003"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3">Then Esther spoke again to the king. She fell at his feet and wept and pleaded with him to avert the evil plan of Haman <crossref let="r" cid="c72008003.1"/>the Agagite and the plot that he had devised against the Jews.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="s" cid="c72008004.1"/>When the king held out the golden scepter to Esther, Esther rose and stood before the king.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008005"/>
    <verse num="5">And she said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72008005.1" from="72008005.1" to="72008006.1"/>If it please the king, <crossref let="t" cid="c72008005.1"/>and if I have found favor in his sight, and if the thing seems right before the king, and I am pleasing in his eyes, let an order be written to revoke <crossref let="u" cid="c72008005.2"/>the letters devised by Haman <crossref let="r" cid="c72008005.3"/>the Agagite, the son of Hammedatha, which he wrote to destroy the Jews who are in all the provinces of the king.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008006"/>
    <verse num="6">For how can I bear <crossref let="v" cid="c72008006.1"/>to see the calamity that is coming to my people? Or how can I bear to see the destruction of my kindred?<q class="end-double" qid="72008006.1" from="72008005.1" to="72008006.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008007"/>
    <verse num="7">Then King Ahasuerus said to Queen Esther and to Mordecai the Jew, <q class="begin-double" qid="72008007.1" from="72008007.1" to="72008008.1"/>Behold, <crossref let="w" cid="c72008007.1"/>I have given Esther the house of Haman, and they have hanged him on the gallows,<note nid="n72008007.1"/> because he intended to lay hands on the Jews.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008008"/>
    <verse num="8">But you may write as you please with regard to the Jews, in the name of the king, <crossref let="x" cid="c72008008.1"/>and seal it with the king&apos;s ring, for an edict written in the name of the king and sealed with the king&apos;s ring <crossref let="y" cid="c72008008.2"/>cannot be revoked.<q class="end-double" qid="72008008.1" from="72008007.1" to="72008008.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008009"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="z" cid="c72008009.1"/>The king&apos;s scribes were summoned at that time, in the third month, which is the month of Sivan, on the twenty-third day. And an edict was written, according to all that Mordecai commanded concerning the Jews, to <crossref let="a" cid="c72008009.2"/>the satraps and the governors and the officials of the provinces <crossref let="b" cid="c72008009.3"/>from India to Ethiopia, <crossref let="b" cid="c72008009.4"/>127 provinces, <crossref let="c" cid="c72008009.5"/>to each province in its own script and to each people in its own language, and also to the Jews in their script and their language.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="d" cid="c72008010.1"/>And he wrote in the name of King Ahasuerus <crossref let="e" cid="c72008010.2"/>and sealed it with the king&apos;s signet ring. Then he sent the letters by mounted couriers riding on <crossref let="f" cid="c72008010.3"/>swift horses that were used in the king&apos;s service, bred from the royal stud,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008011"/>
    <verse num="11">saying that the king allowed the Jews who were in every city <crossref let="g" cid="c72008011.1"/>to gather and defend their lives, <crossref let="h" cid="c72008011.2"/>to destroy, to kill, and to annihilate any armed force of any people or province that might attack them, children and women included, <crossref let="i" cid="c72008011.3"/>and to plunder their goods,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="j" cid="c72008012.1"/>on one day throughout all the provinces of King Ahasuerus, on the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, which is the month of Adar.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.a"/>
    <heading>Decree of Artaxerxes</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12a"><deutero><note nid="n72008012a.1"/> The following is a copy of this letter:</deutero>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <deutero><q class="begin-double" qid="72008012a.1" from="72008012a.1" to="72008012y.2"/>The great king, Artaxerxes, to the rulers of the provinces from India to Ethiopia, 127 satrapies, and to those who are loyal to our government, greeting.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.b"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12b"><deutero><q class="continue-double" qid="72008012b.1" from="72008012a.1" to="72008012y.2"/>The more often they are honored by the too great kindness of their benefactors, the prouder do many become.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.c"/>
    <verse num="12c"><deutero>They not only seek to injure our subjects, but in their inability to stand prosperity they even undertake to scheme against their own benefactors.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.d"/>
    <verse num="12d"><deutero>They not only take away thankfulness from among people, but, carried away by the boasts of those who know nothing of goodness, they suppose that they will escape the evil-hating justice of God, who always sees everything.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.e"/>
    <verse num="12e"><deutero>And often many of those who are set in places of authority have been made in part responsible for the shedding of innocent blood and have been involved in irremediable calamities, by the persuasion of friends who have been entrusted with the administration of public affairs,</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.f"/>
    <verse num="12f"><deutero>when these people by the false trickery of their evil natures beguile the sincere good will of their sovereigns.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.g"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12g"><deutero><q class="continue-double" qid="72008012g.1" from="72008012a.1" to="72008012y.2"/>What has been wickedly accomplished through the pestilent behavior of those who exercise authority unworthily can be seen not so much from the more ancient records that we hand on as from investigation of matters close at hand.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.h"/>
    <verse num="12h"><deutero>For the future we will take care to render our kingdom quiet and peaceable for all people,</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.i"/>
    <verse num="12i"><deutero>by changing our methods and always judging what comes before our eyes with more equitable consideration.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.k"/>
    <verse num="12k"><deutero>For Haman son of Hamadathos, a Macedonian (really an alien to the Persian blood and quite devoid of our kindliness), having become our guest,</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.l"/>
    <verse num="12l"><deutero>so far enjoyed the good will that we have for every nation that he was publicly proclaimed our father and was continually bowed down to by all as the person second to the royal throne.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.m"/>
    <verse num="12m"><deutero>But, unable to restrain his arrogance, he undertook to deprive us of our kingdom and our life</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.n"/>
    <verse num="12n"><deutero>and with intricate craft and deceit asked for the destruction of Mordecai, our savior and perpetual benefactor, and of Esther, the blameless partner of our kingdom, together with their whole nation.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.o"/>
    <verse num="12o"><deutero>He thought that in this way he would find us undefended and would transfer the kingdom of the Persians to the Macedonians.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.p"/>
    <verse num="12p"><deutero><q class="continue-double" qid="72008012p.1" from="72008012a.1" to="72008012y.2"/>But we find that the Jews, who were consigned to annihilation by this thrice-accursed man, are not evildoers but are governed by most righteous laws</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.q"/>
    <verse num="12q"><deutero>and are sons of the Most High, the mightiest living God, who has directed the kingdom both for us and for our ancestors in the most excellent order.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.r"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12r"><deutero><q class="continue-double" qid="72008012r.1" from="72008012a.1" to="72008012y.2"/>You will therefore do well not to put in execution the letters sent by Haman son of Hamadathos,</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.s"/>
    <verse num="12s"><deutero>because the man himself who did these things has been hanged at the gates of Susa, with all his household. For God, who rules over all things, has speedily inflicted on him the punishment he deserved.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.t"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12t"><deutero><q class="continue-double" qid="72008012t.1" from="72008012a.1" to="72008012y.2"/>Therefore post a copy of this letter publicly in every place and permit the Jews to live under their own laws.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.u"/>
    <verse num="12u"><deutero>And give them reinforcements, so that on the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, Adar, on that very day they may defend themselves against those who attack them at the time of their affliction.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.v"/>
    <verse num="12v"><deutero>For God, who rules over all things, has made this day to be a joy to his chosen people instead of a day of destruction for them.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.w"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12w"><deutero><q class="continue-double" qid="72008012w.1" from="72008012a.1" to="72008012y.2"/>Therefore you shall observe this with all good cheer as a notable day among your commemorative festivals,</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.x"/>
    <verse num="12x"><deutero>so that both now and hereafter it may mean salvation for us and the loyal Persians, but that for those who plot against us it may be a reminder of destruction.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008012.y"/>
    <verse num="12y"><deutero><q class="continue-double" qid="72008012y.1" from="72008012a.1" to="72008012y.2"/>Every city and country, without exception, which does not act accordingly, shall be destroyed in wrath with spear and fire. It shall be made not only impassable for people, but also most hateful for all time to beasts and birds.<q class="end-double" qid="72008012y.2" from="72008012a.1" to="72008012y.2"/></deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="k" cid="c72008013.1"/>A copy of what was written was to be issued as a decree in every province, being publicly displayed to all peoples, and the Jews were to be ready on that day to take vengeance on their enemies.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008014"/>
    <verse num="14">So the couriers, mounted on their <crossref let="f" cid="c72008014.1"/>swift horses that were used in the king&apos;s service, rode out hurriedly, urged by the king&apos;s command. And the decree was issued in Susa the citadel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">Then Mordecai went out from the presence of the king <crossref let="l" cid="c72008015.1"/>in royal robes of blue and white, with a great golden crown<note nid="n72008015.1"/> and <crossref let="m" cid="c72008015.2"/>a robe of fine linen and purple, <crossref let="n" cid="c72008015.3"/>and the city of Susa shouted and rejoiced.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008016"/>
    <verse num="16">The Jews had <crossref let="o" cid="c72008016.1"/>light and gladness and joy and honor.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72008017"/>
    <verse num="17">And in every province and in every city, wherever the king&apos;s command and his edict reached, there was gladness and joy among the Jews, a feast and <crossref let="p" cid="c72008017.1"/>a holiday. <crossref let="q" cid="c72008017.2"/>And many from the peoples of the country declared themselves Jews, <crossref let="r" cid="c72008017.3"/>for fear of the Jews had fallen on them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009001"/>
  <chapter num="9">
    <heading>The Jews Destroy Their Enemies</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="s" cid="c72009001.1"/>Now in the twelfth month, which is the month of Adar, <crossref let="t" cid="c72009001.2"/>on the thirteenth day of the same, <crossref let="u" cid="c72009001.3"/>when the king&apos;s command and edict were about to be carried out, <crossref let="j" cid="c72009001.4"/>on the very day when the enemies of the Jews hoped to gain the mastery over them, the reverse occurred: the Jews gained mastery over those who hated them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="v" cid="c72009002.1"/>The Jews gathered in their cities throughout all the provinces of King Ahasuerus to lay hands on those who sought their harm. And no one could stand against them, <crossref let="w" cid="c72009002.2"/>for the fear of them had fallen on all peoples.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009003"/>
    <verse num="3">All the officials of the provinces and <crossref let="x" cid="c72009003.1"/>the satraps and the governors and the royal agents also helped the Jews, for the fear of Mordecai had fallen on them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009004"/>
    <verse num="4">For Mordecai was great in the king&apos;s house, and his fame spread throughout all the provinces, for the man Mordecai grew <crossref let="y" cid="c72009004.1"/>more and more powerful.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009005"/>
    <verse num="5">The Jews struck all their enemies with the sword, killing and destroying them, and did as they pleased to those who hated them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009006"/>
    <verse num="6">In Susa the citadel itself the Jews killed and destroyed 500 men,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009007"/>
    <verse num="7">and also killed Parshandatha and Dalphon and Aspatha</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009008"/>
    <verse num="8">and Poratha and Adalia and Aridatha</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009009"/>
    <verse num="9">and Parmashta and Arisai and Aridai and Vaizatha,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="z" cid="c72009010.1"/>the ten sons of Haman the son of Hammedatha, <crossref let="a" cid="c72009010.2"/>the enemy of the Jews, <crossref let="b" cid="c72009010.3"/>but they laid no hand on the plunder.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11">That very day the number of those killed in Susa the citadel was reported to the king.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009012"/>
    <verse num="12">And the king said to Queen Esther, <q class="begin-double" qid="72009012.1" from="72009012.1" to="72009012.2"/>In Susa the citadel the Jews have killed and destroyed 500 men and also the ten sons of Haman. What then have they done in the rest of the king&apos;s provinces! <crossref let="c" cid="c72009012.1"/>Now what is your wish? It shall be granted you. And what further is your request? It shall be fulfilled.<q class="end-double" qid="72009012.2" from="72009012.1" to="72009012.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009013"/>
    <verse num="13">And Esther said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72009013.1" from="72009013.1" to="72009013.2"/>If it please the king, let the Jews who are in Susa be allowed <crossref let="d" cid="c72009013.1"/>tomorrow also to do according to this day&apos;s edict. And let the ten sons of Haman be hanged on the gallows.<q class="end-double" qid="72009013.2" from="72009013.1" to="72009013.2"/><note nid="n72009013.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009014"/>
    <verse num="14">So the king commanded this to be done. A decree was issued in Susa, and the ten sons of Haman were hanged.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009015"/>
    <verse num="15">The Jews who were in Susa gathered also on the fourteenth day of the month of Adar and they killed 300 men in Susa, but they laid no hands on the plunder.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="e" cid="c72009016.1"/>Now the rest of the Jews who were in the king&apos;s provinces also <crossref let="f" cid="c72009016.2"/>gathered to defend their lives, and got relief from their enemies and killed 75,000 of those who hated them, but they laid no hands on the plunder.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009017"/>
    <verse num="17">This was <crossref let="g" cid="c72009017.1"/>on the thirteenth day of the month of Adar, and on the fourteenth day they rested and made that a day of feasting and gladness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009018"/>
    <verse num="18">But the Jews who were in Susa gathered <crossref let="g" cid="c72009018.1"/>on the thirteenth day and on the fourteenth, and rested <crossref let="h" cid="c72009018.2"/>on the fifteenth day, making that a day of feasting and gladness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009019"/>
    <verse num="19">Therefore the Jews of the villages, who live in <crossref let="i" cid="c72009019.1"/>the rural towns, hold the fourteenth day of the month of Adar as a day for gladness and feasting, as <crossref let="j" cid="c72009019.2"/>a holiday, and <crossref let="k" cid="c72009019.3"/>as a day on which they send gifts of food to one another.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009020"/>
    <heading>The Feast of Purim Inaugurated</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20">And Mordecai recorded these things and sent letters to all the Jews who were in all the provinces of King Ahasuerus, both near and far,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009021"/>
    <verse num="21">obliging them to keep the fourteenth day of the month Adar and also the fifteenth day of the same, year by year,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009022"/>
    <verse num="22">as the days on which the Jews got relief from their enemies, and as the month that had been turned for them from sorrow into gladness and from mourning into <crossref let="j" cid="c72009022.1"/>a holiday; that they should make them days of feasting and gladness, days for sending gifts of food to one another and gifts to the poor.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009023"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="23">So the Jews accepted what they had started to do, and what Mordecai had written to them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009024"/>
    <verse num="24">For Haman the Agagite, the son of Hammedatha, <crossref let="l" cid="c72009024.1"/>the enemy of all the Jews, <crossref let="m" cid="c72009024.2"/>had plotted against the Jews to destroy them, and <crossref let="n" cid="c72009024.3"/>had cast Pur (that is, cast lots), to crush and to destroy them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009025"/>
    <verse num="25">But when it came before the king, he gave orders in writing <crossref let="o" cid="c72009025.1"/>that his evil plan that he had devised against the Jews <crossref let="p" cid="c72009025.2"/>should return on his own head, and that he and his sons should be hanged on the gallows.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009026"/>
    <verse num="26">Therefore they called these days Purim, after the term <crossref let="n" cid="c72009026.1"/>Pur. Therefore, because of all that was written in <crossref let="q" cid="c72009026.2"/>this letter, and of what they had faced in this matter, and of what had happened to them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009027"/>
    <verse num="27">the Jews firmly obligated themselves and their offspring and <crossref let="r" cid="c72009027.1"/>all who joined them, that without fail they would keep <crossref let="s" cid="c72009027.2"/>these two days according to what was written and at the time appointed every year,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009028"/>
    <verse num="28">that these days should be remembered and kept throughout every generation, in every clan, province, and city, and that these days of Purim should never fall into disuse among the Jews, nor should the commemoration of these days cease among their descendants.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009029"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29">Then Queen Esther, <crossref let="t" cid="c72009029.1"/>the daughter of Abihail, and Mordecai the Jew gave full written authority, confirming <crossref let="u" cid="c72009029.2"/>this second letter about Purim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009030"/>
    <verse num="30">Letters were sent to all the Jews, <crossref let="v" cid="c72009030.1"/>to the 127 provinces of the kingdom of Ahasuerus, in words of peace and truth,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009031"/>
    <verse num="31">that these days of Purim should be observed at their appointed seasons, as Mordecai the Jew and Queen Esther obligated them, and as they had obligated themselves and their offspring, with regard to <crossref let="w" cid="c72009031.1"/>their fasts and their lamenting.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72009032"/>
    <verse num="32">The command of Esther confirmed these practices of <crossref let="x" cid="c72009032.1"/>Purim, and it was recorded in writing.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010001"/>
  <chapter num="10">
    <heading>The Greatness of Mordecai</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">King Ahasuerus imposed tax on the land and on <crossref let="y" cid="c72010001.1"/>the coastlands of the sea.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010002"/>
    <verse num="2">And all the acts of his power and might, and the full account of the high honor of Mordecai, <crossref let="z" cid="c72010002.1"/>to which the king advanced him, are they not written in <crossref let="a" cid="c72010002.2"/>the Book of the Chronicles of the kings of Media and Persia?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010003"/>
    <verse num="3">For Mordecai the Jew was <crossref let="b" cid="c72010003.1"/>second in rank to King Ahasuerus, and he was great among the Jews and popular with the multitude of his brothers, for he <crossref let="c" cid="c72010003.2"/>sought the welfare of his people and spoke peace to all his people.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010003.a"/>
    <heading>Mordecai&apos;s Dream Fulfilled</heading>
    <verse num="3a"><deutero><note nid="n72010003a.1"/> And Mordecai said, <q class="begin-double" qid="72010003a.1" from="72010003a.1" to="72010003k.1"/> These things have come from God.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010003.b"/>
    <verse num="3b"><deutero>For I remember the dream that I saw concerning these matters; and none of them has failed to be fulfilled.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010003.c"/>
    <verse num="3c"><deutero>The tiny spring that became a river, and there was light and the sun and abundant water—the river is Esther, whom the king married and made queen.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010003.d"/>
    <verse num="3d"><deutero>The two dragons are Haman and myself.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010003.e"/>
    <verse num="3e"><deutero>The nations are those that gathered to destroy the name of the Jews.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010003.f"/>
    <verse num="3f"><deutero>And my nation, this is Israel, who cried out to God and were saved. The Lord has saved his people; the Lord has delivered us from all these evils; God has done great signs and wonders, which have not occurred among the nations.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010003.g"/>
    <verse num="3g"><deutero>For this purpose he made two lots, one for the people of God and one for all the nations.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010003.h"/>
    <verse num="3h"><deutero>And these two lots came to the hour and moment and day of decision before God and among all the nations.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010003.i"/>
    <verse num="3i"><deutero>And God remembered his people and vindicated his inheritance.</deutero></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010003.k"/>
    <verse num="3k"><deutero>So they will observe these days in the month of Adar, on the fourteenth and fifteenth of that month, with an assembly and joy and gladness before God, from generation to generation forever among his people Israel.<q class="end-double" qid="72010003.k" from="72010003a.1" to="72010003k.1"/></deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v72010003.l"/>
    <heading>Postscript</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3l"><deutero>In the fourth year of the reign of Ptolemy and Cleopatra, Dositheus, who said that he was a priest and a Levite,<note nid="n72010003l.1"/> and Ptolemy his son brought the preceding Letter of Phrourai, which they said was genuine and had been translated by Lysimachus son of Ptolemy, one of the residents of Jerusalem.</deutero></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
</book>
</crossway-bible>
