<?xml version='1.0' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" translation="English Standard Version" revision="2018-3-26" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
  <book title="Letter of Jeremiah" num="76">
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001001"/>
    <chapter num="1">
      <heading>The Letter of Jeremiah</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">A copy of a letter that Jeremiah sent to those who were to be taken to Babylon as captives by the king of the Babylonians, to give them the message that God had commanded him.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001002"/>
      <heading>The People Face a Long Captivity</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="2">Because of the sins that you have committed before God, you will be taken to Babylon as captives by King Nebuchadnezzar of the Babylonians.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001003"/>
      <verse num="3">Therefore when you have come to Babylon you will remain there for many years, for a long time, up to seven generations; after that I will bring you away from there in peace.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001004"/>
      <verse num="4">Now in Babylon you will see gods made of silver and gold and wood, which are carried aloft on the shoulders and inspire awe among the nations.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001005"/>
      <verse num="5">So take care not to become at all like the foreigners or to let awe of these gods<note nid="n76001005.1"/> possess you, when you see the multitude before and behind them worshiping them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001006"/>
      <verse num="6">But say to yourself, <q class="begin-double" qid="76001006.1" from="76001006.1" to="76001006.2"/>It is you, O Lord, whom we must worship.<q class="end-double" qid="76001006.2" from="76001006.1" to="76001006.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001007"/>
      <verse num="7">For my angel is with you, demanding an account of your souls.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001008"/>
      <heading>Helplessness of Idols</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="8">Their tongues are smoothed by the carpenter, and they themselves are overlaid with gold and silver; but they are false and cannot speak.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001009"/>
      <verse num="9">People<note nid="n76001009.1"/> take gold and make crowns for the heads of their gods, as they would for a girl who loves ornaments;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001010"/>
      <verse num="10">and sometimes the priests secretly take gold and silver from their gods and spend it upon themselves</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001011"/>
      <verse num="11">and even give some of it to the prostitutes in the brothel. They adorn their gods<note nid="n76001011.1"/> out with garments like people&emdash;these gods of silver and gold and wood,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001012"/>
      <verse num="12">which cannot save themselves from rust and corrosion. When they have been dressed in purple robes,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001013"/>
      <verse num="13">their faces are wiped because of the dust from the temple, which is thick upon them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001014"/>
      <verse num="14">Like a local ruler the god<note nid="n76001014.1"/> holds a scepter, though unable to destroy anyone who offends it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001015"/>
      <verse num="15">It has a dagger in its right hand and has an axe; but it cannot save itself from war and robbers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001016"/>
      <verse num="16">Therefore they evidently are not gods; so do not revere them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001017"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="17">For just as one&apos;s dish is useless when it is broken, so are their gods,<note nid="n76001017.1"/> when they have been set up in the temples. Their eyes are full of the dust raised by the feet of those who enter.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001018"/>
      <verse num="18">And just as the gates are shut on every side upon a man who has offended a king, as though he were sentenced to death, so the priests make their temples secure with doors and locks and bars, in order that they may not be plundered by robbers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001019"/>
      <verse num="19">They light lamps, even more than they light for themselves, though their gods<note nid="n76001019.1"/> can see none of them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001020"/>
      <verse num="20">They are<note nid="n76001020.1"/> just like a beam of the temple, but people say they melt their hearts. When worms from the earth devour them and their robes, they do not notice,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001021"/>
      <verse num="21">since their faces have been blackened by the smoke of the temple.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001022"/>
      <verse num="22">Bats, swallows, and birds light on their bodies and heads; and so do cats.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001023"/>
      <verse num="23">From this you will know that they are not gods; so do not revere them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001024"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="24">As for the gold that they wear for beauty&emdash;they will not shine unless someone wipes off the rust; for even when they were being cast, they had no feeling.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001025"/>
      <verse num="25">They are bought at any cost, but there is no breath in them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001026"/>
      <verse num="26">Having no feet, they are carried on attendants&apos; shoulders, revealing their worthlessness to all.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001027"/>
      <verse num="27">And those who serve them are ashamed because through them these gods<note nid="n76001027.1"/> are made to stand, lest they fall to the ground. If anyone sets one of them upright, it cannot move by itself; and if it is tipped over, it will never straighten itself; but gifts are placed before them just as before the dead.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001028"/>
      <verse num="28">The priests sell the sacrifices that are offered to these gods<note nid="n76001028.1"/> and use the money; and likewise their wives preserve some with salt, but share none with the poor or helpless.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001029"/>
      <verse num="29">Women in menstruation or after childbirth take part in their sacrifices. Since you know by these things that they are not gods, do not revere them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001030"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="30">For why should they be called gods? Because women serve meals for gods of silver and gold and wood?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001031"/>
      <verse num="31">Or because priests rush into their temples with their clothes rent, their heads and beards shaved, and their heads uncovered,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001032"/>
      <verse num="32">howling and shouting before their gods as some do at a funeral feast for a man who has died?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001033"/>
      <verse num="33">The priests take some of the clothing of their gods<note nid="n76001033.1"/> to clothe their wives and children.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001034"/>
      <verse num="34">Whether one does evil to them or good, they will not be able to repay it. They cannot set up a king or depose one.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001035"/>
      <verse num="35">Likewise they are unable to give either wealth or money; if one makes a vow to them and does not keep it, they will never enforce it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001036"/>
      <verse num="36">They will never save anyone from death or rescue the weak from the strong.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001037"/>
      <verse num="37">They will never restore sight to a blind person or rescue anyone who is in distress.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001038"/>
      <verse num="38">They will never take pity on a widow or do good to an orphan.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001039"/>
      <verse num="39">These things that are made of wood and overlaid with gold and silver are like stones from the mountain, and those who serve them will be put to shame.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001040"/>
      <verse num="40">Why then must anyone think that they are gods or call them gods?
        <end-paragraph/>
        <heading>Foolishness of Worshiping Idols</heading>
        <begin-paragraph/>Besides, even the Chaldeans themselves dishonor them;
      </verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001041"/>
      <verse num="41">for when they see a mute person who cannot speak, they bring him before Bel<note nid="n76001041.1"/> and think it appropriate to call out to him, as though Bel<note nid="n76001041.2"/> were able to understand.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001042"/>
      <verse num="42">Yet they themselves cannot perceive this and abandon their gods,<note nid="n76001042.1"/> for they have no sense.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001043"/>
      <verse num="43">And the women, with cords about them, sit along the passageways, burning bran for incense; and when one of them is led off by one of the passersby and is lain with, she derides the woman next to her, because she was not as attractive as herself and her cord was not broken.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001044"/>
      <verse num="44">Whatever is done for them is false. Why then must anyone think that they are gods or call them gods?</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001045"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="45">They are made by carpenters and goldsmiths; they can be nothing but what the artisans wish them to be.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001046"/>
      <verse num="46">Those who make them will certainly not live very long themselves; how then can the things that are made by them be gods?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001047"/>
      <verse num="47">They have left only lies and reproach for those who come after.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001048"/>
      <verse num="48">For when war or calamity comes upon them, the priests consult together as to where they can hide themselves and their gods.<note nid="n76001048.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001049"/>
      <verse num="49">How then can one fail to see that these are not gods, for they cannot save themselves from war or calamity?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001050"/>
      <verse num="50">Since they are made of wood and overlaid with gold and silver, it will afterward be known that they are false.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001051"/>
      <verse num="51">It will be apparent to all the nations and kings that they are not gods but the work of men&apos;s hands and that there is no work of God in them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001052"/>
      <verse num="52">Who then can fail to know that they are not gods?<note nid="n76001052.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001053"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="53">For they will never set up a king over a country or give rain to the people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001054"/>
      <verse num="54">They will never judge their own cause or deliver one who is wronged, for they have no power; they are like crows between heaven and earth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001055"/>
      <verse num="55">When fire breaks out in a temple of gods made of wood or overlaid with gold or silver, their priests will flee and escape, but the gods<note nid="n76001055.1"/> will be burnt in two like beams.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001056"/>
      <verse num="56">Besides, they will surely offer no resistance to a king or any enemies. Why then must anyone admit or think that they are gods?</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001057"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="57">Gods made of wood and overlaid with silver and gold will never save themselves from thieves and robbers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001058"/>
      <verse num="58">Strong men will strip them of their gold and silver and of the robes they wear and go off with this booty, and they will not be able to help themselves.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001059"/>
      <verse num="59">So it is better to be a king who shows his courage or a useful household utensil that serves its owner&apos;s need than to be these false gods; better even the door of a house that protects its contents than these false gods; better also a wooden pillar in a palace than these false gods.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001060"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="60">For sun and moon and stars, shining and sent forth for service, are obedient.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001061"/>
      <verse num="61">So also the lightning, when it flashes, is widely seen; and the wind likewise blows in every land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001062"/>
      <verse num="62">When God commands the clouds to go over the whole world, they carry out his command.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001063"/>
      <verse num="63">And the fire sent from above to consume mountains and woods does what it is ordered. But these idols<note nid="n76001063.1"/> are not to be compared with them in appearance or power.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001064"/>
      <verse num="64">Therefore one must not think that they are gods or call them gods, for they are unable either to decide a case or to do good to people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001065"/>
      <verse num="65">Since you know then that they are not gods, do not revere them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001066"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="66">For they will never curse or bless kings;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001067"/>
      <verse num="67">they will never show signs in the heavens and<note nid="n76001067.1"/> among the nations or shine like the sun or give light like the moon.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001068"/>
      <verse num="68">The wild beasts are better than they are, for they can flee to cover and help themselves.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001069"/>
      <verse num="69">So we have no evidence whatever that they are gods; therefore do not revere them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001070"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="70">Like a scarecrow in a cucumber bed, that guards nothing, so are their gods of wood, overlaid with gold and silver.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001071"/>
      <verse num="71">In the same way, their gods of wood, overlaid with gold and silver, are like a thornbush in a garden, on which every bird sits; or like a dead body cast out in the darkness.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001072"/>
      <verse num="72">By the purple and linen<note nid="n76001072.1"/> that rot upon them you will know that they are not gods; and they will finally themselves be consumed and be a reproach in the land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v76001073"/>
      <verse num="73">Better therefore is a just man who has no idols, for he will be far from reproach.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
  </book>
</crossway-bible>
