<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible translation="English Standard Version" revision="2018-3-26" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
<book title="Susanna" num="78">
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001001"/>
  <chapter num="1">
    <heading>Susanna&apos;s Beauty Attracts Two Elders</heading>
    <verse num="1">There was a man living in Babylon whose name was Joakim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001002"/>
    <verse num="2">And he took a wife named Susanna daughter of Hilkiah, a very beautiful woman and one who feared the Lord.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001003"/>
    <verse num="3">Her parents were righteous and had taught their daughter according to the law of Moses.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001004"/>
    <verse num="4">Joakim was very rich and had a spacious garden adjoining his house; and the Jews used to come to him because he was the most honored of them all.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001005"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5">In that year two elders from the people were appointed as judges. Concerning them the Lord had said: <q class="begin-double" qid="78001005.1" from="78001005.1" to="78001005.2"/>Iniquity came forth from Babylon, from elders who were judges, who were supposed to govern the people.<q class="end-double" qid="78001005.2" from="78001005.1" to="78001005.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001006"/>
    <verse num="6">These men were frequently at Joakim&apos;s house, and all who had lawsuits came to them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">When the people departed at noon, Susanna would go into her husband&apos;s garden to walk.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001008"/>
    <verse num="8">The two elders used to see her every day, going in and walking about, and they began to desire her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001009"/>
    <verse num="9">And they perverted their minds and turned away their eyes from looking to heaven or remembering righteous judgments.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001010"/>
    <verse num="10">Both were overwhelmed with passion for her, but they did not tell each other of their distress,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001011"/>
    <verse num="11">for they were ashamed to disclose their lustful desire to possess her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001012"/>
    <verse num="12">And they watched eagerly, day after day, to see her.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">They said to each other, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001013.1" from="78001013.1" to="78001013.2"/>Let us go home, for it is mealtime.<q class="end-double" qid="78001013.2" from="78001013.1" to="78001013.2"/> And when they went out, they parted from each other.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001014"/>
    <verse num="14">But turning back, they met again; and when each pressed the other for the reason, they confessed their lust. And then together they arranged for a time when they could find her alone.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001015"/>
    <heading>The Elders Attempt to Seduce Susanna</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">Once, while they were watching for an opportune day, she went in as before with only two maids and wished to bathe in the garden, for it was very hot.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001016"/>
    <verse num="16">And no one was there except the two elders, who had hid themselves and were watching her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001017"/>
    <verse num="17">She said to her maids, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001017.1" from="78001017.1" to="78001017.2"/>Bring me oil and ointments and shut the garden doors so that I may bathe.<q class="end-double" qid="78001017.2" from="78001017.1" to="78001017.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001018"/>
    <verse num="18">They did as she said, shut the garden doors, and went out by the side doors to bring what they had been commanded; and they did not see the elders, because they were hidden.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19">When the maids had gone out, the two elders rose and ran to her and said:</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001020"/>
    <verse num="20"><q class="begin-double" qid="78001020.1" from="78001020.1" to="78001021.1"/>Look, the garden doors are shut, no one sees us, and we lust for you; so give your consent and be with us.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001021"/>
    <verse num="21">If you refuse, we will testify against you that a young man was with you, and this was why you sent your maids away from you.<q class="end-double" qid="78001021.1" from="78001020.1" to="78001021.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">Susanna sighed deeply and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001022.1" from="78001022.1" to="78001023.1"/>I am hemmed in on every side. For if I do this thing, it is death for me; and if I do not, I shall not escape your hands.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001023"/>
    <verse num="23">I choose not to do it and to fall into your hands, rather than to sin in the sight of the Lord.<q class="end-double" qid="78001023.1" from="78001022.1" to="78001023.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001024"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24">Then Susanna cried out with a loud voice, and the two elders shouted against her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001025"/>
    <verse num="25">And one of them ran and opened the garden doors.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001026"/>
    <verse num="26">When the household servants heard the shouting in the garden, they rushed in at the side door to see what had happened to her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001027"/>
    <verse num="27">And when the elders told their tale, the servants were greatly ashamed, for nothing like this had ever been said about Susanna.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001028"/>
    <heading>The Elders Testify Against Susanna</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="28">The next day, when the people gathered to her husband Joakim, the two elders came, full of their wicked plot to have Susanna put to death. They said before the people,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001029"/>
    <verse num="29"><q class="begin-double" qid="78001029.1" from="78001029.1" to="78001029.2"/>Send for Susanna daughter of Hilkiah, who is the wife of Joakim.<q class="end-double" qid="78001029.2" from="78001029.1" to="78001029.2"/> So they sent for her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001030"/>
    <verse num="30">And she came, with her parents, her children, and all her kindred.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001031"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="31">Now Susanna was a woman of great refinement and beautiful in appearance.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001032"/>
    <verse num="32">As she was veiled, the wicked men ordered her to be unveiled, that they might feast upon her beauty.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001033"/>
    <verse num="33">But her family and friends and all who saw her wept.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001034"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="34">Then the two elders stood up in the midst of the people and laid their hands upon her head.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001035"/>
    <verse num="35">And she, weeping, looked up toward heaven, for her heart trusted in the Lord.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001036"/>
    <verse num="36">The elders said, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001036.1" from="78001036.1" to="78001041.1"/>As we were walking in the garden alone, this woman came in with two maids, shut the garden doors, and dismissed the maids.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001037"/>
    <verse num="37">Then a young man, who had been hidden, came to her and lay with her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001038"/>
    <verse num="38">We were in a corner of the garden, and when we saw this wickedness we ran to them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001039"/>
    <verse num="39">We saw them embracing, but we could not hold the man, for he was too strong for us, and he opened the doors and dashed out.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001040"/>
    <verse num="40">So we seized this woman and asked her who the young man was,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001041"/>
    <verse num="41">but she would not tell us. These things we testify.<q class="end-double" qid="78001041.1" from="78001036.1" to="78001041.1"/><end-paragraph/>
      <begin-paragraph/>The assembly believed them, because they were elders of the people and judges; and they condemned her to death.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001042"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="42">Then Susanna cried out with a loud voice and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001042.1" from="78001042.1" to="78001043.1"/>O eternal God, who does discern what is secret, who is aware of all things before they come to be,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001043"/>
    <verse num="43">you know that these men have borne false witness against me. And now I am to die! Yet I have done none of the things that they have wickedly invented against me!<q class="end-double" qid="78001043.1" from="78001042.1" to="78001043.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001044"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="44">The Lord heard her cry.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001045"/>
    <verse num="45">And as she was being led away to be put to death, God aroused the holy spirit of a young lad named Daniel;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001046"/>
    <verse num="46">and he cried with a loud voice, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001046.1" from="78001046.1" to="78001046.2"/>I am innocent of the blood of this woman.<q class="end-double" qid="78001046.2" from="78001046.1" to="78001046.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001047"/>
    <heading>Daniel Rescues Susanna</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="47">All the people turned to him and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001047.1" from="78001047.1" to="78001047.2"/>What is this that you have said?<q class="end-double" qid="78001047.2" from="78001047.1" to="78001047.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001048"/>
    <verse num="48">Taking his stand in the midst of them, he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001048.1" from="78001048.1" to="78001049.1"/>Are you such fools, you sons of Israel? Have you condemned a daughter of Israel without examination and without learning the facts?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001049"/>
    <verse num="49">Return to the place of judgment. For these men have borne false witness against her.<q class="end-double" qid="78001049.1" from="78001048.1" to="78001049.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001050"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="50">Then all the people returned in haste. And the elders said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001050.1" from="78001050.1" to="78001050.2"/>Come, sit among us and inform us, for God has given you that right.<q class="end-double" qid="78001050.2" from="78001050.1" to="78001050.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001051"/>
    <verse num="51">And Daniel said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001051.1" from="78001051.1" to="78001051.2"/>Separate them far from each other, and I will examine them.<q class="end-double" qid="78001051.2" from="78001051.1" to="78001051.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001052"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="52">When they were separated from each other, he summoned one of them and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001052.1" from="78001052.1" to="78001054.1"/>You old relic of wicked days, your sins have now come home, which you have committed in the past,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001053"/>
    <verse num="53">pronouncing unjust judgments, condemning the innocent, and letting the guilty go free, though the Lord said, <q class="begin-single" qid="78001053.1" from="78001053.1" to="78001053.2"/>Do not put to death an innocent and righteous person.<q class="end-single" qid="78001053.2" from="78001053.1" to="78001053.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001054"/>
    <verse num="54">Now then, if you really saw her, tell me this: Under what tree did you see them being intimate with each other?<q class="end-double" qid="78001054.1" from="78001052.1" to="78001054.1"/> He answered, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001054.2" from="78001054.2" to="78001054.3"/>Under a mastic tree.<q class="end-double" qid="78001054.3" from="78001054.2" to="78001054.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001055"/>
    <verse num="55">And Daniel said, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001055.1" from="78001055.1" to="78001055.2"/>Very well! You have lied against your own head, for the angel of God has received the sentence from God and will immediately cut<note nid="n78001055.1"/> you in two.<q class="end-double" qid="78001055.2" from="78001055.1" to="78001055.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001056"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="56">Then he put him aside and commanded them to bring the other. And he said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001056.1" from="78001056.1" to="78001058.1"/>You offspring of Canaan and not of Judah, beauty has deceived you and lust has perverted your heart.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001057"/>
    <verse num="57">This is how you both have been dealing with the daughters of Israel, and they were intimate with you through fear; but a daughter of Judah would not endure your wickedness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001058"/>
    <verse num="58">Now then, tell me: Under what tree did you catch them being intimate with each other?<q class="end-double" qid="78001058.1" from="78001056.1" to="78001058.1"/> He answered, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001058.2" from="78001058.2" to="78001058.3"/>Under an evergreen oak.<q class="end-double" qid="78001058.3" from="78001058.2" to="78001058.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001059"/>
    <verse num="59">And Daniel said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="78001059.1" from="78001059.1" to="78001059.2"/>Very well! You also have lied against your own head, for the angel of God is waiting with his sword to saw<note nid="n78001059.1"/> you in two, that he may destroy you both.<q class="end-double" qid="78001059.2" from="78001059.1" to="78001059.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001060"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="60">Then all the assembly shouted loudly and blessed God, who saves those who hope in him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001061"/>
    <verse num="61">And they rose against the two elders, for out of their own mouths Daniel had convicted them of bearing false witness; and they did to them as they had wickedly planned to do to their neighbor;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001062"/>
    <verse num="62">acting in accordance with the law of Moses, they put them to death. Thus innocent blood was saved that day.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001063"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="63">And Hilkiah and his wife praised God for their daughter Susanna, and so did Joakim her husband and all her kindred, because nothing shameful was found in her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v78001064"/>
    <verse num="64">And from that day onward Daniel had a great reputation among the people.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
</book>
</crossway-bible>
