<?xml version='1.0' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" translation="English Standard Version" revision="2018-3-26" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
  <book title="1 Maccabees" num="80">
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001001"/>
    <chapter num="1">
      <heading>Alexander the Great</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">After Alexander son of Philip the Macedonian, who came from the land of Kittim, had defeated<note nid="n80001001.2"/> King Darius of the Persians and the Medes, he succeeded him as king. (He had previously become king of Greece.)</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001002"/>
      <verse num="2">He fought many battles, conquered strongholds, and put to death the kings of the earth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001003"/>
      <verse num="3">He advanced to the ends of the earth and plundered many nations. When the earth became quiet before him, he was exalted, and his heart was lifted up.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001004"/>
      <verse num="4">He gathered a very strong army and ruled over countries, nations, and princes, and they became tributary to him.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">After this he fell sick and perceived that he was dying.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001006"/>
      <verse num="6">So he summoned his most honored officers, who had been brought up with him from youth, and divided his kingdom among them while he was still alive.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001007"/>
      <verse num="7">And after Alexander had reigned twelve years, he died.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001008"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="8">Then his officers seized control, each in his own place.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001009"/>
      <verse num="9">They all put on crowns after his death, and so did their sons after them for many years; and they caused many evils on the earth.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001010"/>
      <heading>Antiochus Epiphanes and Renegade Jews</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">From them came forth a sinful root, Antiochus Epiphanes son of King Antiochus; he had been a hostage in Rome. He began to reign in the 137th year<note nid="n80001010.1"/> of the kingdom of the Greeks.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001011"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="11">In those days lawless men came forth from Israel and misled many, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="80001011.1" from="80001011.1" to="80001011.2"/>Let us go and make a covenant with the Gentiles round about us, for since we separated from them many evils have come upon us.<q class="end-double" qid="80001011.2" from="80001011.1" to="80001011.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001012"/>
      <verse num="12">This proposal pleased them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001013"/>
      <verse num="13">and some of the people eagerly went to the king. He authorized them to observe the ordinances of the Gentiles.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001014"/>
      <verse num="14">So they built a gymnasium in Jerusalem, according to Gentile custom,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001015"/>
      <verse num="15">and removed the marks of circumcision and abandoned the holy covenant. They joined with the Gentiles and sold themselves to do evil.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001016"/>
      <heading>Antiochus in Egypt</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">When Antiochus saw that his kingdom was established, he determined to become king of the land of Egypt, that he might reign over both kingdoms.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001017"/>
      <verse num="17">So he invaded Egypt with a strong force, with chariots and elephants and with a large fleet.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001018"/>
      <verse num="18">He engaged King Ptolemy of Egypt in battle, and Ptolemy turned and fled before him, and many were wounded and fell.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001019"/>
      <verse num="19">And they captured the fortified cities in the land of Egypt, and he plundered the land of Egypt.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001020"/>
      <heading>Persecution of the Jews</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="20">After subduing Egypt, Antiochus returned in the 143rd year.<note nid="n80001020.1"/> He went up against Israel and came to Jerusalem with a strong force.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001021"/>
      <verse num="21">He arrogantly entered the sanctuary and took the golden altar, the lampstand for the light, and all its utensils.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001022"/>
      <verse num="22">He took also the table for the bread of the Presence, the cups for drink offerings, the bowls, the golden censers, the curtain, the crowns, and the gold decoration on the front of the temple; he stripped it all off.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001023"/>
      <verse num="23">He took the silver and the gold and the costly vessels; he took also the hidden treasures that he found.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001024"/>
      <verse num="24">Taking them all, he departed to his own land.<end-paragraph/><begin-block-indent/><begin-paragraph class="line-group"/><begin-line/>He committed deeds of murder<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and spoke with great arrogance.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001025"/>
      <verse num="25"><begin-line/>Israel mourned deeply in every community,<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001026"/>
      <verse num="26"><begin-line class="indent"/>rulers and elders groaned,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>maidens and young men became faint,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>the beauty of the women faded.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001027"/>
      <verse num="27"><begin-line/>Every bridegroom took up the lament;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>she who sat in the bridal chamber was mourning.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001028"/>
      <verse num="28"><begin-line/>Even the land shook for its inhabitants,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and all the house of Jacob was clothed with shame.<end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001029"/>
      <heading>Occupation of Jerusalem</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="29">Two years later the king sent to the cities of Judah a chief collector of tribute, and he came to Jerusalem with a large force.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001030"/>
      <verse num="30">Deceitfully he spoke peaceable words to them, and they believed him; but he suddenly fell upon the city, dealt it a severe blow, and destroyed many people of Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001031"/>
      <verse num="31">He plundered the city, burned it with fire, and tore down its houses and its surrounding walls.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001032"/>
      <verse num="32">And they took captive the women and children and took possession of the cattle.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001033"/>
      <verse num="33">Then they fortified the city of David with a great strong wall and strong towers, and it became their citadel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001034"/>
      <verse num="34">And they stationed there a sinful people, lawless men. These strengthened their position;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001035"/>
      <verse num="35">they stored up arms and food, and collecting the spoils of Jerusalem they stored them there and became a great snare.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001036"/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
      <verse num="36"><begin-line/>It became an ambush against the sanctuary,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>an evil adversary of Israel continually.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001037"/>
      <verse num="37"><begin-line/>On every side of the sanctuary they shed innocent blood;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>they even defiled the sanctuary.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001038"/>
      <verse num="38"><begin-line/>Because of them the residents of Jerusalem fled;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>she became a dwelling of strangers;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>she became strange to her offspring,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and her children forsook her.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001039"/>
      <verse num="39"><begin-line/>Her sanctuary became desolate as a desert;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>her feasts were turned into mourning,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>her Sabbaths into a reproach,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>her honor into contempt.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001040"/>
      <verse num="40"><begin-line/>Her dishonor now grew as great as her glory;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>her exaltation was turned into mourning.<end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001041"/>
      <heading>Installation of Gentile Cults</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="41">Then the king wrote to his whole kingdom that all should be one people</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001042"/>
      <verse num="42">and that each should give up his customs.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001043"/>
      <verse num="43">All the Gentiles accepted the command of the king. Many even from Israel gladly adopted his religion; they sacrificed to idols and profaned the Sabbath.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001044"/>
      <verse num="44">And the king sent letters by messengers to Jerusalem and the cities of Judah; he directed them to follow customs strange to the land,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001045"/>
      <verse num="45">to forbid whole burnt offerings and sacrifice and drink offering in the sanctuary, to profane Sabbaths and feasts,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001046"/>
      <verse num="46">to defile the sanctuary and the priests,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001047"/>
      <verse num="47">to build altars and sacred precincts and shrines for idols, to sacrifice swine and unclean animals,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001048"/>
      <verse num="48">and to leave their sons uncircumcised. They were to make themselves abominable by everything unclean and profane,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001049"/>
      <verse num="49">so that they should forget the law and change all the ordinances.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001050"/>
      <verse num="50"><q class="begin-double" qid="80001050.1" from="80001050.1" to="80001050.2"/>And whoever does not obey the command of the king shall die.<q class="end-double" qid="80001050.2" from="80001050.1" to="80001050.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001051"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="51">In such words he wrote to his whole kingdom. And he appointed inspectors over all the people and commanded the cities of Judah to offer sacrifice, city by city.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001052"/>
      <verse num="52">Many of the people, everyone who forsook the law, joined them, and they did evil in the land;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001053"/>
      <verse num="53">they drove Israel into hiding in every place of refuge they had.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001054"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="54">Now on the fifteenth day of Chislev, in the 145th year,<note nid="n80001054.1"/> they erected a desolating sacrilege upon the altar of whole burnt offering. They also built altars in the surrounding cities of Judah</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001055"/>
      <verse num="55">and burned incense at the doors of the houses and in the streets.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001056"/>
      <verse num="56">The books of the law that they found they tore to pieces and burned with fire.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001057"/>
      <verse num="57">Where the book of the covenant was found in the possession of anyone or if anyone adhered to the law, the decree of the king condemned him to death.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001058"/>
      <verse num="58">They kept using violence against Israel, against those found month after month in the cities.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001059"/>
      <verse num="59">And on the twenty-fifth day of the month they offered sacrifice on the altar that was upon the altar of whole burnt offering.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001060"/>
      <verse num="60">According to the decree, they put to death the women who had their children circumcised</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001061"/>
      <verse num="61">and their families and those who circumcised them; and they hung the infants from their mothers&apos; necks.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001062"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="62">But many in Israel stood firm and were resolved in their hearts not to eat unclean food.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001063"/>
      <verse num="63">They chose to die rather than to be defiled by food or to profane the holy covenant; and they did die.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80001064"/>
      <verse num="64">And very great wrath came upon Israel.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002001"/>
    <chapter num="2">
      <heading>Mattathias and His Sons</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">In those days Mattathias son of John, son of Simeon, a priest of the sons of Joarib, moved from Jerusalem and settled in Modein.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002002"/>
      <verse num="2">He had five sons, John surnamed Gaddi,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002003"/>
      <verse num="3">Simon called Thassi,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002004"/>
      <verse num="4">Judas called Maccabeus,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002005"/>
      <verse num="5">Eleazar called Avaran, and Jonathan called Apphus.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002006"/>
      <verse num="6">He saw the blasphemies being committed in Judah and Jerusalem</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002007"/>
      <verse num="7">and said:<end-paragraph/><begin-block-indent/><begin-paragraph class="line-group"/><begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="80002007.1" from="80002007.1" to="80002013.1"/>Alas! Why was I born to see this,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>the ruin of my people, the ruin of the holy city,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>and they lived there when it was given over to the enemy,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>the sanctuary given over to aliens?<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002008"/>
      <verse num="8"><begin-line/>Her temple has become like a man without honor;<note nid="n80002008.1"/><end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002009"/>
      <verse num="9"><begin-line class="indent"/>her glorious vessels have been carried into captivity.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>Her infants have been killed in her streets,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>her youths by the sword of the foe.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002010"/>
      <verse num="10"><begin-line/>What nation has not possessed her in its kingdom<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and has not seized her spoils?<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002011"/>
      <verse num="11"><begin-line/>All her adornment has been taken away;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>no longer free, she has become a slave.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002012"/>
      <verse num="12"><begin-line/>And behold, our holy place, our beauty,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and our glory have been laid waste;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>the Gentiles have profaned them.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002013"/>
      <verse num="13"><begin-line class="indent"/>Why should we live any longer?<q class="end-double" qid="80002013.1" from="80002007.1" to="80002013.1"/><end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002014"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="14">And Mattathias and his sons rent their clothes, put on sackcloth, and mourned greatly.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002015"/>
      <heading>Pagan Worship Refused</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="15">Then the king&apos;s officers who were enforcing the apostasy came to the city of Modein to make them offer sacrifice.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002016"/>
      <verse num="16">Many from Israel came to them; and Mattathias and his sons were assembled.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002017"/>
      <verse num="17">Then the king&apos;s officers spoke to Mattathias as follows: <q class="begin-double" qid="80002017.1" from="80002017.1" to="80002018.1"/>You are a leader, honored and great in this city, and supported by sons and brothers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002018"/>
      <verse num="18">Now be the first to come and do what the king commands, as all the Gentiles and the men of Judah and those that are left in Jerusalem have done. Then you and your sons will be numbered among the friends of the king, and you and your sons will be honored with silver and gold and many gifts.<q class="end-double" qid="80002018.1" from="80002017.1" to="80002018.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002019"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">But Mattathias answered and said in a loud voice: <q class="begin-double" qid="80002019.1" from="80002019.1" to="80002022.1"/>Even if all the nations that live under the rule of the king obey him and have chosen to do his commandments, departing each one from the religion of his fathers,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002020"/>
      <verse num="20">yet I and my sons and my brothers will live by the covenant of our fathers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002021"/>
      <verse num="21">Far be it from us to desert the law and the ordinances.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002022"/>
      <verse num="22">We will not obey the king&apos;s words by turning aside from our religion to the right hand or to the left.<q class="end-double" qid="80002022.1" from="80002019.1" to="80002022.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002023"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="23">When he had finished speaking these words, a Jew came forward in the sight of all to offer sacrifice upon the altar in Modein, according to the king&apos;s command.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002024"/>
      <verse num="24">When Mattathias saw it, he burned with zeal and his heart was stirred. He gave vent to righteous anger; he ran and slaughtered him upon the altar.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002025"/>
      <verse num="25">At the same time he killed the king&apos;s officer who was forcing them to sacrifice, and he tore down the altar.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002026"/>
      <verse num="26">Thus he burned with zeal for the law, as Phinehas did against Zimri son of Salom.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002027"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="27">Then Mattathias cried out in the city with a loud voice, saying: <q class="begin-double" qid="80002027.1" from="80002027.1" to="80002027.2"/>Let everyone who is zealous for the law and supports the covenant come out with me!<q class="end-double" qid="80002027.2" from="80002027.1" to="80002027.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002028"/>
      <verse num="28">And he and his sons fled to the hills and left all that they had in the city.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002029"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="29">Then many who were seeking righteousness and justice went down to the wilderness to dwell there,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002030"/>
      <verse num="30">they, their sons, their wives, and their cattle, because evils pressed heavily upon them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002031"/>
      <verse num="31">And it was reported to the king&apos;s officers and to the troops in Jerusalem the city of David that men who had rejected the king&apos;s command had gone down to the hiding places in the wilderness.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002032"/>
      <verse num="32">Many pursued them, and overtaking them, they encamped opposite them and prepared for battle against them on the Sabbath day.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002033"/>
      <verse num="33">And they said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="80002033.1" from="80002033.1" to="80002033.2"/>Enough of this! Come out and do what the king commands, and you will live.<q class="end-double" qid="80002033.2" from="80002033.1" to="80002033.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002034"/>
      <verse num="34">But they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80002034.1" from="80002034.1" to="80002034.2"/>We will not come out, nor will we do what the king commands and so profane the Sabbath day.<q class="end-double" qid="80002034.2" from="80002034.1" to="80002034.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002035"/>
      <verse num="35">Then the enemy<note nid="n80002035.1"/> hastened to attack them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002036"/>
      <verse num="36">But they did not answer them or hurl a stone at them or block up their hiding places,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002037"/>
      <verse num="37">for they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80002037.1" from="80002037.1" to="80002037.2"/>Let us all die in our innocence; heaven and earth testify for us that you are killing us unjustly.<q class="end-double" qid="80002037.2" from="80002037.1" to="80002037.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002038"/>
      <verse num="38">So they attacked them on the Sabbath, and they died, with their wives and children and cattle, to the number of 1,000 persons.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002039"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="39">When Mattathias and his friends learned of it, they mourned for them deeply.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002040"/>
      <verse num="40">And each said to his neighbor: <q class="begin-double" qid="80002040.1" from="80002040.1" to="80002040.2"/>If we all do as our brothers have done and refuse to fight with the Gentiles for our lives and our ordinances, they will quickly destroy us from the earth.<q class="end-double" qid="80002040.2" from="80002040.1" to="80002040.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002041"/>
      <verse num="41">So they made this decision that day: <q class="begin-double" qid="80002041.1" from="80002041.1" to="80002041.2"/>Let us fight against every man who comes to attack us on the Sabbath day; let us not all die as our brothers died in their hiding places.<q class="end-double" qid="80002041.2" from="80002041.1" to="80002041.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002042"/>
      <heading>Counterattack</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="42">Then there united with them a company of Hasideans, mighty warriors of Israel, everyone who offered himself willingly for the law.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002043"/>
      <verse num="43">And all who became fugitives to escape their troubles joined them and reinforced them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002044"/>
      <verse num="44">They organized an army and struck down sinners in their anger and lawless men in their wrath; the survivors fled to the Gentiles for safety.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002045"/>
      <verse num="45">And Mattathias and his friends went about and tore down the altars;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002046"/>
      <verse num="46">they forcibly circumcised all the uncircumcised boys that they found within the borders of Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002047"/>
      <verse num="47">They hunted down the arrogant men, and the work prospered in their hands.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002048"/>
      <verse num="48">They rescued the law out of the hands of the Gentiles and kings, and they never let the sinner gain the upper hand.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002049"/>
      <heading>Last Words of Mattathias</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="49">Now the days drew near for Mattathias to die, and he said to his sons: <q class="begin-double" qid="80002049.1" from="80002049.1" to="80002068.1"/>Arrogance and reproach have now become strong; it is a time of ruin and furious anger.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002050"/>
      <verse num="50">Now, my children, show zeal for the law and give your lives for the covenant of our fathers.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002051"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="51"><q class="continue-double" qid="80002051.1" from="80002049.1" to="80002068.1"/>Remember the deeds of the fathers, which they did in their generations; and receive great honor and an everlasting name.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002052"/>
      <verse num="52">Was not Abraham found faithful when tested, and it was reckoned to him as righteousness?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002053"/>
      <verse num="53">Joseph in the time of his distress kept the commandment and became lord of Egypt.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002054"/>
      <verse num="54">Phinehas our father, because he was deeply zealous, received the covenant of everlasting priesthood.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002055"/>
      <verse num="55">Joshua, because he fulfilled the command, became a judge in Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002056"/>
      <verse num="56">Caleb, because he testified in the assembly, received an inheritance in the land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002057"/>
      <verse num="57">David, because he was merciful, inherited the throne of the kingdom forever.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002058"/>
      <verse num="58">Elijah, because of great zeal for the law, was taken up into heaven.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002059"/>
      <verse num="59">Hananiah, Azariah, and Mishael believed and were saved from the flame.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002060"/>
      <verse num="60">Daniel, because of his innocence, was delivered from the mouth of the lions.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002061"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="61"><q class="continue-double" qid="80002061.1" from="80002049.1" to="80002068.1"/>And so observe, from generation to generation, that none who hope in him will lack strength.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002062"/>
      <verse num="62">Do not fear the words of a sinner, for his splendor will turn into dung and worms.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002063"/>
      <verse num="63">Today he will be exalted, but tomorrow he will not be found, because he has returned to the dust, and his plans will perish.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002064"/>
      <verse num="64">My children, be courageous and grow strong in the law, for by it you will gain honor.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002065"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="65"><q class="continue-double" qid="80002065.1" from="80002049.1" to="80002068.1"/>Now behold, I know that Simeon your brother is wise in counsel; always listen to him; he shall be your father.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002066"/>
      <verse num="66">Judas Maccabeus has been a mighty warrior from his youth; he shall command the army for you and fight the battle against<note nid="n80002066.1"/> the peoples.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002067"/>
      <verse num="67">You shall rally about you all who observe the law and avenge the wrong done to your people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002068"/>
      <verse num="68">Pay back the Gentiles in full and heed what the law commands.<q class="end-double" qid="80002068.1" from="80002049.1" to="80002068.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002069"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="69">Then he blessed them and was gathered to his fathers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80002070"/>
      <verse num="70">He died in the 146th year<note nid="n80002070.1"/> and was buried in the tomb of his fathers at Modein. And all Israel mourned for him with great lamentation.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003001"/>
    <chapter num="3">
      <heading>Early Victories of Judas</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Then Judas his son, who was called Maccabeus, took command in his place.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003002"/>
      <verse num="2">All his brothers and all who had joined his father helped him; they gladly fought for Israel.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003003"/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
      <verse num="3"><begin-line/>He extended the glory of his people.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>Like a giant he put on his breastplate;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>he girded on his armor of war and waged battles,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>protecting the host by his sword.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003004"/>
      <verse num="4"><begin-line/>He was like a lion in his deeds,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>like a lion&apos;s cub roaring for prey.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003005"/>
      <verse num="5"><begin-line/>He searched out and pursued the lawless;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>he burned those who troubled his people.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003006"/>
      <verse num="6"><begin-line/>Lawless men shrank back for fear of him;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>all the evildoers were confounded;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and deliverance prospered by his hand.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003007"/>
      <verse num="7"><begin-line/>He embittered many kings,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>but he made Jacob glad by his deeds,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and his memory is blessed forever.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003008"/>
      <verse num="8"><begin-line/>He went through the cities of Judah;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>he destroyed the ungodly out of the land;<note nid="n80003008.1"/><end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>thus he turned away wrath from Israel.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003009"/>
      <verse num="9"><begin-line/>He was renowned to the ends of the earth;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>he gathered in those who were perishing.<end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003010"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">But Apollonius gathered together Gentiles and a large force from Samaria to fight against Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003011"/>
      <verse num="11">When Judas learned of it, he went out to meet him, and he defeated and killed him. Many were wounded and fell, and the rest fled.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003012"/>
      <verse num="12">Then they seized their spoils; and Judas took the sword of Apollonius and used it in battle the rest of his life.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003013"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="13">Now when Seron, the commander of the Syrian army, heard that Judas had gathered a large company, including a body of faithful men who stayed with him and went out to battle,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003014"/>
      <verse num="14">he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80003014.1" from="80003014.1" to="80003014.2"/>I will make a name for myself and win honor in the kingdom. I will make war on Judas and his companions, who scorn the king&apos;s command.<q class="end-double" qid="80003014.2" from="80003014.1" to="80003014.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003015"/>
      <verse num="15">And again a strong army of ungodly men went up with him to help him, to take vengeance on the sons of Israel.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003016"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">When he approached the ascent of Beth-horon, Judas went out to meet him with a small company.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003017"/>
      <verse num="17">But when they saw the army coming to meet them, they said to Judas, <q class="begin-double" qid="80003017.1" from="80003017.1" to="80003017.2"/>How can we, few as we are, fight against so great and strong a multitude? And we are faint, for we have eaten nothing today.<q class="end-double" qid="80003017.2" from="80003017.1" to="80003017.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003018"/>
      <verse num="18">Judas replied, <q class="begin-double" qid="80003018.1" from="80003018.1" to="80003022.1"/>It is easy for many to be hemmed in by few, for in the sight of heaven there is no difference between saving by many or by few.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003019"/>
      <verse num="19">It is not on the size of the army that victory in battle depends, but strength comes from heaven.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003020"/>
      <verse num="20">They come against us in great pride and lawlessness to destroy us and our wives and our children and to despoil us;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003021"/>
      <verse num="21">but we fight for our lives and our laws.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003022"/>
      <verse num="22">He himself will crush them before us; as for you, do not be afraid of them.<q class="end-double" qid="80003022.1" from="80003018.1" to="80003022.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003023"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="23">When he finished speaking, he rushed suddenly against Seron and his army, and they were crushed before him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003024"/>
      <verse num="24">They pursued him down the descent of Beth-horon to the plain; 800 of them fell, and the rest fled into the land of the Philistines.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003025"/>
      <verse num="25">Then Judas and his brothers began to be feared, and terror fell upon the Gentiles round about them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003026"/>
      <verse num="26">His fame reached the king, and the Gentiles talked of the battles of Judas.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003027"/>
      <heading>Policy of Antiochus</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="27">When King Antiochus heard these reports, he was greatly angered; and he sent and gathered all the forces of his kingdom, a very strong army.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003028"/>
      <verse num="28">And he opened his coffers and gave a year&apos;s pay to his forces and ordered them to be ready for any need.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003029"/>
      <verse num="29">Then he saw that the money in the treasury was exhausted and that the revenues from the country were small because of the dissension and disaster that he had caused in the land by abolishing the laws that had existed from the earliest days.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003030"/>
      <verse num="30">He feared that he might not have such funds as he had before for his expenses and for the gifts that he used to give more lavishly than preceding kings.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003031"/>
      <verse num="31">He was greatly perplexed in mind and determined to go to Persia and collect the revenues from those regions and raise a large fund.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003032"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="32">He left Lysias, a distinguished man of royal lineage, in charge of the king&apos;s affairs from the river Euphrates to the borders of Egypt.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003033"/>
      <verse num="33">Lysias was also to take care of Antiochus his son until he returned.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003034"/>
      <verse num="34">And he turned over to Lysias<note nid="n80003034.1"/> half of his troops and the elephants and gave him orders about all that he wanted done. As for the residents of Judea and Jerusalem,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003035"/>
      <verse num="35">Lysias was to send a force against them to wipe out and destroy the strength of Israel and the remnant of Jerusalem; he was to banish the memory of them from the place,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003036"/>
      <verse num="36">settle aliens in all their territory, and distribute their land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003037"/>
      <verse num="37">Then the king took the remaining half of his troops and departed from Antioch his capital in the 147th year.<note nid="n80003037.1"/> He crossed the Euphrates river and went through the upper provinces.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003038"/>
      <heading>Preparations for Battle</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="38">Lysias chose Ptolemy son of Dorymenes and Nicanor and Gorgias, mighty men among the friends of the king,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003039"/>
      <verse num="39">and sent with them 40,000 infantry and 7,000 cavalry to go into the land of Judah and destroy it, as the king had commanded.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003040"/>
      <verse num="40">So they departed with their entire force, and when they arrived they encamped near Emmaus in the plain.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003041"/>
      <verse num="41">When the traders of the region heard what was said of them, they took silver and gold in immense amounts and fetters<note nid="n80003041.1"/> and went to the camp to get the sons of Israel for slaves. And forces from Syria and the land of the Philistines joined with them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003042"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="42">Now Judas and his brothers saw that misfortunes had increased and that the forces were encamped in their territory. They also learned what the king had commanded to do to the people to cause their final destruction.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003043"/>
      <verse num="43">But they said to one another, <q class="begin-double" qid="80003043.1" from="80003043.1" to="80003043.2"/>Let us repair the destruction of our people and fight for our people and the sanctuary.<q class="end-double" qid="80003043.2" from="80003043.1" to="80003043.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003044"/>
      <verse num="44">And the congregation assembled to be ready for battle and to pray and ask for mercy and compassion.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003045"/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
      <verse num="45"><begin-line/>Jerusalem was uninhabited like a wilderness;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>not one of her children went in or out.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>The sanctuary was trampled down,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and the sons of aliens held the citadel;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>it was a lodging place for the Gentiles.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>Joy was taken from Jacob;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>the flute and the harp ceased to play.<end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003046"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="46">So they assembled and went to Mizpah, opposite Jerusalem, because Israel formerly had a place of prayer in Mizpah.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003047"/>
      <verse num="47">They fasted that day, put on sackcloth and sprinkled ashes on their heads, and rent their clothes.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003048"/>
      <verse num="48">And they opened the book of the law to inquire into those matters about which the Gentiles were consulting the images of their idols.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003049"/>
      <verse num="49">They also brought the garments of the priesthood and the firstfruits and the tithes, and they stirred up the Nazirites who had completed their days;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003050"/>
      <verse num="50">and they cried aloud to heaven, saying:<end-paragraph/><begin-block-indent/><begin-paragraph class="line-group"/><begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="80003050.1" from="80003050.1" to="80003053.1"/>What shall we do with these?<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>Where shall we take them?<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003051"/>
      <verse num="51"><begin-line/>Your sanctuary is trampled down and profaned,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and your priests mourn in humiliation.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003052"/>
      <verse num="52"><begin-line/>And behold, the Gentiles are assembled against us to destroy us;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>you know what they plot against us.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003053"/>
      <verse num="53"><begin-line/>How will we be able to withstand them,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>if you do not help us?<q class="end-double" qid="80003053.1" from="80003050.1" to="80003053.1"/><end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003054"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="54">Then they sounded the trumpets and gave a loud shout.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003055"/>
      <verse num="55">After this Judas appointed leaders of the people, in charge of thousands and hundreds and fifties and tens.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003056"/>
      <verse num="56">And he said to those who were building houses or were betrothed or were planting vineyards or were fainthearted that each should return to his home, according to the law.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003057"/>
      <verse num="57">Then the army marched out and encamped to the south of Emmaus.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003058"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="58">And Judas said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80003058.1" from="80003058.1" to="80003060.1"/>Gird yourselves and be valiant. Be ready early in the morning to fight with these Gentiles who have assembled against us to destroy us and our sanctuary.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003059"/>
      <verse num="59">It is better for us to die in battle than to see the misfortunes of our nation and of the sanctuary.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80003060"/>
      <verse num="60">But as his will in heaven may be, so he will do.<q class="end-double" qid="80003060.1" from="80003058.1" to="80003060.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004001"/>
    <chapter num="4">
      <heading>Battle at Emmaus</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Now Gorgias took 5,000 infantry and 1,000 picked cavalry, and this division moved out by night</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004002"/>
      <verse num="2">to fall upon the camp of the Jews and attack them suddenly. Men from the citadel were his guides.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004003"/>
      <verse num="3">But Judas heard of it, and he and his mighty men moved out to attack the king&apos;s force in Emmaus</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004004"/>
      <verse num="4">while the division was still absent from the camp.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004005"/>
      <verse num="5">When Gorgias entered the camp of Judas by night, he found no one there, so he looked for them in the hills, because he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80004005.1" from="80004005.1" to="80004005.2"/>These men are fleeing from us.<q class="end-double" qid="80004005.2" from="80004005.1" to="80004005.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004006"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="6">At daybreak Judas appeared in the plain with 3,000 men, but they did not have armor<note nid="n80004006.1"/> and swords such as they desired.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004007"/>
      <verse num="7">And they saw the camp of the Gentiles, strong and fortified, with cavalry round about it; and these men were trained in war.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004008"/>
      <verse num="8">But Judas said to the men who were with him, <q class="begin-double" qid="80004008.1" from="80004008.1" to="80004011.1"/>Do not fear their numbers or be afraid when they charge.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004009"/>
      <verse num="9">Remember how our fathers were saved at the Red Sea, when Pharaoh with his forces pursued them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004010"/>
      <verse num="10">And now let us cry to heaven, to see whether he will favor us and remember his covenant with our fathers and crush this army before us today.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004011"/>
      <verse num="11">Then all the Gentiles will know that there is one who redeems and saves Israel.<q class="end-double" qid="80004011.1" from="80004008.1" to="80004011.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004012"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="12">When the foreigners looked up and saw them coming against them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004013"/>
      <verse num="13">they went forth from their camp to battle. Then the men with Judas blew their trumpets</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004014"/>
      <verse num="14">and engaged in battle. The Gentiles were crushed and fled into the plain,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004015"/>
      <verse num="15">and all those in the rear fell by the sword. They pursued them to Gazara and to the plains of Idumea and to Azotus and Jamnia; and 3,000 of them fell.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004016"/>
      <verse num="16">Then Judas and his force turned back from pursuing them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004017"/>
      <verse num="17">and he said to the people, <q class="begin-double" qid="80004017.1" from="80004017.1" to="80004018.1"/>Do not be greedy for plunder, for there is a battle before us;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004018"/>
      <verse num="18">Gorgias and his force are near us in the hills. But stand now against our enemies and fight them and afterward seize the plunder boldly.<q class="end-double" qid="80004018.1" from="80004017.1" to="80004018.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004019"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">Just as Judas was finishing this speech, a detachment was seen, peering out of the hills.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004020"/>
      <verse num="20">They saw that their army<note nid="n80004020.1"/> had been put to flight and that the Jews<note nid="n80004020.2"/> were burning the camp, for the smoke that was seen showed what had happened.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004021"/>
      <verse num="21">When they perceived this they were greatly frightened and when they also saw the army of Judas drawn up in the plain for battle,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004022"/>
      <verse num="22">they all fled into the land of the Philistines.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004023"/>
      <verse num="23">Then Judas returned to plunder the camp, and they seized much gold and silver and cloth dyed blue and sea purple and great riches.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004024"/>
      <verse num="24">On their return they sang hymns and praises to heaven, for he is good, for his mercy endures forever.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004025"/>
      <verse num="25">Thus Israel had a great deliverance that day.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004026"/>
      <heading>First Campaign of Lysias</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="26">Those of the foreigners who escaped went and reported to Lysias all that had happened.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004027"/>
      <verse num="27">When he heard it, he was perplexed and discouraged, for things had not happened to Israel as he had intended, nor had they turned out as the king had commanded him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004028"/>
      <verse num="28">But the next year he mustered 60,000 picked infantrymen and 5,000 cavalry to subdue them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004029"/>
      <verse num="29">They came into Idumea and encamped at Beth-zur, and Judas met them with 10,000 men.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004030"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="30">When he saw that the army was strong, he prayed, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="80004030.1" from="80004030.1" to="80004033.1"/>Blessed are you, O Savior of Israel, who crushed the attack of the mighty warrior by the hand of your servant David and gave the camp of the Philistines into the hands of Jonathan son of Saul and of the man who carried his armor.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004031"/>
      <verse num="31">So do you hem in this army by the hand of your people Israel, and let them be ashamed of their troops and their cavalry.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004032"/>
      <verse num="32">Fill them with cowardice; melt the boldness of their strength; let them tremble in their destruction.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004033"/>
      <verse num="33">Strike them down with the sword of those who love you, and let all who know your name praise you with hymns.<q class="end-double" qid="80004033.1" from="80004030.1" to="80004033.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004034"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="34">Then both sides attacked, and there fell of the army of Lysias 5,000 men; they fell from before them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004035"/>
      <verse num="35">And when Lysias saw the rout of his troops and observed the boldness that inspired those of Judas and how ready they were either to live or to die nobly, he departed to Antioch and enlisted mercenaries, to invade Judea when they were numerous again.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004036"/>
      <heading>Cleansing and Dedication of the Temple</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="36">Then said Judas and his brothers, <q class="begin-double" qid="80004036.1" from="80004036.1" to="80004036.2"/>Behold, our enemies are crushed; let us go up to cleanse the sanctuary and dedicate it.<q class="end-double" qid="80004036.2" from="80004036.1" to="80004036.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004037"/>
      <verse num="37">So all the army assembled and they went up to Mount Zion.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004038"/>
      <verse num="38">And they saw the sanctuary desolate, the altar profaned, and the gates burned. In the courts they saw bushes sprung up as in a thicket or as on one of the mountains. They saw also the chambers of the priests in ruins.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004039"/>
      <verse num="39">Then they rent their clothes and mourned with great lamentation and sprinkled themselves with ashes.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004040"/>
      <verse num="40">They fell face down on the ground and sounded the signal on the trumpets and cried out to heaven.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004041"/>
      <verse num="41">Then Judas detailed men to fight against those in the citadel until he had cleansed the sanctuary.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004042"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="42">He chose blameless priests devoted to the law,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004043"/>
      <verse num="43">and they cleansed the sanctuary and removed the defiled stones to an unclean place.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004044"/>
      <verse num="44">They deliberated what to do about the altar of whole burnt offering, which had been profaned.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004045"/>
      <verse num="45">And they thought it best to tear it down, lest it bring reproach upon them, for the Gentiles had defiled it. So they tore down the altar</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004046"/>
      <verse num="46">and stored the stones in a convenient place on the temple hill until there should come a prophet to tell what to do with them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004047"/>
      <verse num="47">Then they took whole stones, as the law directs, and built a new altar like the former one.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004048"/>
      <verse num="48">They also rebuilt the sanctuary and the interior of the temple and consecrated the courts.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004049"/>
      <verse num="49">They made new holy vessels and brought the lampstand, the altar of incense, and the table into the temple.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004050"/>
      <verse num="50">Then they burned incense on the altar and lighted the lamps on the lampstand, and these gave light in the temple.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004051"/>
      <verse num="51">They placed the bread on the table and hung up the curtains. Thus they finished all the work they had undertaken.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004052"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="52">Early in the morning on the twenty-fifth day of the ninth month, which is the month of Chislev, in the 148th year,<note nid="n80004052.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004053"/>
      <verse num="53">they rose and offered sacrifice, as the law directs, on the new altar of whole burnt offering that they had built.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004054"/>
      <verse num="54">At the very season and on the very day that the Gentiles had profaned it, it was dedicated with songs and harps and lutes and cymbals.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004055"/>
      <verse num="55">All the people fell on their faces and worshiped and blessed heaven, who had prospered them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004056"/>
      <verse num="56">So they celebrated the dedication of the altar for eight days and offered whole burnt offerings with gladness; they offered a sacrifice of deliverance and praise.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004057"/>
      <verse num="57">They decorated the front of the temple with golden crowns and small shields; they restored the gates and the chambers for the priests and furnished them with doors.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004058"/>
      <verse num="58">There was very great gladness among the people, and the reproach of the Gentiles was removed.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004059"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="59">Then Judas and his brothers and all the assembly of Israel determined that every year at that season the days of the dedication of the altar should be observed with gladness and joy for eight days, beginning with the twenty-fifth day of the month of Chislev.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004060"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="60">At that time they fortified Mount Zion with high walls and strong towers round about, to keep the Gentiles from coming and trampling them down as they had done before.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80004061"/>
      <verse num="61">And he stationed a garrison there to hold it, and he fortified it to hold Beth-zur, so that the people might have a stronghold that faced Idumea.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005001"/>
    <chapter num="5">
      <heading>Wars with Neighboring Peoples</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">When the Gentiles round about heard that the altar had been built and the sanctuary dedicated as it was before, they became very angry,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005002"/>
      <verse num="2">and they determined to destroy the descendants of Jacob who lived among them. So they began to kill and destroy among the people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005003"/>
      <verse num="3">But Judas made war on the sons of Esau in Idumea, at Akrabattene, because they kept lying in wait for Israel. He dealt them a heavy blow and humbled them and despoiled them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005004"/>
      <verse num="4">He also remembered the wickedness of the sons of Baean, who were a trap and a snare to the people and ambushed them on the highways.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005005"/>
      <verse num="5">They were shut up by him in their towers; and he encamped against them, vowed their complete destruction, and burned with fire its towers and all who were inside.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005006"/>
      <verse num="6">Then he crossed over to attack the Ammonites, where he found a strong band and many people with Timothy as their leader.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005007"/>
      <verse num="7">He engaged in many battles with them, and they were crushed before him; he struck them down.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005008"/>
      <verse num="8">He also overtook Jazer and its villages; then he returned to Judea.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005009"/>
      <heading>Liberation of Galilean Jews</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="9">Now the Gentiles in Gilead gathered together against the Israelites who lived in their territory and planned to destroy them. But they fled to the stronghold of Dathema</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005010"/>
      <verse num="10">and sent to Judas and his brothers a letter that said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80005010.1" from="80005010.1" to="80005013.1"/>The Gentiles around us have gathered together against us to destroy us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005011"/>
      <verse num="11">They are preparing to come and capture the stronghold to which we have fled, and Timothy is leading their forces.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005012"/>
      <verse num="12">Now then come and rescue us from their hands, for many of us have fallen,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005013"/>
      <verse num="13">and all our brothers who were in the land of Tob have been killed; the enemy<note nid="n80005013.1"/> have captured their wives and children and goods and have destroyed about 1,000 men there.<q class="end-double" qid="80005013.1" from="80005010.1" to="80005013.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005014"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="14">While the letter was still being read, behold, other messengers, with their garments rent, came from Galilee and made a similar report;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005015"/>
      <verse num="15">they said that against them had gathered together men of Ptolemais and Tyre and Sidon and all Galilee of the Gentiles<note nid="n80005015.1"/> <q class="begin-double" qid="80005015.1" from="80005015.1" to="80005015.2"/>to annihilate us.<q class="end-double" qid="80005015.2" from="80005015.1" to="80005015.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005016"/>
      <verse num="16">When Judas and the people heard these messages, a great assembly was called to determine what they should do for their brothers who were in distress and were being attacked by enemies.<note nid="n80005016.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005017"/>
      <verse num="17">Then Judas said to Simon his brother, <q class="begin-double" qid="80005017.1" from="80005017.1" to="80005017.2"/>Choose your men and go and rescue your brothers in Galilee; I and Jonathan my brother will go to Gilead.<q class="end-double" qid="80005017.2" from="80005017.1" to="80005017.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005018"/>
      <verse num="18">But he left Joseph son of Zechariah and Azariah, a leader of the people, with the rest of the forces, in Judea for defense;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005019"/>
      <verse num="19">and he gave them this command, <q class="begin-double" qid="80005019.1" from="80005019.1" to="80005019.2"/>Take charge of this people, but do not engage in battle with the Gentiles until we return.<q class="end-double" qid="80005019.2" from="80005019.1" to="80005019.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005020"/>
      <verse num="20">Then 3,000 men were assigned to Simon to go to Galilee, and 8,000 to Judas for Gilead.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005021"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="21">So Simon went to Galilee and fought many battles against the Gentiles, and the Gentiles were crushed before him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005022"/>
      <verse num="22">He pursued them to the gate of Ptolemais, and as many as 3,000 of the Gentiles fell, and he despoiled them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005023"/>
      <verse num="23">Then he took the Jews<note nid="n80005023.1"/> of Galilee and Arbatta, with their wives and children and all they possessed, and led them to Judea with great rejoicing.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005024"/>
      <heading>Judas and Jonathan in Gilead</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="24">Judas Maccabeus and Jonathan his brother crossed the Jordan and went three days&apos; journey into the wilderness.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005025"/>
      <verse num="25">They encountered the Nabateans, who met them peaceably and told them all that had happened to their brothers in Gilead:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005026"/>
      <verse num="26"><q class="begin-double" qid="80005026.1" from="80005026.1" to="80005026.2"/>Many of them have been shut up in Bozrah and Bosor, in Alema and Chaspho, Maked and Carnaim<q class="end-double" qid="80005026.2" from="80005026.1" to="80005026.2"/>&emdash;all these cities were strong and large&emdash;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005027"/>
      <verse num="27"><q class="begin-double" qid="80005027.1" from="80005027.1" to="80005027.2"/>and some have been shut up in the other cities of Gilead; the enemy is<note nid="n80005027.1"/> getting ready to attack the strongholds tomorrow and take and destroy all these people in one day.<q class="end-double" qid="80005027.2" from="80005027.1" to="80005027.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005028"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="28">Then Judas and his army quickly turned back by the wilderness road to Bozrah; and he took the city and killed every male by the edge of the sword; then he seized all its spoils and burned it with fire.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005029"/>
      <verse num="29">He departed from there at night, and they went all the way to the stronghold of Dathema.<note nid="n80005029.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005030"/>
      <verse num="30">At dawn they looked up, and behold, a large company, that could not be counted, carrying ladders and engines of war to capture the stronghold, and they were attacking them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005031"/>
      <verse num="31">So Judas saw that the battle had begun and that the cry of the city went up to heaven with trumpets and loud shouts,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005032"/>
      <verse num="32">and he said to the men of his forces, <q class="begin-double" qid="80005032.1" from="80005032.1" to="80005032.2"/>Fight today for your brothers!<q class="end-double" qid="80005032.2" from="80005032.1" to="80005032.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005033"/>
      <verse num="33">Then he came up behind them in three companies, who sounded their trumpets and cried aloud in prayer.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005034"/>
      <verse num="34">And when the army of Timothy realized that it was Maccabeus, they fled before him, and he dealt them a heavy blow. As many as 8,000 of them fell that day.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005035"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="35">Next he turned aside to Maapha<note nid="n80005035.1"/> and fought against it and took it; and he killed every male in it, plundered it, and burned it with fire.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005036"/>
      <verse num="36">From there he marched on and took Chaspho, Maked, and Bosor and the other cities of Gilead.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005037"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="37">After these things Timothy gathered another army and encamped opposite Raphon, on the other side of the stream.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005038"/>
      <verse num="38">Judas sent men to spy out the camp, and they reported to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="80005038.1" from="80005038.1" to="80005039.1"/>All the Gentiles around us have gathered to him; it is a very large force.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005039"/>
      <verse num="39">They also have hired Arabs to help them, and they are encamped across the stream, ready to come and fight against you.<q class="end-double" qid="80005039.1" from="80005038.1" to="80005039.1"/> And Judas went to meet them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005040"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="40">Now as Judas and his army drew near to the stream of water, Timothy said to the officers of his forces, <q class="begin-double" qid="80005040.1" from="80005040.1" to="80005041.1"/>If he crosses over to us first, we will not be able to resist him, for he will surely defeat us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005041"/>
      <verse num="41">But if he shows fear and camps on the other side of the river, we will cross over to him and defeat him.<q class="end-double" qid="80005041.1" from="80005040.1" to="80005041.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005042"/>
      <verse num="42">When Judas approached the stream of water, he stationed the scribes of the people at the stream and gave them this command, <q class="begin-double" qid="80005042.1" from="80005042.1" to="80005042.2"/>Permit no man to encamp, but make them all enter the battle.<q class="end-double" qid="80005042.2" from="80005042.1" to="80005042.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005043"/>
      <verse num="43">Then he crossed over against them first, and the whole army followed him. All the Gentiles were defeated before him, and they threw away their arms and fled into the sacred precincts at Carnaim.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005044"/>
      <verse num="44">But he took the city and burned the sacred precinct with fire, together with all who were in it. Thus Carnaim was conquered; they could stand before Judas no longer.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005045"/>
      <heading>Return to Jerusalem</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="45">Then Judas gathered together all the Israelites in Gilead, the small and the great, with their wives and children and goods, a very large company, to go to the land of Judah.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005046"/>
      <verse num="46">So they came to Ephron. This was a large and very strong city on the road, and they could not go round it to the right or to the left; they had to go through the middle of it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005047"/>
      <verse num="47">But the men of the city shut them out and blocked up the gates with stones.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005048"/>
      <verse num="48">And Judas sent them this friendly message, <q class="begin-double" qid="80005048.1" from="80005048.1" to="80005048.2"/>Let us pass through your land to get to our land. No one will do you harm; we will simply pass by on foot.<q class="end-double" qid="80005048.2" from="80005048.1" to="80005048.2"/> But they refused to open to him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005049"/>
      <verse num="49">Then Judas ordered proclamation to be made to the army that each should encamp where he was.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005050"/>
      <verse num="50">So the men of the forces encamped, and he fought against the city all that day and all the night, and the city was delivered into his hands.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005051"/>
      <verse num="51">He destroyed every male by the edge of the sword and razed and plundered the city. Then he passed through the city over the slain.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005052"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="52">And they crossed the Jordan into the large plain before Beth-shan.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005053"/>
      <verse num="53">And Judas kept rallying the stragglers and encouraging the people all the way till he came to the land of Judah.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005054"/>
      <verse num="54">So they went up to Mount Zion with gladness and joy and offered whole burnt offerings, because not one of them had fallen before they returned in safety.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005055"/>
      <heading>Joseph and Azariah Defeated</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="55">Now while Judas and Jonathan were in Gilead and Simon his brother was in Galilee before Ptolemais,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005056"/>
      <verse num="56">Joseph son of Zechariah and Azariah, the commanders of the forces, heard of their brave deeds and of the heroic war they had fought.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005057"/>
      <verse num="57">So they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80005057.1" from="80005057.1" to="80005057.2"/>Let us also make a name for ourselves; let us go and make war on the Gentiles around us.<q class="end-double" qid="80005057.2" from="80005057.1" to="80005057.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005058"/>
      <verse num="58">And they issued orders to the men of the forces that were with them, and they marched against Jamnia.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005059"/>
      <verse num="59">And Gorgias and his men came out of the city to meet them in battle.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005060"/>
      <verse num="60">Then Joseph and Azariah were routed and were pursued to the borders of Judea; as many as 2,000 of the people of Israel fell that day.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005061"/>
      <verse num="61">Thus the people suffered a great rout because, thinking to do a brave deed, they did not listen to Judas and his brothers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005062"/>
      <verse num="62">But they did not belong to the family of those men through whom deliverance was given to Israel.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005063"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="63">The man Judas and his brothers were greatly honored in all Israel and among all the Gentiles, wherever their name was heard.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005064"/>
      <verse num="64">Men gathered to them and praised them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005065"/>
      <heading>Success at Hebron and Philistia</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="65">Then Judas and his brothers went forth and fought the sons of Esau in the land to the south. He struck Hebron and its villages and tore down its strongholds and burned its towers round about.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005066"/>
      <verse num="66">Then he marched off to go into the land of the Philistines and passed through Marisa.<note nid="n80005066.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005067"/>
      <verse num="67">On that day some priests, who wished to do a brave deed, fell in battle, for they went out to battle unwisely.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80005068"/>
      <verse num="68">But Judas turned aside to Azotus in the land of the Philistines; he tore down their altars, and the carved images of their gods he burned with fire; he plundered the cities and returned to the land of Judah.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006001"/>
    <chapter num="6">
      <heading>Last Days of Antiochus Epiphanes</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">King Antiochus was going through the upper provinces when he heard that Elymais in Persia was a city famed for its wealth in silver and gold.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006002"/>
      <verse num="2">Its temple was very rich, containing golden shields,<note nid="n80006002.1"/> breastplates, and weapons left there by Alexander son of Philip, the Macedonian king who first reigned over the Greeks.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006003"/>
      <verse num="3">So he came and tried to take the city and plunder it, but he could not, because his plan became known to the men of the city</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006004"/>
      <verse num="4">and they withstood him in battle. So he fled and in great grief departed from there to return to Babylon.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">Then someone came to him in Persia and reported that the armies that had gone into the land of Judah had been routed;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006006"/>
      <verse num="6">that Lysias had gone first with a strong force, but was turned back before the Jews;<note nid="n80006006.1"/> that the Jews<note nid="n80006006.2"/> had grown strong from the arms, supplies, and abundant spoils that they had taken from the armies they had cut down;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006007"/>
      <verse num="7">that they had torn down the abomination that he had erected upon the altar in Jerusalem; and that they had surrounded the sanctuary with high walls as before and also Beth-zur, his city.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006008"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="8">When the king heard this news, he was astounded and badly shaken. He took to his bed and became sick from grief, because things had not turned out for him as he had planned.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006009"/>
      <verse num="9">He lay there for many days, because deep grief continually gripped him, and he concluded that he was dying.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006010"/>
      <verse num="10">So he called all his friends and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="80006010.1" from="80006010.1" to="80006013.1"/>Sleep departs from my eyes and I am downhearted with worry.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006011"/>
      <verse num="11">I said to myself, <q class="begin-single" qid="80006011.1" from="80006011.1" to="80006011.2"/>To what distress I have come! And into what a great flood I now am plunged! For I was kind and beloved in my power.<q class="end-single" qid="80006011.2" from="80006011.1" to="80006011.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006012"/>
      <verse num="12">But now I remember the evils I did in Jerusalem. I seized all her vessels of silver and gold; and I sent to destroy the inhabitants of Judah without good reason.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006013"/>
      <verse num="13">I know that it is because of this that these evils have come upon me; and behold, I am perishing of deep grief in a strange land.<q class="end-double" qid="80006013.1" from="80006010.1" to="80006013.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006014"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="14">Then he called for Philip, one of his friends, and made him ruler over all his kingdom.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006015"/>
      <verse num="15">He gave him the crown and his robe and the signet, that he might guide Antiochus his son and bring him up to be king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006016"/>
      <verse num="16">Thus King Antiochus died there in the 149th year.<note nid="n80006016.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006017"/>
      <verse num="17">And when Lysias learned that the king was dead, he set up Antiochus the king&apos;s son<note nid="n80006017.1"/> to reign. Lysias<note nid="n80006017.2"/> had brought him up as a boy, and he named him Eupator.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006018"/>
      <heading>Renewed Attacks from Syria</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">Now the men in the citadel kept hemming Israel in around the sanctuary. They were trying in every way to harm them and strengthen the Gentiles.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006019"/>
      <verse num="19">So Judas decided to destroy them and assembled all the people to besiege them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006020"/>
      <verse num="20">They gathered together and besieged the citadel<note nid="n80006020.1"/> in the 150th year;<note nid="n80006020.2"/> and he built siege towers and other engines of war.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006021"/>
      <verse num="21">But some of the garrison escaped from the siege and some of the ungodly Israelites joined them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006022"/>
      <verse num="22">They went to the king and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80006022.1" from="80006022.1" to="80006027.1"/>How long will you fail to do justice and to avenge our brothers?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006023"/>
      <verse num="23">We were happy to serve your father, to live by what he said and to follow his commands.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006024"/>
      <verse num="24">For this reason the sons of our people besieged the citadel<note nid="n80006024.1"/> and became hostile to us; moreover, they have put to death as many of us as they have caught, and they have seized our inheritances.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006025"/>
      <verse num="25">And not against us alone have they stretched out their hands, but also against all the lands on their borders.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006026"/>
      <verse num="26">And behold, today they have encamped against the citadel in Jerusalem to take it; they have fortified both the sanctuary and Beth-zur;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006027"/>
      <verse num="27">and unless you quickly prevent them, they will do still greater things, and you will not be able to stop them.<q class="end-double" qid="80006027.1" from="80006022.1" to="80006027.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006028"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="28">The king was enraged when he heard this. He assembled all his friends, the commanders of his forces and those over the cavalry.<note nid="n80006028.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006029"/>
      <verse num="29">And mercenary forces came to him from other kingdoms and from islands of the seas.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006030"/>
      <verse num="30">The number of his forces was 100,000 foot soldiers, 20,000 horsemen, and 32 elephants accustomed to war.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006031"/>
      <verse num="31">They came through Idumea and encamped against Beth-zur, and for many days they fought and built engines of war; but the Jews<note nid="n80006031.1"/> sallied out and burned these with fire and fought manfully.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006032"/>
      <heading>Battle at Beth-zechariah</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="32">Then Judas marched away from the citadel and encamped at Beth-zechariah, opposite the camp of the king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006033"/>
      <verse num="33">Early in the morning the king rose and took his army by a forced march along the road to Beth-zechariah, and his troops made ready for battle and sounded their trumpets.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006034"/>
      <verse num="34">They showed the elephants the juice of grapes and mulberries, to arouse them for battle.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006035"/>
      <verse num="35">And they distributed the beasts among the phalanxes; with each elephant they stationed 1,000 men armed with coats of mail and with brass helmets on their heads; and 500 picked horsemen were assigned to each beast.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006036"/>
      <verse num="36">These took their position beforehand wherever the beast was; wherever it went they went with it, and they never left it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006037"/>
      <verse num="37">And upon the elephants<note nid="n80006037.1"/> were wooden towers, strong and covered; they were fastened upon each beast by special harness, and upon each were four<note nid="n80006037.2"/> armed men who fought from there, and also its Indian driver.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006038"/>
      <verse num="38">The rest of the horsemen were stationed on either side, on the two flanks of the army, to harass the enemy while being themselves protected by the phalanxes.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006039"/>
      <verse num="39">When the sun shone upon the shields of gold and brass, the hills were ablaze with them and gleamed like flaming torches.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006040"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="40">Now a part of the king&apos;s army was spread out on the high hills, and some troops were on the plain, and they advanced steadily and in good order.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006041"/>
      <verse num="41">All who heard the noise made by their multitude, by the marching of the multitude and the clanking of their arms, trembled, for the army was very large and strong.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006042"/>
      <verse num="42">But Judas and his army advanced to the battle, and 600 men of the king&apos;s army fell.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006043"/>
      <verse num="43">And Eleazar called Avaran saw that one of the beasts was equipped with royal armor. It was taller than all the others, and he supposed that the king was upon it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006044"/>
      <verse num="44">So he gave his life to save his people and to win for himself an everlasting name.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006045"/>
      <verse num="45">He courageously ran into the midst of the phalanx to reach it; he killed men right and left, and they parted before him on both sides.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006046"/>
      <verse num="46">He got under the elephant, stabbed it from beneath, and killed it; but it fell to the ground upon him and there he died.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006047"/>
      <verse num="47">And when the Jews<note nid="n80006047.1"/> saw the royal might and the fierce attack of the forces, they turned away in flight.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006048"/>
      <heading>Siege of the Temple</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="48">The soldiers of the king&apos;s army went up to Jerusalem against them, and the king encamped in Judea and at Mount Zion.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006049"/>
      <verse num="49">He made peace with the men of Beth-zur, and they evacuated the city, because they had no provisions there to withstand a siege, since it was a sabbatical year for the land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006050"/>
      <verse num="50">So the king took Beth-zur and stationed a guard there to hold it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006051"/>
      <verse num="51">Then he encamped before the sanctuary for many days. He set up siege towers, engines of war to throw fire and stones, machines to shoot arrows, and catapults.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006052"/>
      <verse num="52">The Jews<note nid="n80006052.1"/> also made engines of war to match theirs and fought for many days.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006053"/>
      <verse num="53">But they had no food in storage,<note nid="n80006053.1"/> because it was the seventh year; those who found safety in Judea from the Gentiles had consumed the last of the stores.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006054"/>
      <verse num="54">Few men were left in the sanctuary, because famine had prevailed over the rest and they had been scattered, each to his own place.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006055"/>
      <heading>Syria Offers Terms</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="55">Then Lysias heard that Philip, whom King Antiochus while still living had appointed to bring up Antiochus his son to be king,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006056"/>
      <verse num="56">had returned from Persia and Media with the forces that had gone with the king and that he was trying to seize control of the government.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006057"/>
      <verse num="57">So he quickly gave orders to depart and said to the king, to the commanders of the forces, and to the men, <q class="begin-double" qid="80006057.1" from="80006057.1" to="80006059.1"/>We daily grow weaker, our food supply is scant, the place against which we are fighting is strong, and the affairs of the kingdom press urgently upon us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006058"/>
      <verse num="58">Now then let us come to terms with these men and make peace with them and with all their nation</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006059"/>
      <verse num="59">and agree to let them live by their laws as they did before; for it was on account of their laws that we abolished that they became angry and did all these things.<q class="end-double" qid="80006059.1" from="80006057.1" to="80006059.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006060"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="60">The speech pleased the king and the commanders, and he sent to the Jews<note nid="n80006060.1"/> an offer of peace, and they accepted it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006061"/>
      <verse num="61">So the king and the commanders gave them their oath. On these conditions the Jews<note nid="n80006061.1"/> evacuated the stronghold.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006062"/>
      <verse num="62">But when the king entered Mount Zion and saw what a strong fortress the place was, he broke the oath he had sworn and commanded and tore down the wall all around.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80006063"/>
      <verse num="63">Then he departed with haste and returned to Antioch. He found Philip in control of the city, but he fought against him and took the city by force.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007001"/>
    <chapter num="7">
      <heading>Expedition of Bacchides and Alcimus</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">In the 151st year<note nid="n80007001.1"/> Demetrius son of Seleucus set forth from Rome, sailed with a few men to a city by the sea and there began to reign.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007002"/>
      <verse num="2">As he was entering the royal palace of his fathers, the army seized Antiochus and Lysias to bring them to him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007003"/>
      <verse num="3">But when this act became known to him, he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80007003.1" from="80007003.1" to="80007003.2"/>Do not let me see their faces!<q class="end-double" qid="80007003.2" from="80007003.1" to="80007003.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007004"/>
      <verse num="4">So the army killed them, and Demetrius took his seat upon the throne of his kingdom.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">Then there came to him all the lawless and ungodly Israelites; they were led by Alcimus, who wanted to be high priest.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007006"/>
      <verse num="6">And they brought to the king this accusation against the people: <q class="begin-double" qid="80007006.1" from="80007006.1" to="80007007.1"/>Judas and his brothers have destroyed all your friends and have driven us out of our land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007007"/>
      <verse num="7">Now then send a man whom you trust; let him go and see all the ruin that Judas<note nid="n80007007.1"/> has brought upon us and upon the land of the king, and let him punish them and all who help them.<q class="end-double" qid="80007007.1" from="80007006.1" to="80007007.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007008"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="8">So the king chose Bacchides, one of the king&apos;s friends, governor of the province Beyond the River; he was a great man in the kingdom and was faithful to the king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007009"/>
      <verse num="9">And he sent him and with him the ungodly Alcimus, whom he made high priest; and he commanded him to take vengeance on the sons of Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007010"/>
      <verse num="10">So they marched away and came with a large force into the land of Judah; and he sent messengers to Judas and his brothers with peaceable but treacherous words.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007011"/>
      <verse num="11">But they paid no attention to their words, for they saw that they had come with a large force.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007012"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="12">Then a group of scribes appeared in a body before Alcimus and Bacchides to ask for just terms.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007013"/>
      <verse num="13">The Hasideans were first among the sons of Israel to seek peace from them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007014"/>
      <verse num="14">for they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80007014.1" from="80007014.1" to="80007014.2"/>A priest of the line of Aaron has come with the army, and he will not harm us.<q class="end-double" qid="80007014.2" from="80007014.1" to="80007014.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007015"/>
      <verse num="15">And he spoke peaceable words to them and swore this oath to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="80007015.1" from="80007015.1" to="80007015.2"/>We will not seek to injure you or your friends.<q class="end-double" qid="80007015.2" from="80007015.1" to="80007015.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007016"/>
      <verse num="16">So they trusted him; but he seized sixty of them and killed them in one day, in accordance with the word that was written:</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007017"/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
      <verse num="17"><begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="80007017.1" from="80007017.1" to="80007017.2"/>The flesh of your saints and their blood<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>they poured out round about Jerusalem,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and there was none to bury them.<q class="end-double" qid="80007017.2" from="80007017.1" to="80007017.2"/><end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007018"/>
      <begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/>
      <verse num="18">Then the fear and dread of them fell upon all the people, for they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80007018.1" from="80007018.1" to="80007018.2"/>There is no truth or justice in them, for they have violated the agreement and the oath that they swore.<q class="end-double" qid="80007018.2" from="80007018.1" to="80007018.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007019"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">Then Bacchides departed from Jerusalem and encamped in Beth-zaith. And he sent and seized many of the men who had deserted to him,<note nid="n80007019.1"/> and some of the people, and killed them and threw them into the great pit.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007020"/>
      <verse num="20">He placed Alcimus in charge of the country and left with him a force to help him; then Bacchides went back to the king.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007021"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="21">Alcimus fought for the high priesthood,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007022"/>
      <verse num="22">and all who were troubling their people joined him. They gained control of the land of Judah and did great damage in Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007023"/>
      <verse num="23">And Judas saw all the evil that Alcimus and those with him had done among the sons of Israel; it was more than the Gentiles had done.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007024"/>
      <verse num="24">So Judas went out into all the surrounding parts of Judea and took vengeance on the men who had deserted, and they were prevented from going out into the country.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007025"/>
      <verse num="25">When Alcimus saw that Judas and those with him had grown strong and realized that he could not withstand them, he returned to the king and brought wicked charges against them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007026"/>
      <heading>Nicanor in Judea</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="26">Then the king sent Nicanor, one of his honored princes, who hated and detested Israel, and he commanded him to destroy the people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007027"/>
      <verse num="27">So Nicanor came to Jerusalem with a large force and treacherously sent to Judas and his brothers this peaceable message,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007028"/>
      <verse num="28"><q class="begin-double" qid="80007028.1" from="80007028.1" to="80007028.2"/>Let there be no fighting between me and you; I shall come with a few men to see you face to face in peace.<q class="end-double" qid="80007028.2" from="80007028.1" to="80007028.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007029"/>
      <verse num="29">So he came to Judas, and they greeted one another peaceably. But the enemy were ready to seize Judas.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007030"/>
      <verse num="30">It became known to Judas that Nicanor<note nid="n80007030.1"/> had come to him with treacherous intent, and he was afraid of him and would not meet him again.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007031"/>
      <verse num="31">When Nicanor learned that his plan had been disclosed, he went out to meet Judas in battle near Caphar-salama.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007032"/>
      <verse num="32">About 500 men of the army of Nicanor fell, and the rest<note nid="n80007032.1"/> fled into the city of David.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007033"/>
      <heading>Nicanor Threatens the Temple</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="33">After these events Nicanor went up to Mount Zion. Some of the priests came out of the sanctuary, and some of the elders of the people, to greet him peaceably and to show him the whole burnt offering that was being offered for the king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007034"/>
      <verse num="34">But he mocked them and derided them and defiled them and spoke arrogantly,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007035"/>
      <verse num="35">and in anger he swore this oath, <q class="begin-double" qid="80007035.1" from="80007035.1" to="80007035.2"/>Unless Judas and his army are delivered into my hands this time, then if I return safely I will burn up this house.<q class="end-double" qid="80007035.2" from="80007035.1" to="80007035.2"/> And he went out in great anger.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007036"/>
      <verse num="36">Then the priests went in and stood before the altar and the temple, and they wept and said:</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007037"/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
      <verse num="37"><begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="80007037.1" from="80007037.1" to="80007038.1"/>You chose this house to be called by your name<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and to be for your people a house of prayer and supplication.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007038"/>
      <verse num="38"><begin-line/>Take vengeance on this man and on his army<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and let them fall by the sword;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>remember their blasphemies<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and let them live no longer.<q class="end-double" qid="80007038.1" from="80007037.1" to="80007038.1"/><end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007039"/>
      <heading>Death of Nicanor</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="39">Now Nicanor went out from Jerusalem and encamped in Beth-horon, and the Syrian army joined him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007040"/>
      <verse num="40">And Judas encamped in Adasa with 3,000 men. Then Judas prayed and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007041"/>
      <verse num="41"><q class="begin-double" qid="80007041.1" from="80007041.1" to="80007042.1"/>When the messengers from the king spoke blasphemy, your angel went forth and struck down 185,000 of the Assyrians.<note nid="n80007041.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007042"/>
      <verse num="42">So also crush this army before us today; let the rest learn that Nicanor has spoken wickedly against your sanctuary, and judge him according to this wickedness.<q class="end-double" qid="80007042.1" from="80007041.1" to="80007042.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007043"/>
      <verse num="43">So the armies met in battle on the thirteenth day of the month of Adar. The army of Nicanor was crushed, and he himself was the first to fall in the battle.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007044"/>
      <verse num="44">When his army saw that Nicanor had fallen, they threw down their arms and fled.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007045"/>
      <verse num="45">The Jews<note nid="n80007045.1"/> pursued them a day&apos;s journey, from Adasa as far as Gazara, and as they followed kept sounding the battle call on the trumpets.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007046"/>
      <verse num="46">And men came out of all the villages of Judea round about, and they outflanked the enemy<note nid="n80007046.1"/> and drove them back to their pursuers,<note nid="n80007046.2"/> so that they all fell by the sword; not even one of them was left.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007047"/>
      <verse num="47">Then the Jews<note nid="n80007047.1"/> seized the spoils and the plunder, and they cut off Nicanor&apos;s head and the right hand that he had so arrogantly stretched out and brought them and displayed them just outside Jerusalem.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007048"/>
      <verse num="48">The people rejoiced greatly and celebrated that day as a day of great gladness.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007049"/>
      <verse num="49">And they decreed that this day should be celebrated each year on the thirteenth day of Adar.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80007050"/>
      <verse num="50">So the land of Judah had rest for a few days.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008001"/>
    <chapter num="8">
      <heading>Eulogy of the Romans</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Now Judas heard of the fame of the Romans, that they were very strong and were well disposed toward all who made an alliance with them, that they pledged friendship to those who came to them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008002"/>
      <verse num="2">and that they were very strong. Men told him of their wars and of the brave deeds that they were doing among the Gauls, how they had defeated them and forced them to pay tribute,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008003"/>
      <verse num="3">and what they had done in the land of Spain to get control of the silver and gold mines there,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008004"/>
      <verse num="4">and how they had gained control of the whole region by their planning and patience, even though the place was far distant from them. They also subdued the kings who came against them from the ends of the earth, until they crushed them and inflicted great disaster upon them; the rest paid them tribute every year.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008005"/>
      <verse num="5">Philip and King Perseus of the Macedonians<note nid="n80008005.1"/> and the others who rose up against them, they crushed in battle and conquered.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008006"/>
      <verse num="6">They also defeated King Antiochus the Great of Asia, who went to fight against them with 120 elephants and with cavalry and chariots and a very large army. He was crushed by them;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008007"/>
      <verse num="7">they took him alive and decreed that he and those who should reign after him should pay a heavy tribute and give hostages and surrender some of their best provinces,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008008"/>
      <verse num="8">the country of India and Media and Lydia. These they took from him and gave to King Eumenes.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008009"/>
      <verse num="9">The Greeks planned to come and destroy them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008010"/>
      <verse num="10">but this became known to them, and they sent a general against the Greeks<note nid="n80008010.1"/> and attacked them. Many of them were wounded and fell, and the Romans<note nid="n80008010.2"/> took captive their wives and children; they plundered them, conquered the land, tore down their strongholds, and enslaved them to this day.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008011"/>
      <verse num="11">The remaining kingdoms and islands, as many as ever opposed them, they destroyed and enslaved;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008012"/>
      <verse num="12">but with their friends and those who rely on them they have kept friendship. They have subdued kings far and near, and as many as have heard of their fame have feared them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008013"/>
      <verse num="13">Those whom they wish to help and to make kings, they make kings, and those whom they wish they depose; and they have been greatly exalted.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008014"/>
      <verse num="14">Yet for all this not one of them has put on a crown or worn purple as a mark of pride,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008015"/>
      <verse num="15">but they have built for themselves a senate chamber, and every day 320 senators constantly deliberate concerning the people, to govern them well.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008016"/>
      <verse num="16">They trust one man each year to rule over them and to control all their land; they all heed the one man, and there is no envy or jealousy among them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008017"/>
      <heading>Alliance with Rome</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="17">So Judas chose Eupolemus son of John, son of Accos, and Jason son of Eleazar and sent them to Rome to establish friendship and alliance</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008018"/>
      <verse num="18">and to free themselves from the yoke; for they saw that the kingdom of the Greeks was completely enslaving Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008019"/>
      <verse num="19">They went to Rome, a very long journey; and they entered the senate chamber and spoke as follows:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008020"/>
      <verse num="20"><q class="begin-double" qid="80008020.1" from="80008020.1" to="80008020.2"/>Judas, who is also called Maccabeus, and his brothers and the people of the Jews have sent us to you to establish alliance and peace with you, that we may be enrolled as your allies and friends.<q class="end-double" qid="80008020.2" from="80008020.1" to="80008020.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008021"/>
      <verse num="21">The proposal pleased them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008022"/>
      <verse num="22">and this is a copy of the letter that they wrote in reply, on bronze tablets, and sent to Jerusalem to remain with them there as a memorial of peace and alliance:</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008023"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="23"><q class="begin-double" qid="80008023.1" from="80008023.1" to="80008032.2"/>May all go well with the Romans and with the nation of the Jews at sea and on land forever, and may sword and enemy be far from them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008024"/>
      <verse num="24">If war comes first to Rome or to any of their allies in all their dominion,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008025"/>
      <verse num="25">the nation of the Jews shall act as their allies wholeheartedly, as the occasion may indicate to them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008026"/>
      <verse num="26">And to the enemy who makes war they shall not give or supply grain, arms, money, or ships, as Rome has decided; and they shall keep their obligations without receiving any return.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008027"/>
      <verse num="27">In the same way, if war comes first to the nation of the Jews, the Romans shall willingly act as their allies, as the occasion may indicate to them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008028"/>
      <verse num="28">And to the enemy allies shall be given no grain, arms, money, or ships, as Rome has decided; and they shall keep these obligations and do so without deceit.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008029"/>
      <verse num="29">Thus on these terms the Romans make a treaty with the Jewish people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008030"/>
      <verse num="30">If after these terms are in effect both parties shall determine to add or delete anything, they shall do so at their discretion, and any addition or deletion that they may make shall be valid.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008031"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="31"><q class="continue-double" qid="80008031.1" from="80008023.1" to="80008032.2"/>And concerning the wrongs that King Demetrius is doing to them we have written to him as follows: <q class="begin-single" qid="80008031.2" from="80008031.2" to="80008032.1"/>Why have you made your yoke heavy upon our friends and allies the Jews?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80008032"/>
      <verse num="32">If now they appeal again for help against you, we will defend their rights and fight you on sea and on land.<q class="end-single" qid="80008032.1" from="80008031.2" to="80008032.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="80008032.2" from="80008023.1" to="80008032.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009001"/>
    <chapter num="9">
      <heading>Bacchides Returns to Judea</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">When Demetrius heard that Nicanor and his army had fallen in battle, he sent Bacchides and Alcimus into the land of Judah a second time, and with them the right wing of the army.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009002"/>
      <verse num="2">They went by the road that leads to Gilgal and encamped against Mesaloth in Arbela, and they took it and killed many people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009003"/>
      <verse num="3">In the first month of the 152nd year<note nid="n80009003.1"/> they encamped against Jerusalem;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009004"/>
      <verse num="4">then they marched off and went to Berea with 20,000 foot soldiers and 2,000 cavalry.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">Now Judas was encamped in Elasa, and with him were 3,000 picked men.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009006"/>
      <verse num="6">When they saw the huge number of the enemy forces, they were greatly frightened, and many slipped away from the camp, until no more than 800 of them were left.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009007"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">When Judas saw that his army had slipped away and the battle was imminent, he was crushed in spirit, for he had no time to assemble them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009008"/>
      <verse num="8">He became faint, but he said to those who were left, <q class="begin-double" qid="80009008.1" from="80009008.1" to="80009008.2"/>Let us rise and go up against our enemies. We may be able to fight them.<q class="end-double" qid="80009008.2" from="80009008.1" to="80009008.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009009"/>
      <verse num="9">But they tried to dissuade him, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="80009009.1" from="80009009.1" to="80009009.2"/>We are unable. Let us rather save our own lives now, and let us come back with our brothers and fight them; we are too few.<q class="end-double" qid="80009009.2" from="80009009.1" to="80009009.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009010"/>
      <verse num="10">But Judas said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80009010.1" from="80009010.1" to="80009010.2"/>Far be it from us to do such a thing as to flee from them. If our time has come, let us die bravely for our brothers and leave no cause to question our honor.<q class="end-double" qid="80009010.2" from="80009010.1" to="80009010.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009011"/>
      <heading>Last Battle of Judas</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="11">Then the army of Bacchides<note nid="n80009011.1"/> marched out from the camp and took its stand for the encounter. The cavalry was divided into two companies, and the slingers and the archers went ahead of the army, as did all the chief warriors.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009012"/>
      <verse num="12">Bacchides was on the right wing. Flanked by the two companies, the phalanx advanced to the sound of the trumpets; and the men with Judas also blew their trumpets.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009013"/>
      <verse num="13">The earth was shaken by the noise of the armies, and the battle raged from morning till evening.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009014"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="14">Judas saw that Bacchides and the strength of his army were on the right; then all the stouthearted men went with him,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009015"/>
      <verse num="15">and they crushed the right wing, and he pursued them as far as Mount Azotus.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009016"/>
      <verse num="16">When those on the left wing saw that the right wing was crushed, they turned and followed close behind Judas and his men.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009017"/>
      <verse num="17">The battle became desperate, and many on both sides were wounded and fell.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009018"/>
      <verse num="18">Judas also fell, and the rest fled.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009019"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">Then Jonathan and Simon took Judas their brother and buried him in the tomb of their fathers at Modein</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009020"/>
      <verse num="20">and wept for him. And all Israel made great lamentation for him; they mourned many days and said:</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009021"/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
      <verse num="21"><begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="80009021.1" from="80009021.1" to="80009021.2"/>How is the mighty fallen,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>the savior of Israel!<q class="end-double" qid="80009021.2" from="80009021.1" to="80009021.2"/><end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009022"/>
      <begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/>
      <verse num="22">Now the rest of the acts of Judas and his wars and the brave deeds that he did and his greatness have not been recorded, for they were very many.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009023"/>
      <heading>Jonathan Succeeds Judas</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="23">After the death of Judas, the lawless emerged in all parts of Israel; all the doers of injustice appeared.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009024"/>
      <verse num="24">In those days a very great famine occurred, and the country deserted with them to the enemy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009025"/>
      <verse num="25">And Bacchides chose the ungodly and put them in charge of the country.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009026"/>
      <verse num="26">They sought and searched for the friends of Judas and brought them to Bacchides, and he took vengeance on them and made sport of them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009027"/>
      <verse num="27">Thus there was great distress in Israel, such as had not been since the time that prophets ceased to appear among them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009028"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="28">Then all the friends of Judas assembled and said to Jonathan,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009029"/>
      <verse num="29"><q class="begin-double" qid="80009029.1" from="80009029.1" to="80009030.1"/>Since the death of your brother Judas there has been no one like him to go against our enemies and Bacchides and to deal with those of our nation who hate us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009030"/>
      <verse num="30">So now we have chosen you today to take his place as our ruler and leader, to fight our battle.<q class="end-double" qid="80009030.1" from="80009029.1" to="80009030.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009031"/>
      <verse num="31">And Jonathan at that time accepted the leadership and took the place of Judas his brother.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009032"/>
      <heading>Campaigns of Jonathan</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="32">When Bacchides learned of this, he tried to kill him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009033"/>
      <verse num="33">But Jonathan and Simon his brother and all who were with him heard of it, and they fled into the wilderness of Tekoa and camped by the water of the pool of Asphar.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009034"/>
      <verse num="34">Bacchides found this out on the Sabbath day, and he with all his army crossed the Jordan.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009035"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="35">And Jonathan<note nid="n80009035.1"/> sent his brother as leader of the multitude and begged the Nabateans, who were his friends, for permission to store with them the great amount of baggage that they had.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009036"/>
      <verse num="36">But the sons of Jambri from Medeba came out and seized John and all that he had and departed with it.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009037"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="37">After these things it was reported to Jonathan and Simon his brother, <q class="begin-double" qid="80009037.1" from="80009037.1" to="80009037.2"/>The sons of Jambri are celebrating a great wedding and are conducting the bride, a daughter of one of the great nobles of Canaan, from Nadabath with a large escort.<q class="end-double" qid="80009037.2" from="80009037.1" to="80009037.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009038"/>
      <verse num="38">And they remembered the blood of John their brother and went up and hid under cover of the mountain.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009039"/>
      <verse num="39">They raised their eyes and looked and saw a tumultuous procession with much baggage; and the bridegroom came out with his friends and his brothers to meet them with tambourines and musicians and many weapons.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009040"/>
      <verse num="40">Then they rushed upon them from the ambush and began killing them. Many were wounded and fell, and the rest fled to the mountain; and they took all their goods.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009041"/>
      <verse num="41">Thus the wedding was turned into mourning and the voice of their musicians into a funeral dirge.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009042"/>
      <verse num="42">And when they had fully avenged the blood of their brother, they returned to the marshes of the Jordan.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009043"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="43">When Bacchides heard of this, he came with a large force on the Sabbath day to the banks of the Jordan.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009044"/>
      <verse num="44">And Jonathan said to those with him, <q class="begin-double" qid="80009044.1" from="80009044.1" to="80009046.1"/>Let us rise up now and fight for our lives, for today things are not as they were before.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009045"/>
      <verse num="45">For look! the battle is in front of us and behind us; the water of the Jordan is on this side and on that, with marsh and thicket; there is no place to turn.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009046"/>
      <verse num="46">Cry out now to heaven that you may be delivered from the hands of our enemies.<q class="end-double" qid="80009046.1" from="80009044.1" to="80009046.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009047"/>
      <verse num="47">So the battle began, and Jonathan stretched out his hand to strike Bacchides, but he eluded him and went to the rear.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009048"/>
      <verse num="48">Then Jonathan and the men with him leaped into the Jordan and swam across to the other side, and the enemy<note nid="n80009048.1"/> did not cross the Jordan to attack them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009049"/>
      <verse num="49">And about 1,000 of Bacchides&apos; men fell that day.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009050"/>
      <heading>Bacchides Builds Fortifications</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="50">Bacchides<note nid="n80009050.1"/> then returned to Jerusalem and built strong cities in Judea: the fortress in Jericho and Emmaus and Beth-horon and Bethel and Timnath and Pharathon and Tephon, with high walls and gates and bars.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009051"/>
      <verse num="51">And he placed garrisons in them to harass Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009052"/>
      <verse num="52">He also fortified the city of Beth-zur and Gazara and the citadel, and in them he put troops and stores of food.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009053"/>
      <verse num="53">And he took the sons of the leading men of the land as hostages and put them under guard in the citadel at Jerusalem.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009054"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="54">In the 153rd year,<note nid="n80009054.1"/> in the second month, Alcimus gave orders to tear down the wall of the inner court of the sanctuary. He tore down the work of the prophets!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009055"/>
      <verse num="55">But he only began to tear it down, for at that time Alcimus was stricken and his work was hindered; his mouth was stopped and he was paralyzed, so that he could no longer say a word or give commands concerning his house.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009056"/>
      <verse num="56">And Alcimus died at that time in great agony.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009057"/>
      <verse num="57">When Bacchides saw that Alcimus was dead, he returned to the king, and the land of Judah had rest for two years.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009058"/>
      <heading>End of the War</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="58">Then all the lawless plotted and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80009058.1" from="80009058.1" to="80009058.2"/>See! Jonathan and his men are living in quiet and confidence. So now let us bring Bacchides back, and he will capture them all in one night.<q class="end-double" qid="80009058.2" from="80009058.1" to="80009058.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009059"/>
      <verse num="59">And they went and consulted with him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009060"/>
      <verse num="60">He started to come with a large force and secretly sent letters to all his allies in Judea, telling them to seize Jonathan and his men; but they were unable to do it, because their plan became known.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009061"/>
      <verse num="61">And Jonathan&apos;s men<note nid="n80009061.1"/> seized about fifty of the men of the country who were leaders in this treachery and killed them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009062"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="62">Then Jonathan with his men and Simon withdrew to Beth-basi in the wilderness; he rebuilt the parts of it that had been demolished, and they fortified it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009063"/>
      <verse num="63">When Bacchides learned of this, he assembled all his forces and sent orders to the men of Judea.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009064"/>
      <verse num="64">Then he came and encamped against Beth-basi; he fought against it for many days and made machines of war.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009065"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="65">But Jonathan left Simon his brother in the city, while he went out into the country; and he went with only a few men.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009066"/>
      <verse num="66">He struck down Odomera and his brothers and the sons of Phasiron in their tents.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009067"/>
      <verse num="67">Then he<note nid="n80009067.1"/> began to attack and went into battle with his forces; and Simon and his men sallied out from the city and set fire to the machines of war.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009068"/>
      <verse num="68">They fought with Bacchides, and he was crushed by them. They distressed him greatly, for his plan and his expedition had been in vain.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009069"/>
      <verse num="69">So he was greatly enraged at the lawless men who had counseled him to come into the country, and he killed many of them. Then he decided to depart to his own land.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009070"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="70">When Jonathan learned of this, he sent ambassadors to him to make peace with him and obtain release of the captives.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009071"/>
      <verse num="71">He agreed and did as he said; and he swore to Jonathan<note nid="n80009071.1"/> that he would not try to harm him as long as he lived.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009072"/>
      <verse num="72">He restored to him the captives whom he had formerly taken from the land of Judah; then he turned and departed to his own land and came no more into their territory.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80009073"/>
      <verse num="73">Thus the sword ceased from Israel. And Jonathan dwelt in Michmash. And Jonathan began to judge the people, and he destroyed the ungodly out of Israel.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010001"/>
    <chapter num="10">
      <heading>Revolt of Alexander Epiphanes</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">In the 160th year<note nid="n80010001.1"/> Alexander Epiphanes son of Antiochus landed and occupied Ptolemais. They welcomed him, and there he began to reign.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010002"/>
      <verse num="2">When King Demetrius heard of it, he assembled a very large army and marched out to meet him in battle.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010003"/>
      <verse num="3">And Demetrius sent Jonathan a letter in peaceable words to honor him;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010004"/>
      <verse num="4">for he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80010004.1" from="80010004.1" to="80010005.1"/>Let us act first to make peace with them before he makes peace with Alexander against us,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010005"/>
      <verse num="5">for he will remember all the wrongs that we did to him and to his brothers and his nation.<q class="end-double" qid="80010005.1" from="80010004.1" to="80010005.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010006"/>
      <verse num="6">So Demetrius<note nid="n80010006.1"/> gave him authority to recruit troops, to equip them with arms, and to become his ally; and he commanded that the hostages in the citadel should be released to him.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010007"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">Then Jonathan came to Jerusalem and read the letter in the hearing of all the people and of the men in the citadel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010008"/>
      <verse num="8">They were greatly alarmed when they heard that the king had given him authority to recruit troops.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010009"/>
      <verse num="9">But the men in the citadel released the hostages to Jonathan, and he returned them to their parents.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010010"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">And Jonathan dwelt in Jerusalem and began to rebuild and restore the city.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010011"/>
      <verse num="11">He directed those who were doing the work to build the walls and encircle Mount Zion with squared stones, for better fortification; and they did so.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010012"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="12">Then the foreigners who were in the strongholds that Bacchides had built fled;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010013"/>
      <verse num="13">each left his place and departed to his own land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010014"/>
      <verse num="14">Only in Beth-zur did some remain who had forsaken the law and the commandments, for it served as a place of refuge.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010015"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="15">Now King Alexander heard of all the promises that Demetrius had sent to Jonathan, and men told him of the battles that Jonathan<note nid="n80010015.1"/> and his brothers had fought, of the brave deeds that they had done, and of the troubles that they had endured.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010016"/>
      <verse num="16">So he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80010016.1" from="80010016.1" to="80010016.2"/>Shall we find another such man? Come now, we will make him our friend and ally.<q class="end-double" qid="80010016.2" from="80010016.1" to="80010016.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010017"/>
      <verse num="17">And he wrote a letter and sent it to him, in the following words:</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010018"/>
      <heading>Jonathan Becomes High Priest</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18"><q class="begin-double" qid="80010018.1" from="80010018.1" to="80010020.1"/>King Alexander to his brother Jonathan, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010019"/>
      <verse num="19">We have heard about you, that you are a mighty warrior and worthy to be our friend.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010020"/>
      <verse num="20">And so we have appointed you today to be the high priest of your nation; you are to be called the king&apos;s friend<q class="end-double" qid="80010020.1" from="80010018.1" to="80010020.1"/> (and he sent him a purple robe and a golden crown) <q class="begin-double" qid="80010020.2" from="80010020.2" to="80010020.3"/>and you are to take our side and keep friendship with us.<q class="end-double" qid="80010020.3" from="80010020.2" to="80010020.3"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010021"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="21">So Jonathan put on the holy garments in the seventh month of the 160th year, at the Feast of Tabernacles, and he recruited troops and equipped them with arms in abundance.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010022"/>
      <verse num="22">When Demetrius heard of these things he was grieved and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010023"/>
      <verse num="23"><q class="begin-double" qid="80010023.1" from="80010023.1" to="80010024.1"/>What is this that we have done? Alexander has gotten ahead of us in forming a friendship with the Jews to strengthen himself.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010024"/>
      <verse num="24">I also will write them words of encouragement and promise them honor and gifts, that I may have their help.<q class="end-double" qid="80010024.1" from="80010023.1" to="80010024.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010025"/>
      <verse num="25">So he sent a message to them in the following words:
        <end-paragraph/>
        <heading>Letter from Demetrius to Jonathan</heading>
        <begin-paragraph/><q class="begin-double" qid="80010025.1" from="80010025.1" to="80010045.1"/>King Demetrius to the nation of the Jews, greeting.
      </verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010026"/>
      <verse num="26">Since you have kept your agreement with us and have continued your friendship with us and have not sided with our enemies, we have heard of it and rejoiced.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010027"/>
      <verse num="27">And now continue still to keep faith with us, and we will repay you with good for what you do for us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010028"/>
      <verse num="28">We will grant you many immunities and give you gifts.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010029"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="29"><q class="continue-double" qid="80010029.1" from="80010025.1" to="80010045.1"/>And now I free you and exempt all the Jews from payment of tribute and salt tax and crown levies,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010030"/>
      <verse num="30">and instead of collecting the third of the grain and the half of the fruit of the trees that I should receive, I release them from this day and henceforth. I will not collect them from the land of Judah or from the three districts added to it from Samaria and Galilee, from this day and for all time.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010031"/>
      <verse num="31">And let Jerusalem and her environs, her tithes and her revenues, be holy and free from tax.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010032"/>
      <verse num="32">I release also my control of the citadel in Jerusalem and give it to the high priest, that he may station in it men of his own choice to guard it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010033"/>
      <verse num="33">And every one of the Jews taken as a captive from the land of Judah into any part of my kingdom, I set free without payment; and let all officials cancel also the taxes on their cattle.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010034"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="34"><q class="continue-double" qid="80010034.1" from="80010025.1" to="80010045.1"/>And all the feasts and Sabbaths and new moons and appointed days and the three days before a feast and the three after a feast&emdash;let them all be days of immunity and release for all the Jews who are in my kingdom.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010035"/>
      <verse num="35">No one shall have authority to exact anything from them or annoy any of them about any matter.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010036"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="36"><q class="continue-double" qid="80010036.1" from="80010025.1" to="80010045.1"/>Let Jews be enrolled in the king&apos;s forces to the number of 30,000 men, and let the maintenance be given them that is due to all the forces of the king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010037"/>
      <verse num="37">Let some of them be stationed in the great strongholds of the king, and let some of them be put in positions of trust in the kingdom. Let their officers and leaders be of their own number, and let them live by their own laws, just as the king has commanded in the land of Judah.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010038"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="38"><q class="continue-double" qid="80010038.1" from="80010025.1" to="80010045.1"/>As for the three districts that have been added to Judea from the country of Samaria, let them be so annexed to Judea that they are considered to be under one ruler and obey no other authority but the high priest.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010039"/>
      <verse num="39">Ptolemais and the land adjoining it I have given as a gift to the sanctuary in Jerusalem, to meet the necessary expenses of the sanctuary.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010040"/>
      <verse num="40">I also grant 15,000 shekels of silver yearly out of the king&apos;s revenues from appropriate places.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010041"/>
      <verse num="41">And all the additional funds that the government officials have not paid as they did among the first nations,<note nid="n80010041.1"/> they shall give from now on for the service of the temple.<note nid="n80010041.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010042"/>
      <verse num="42">Moreover, the 5,000 shekels of silver that my officials<note nid="n80010042.1"/> have received every year from the income of the services of the temple, this too is canceled, because it belongs to the priests who minister there.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010043"/>
      <verse num="43">And whoever takes refuge at the temple in Jerusalem or in any of its precincts, because he owes money to the king or has any debt, let him be released and receive back all his property in my kingdom.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010044"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="44"><q class="continue-double" qid="80010044.1" from="80010025.1" to="80010045.1"/>Let the cost of rebuilding and restoring the structures of the sanctuary be paid from the revenues of the king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010045"/>
      <verse num="45">And let the cost of rebuilding the walls of Jerusalem and fortifying it round about and the cost of rebuilding the walls in Judea also be paid from the revenues of the king.<q class="end-double" qid="80010045.1" from="80010025.1" to="80010045.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010046"/>
      <heading>Death of Demetrius</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="46">When Jonathan and the people heard these words, they did not believe or accept them, because they remembered the great wrongs that Demetrius had done in Israel and how he had greatly oppressed them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010047"/>
      <verse num="47">They favored Alexander, because he had been the first to speak peaceable words to them, and they remained his allies all his days.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010048"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="48">Now King Alexander assembled large forces and encamped opposite Demetrius.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010049"/>
      <verse num="49">The two kings met in battle, and the army of Demetrius fled, and Alexander<note nid="n80010049.1"/> pursued him and defeated them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010050"/>
      <verse num="50">He pressed the battle strongly until the sun set, and Demetrius fell on that day.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010051"/>
      <heading>Treaty of Ptolemy and Alexander</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="51">Then Alexander sent ambassadors to King Ptolemy of Egypt with the following message:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010052"/>
      <verse num="52"><q class="begin-double" qid="80010052.1" from="80010052.1" to="80010054.1"/>Since I have returned to my kingdom and have taken my seat on the throne of my fathers and established my rule&emdash;for I crushed Demetrius and gained control of our country;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010053"/>
      <verse num="53">I met him in battle, and he and his army were crushed by us, and we have taken our seat on the throne of his kingdom&emdash;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010054"/>
      <verse num="54">now therefore let us establish friendship with one another; give me now your daughter as my wife, and I will become your son-in-law and will make gifts to you and to her in keeping with your position.<q class="end-double" qid="80010054.1" from="80010052.1" to="80010054.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010055"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="55">King Ptolemy replied and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80010055.1" from="80010055.1" to="80010056.1"/>Happy was the day on which you returned to the land of your fathers and took your seat on the throne of their kingdom.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010056"/>
      <verse num="56">And now I will do for you as you wrote, but meet me at Ptolemais, so that we may see one another, and I will become your father-in-law, as you have said.<q class="end-double" qid="80010056.1" from="80010055.1" to="80010056.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010057"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="57">So Ptolemy set out from Egypt, he and Cleopatra his daughter, and came to Ptolemais in the 162nd year.<note nid="n80010057.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010058"/>
      <verse num="58">King Alexander met him, and Ptolemy<note nid="n80010058.1"/> gave him Cleopatra his daughter in marriage and celebrated her wedding at Ptolemais with great pomp, as kings do.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010059"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="59">Then King Alexander wrote to Jonathan to come to meet him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010060"/>
      <verse num="60">So he went with pomp to Ptolemais and met the two kings; he gave them and their friends silver and gold and many gifts and found favor with them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010061"/>
      <verse num="61">A group of pestilent men from Israel, lawless men, gathered together against him to accuse him; but the king paid no attention to them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010062"/>
      <verse num="62">The king gave orders to take off Jonathan&apos;s garments and to clothe him in purple, and they did so.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010063"/>
      <verse num="63">The king also seated him at his side; and he said to his officers, <q class="begin-double" qid="80010063.1" from="80010063.1" to="80010063.2"/>Go forth with him into the middle of the city and proclaim that no one is to bring charges against him about any matter, and let no one annoy him for any reason.<q class="end-double" qid="80010063.2" from="80010063.1" to="80010063.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010064"/>
      <verse num="64">And when his accusers saw the honor that was paid him, in accordance with the proclamation, and saw him clothed in purple, they all fled.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010065"/>
      <verse num="65">Thus the king honored him and enrolled him among his chief friends and made him general and governor of the province.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010066"/>
      <verse num="66">And Jonathan returned to Jerusalem in peace and gladness.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010067"/>
      <heading>Apollonius Is Defeated by Jonathan</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="67">In the 165th year<note nid="n80010067.1"/> Demetrius son of Demetrius came from Crete to the land of his fathers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010068"/>
      <verse num="68">When King Alexander heard of it, he was greatly grieved and returned to Antioch.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010069"/>
      <verse num="69">And Demetrius appointed Apollonius the governor of Coelesyria, and he assembled a large force and encamped against Jamnia. Then he sent the following message to Jonathan the high priest:</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010070"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="70"><q class="begin-double" qid="80010070.1" from="80010070.1" to="80010073.1"/>You are the only one to rise up against us, and I have become a laughingstock and reproach because of you. Why do you assume authority against us in the hill country?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010071"/>
      <verse num="71">If you now have confidence in your forces, come down to the plain to meet us, and let us match strength with each other there, for I have with me the power of the cities.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010072"/>
      <verse num="72">Ask and learn who I am and who the others are that are helping us. They will tell you that you cannot stand before us, for your fathers were twice put to flight in their own land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010073"/>
      <verse num="73">And now you will not be able to withstand my cavalry and such an army in the plain, where there is no stone or pebble or place to flee.<q class="end-double" qid="80010073.1" from="80010070.1" to="80010073.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010074"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="74">When Jonathan heard the words of Apollonius, his spirit was aroused. He chose 10,000 men and set out from Jerusalem, and Simon his brother met him to help him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010075"/>
      <verse num="75">He encamped before Joppa, but the men of the city closed its gates, for Apollonius had a garrison in Joppa.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010076"/>
      <verse num="76">So they fought against it, and the men of the city became afraid and opened the gates, and Jonathan gained possession of Joppa.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010077"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="77">When Apollonius heard of it, he mustered 3,000 cavalry and a large army and went to Azotus as though he were going farther. At the same time he advanced into the plain, for he had a large troop of cavalry and put confidence in it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010078"/>
      <verse num="78">Jonathan pursued him to Azotus, and the armies engaged in battle.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010079"/>
      <verse num="79">Now Apollonius had secretly left 1,000 cavalry behind them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010080"/>
      <verse num="80">Jonathan learned that there was an ambush behind him, for they surrounded his army and shot arrows at his men from early morning till late afternoon.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010081"/>
      <verse num="81">But his men stood fast, as Jonathan commanded, and the enemy&apos;s<note nid="n80010081.1"/> horses grew tired.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010082"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="82">Then Simon brought forward his force and engaged the phalanx in battle (for the cavalry was exhausted); they were overwhelmed by him and fled,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010083"/>
      <verse num="83">and the cavalry was dispersed in the plain. They fled to Azotus and entered Beth-dagon, the temple of their idol, for safety.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010084"/>
      <verse num="84">But Jonathan burned Azotus and the surrounding towns and plundered them; and the temple of Dagon and those who had taken refuge in it, he burned with fire.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010085"/>
      <verse num="85">The number of those who fell by the sword, with those burned alive, came to 8,000 men.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010086"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="86">Then Jonathan departed from there and encamped against Ascalon, and the men of the city came out to meet him with great pomp.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010087"/>
      <verse num="87">And Jonathan and those with him returned to Jerusalem with much booty.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010088"/>
      <verse num="88">When King Alexander heard of these things, he honored Jonathan still more;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80010089"/>
      <verse num="89">and he sent to him a golden buckle,<note nid="n80010089.1"/> such as it is the custom to give to the kinsmen of kings. He also gave him Ekron and all its environs as his possession.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011001"/>
    <chapter num="11">
      <heading>Ptolemy Invades Syria</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Then the king of Egypt gathered great forces, like the sand by the seashore, and many ships; and he tried to get possession of Alexander&apos;s kingdom by trickery and add it to his own kingdom.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011002"/>
      <verse num="2">He set out for Syria with peaceable words, and the people of the cities opened their gates to him and went to meet him, for King Alexander had commanded them to meet him, since he was Alexander&apos;s<note nid="n80011002.1"/> father-in-law.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011003"/>
      <verse num="3">But when Ptolemy entered the cities he stationed forces as a garrison in each city.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011004"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="4">When he<note nid="n80011004.1"/> approached Azotus, they showed him the temple of Dagon burned down and Azotus and its suburbs destroyed and the corpses lying about and the charred bodies of those whom Jonathan<note nid="n80011004.2"/> had burned in the war, for they had piled them in heaps along his route.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011005"/>
      <verse num="5">They also told the king what Jonathan had done, to throw blame on him; but the king kept silent.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011006"/>
      <verse num="6">Jonathan met the king at Joppa with pomp, and they greeted one another and spent the night there.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011007"/>
      <verse num="7">And Jonathan went with the king as far as the river called Eleutherus; then he returned to Jerusalem.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011008"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="8">So King Ptolemy gained control of the coastal cities as far as Seleucia by the sea, and he kept devising evil designs against Alexander.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011009"/>
      <verse num="9">He sent envoys to King Demetrius, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="80011009.1" from="80011009.1" to="80011010.1"/>Come, let us make a covenant with each other, and I will give you in marriage my daughter who was Alexander&apos;s wife, and you shall reign over your father&apos;s kingdom.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011010"/>
      <verse num="10">For I now regret that I gave him my daughter, for he has tried to kill me.<q class="end-double" qid="80011010.1" from="80011009.1" to="80011010.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011011"/>
      <verse num="11">He threw blame on Alexander<note nid="n80011011.1"/> because he coveted his kingdom.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011012"/>
      <verse num="12">So he took his daughter away from him and gave her to Demetrius. He was estranged from Alexander, and their enmity became manifest.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011013"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="13">Then Ptolemy entered Antioch and put on the crown of Asia. Thus he put two crowns upon his head, the crown of Egypt and that of Asia.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011014"/>
      <verse num="14">Now King Alexander was in Cilicia at that time, because the people of that region were in revolt.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011015"/>
      <verse num="15">And Alexander heard of it and came against him in battle. Ptolemy marched out and met him with a strong force and put him to flight.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011016"/>
      <verse num="16">So Alexander fled into Arabia to find protection there, and King Ptolemy was exalted.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011017"/>
      <verse num="17">And Zabdiel the Arab cut off the head of Alexander and sent it to Ptolemy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011018"/>
      <verse num="18">But King Ptolemy died three days later, and his troops in the strongholds were killed by the inhabitants of the strongholds.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011019"/>
      <verse num="19">So Demetrius became king in the 167th year.<note nid="n80011019.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011020"/>
      <heading>Jonathan&apos;s Diplomacy</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="20">In those days Jonathan assembled the men of Judea to attack the citadel in Jerusalem, and he built many engines of war to use against it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011021"/>
      <verse num="21">But certain lawless men who hated their nation went to the king and reported to him that Jonathan was besieging the citadel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011022"/>
      <verse num="22">When he heard this he was angry, and as soon as he heard it he set out and came to Ptolemais; and he wrote Jonathan not to continue the siege, but to meet him for a conference at Ptolemais as quickly as possible.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011023"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="23">When Jonathan heard this, he gave orders to continue the siege; and he chose some of the elders of Israel and some of the priests and put himself in danger,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011024"/>
      <verse num="24">for he went to the king at Ptolemais, taking silver and gold and clothing and numerous other gifts. And he won his favor.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011025"/>
      <verse num="25">Although certain lawless men of his nation kept making complaints against him,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011026"/>
      <verse num="26">the king treated him as his predecessors had treated him; he exalted him in the presence of all his friends.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011027"/>
      <verse num="27">He confirmed him in the high priesthood and in as many other honors as he had formerly had and made him to be regarded as one of his chief friends.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011028"/>
      <verse num="28">Then Jonathan asked the king to free Judea and the three districts of<note nid="n80011028.1"/> Samaria from tribute and promised him 300 talents.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011029"/>
      <verse num="29">The king consented and wrote a letter to Jonathan about all these things; its contents were as follows:</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011030"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="30"><q class="begin-double" qid="80011030.1" from="80011030.1" to="80011037.2"/>King Demetrius to Jonathan his brother and to the nation of the Jews, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011031"/>
      <verse num="31">This copy of the letter that we wrote concerning you to Lasthenes our kinsman we have written to you also, so that you may know what it says.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011032"/>
      <verse num="32"><q class="begin-single" qid="80011032.1" from="80011032.1" to="80011037.1"/>King Demetrius to Lasthenes his father, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011033"/>
      <verse num="33">To the nation of the Jews, who are our friends and fulfill their obligations to us, we have determined to do good, because of the good will they show toward us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011034"/>
      <verse num="34">We have confirmed as their possession both the territory of Judea and the three districts of Aphairema and Lydda and Ramathaim; these were added to Judea from Samaria, with all the region bordering them, for all those who offer sacrifice in Jerusalem in exchange for the royal taxes that the king formerly received from them each year, from the crops of the land and the fruit of the trees.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011035"/>
      <verse num="35">And the other payments henceforth due to us of the tithes, and the taxes due to us, and the salt pits and the crown taxes due to us&emdash;from all these we shall grant them release.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011036"/>
      <verse num="36">And not one of these grants shall be canceled from this time forth forever.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011037"/>
      <verse num="37">Now therefore take care to make a copy of this, and let it be given to Jonathan and put up in a conspicuous place on the holy mountain.<q class="end-single" qid="80011037.1" from="80011032.1" to="80011037.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="80011037.2" from="80011030.1" to="80011037.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011038"/>
      <heading>Intrigue of Trypho</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="38">Now when King Demetrius saw that the land was quiet before him and that there was no opposition to him, he dismissed all his troops, each man to his own place, except the foreign troops that he had recruited from the islands of the nations. So all the troops who had served his fathers hated him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011039"/>
      <verse num="39">Now Trypho had formerly been one of Alexander&apos;s supporters. He saw that all the troops were murmuring against Demetrius. So he went to Imalkue the Arab, who was bringing up Antiochus, the young son of Alexander,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011040"/>
      <verse num="40">and insistently urged him to hand Antiochus<note nid="n80011040.1"/> over to him, to become king in place of his father. He also reported to Imalkue<note nid="n80011040.2"/> what Demetrius had done and told of the hatred that the troops of Demetrius<note nid="n80011040.3"/> had for him; and he stayed there many days.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011041"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="41">Now Jonathan sent to King Demetrius the request that he remove the troops of the citadel from Jerusalem and the troops in the strongholds; for they kept fighting against Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011042"/>
      <verse num="42">And Demetrius sent this message to Jonathan, <q class="begin-double" qid="80011042.1" from="80011042.1" to="80011043.1"/>Not only will I do these things for you and your nation, but I will confer great honor on you and your nation, if I find an opportunity.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011043"/>
      <verse num="43">Now then you will do well to send me men who will help me, for all my troops have revolted.<q class="end-double" qid="80011043.1" from="80011042.1" to="80011043.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011044"/>
      <verse num="44">So Jonathan sent 3,000 stalwart men to him at Antioch, and when they came to the king, the king rejoiced at their arrival.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011045"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="45">Then the men of the city assembled within the city, to the number of 120,000, and they wanted to kill the king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011046"/>
      <verse num="46">But the king fled into the palace. Then the men of the city seized the main streets of the city and began to fight.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011047"/>
      <verse num="47">So the king called the Jews to his aid, and they all rallied about him and then spread out through the city; and they killed on that day as many as 100,000 men.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011048"/>
      <verse num="48">They set fire to the city and seized much spoil on that day, and they saved the king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011049"/>
      <verse num="49">When the men of the city saw that the Jews had gained control of the city as they pleased, their courage failed and they cried out to the king with this entreaty,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011050"/>
      <verse num="50"><q class="begin-double" qid="80011050.1" from="80011050.1" to="80011050.2"/>Grant us peace and make the Jews stop fighting against us and our city.<q class="end-double" qid="80011050.2" from="80011050.1" to="80011050.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011051"/>
      <verse num="51">And they threw down their arms and made peace. So the Jews gained glory in the eyes of the king and of all the people in his kingdom. And they became renowned in his kingdom, and they returned to Jerusalem with much spoil.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011052"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="52">So King Demetrius sat on the throne of his kingdom, and the land was quiet before him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011053"/>
      <verse num="53">But he broke his word about all that he had promised; and he became estranged from Jonathan and did not repay the favors that Jonathan had done him, but oppressed him greatly.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011054"/>
      <heading>Trypho Seizes Power</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="54">After this Trypho returned, and with him the young boy Antiochus, who began to reign and put on the crown.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011055"/>
      <verse num="55">All the troops that Demetrius had cast off gathered around him, and they fought against Demetrius, and he fled and was routed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011056"/>
      <verse num="56">And Trypho captured the elephants<note nid="n80011056.1"/> and gained control of Antioch.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011057"/>
      <verse num="57">Then the young Antiochus wrote to Jonathan, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="80011057.1" from="80011057.1" to="80011057.2"/>I confirm you in the high priesthood and set you over the four districts and make you one of the friends of the king.<q class="end-double" qid="80011057.2" from="80011057.1" to="80011057.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011058"/>
      <verse num="58">And he sent him gold plate and a table service and granted him the right to drink from gold cups and dress in purple and wear a gold buckle.<note nid="n80011058.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011059"/>
      <verse num="59">Simon his brother he made governor from the Ladder of Tyre to the borders of Egypt.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011060"/>
      <heading>Campaigns of Jonathan and Simon</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="60">Then Jonathan set forth and traveled beyond the river and among the cities, and all the army of Syria gathered to him as allies. When he came to Ascalon, the people of the city met him and paid him honor.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011061"/>
      <verse num="61">From there he departed to Gaza, but the men of Gaza shut him out. So he besieged it and burned its suburbs with fire and plundered them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011062"/>
      <verse num="62">Then the people of Gaza pleaded with Jonathan, and he made peace with them and took the sons of their rulers as hostages and sent them to Jerusalem. And he passed through the country as far as Damascus.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011063"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="63">Then Jonathan heard that the officers of Demetrius had come to Kadesh in Galilee with a large army, intending to remove him from office.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011064"/>
      <verse num="64">He went to meet them, but left his brother Simon in the country.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011065"/>
      <verse num="65">Simon encamped before Beth-zur and fought against it for many days and hemmed it in.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011066"/>
      <verse num="66">Then they asked him to grant them terms of peace, and he did so. He removed them from there, took possession of the city, and set a garrison over it.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011067"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="67">Jonathan and his army encamped by the waters of Gennesaret. Early in the morning they marched to the plain of Hazor,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011068"/>
      <verse num="68">and behold, the army of the foreigners met him in the plain; they had set an ambush against him in the mountains, but they themselves met him face to face.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011069"/>
      <verse num="69">Then the men in ambush emerged from their places and joined battle.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011070"/>
      <verse num="70">All the men with Jonathan fled; not one of them was left except Mattathias son of Absalom and Judas son of Chalphi, commanders of the forces of the army.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011071"/>
      <verse num="71">Jonathan rent his garments and put dust on his head and prayed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011072"/>
      <verse num="72">Then he turned back to the battle against the enemy<note nid="n80011072.1"/> and routed them, and they fled.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011073"/>
      <verse num="73">When his men who were fleeing saw this, they returned to him and joined him in the pursuit as far as Kadesh, to their camp, and there they encamped.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80011074"/>
      <verse num="74">As many as 3,000 of the foreigners fell that day. And Jonathan returned to Jerusalem.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012001"/>
    <chapter num="12">
      <heading>Alliances with Rome and Sparta</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Now when Jonathan saw that the time was favorable for him, he chose men and sent them to Rome to confirm and renew the friendship with them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012002"/>
      <verse num="2">He also sent letters to the same effect to the Spartans and to other places.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012003"/>
      <verse num="3">So they went to Rome and entered the senate chamber and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80012003.1" from="80012003.1" to="80012003.2"/>Jonathan the high priest and the Jewish nation have sent us to renew the former friendship and alliance with them.<q class="end-double" qid="80012003.2" from="80012003.1" to="80012003.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012004"/>
      <verse num="4">And the Romans<note nid="n80012004.1"/> gave them letters to the people in every place, asking them to provide for the envoys<note nid="n80012004.2"/> safe conduct to the land of Judah.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">This is a copy of the letter that Jonathan wrote to the Spartans:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012006"/>
      <verse num="6"><q class="begin-double" qid="80012006.1" from="80012006.1" to="80012018.1"/>Jonathan the high priest, the senate of the nation, the priests, and the rest of the Jewish people to their brothers the Spartans, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012007"/>
      <verse num="7">Already in time past a letter was sent to Onias the high priest from Arius,<note nid="n80012007.1"/> who was king among you, stating that you are our brothers, as the appended copy shows.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012008"/>
      <verse num="8">Onias welcomed the envoy with honor and received the letter, which contained a clear declaration of alliance and friendship.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012009"/>
      <verse num="9">Therefore, though we have no need of these things, since we have as encouragement the holy books that are in our hands,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012010"/>
      <verse num="10">we have undertaken to send to renew our brotherhood and friendship with you, so that we may not become estranged from you, for considerable time has passed since you sent your letter to us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012011"/>
      <verse num="11">We therefore remember you constantly on every occasion, both in our feasts and on other appropriate days, at the sacrifices that we offer and in our prayers, as it is right and proper to remember brothers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012012"/>
      <verse num="12">And we rejoice in your glory.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012013"/>
      <verse num="13">But as for ourselves, many afflictions and many wars have encircled us; the kings round about us have waged war against us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012014"/>
      <verse num="14">We were unwilling to annoy you and our other allies and friends with these wars,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012015"/>
      <verse num="15">for we have the help that comes from heaven for our aid; and we were delivered from our enemies and our enemies were humbled.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012016"/>
      <verse num="16">We therefore have chosen Numenius son of Antiochus and Antipater son of Jason and have sent them to Rome to renew our former friendship and alliance with them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012017"/>
      <verse num="17">We have commanded them to go also to you and greet you and deliver to you this letter from us concerning the renewal of our brotherhood.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012018"/>
      <verse num="18">And now please send us a reply to this.<q class="end-double" qid="80012018.1" from="80012006.1" to="80012018.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012019"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">This is a copy of the letter that they sent to Onias:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012020"/>
      <verse num="20"><q class="begin-double" qid="80012020.1" from="80012020.1" to="80012023.1"/>King Arius of the Spartans, to Onias the great priest, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012021"/>
      <verse num="21">It has been found in writing concerning the Spartans and the Jews that they are brothers and are of the family of Abraham.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012022"/>
      <verse num="22">And now that we have learned this, please write us concerning your welfare;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012023"/>
      <verse num="23">we on our part write to you that your cattle and your property belong to us, and ours belong to you. We therefore command that our envoys<note nid="n80012023.1"/> report to you accordingly.<q class="end-double" qid="80012023.1" from="80012020.1" to="80012023.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012024"/>
      <heading>Further Campaigns of Jonathan and Simon</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="24">Now Jonathan heard that the commanders of Demetrius had returned, with a larger force than before, to wage war against him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012025"/>
      <verse num="25">So he marched away from Jerusalem and met them in the region of Hamath, for he gave them no opportunity to invade his own country.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012026"/>
      <verse num="26">He sent spies to their camp, and they returned and reported to him that the enemy<note nid="n80012026.1"/> were being drawn up in formation to fall upon the Jews<note nid="n80012026.2"/> by night.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012027"/>
      <verse num="27">So when the sun set, Jonathan commanded his men to be alert and to keep their arms at hand so as to be ready all night for battle, and he stationed outposts around the camp.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012028"/>
      <verse num="28">When the enemy heard that Jonathan and his men were prepared for battle, they were afraid and were terrified at heart; so they kindled fires in their camp.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012029"/>
      <verse num="29">But Jonathan and his men did not know it until morning, for they saw the fires burning.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012030"/>
      <verse num="30">Then Jonathan pursued them, but he did not overtake them, for they had crossed the Eleutherus river.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012031"/>
      <verse num="31">So Jonathan turned aside against the Arabs who are called Zabadeans, and he crushed them and plundered them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012032"/>
      <verse num="32">Then he broke camp and went to Damascus and marched through all that region.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012033"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="33">Simon also went forth and marched through the country as far as Ascalon and the neighboring strongholds. He turned aside to Joppa and took it by surprise,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012034"/>
      <verse num="34">for he had heard that they were ready to hand over the stronghold to the men whom Demetrius had sent. And he stationed a garrison there to guard it.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012035"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="35">When Jonathan returned he convened the elders of the people and planned with them to build strongholds in Judea,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012036"/>
      <verse num="36">to build the walls of Jerusalem still higher, and to erect a high barrier between the citadel and the city to separate it from the city, in order to isolate it so that its garrison<note nid="n80012036.1"/> could neither buy nor sell.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012037"/>
      <verse num="37">So they gathered together to build up the city; part of the wall on the valley to the east had fallen, and he repaired the section called Chaphenatha.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012038"/>
      <verse num="38">And Simon built Adida in the Shephelah; he fortified it and installed gates with bolts.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012039"/>
      <heading>Trypho Captures Jonathan</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="39">Then Trypho attempted to become king of Asia and put on the crown and to raise his hand against King Antiochus.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012040"/>
      <verse num="40">He feared that Jonathan might not permit him to do so, but might make war on him, so he kept seeking to seize and kill him, and he marched forth and came to Beth-shan.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012041"/>
      <verse num="41">Jonathan went out to meet him with 40,000 picked fighting men, and he came to Beth-shan.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012042"/>
      <verse num="42">When Trypho saw that he had come with a large army, he was afraid to raise his hand against him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012043"/>
      <verse num="43">So he received him with honor and commended him to all his friends, and he gave him gifts and commanded his friends and his troops to obey him as they would himself.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012044"/>
      <verse num="44">Then he said to Jonathan, <q class="begin-double" qid="80012044.1" from="80012044.1" to="80012045.1"/>Why have you wearied all these people when we are not at war?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012045"/>
      <verse num="45">Dismiss them now to their homes and choose for yourself a few men to stay with you and come with me to Ptolemais. I will hand it over to you as well as the other strongholds and the remaining troops and all the officials and will turn round and go home. For that is why I am here.<q class="end-double" qid="80012045.1" from="80012044.1" to="80012045.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012046"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="46">Jonathan<note nid="n80012046.1"/> trusted him and did as he said; he sent away the troops, and they returned to the land of Judah.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012047"/>
      <verse num="47">He kept with himself 3,000 men, 2,000 of whom he left in Galilee, while 1,000 accompanied him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012048"/>
      <verse num="48">But when Jonathan entered Ptolemais, the men of Ptolemais closed the gates and seized him, and all who had entered with him they killed with the sword.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012049"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="49">Then Trypho sent troops and cavalry into Galilee and the Great Plain to destroy all Jonathan&apos;s soldiers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012050"/>
      <verse num="50">But they realized that Jonathan had been seized and had perished along with his men, and they encouraged one another and kept marching in close formation, ready for battle.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012051"/>
      <verse num="51">When their pursuers saw that they would fight for their lives, they turned back.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012052"/>
      <verse num="52">So they all reached the land of Judah safely, and they mourned for Jonathan and his companions and were in great fear; and all Israel mourned deeply.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80012053"/>
      <verse num="53">And all the nations round about them tried to destroy them, for they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80012053.1" from="80012053.1" to="80012053.2"/>They have no leader or helper. Now therefore let us make war on them and blot out the memory of them from among men.<q class="end-double" qid="80012053.2" from="80012053.1" to="80012053.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013001"/>
    <chapter num="13">
      <heading>Simon Takes Command</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Simon heard that Trypho had assembled a large army to invade the land of Judah and destroy it,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013002"/>
      <verse num="2">and he saw that the people were trembling and fearful. So he went up to Jerusalem, and gathering the people together</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013003"/>
      <verse num="3">he encouraged them, saying to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="80013003.1" from="80013003.1" to="80013006.1"/>You yourselves know all that I and my brothers and the house of my father have done for the laws and the sanctuary; you know also the wars and the difficulties that we have seen.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013004"/>
      <verse num="4">By reason of this all my brothers have perished for the sake of Israel, and I alone am left.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013005"/>
      <verse num="5">And now, far be it from me to spare my life in any time of distress, for I am not better than my brothers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013006"/>
      <verse num="6">But I will avenge my nation and the sanctuary and your wives and children, for all the nations have gathered together out of hatred to destroy us.<q class="end-double" qid="80013006.1" from="80013003.1" to="80013006.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013007"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">The spirit of the people was rekindled when they heard these words,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013008"/>
      <verse num="8">and they answered in a loud voice, <q class="begin-double" qid="80013008.1" from="80013008.1" to="80013009.1"/>You are our leader in place of Judas and Jonathan your brother.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013009"/>
      <verse num="9">Fight our battles, and all that you say to us we will do.<q class="end-double" qid="80013009.1" from="80013008.1" to="80013009.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013010"/>
      <verse num="10">So he assembled all the warriors and hastened to complete the walls of Jerusalem, and he fortified it on every side.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013011"/>
      <verse num="11">He sent Jonathan son of Absalom to Joppa, and with him a considerable army; he drove out its occupants and remained there.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013012"/>
      <heading>Deceit and Treachery of Trypho</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="12">Then Trypho departed from Ptolemais with a large army to invade the land of Judah, and Jonathan was with him under guard.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013013"/>
      <verse num="13">And Simon encamped in Adida, facing the plain.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013014"/>
      <verse num="14">Trypho learned that Simon had risen up in place of Jonathan his brother and that he was about to join battle with him, so he sent envoys to him and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013015"/>
      <verse num="15"><q class="begin-double" qid="80013015.1" from="80013015.1" to="80013016.1"/>It is for the money that Jonathan your brother owed the royal treasury, in connection with the offices he held, that we are detaining him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013016"/>
      <verse num="16">Send now 100 talents of silver and two of his sons as hostages, so that when released he will not revolt against us, and we will release him.<q class="end-double" qid="80013016.1" from="80013015.1" to="80013016.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013017"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="17">Simon knew that they were speaking deceitfully to him, but he sent to get the money and the sons, lest he arouse great hostility among the people, who might say,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013018"/>
      <verse num="18"><q class="begin-double" qid="80013018.1" from="80013018.1" to="80013018.2"/>Because Simon<note nid="n80013018.1"/> did not send him the money and the sons, he perished.<q class="end-double" qid="80013018.2" from="80013018.1" to="80013018.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013019"/>
      <verse num="19">So he sent the sons and 100 talents, but Trypho<note nid="n80013019.1"/> broke his word and did not release Jonathan.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013020"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="20">After this Trypho came to invade the country and destroy it, and he circled around by the way to Adora. But Simon and his army kept marching along opposite him to every place he went.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013021"/>
      <verse num="21">Now the men in the citadel kept sending envoys to Trypho urging him to come to them by way of the wilderness and to send them food.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013022"/>
      <verse num="22">So Trypho got all his cavalry ready to go, but that night a very heavy snow fell, and he did not go because of the snow. He marched off and went into the land of Gilead.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013023"/>
      <verse num="23">When he approached Baskama, he killed Jonathan, and he was buried there.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013024"/>
      <verse num="24">Then Trypho turned back and departed to his own land.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013025"/>
      <heading>Jonathan&apos;s Tomb</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="25">And Simon sent and took the bones of Jonathan his brother and buried him in Modein, the city of his fathers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013026"/>
      <verse num="26">All Israel bewailed him with great lamentation and mourned for him many days.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013027"/>
      <verse num="27">And Simon built upon the tomb of his father and his brothers; he made it high that it might be seen, with polished stone at the front and back.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013028"/>
      <verse num="28">He also erected seven pyramids, opposite one another, for his father and mother and four brothers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013029"/>
      <verse num="29">And for the pyramids<note nid="n80013029.1"/> he devised mechanisms, erecting about them great columns, and upon the columns he put suits of armor for a permanent memorial, and beside the suits of armor carved ships, so that they could be seen by all who sail the sea.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013030"/>
      <verse num="30">This is the tomb that he built in Modein; it remains to this day.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013031"/>
      <heading>Judea Gains Independence</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="31">Trypho dealt treacherously with the young King Antiochus; he killed him</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013032"/>
      <verse num="32">and became king in his place, putting on the crown of Asia; and he brought great calamity upon the land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013033"/>
      <verse num="33">But Simon built up the strongholds of Judea and walled them all around, with high towers and great walls and gates and bolts, and he stored food in the strongholds.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013034"/>
      <verse num="34">Simon also chose men and sent them to King Demetrius with a request to grant relief to the country, for all that Trypho did was to plunder.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013035"/>
      <verse num="35">King Demetrius sent him a favorable reply to this request and wrote him a letter as follows:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013036"/>
      <verse num="36"><q class="begin-double" qid="80013036.1" from="80013036.1" to="80013040.1"/>King Demetrius to Simon, the high priest and friend of kings, and to the elders and nation of the Jews, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013037"/>
      <verse num="37">We have received the gold crown and the palm branch that you<note nid="n80013037.1"/> sent, and we are ready to make a general peace with you and to write to our officials to grant you release from tribute.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013038"/>
      <verse num="38">All the grants that we have made to you remain valid, and let the strongholds that you have built be your possession.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013039"/>
      <verse num="39">We pardon any errors and offenses committed to this day and cancel the crown tax that you owe; and whatever other tax has been collected in Jerusalem shall be collected no longer.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013040"/>
      <verse num="40">And if any of you are qualified to be enrolled in our bodyguard,<note nid="n80013040.1"/> let them be enrolled, and let there be peace between us.<q class="end-double" qid="80013040.1" from="80013036.1" to="80013040.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013041"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="41">In the 170th year<note nid="n80013041.1"/> the yoke of the Gentiles was removed from Israel,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013042"/>
      <verse num="42">and the people began to write in their documents and contracts, <q class="begin-double" qid="80013042.1" from="80013042.1" to="80013042.2"/>In the first year of Simon the great high priest and commander and leader of the Jews.<q class="end-double" qid="80013042.2" from="80013042.1" to="80013042.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013043"/>
      <heading>Capture of Gazara by Simon</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="43">In those days Simon<note nid="n80013043.1"/> encamped against Gazara<note nid="n80013043.2"/> and surrounded it with troops. He made a siege engine, brought it up to the city, and battered and captured one tower.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013044"/>
      <verse num="44">The men in the siege engine leaped out into the city, and a great tumult arose in the city.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013045"/>
      <verse num="45">The men in the city, with their wives and children, went up on the wall with their clothes rent, and they cried out with a loud voice, asking Simon to make peace with them;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013046"/>
      <verse num="46">they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80013046.1" from="80013046.1" to="80013046.2"/>Do not treat us according to our wicked acts but according to your mercy.<q class="end-double" qid="80013046.2" from="80013046.1" to="80013046.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013047"/>
      <verse num="47">So Simon reached an agreement with them and stopped fighting against them. But he expelled them from the city and cleansed the houses in which the idols were, and then entered it with hymns and praise.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013048"/>
      <verse num="48">He cast out of it all uncleanness and settled in it men who observed the law. He also strengthened its fortifications and built in it a house for himself.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013049"/>
      <heading>Simon Regains the Jerusalem Citadel</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="49">The men in the citadel at Jerusalem were prevented from going out to the country and back to buy and sell. So they were very hungry, and many of them perished from famine.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013050"/>
      <verse num="50">Then they cried to Simon to make peace with them, and he did so. But he expelled them from there and cleansed the citadel from its pollutions.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013051"/>
      <verse num="51">On the twenty-third day of the second month, in the 171st year,<note nid="n80013051.1"/> the Jews<note nid="n80013051.2"/> entered it with praise and palm branches and with harps and cymbals and stringed instruments and with hymns and songs, because a great enemy had been crushed and removed from Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013052"/>
      <verse num="52">And Simon decreed that every year they should celebrate this day with rejoicing. He strengthened the fortifications of the temple hill alongside the citadel, and he and his men dwelt there.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80013053"/>
      <verse num="53">And Simon saw that John his son had reached manhood, so he made him commander of all the forces, and he dwelt in Gazara.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014001"/>
    <chapter num="14">
      <heading>Capture of Demetrius</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">In the 172nd year<note nid="n80014001.1"/> King Demetrius assembled his forces and marched into Media to secure help, so that he could make war against Trypho.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014002"/>
      <verse num="2">When King Arsaces of Persia and Media heard that Demetrius had invaded his territory, he sent one of his commanders to take him alive.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014003"/>
      <verse num="3">And he went and defeated the army of Demetrius and seized him and took him to Arsaces, who put him under guard.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014004"/>
      <heading>Eulogy of Simon</heading>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
      <verse num="4"><begin-line/>The land<note nid="n80014004.1"/> had rest all the days of Simon.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>He sought the good of his nation;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>his rule was pleasing to them,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>as was the honor shown him, all his days.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014005"/>
      <verse num="5"><begin-line/>To crown all his honors he took Joppa for a harbor<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and opened a way to the isles of the sea.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014006"/>
      <verse num="6"><begin-line/>He extended the borders of his nation<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and gained full control of the country.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014007"/>
      <verse num="7"><begin-line/>He gathered a host of captives;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>he ruled over Gazara and Beth-zur and the citadel,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>and he removed its uncleanness from it;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and there was none to oppose him.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014008"/>
      <verse num="8"><begin-line/>They tilled their land in peace;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>the ground gave its increase,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and the trees of the plains their fruit.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014009"/>
      <verse num="9"><begin-line/>Old men sat in the streets;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>they all talked together of good things;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and the youths donned the glories and garments of war.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014010"/>
      <verse num="10"><begin-line/>He supplied the cities with food<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and furnished them with the means of defense,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>till his renown spread to the ends of the earth.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014011"/>
      <verse num="11"><begin-line/>He established peace in the land,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and Israel rejoiced with great joy.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014012"/>
      <verse num="12"><begin-line/>Each man sat under his vine and his fig tree,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and there was none to make them afraid.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014013"/>
      <verse num="13"><begin-line/>No one was left in the land to fight them,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and the kings were crushed in those days.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014014"/>
      <verse num="14"><begin-line/>He strengthened all the humble of his people;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>he sought out the law<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and did away with every lawless and wicked man.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014015"/>
      <verse num="15"><begin-line/>He made the sanctuary glorious<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and added to the vessels of the sanctuary.<end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014016"/>
      <heading>Diplomacy with Rome and Sparta</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">It was heard in Rome and as far away as Sparta that Jonathan had died, and they were deeply grieved.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014017"/>
      <verse num="17">When they heard that Simon his brother had become high priest in his place and that he was ruling over the country and the cities in it,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014018"/>
      <verse num="18">they wrote to him on bronze tablets to renew with him the friendship and alliance that they had established with Judas and Jonathan his brothers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014019"/>
      <verse num="19">And these were read before the assembly in Jerusalem.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014020"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="20">This is a copy of the letter that the Spartans sent: <q class="begin-double" qid="80014020.1" from="80014020.1" to="80014023.2"/>The rulers and the city of the Spartans to Simon the great priest and to the elders and the priests and the rest of the Jewish people, our brothers, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014021"/>
      <verse num="21">The envoys who were sent to our people have told us about your glory and honor, and we rejoiced at their coming.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014022"/>
      <verse num="22">And what they said we have recorded in our public decrees, as follows: <q class="begin-single" qid="80014022.1" from="80014022.1" to="80014023.1"/>Numenius son of Antiochus and Antipater son of Jason, envoys of the Jews, have come to us to renew their friendship with us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014023"/>
      <verse num="23">It has pleased our people to receive these men with honor and to put a copy of their words in the public archives, so that the people of the Spartans may have a record of them. And they have sent a copy of this to Simon the high priest.<q class="end-single" qid="80014023.1" from="80014022.1" to="80014023.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="80014023.2" from="80014020.1" to="80014023.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014024"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="24">After this Simon sent Numenius to Rome with a large gold shield weighing 1,000 minas, to confirm the alliance with the Romans.<note nid="n80014024.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014025"/>
      <heading>Official Honors for Simon</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="25">When the people heard these things they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="80014025.1" from="80014025.1" to="80014026.1"/>How shall we thank Simon and his sons?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014026"/>
      <verse num="26">For he and his brothers and the house of his father have stood firm; they have fought and repulsed Israel&apos;s enemies and established its freedom.<q class="end-double" qid="80014026.1" from="80014025.1" to="80014026.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014027"/>
      <verse num="27">So they made a record on bronze tablets and put it upon pillars on Mount Zion.<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>This is a copy of what they wrote: <q class="begin-double" qid="80014027.1" from="80014027.1" to="80014045.1"/>On the eighteenth day of Elul, in the 172nd year, which is the third year of Simon the great high priest,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014028"/>
      <verse num="28">in Asaramel,<note nid="n80014028.1"/> in the great assembly of the priests and the people and the rulers of the nation and the elders of the country, it was proclaimed to us</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014029"/>
      <verse num="29">that when many times wars occurred in the country, Simon son of Mattathias, son of the sons of Joarib, and his brothers exposed themselves to danger and resisted the enemies of their nation, in order that their sanctuary and the law might be preserved; and they brought great glory to their nation.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014030"/>
      <verse num="30">Jonathan rallied his nation and became their high priest and was gathered to his people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014031"/>
      <verse num="31">And when their enemies decided to invade their country to devastate their country and to lay hands on their sanctuary,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014032"/>
      <verse num="32">then Simon rose up and fought for his nation. He spent great sums of his own money; he armed the men of his nation&apos;s forces and paid them wages.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014033"/>
      <verse num="33">He fortified the cities of Judea and Beth-zur on the borders of Judea, where formerly the arms of the enemy had been stored, and he placed there a garrison of Jews.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014034"/>
      <verse num="34">He also fortified Joppa, which is by the sea, and Gazara, which is on the borders of Azotus, where the enemy formerly dwelt. He settled Jews there and provided in those cities<note nid="n80014034.1"/> whatever was necessary for their restoration.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014035"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="35"><q class="continue-double" qid="80014035.1" from="80014027.1" to="80014045.1"/>The people saw Simon&apos;s faithfulness<note nid="n80014035.1"/> and the glory that he had resolved to win for his nation, and they made him their leader and high priest, because he had done all these things and because of the justice and loyalty that he had maintained toward his nation. He sought in every way to exalt his people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014036"/>
      <verse num="36">And in his days things prospered in his hands, so that the Gentiles were put out of the<note nid="n80014036.1"/> country, as were also the men in the city of David in Jerusalem, who had built themselves a citadel from which they used to sally forth and defile the environs of the sanctuary and do great damage to its purity.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014037"/>
      <verse num="37">He settled Jews in it and fortified it for the safety of the country and of the city and built the walls of Jerusalem higher.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014038"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="38"><q class="continue-double" qid="80014038.1" from="80014027.1" to="80014045.1"/>In view of these things King Demetrius confirmed him in the high priesthood,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014039"/>
      <verse num="39">and he made him one of the king&apos;s<note nid="n80014039.1"/> friends and paid him high honors.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014040"/>
      <verse num="40">For he had heard that the Jews were addressed by the Romans as friends and allies and brothers and that the Romans<note nid="n80014040.1"/> had received the envoys of Simon with honor</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014041"/>
      <verse num="41">and that the Jews and the priests were pleased that Simon would be their leader and high priest forever, until a trustworthy prophet should arise,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014042"/>
      <verse num="42">and that he should be governor over them and that he should take charge of the sanctuary and appoint men over its tasks and over the country and the weapons and the strongholds and that he should take charge of the sanctuary</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014043"/>
      <verse num="43">and that he should be obeyed by all and that all contracts in the country should be written in his name and that he should be clothed in purple and wear gold.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014044"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="44"><q class="continue-double" qid="80014044.1" from="80014027.1" to="80014045.1"/>And none of the people or priests shall be permitted to nullify any of these decisions or to oppose what he says or to convene an assembly in the country without his permission or to be clothed in purple or put on a gold buckle.<note nid="n80014044.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014045"/>
      <verse num="45">Whoever acts contrary to these decisions or nullifies any of them shall be liable to punishment.<q class="end-double" qid="80014045.1" from="80014027.1" to="80014045.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014046"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="46">And all the people agreed to grant Simon the right to act in accord with these decisions.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014047"/>
      <verse num="47">So Simon accepted and agreed to be high priest, to be commander and ethnarch of the Jews and priests, and to be protector of<note nid="n80014047.1"/> them all.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014048"/>
      <verse num="48">And they gave orders to inscribe this decree upon bronze tablets, to put them up in a conspicuous place in the precincts of the sanctuary,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80014049"/>
      <verse num="49">and to deposit copies of them in the treasury, so that Simon and his sons might have them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015001"/>
    <chapter num="15">
      <heading>Letter of Antiochus VII</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Antiochus son of King Demetrius sent a letter from the islands of the sea to Simon, the priest and ethnarch of the Jews, and to all the nation;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015002"/>
      <verse num="2">its contents were as follows: <q class="begin-double" qid="80015002.1" from="80015002.1" to="80015009.1"/>King Antiochus to Simon the great priest and ethnarch and to the nation of the Jews, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015003"/>
      <verse num="3">Whereas certain pestilent men have gained control of the kingdom of our fathers, and I intend to lay claim to the kingdom so that I may restore it as it formerly was and have recruited a host of mercenary troops and have equipped warships</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015004"/>
      <verse num="4">and intend to make a landing in the country so that I may proceed against those who have destroyed our country and those who have devastated many cities in my kingdom,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015005"/>
      <verse num="5">now therefore I confirm to you all the tax remissions that the kings before me have granted you and release from all the other payments from which they have released you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015006"/>
      <verse num="6">I permit you to mint your own coinage as money for your country,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015007"/>
      <verse num="7">and I grant freedom to Jerusalem and the sanctuary. All the weapons that you have prepared and the strongholds that you have built and now hold shall remain yours.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015008"/>
      <verse num="8">Every debt you owe to the royal treasury and any such future debts shall be canceled for you from henceforth and for all time.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015009"/>
      <verse num="9">When we gain control of our kingdom, we will bestow great honor upon you and your nation and the temple, so that your glory will become manifest in all the earth.<q class="end-double" qid="80015009.1" from="80015002.1" to="80015009.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015010"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">In the 174th year<note nid="n80015010.1"/> Antiochus set out and invaded the land of his fathers. All the troops rallied to him, so that there were few with Trypho.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015011"/>
      <verse num="11">Antiochus pursued him, and he came in his flight to Dor, which is by the sea;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015012"/>
      <verse num="12">for he knew that troubles had converged upon him, and his troops had deserted him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015013"/>
      <verse num="13">So Antiochus encamped against Dor, and with him were 120,000 warriors and 8,000 cavalry.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015014"/>
      <verse num="14">He surrounded the city, and the ships joined battle from the sea; he pressed the city hard from land and sea and permitted no one to leave or enter it.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015015"/>
      <heading>Rome Supports the Jews</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="15">Then Numenius and his companions arrived from Rome, with letters to the kings and countries, in which the following was written:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015016"/>
      <verse num="16"><q class="begin-double" qid="80015016.1" from="80015016.1" to="80015021.1"/>Lucius, consul of the Romans, to King Ptolemy, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015017"/>
      <verse num="17">The envoys of the Jews have come to us as our friends and allies to renew our ancient friendship and alliance. They had been sent by Simon the high priest and by the people of the Jews</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015018"/>
      <verse num="18">and have brought a gold shield weighing 1,000 minas.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015019"/>
      <verse num="19">We therefore have decided to write to the kings and countries that they should not seek their harm or make war against them and their cities and their country or make alliance with those who war against them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015020"/>
      <verse num="20">And it has seemed good to us to accept the shield from them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015021"/>
      <verse num="21">Therefore if any pestilent men have fled to you from their country, hand them over to Simon the high priest, that he may punish them according to their law.<q class="end-double" qid="80015021.1" from="80015016.1" to="80015021.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015022"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="22">The consul<note nid="n80015022.1"/> wrote the same thing to King Demetrius and to Attalus and Ariarathes and Arsaces</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015023"/>
      <verse num="23">and to all the countries and to Sampsakes<note nid="n80015023.1"/> and to the Spartans and to Delos and to Myndos and to Sicyon and to Caria and to Samos and to Pamphylia and to Lycia and to Halicarnassus and to Rhodes and to Phaselis and to Cos and to Side and to Aradus and Gortyna and Cnidus and Cyprus and Cyrene.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015024"/>
      <verse num="24">They also sent a copy of these things to Simon the high priest.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015025"/>
      <heading>Antiochus VII Threatens Simon</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="25">King Antiochus besieged Dor anew,<note nid="n80015025.1"/> continually throwing his forces against it and making engines of war; and he shut Trypho up and kept him from going out or in.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015026"/>
      <verse num="26">And Simon sent to Antiochus 2,000 picked men to fight for him and silver and gold and much military equipment.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015027"/>
      <verse num="27">But he refused to receive them, and he broke all the agreements he formerly had made with Simon<note nid="n80015027.1"/> and became estranged from him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015028"/>
      <verse num="28">He sent to him Athenobius, one of his friends, to confer with him, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="80015028.1" from="80015028.1" to="80015031.1"/>You hold control of Joppa and Gazara and the citadel in Jerusalem; they are cities of my kingdom.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015029"/>
      <verse num="29">You have devastated their territory, you have done great damage in the land, and you have taken possession of many places in my kingdom.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015030"/>
      <verse num="30">Now then, hand over the cities that you have seized and the tribute money of the places that you have conquered outside the borders of Judea;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015031"/>
      <verse num="31">or else give me for them 500 talents of silver and, for the destruction that you have caused and the tribute money of the cities, 500 talents more. Otherwise we will come and conquer you.<q class="end-double" qid="80015031.1" from="80015028.1" to="80015031.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015032"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="32">So Athenobius the friend of the king came to Jerusalem, and when he saw the splendor of Simon and the sideboard with its gold and silver plate and his great magnificence, he was amazed. He reported to him the words of the king,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015033"/>
      <verse num="33">but Simon gave him this reply: <q class="begin-double" qid="80015033.1" from="80015033.1" to="80015035.1"/>We have neither taken foreign land nor seized foreign property, but only the inheritance of our fathers, which at one time had been unjustly taken by our enemies.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015034"/>
      <verse num="34">Now that we have the opportunity, we are firmly holding the inheritance of our fathers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015035"/>
      <verse num="35">As for Joppa and Gazara, which you demand, they were causing great damage among the people and to our land; for them we will give 100 talents.<q class="end-double" qid="80015035.1" from="80015033.1" to="80015035.1"/> Athenobius<note nid="n80015035.1"/> did not answer him a word,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015036"/>
      <verse num="36">but returned in wrath to the king and reported to him these words and the splendor of Simon and all that he had seen. And the king was greatly angered.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015037"/>
      <heading>Victory over Cendebeus</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="37">Now Trypho embarked on a ship and escaped to Orthosia.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015038"/>
      <verse num="38">Then the king made Cendebeus commander-in-chief of the coastal country and gave him troops of infantry and cavalry.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015039"/>
      <verse num="39">He commanded him to encamp against Judea and commanded him to build up Kedron and fortify its gates and to make war on the people; but the king pursued Trypho.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015040"/>
      <verse num="40">So Cendebeus came to Jamnia and began to provoke the people and invade Judea and take the people captive and kill them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80015041"/>
      <verse num="41">He built up Kedron and stationed there horsemen and troops, so that they might go out and make raids along the highways of Judea, as the king had ordered him.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016001"/>
    <chapter num="16">
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">John went up from Gazara and reported to Simon his father what Cendebeus had done.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016002"/>
      <verse num="2">And Simon called in his two older sons Judas and John and said to them: <q class="begin-double" qid="80016002.1" from="80016002.1" to="80016003.1"/>I and my brothers and the house of my father have fought the wars of Israel from our youth until this day, and things have prospered in our hands so that we have delivered Israel many times.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016003"/>
      <verse num="3">But now I have grown old, and you by his mercy are mature in years. Take my place and my brother&apos;s, and go out and fight for our nation, and may the help that comes from heaven be with you.<q class="end-double" qid="80016003.1" from="80016002.1" to="80016003.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016004"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="4">So John<note nid="n80016004.1"/> chose out of the country 20,000 warriors and horsemen, and they marched against Cendebeus and camped for the night in Modein.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016005"/>
      <verse num="5">Early in the morning they arose and marched into the plain, and behold, a large force of infantry and horsemen was coming to meet them; and a stream lay between them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016006"/>
      <verse num="6">Then he and his army lined up against them. And he saw that the soldiers were afraid to cross the stream, so he crossed over first; and when his men saw him, they crossed over after him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016007"/>
      <verse num="7">Then he divided the army and placed the horsemen in the midst of the infantry, for the cavalry of the enemy were very numerous.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016008"/>
      <verse num="8">And they sounded the trumpets, and Cendebeus and his army were put to flight, and many of them were wounded and fell; the rest fled into the stronghold.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016009"/>
      <verse num="9">At that time Judas the brother of John was wounded, but John pursued them until Cendebeus<note nid="n80016009.1"/> reached Kedron, which he had built.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016010"/>
      <verse num="10">They also fled into the towers that were in the fields of Azotus, and John<note nid="n80016010.1"/> burned it with fire, and about 2,000 of them fell. And he returned to Judea safely.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016011"/>
      <heading>Murder of Simon and His Sons</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="11">Now Ptolemy son of Abubus had been appointed governor over the plain of Jericho, and he had much silver and gold,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016012"/>
      <verse num="12">for he was son-in-law of the high priest.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016013"/>
      <verse num="13">His heart was lifted up; he determined to get control of the country and made treacherous plans against Simon and his sons, to do away with them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016014"/>
      <verse num="14">Now Simon was visiting the cities of the country and attending to their needs, and he went down to Jericho with Mattathias and Judas his sons, in the 177th year,<note nid="n80016014.1"/> in the eleventh month, which is the month of Shebat.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016015"/>
      <verse num="15">The son of Abubus received them treacherously in the little stronghold called Dok, which he had built; he gave them a great banquet and hid men there.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016016"/>
      <verse num="16">When Simon and his sons were drunk, Ptolemy and his men rose up, took their weapons, and rushed in against Simon in the banquet hall, and they killed him and his two sons and some of his servants.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016017"/>
      <verse num="17">So he committed an act of great treachery and returned evil for good.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016018"/>
      <heading>John Succeeds Simon</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">Then Ptolemy wrote a report about these things and sent it to the king, asking him to send troops to aid him and to turn over to him the cities and the country.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016019"/>
      <verse num="19">He sent other men to Gazara to do away with John; he sent letters to the captains asking them to come to him so that he might give them silver and gold and gifts;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016020"/>
      <verse num="20">and he sent other men to take possession of Jerusalem and the temple hill.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016021"/>
      <verse num="21">But someone ran ahead and reported to John at Gazara that his father and brothers had perished and that <q class="begin-double" qid="80016021.1" from="80016021.1" to="80016021.2"/>he has sent men to kill you also.<q class="end-double" qid="80016021.2" from="80016021.1" to="80016021.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016022"/>
      <verse num="22">When he heard this, he was greatly shocked; and he seized the men who came to destroy him and killed them, for he had found out that they were seeking to destroy him.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016023"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="23">The rest of the acts of John and his wars and the brave deeds that he did and the building of the walls that he built and his achievements,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v80016024"/>
      <verse num="24">behold, they are written in the chronicles of his high priesthood, from the time that he became high priest after his father.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
  </book>
</crossway-bible>
