<?xml version='1.0' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" translation="English Standard Version" revision="2018-3-26" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
  <book title="2 Maccabees" num="81">
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001001"/>
    <chapter num="1">
      <heading>Letter to the Jews in Egypt</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">The Jewish brothers in Jerusalem and those in the land of Judea to their Jewish brothers in Egypt: Greeting and good peace.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001002"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="2">May God do good to you, and may he remember his covenant with Abraham and Isaac and Jacob, his faithful servants.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001003"/>
      <verse num="3">May he give you all a heart to worship him and to do his will with a strong heart and a willing spirit.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001004"/>
      <verse num="4">May he open your heart to his law and his commandments, and may he bring peace.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001005"/>
      <verse num="5">May he hear your prayers and be reconciled to you, and may he not forsake you in time of evil.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001006"/>
      <verse num="6">We are now praying for you here.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001007"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">In the reign of Demetrius, in the 169th year,<note nid="n81001007.1"/> we Jews wrote to you, in the critical distress that came upon us in those years after Jason and his company revolted from the Holy Land and the kingdom</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001008"/>
      <verse num="8">and burned the gate and shed innocent blood. We prayed to the Lord, and we were heard, and we offered sacrifice and grain offering, and we lit the lamps and we set out the loaves.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001009"/>
      <verse num="9">And now we see that you keep the Feast of Booths in the month of Chislev, in the 188th year.<note nid="n81001009.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001010"/>
      <heading>Letter to Aristobulus</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">Those in Jerusalem and those in Judea and the senate and Judas to Aristobulus, who is of the family of the anointed priests, teacher of King Ptolemy, and to the Jews in Egypt: Greeting and good health.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001011"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="11">Having been saved by God out of grave dangers, we thank him greatly for taking our side against the king.<note nid="n81001011.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001012"/>
      <verse num="12">For he drove out those who fought against the holy city.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001013"/>
      <verse num="13">For when the leader reached Persia with a force that seemed irresistible, they were cut to pieces in the temple of Nanea by a deception employed by the priests of Nanea.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001014"/>
      <verse num="14">For under pretext of intending to marry her, Antiochus came to the place together with his friends, to secure most of its treasures as a dowry.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001015"/>
      <verse num="15">When the priests of the temple of Nanea had set out the treasures and Antiochus had come with a few men inside the wall of the sacred precinct, they closed the temple as soon as he entered it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001016"/>
      <verse num="16">Opening the secret door in the ceiling, they threw stones and struck down the leader and his men and dismembered them and cut off their heads and threw them to the people outside.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001017"/>
      <verse num="17">Blessed in every way be our God, who has brought judgment upon those who have behaved impiously.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001018"/>
      <heading>Fire Consumes Nehemiah&apos;s Sacrifice</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">Since on the twenty-fifth day of Chislev we shall celebrate the purification of the temple, we thought it necessary to notify you, in order that you also may celebrate the Feast of Booths and the Feast of the Fire given when Nehemiah, who built the temple and the altar, offered sacrifices.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001019"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">For when our fathers were being led captive to Persia, the pious priests of that time took some of the fire of the altar and secretly hid it in the hollow of a dry cistern, where they took such precautions that the place was unknown to anyone.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001020"/>
      <verse num="20">But after many years had passed, when it pleased God, Nehemiah, having been commissioned by the king of Persia, sent the descendants of the priests who had hidden the fire to get it. And when they reported to us that they had not found fire but thick liquid, he ordered them to dip it out and bring it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001021"/>
      <verse num="21">And when the materials for the sacrifices were presented, Nehemiah ordered the priests to sprinkle the liquid on the wood and on what was laid upon it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001022"/>
      <verse num="22">When this was done and some time had passed and the sun, which had been clouded over, shone out, a great fire blazed up, so that all marveled.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001023"/>
      <verse num="23">And while the sacrifice was being consumed, the priests offered prayer&emdash;the priests and everyone. Jonathan led, and the rest responded, as did Nehemiah.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001024"/>
      <verse num="24">The prayer was to this effect:<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/><q class="begin-double" qid="81001024.1" from="81001024.1" to="81001029.1"/>O Lord, Lord God, Creator of all things, who is awe-inspiring and strong and just and merciful, who alone is King and is kind,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001025"/>
      <verse num="25">who alone is bountiful, who alone is just and almighty and eternal, who rescues Israel from every evil, who chose the fathers and consecrated them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001026"/>
      <verse num="26">accept this sacrifice on behalf of all your people Israel and preserve your portion and make it holy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001027"/>
      <verse num="27">Gather together our scattered people, set free those who are slaves among the Gentiles, look upon those who are rejected and despised, and let the Gentiles know that you are our God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001028"/>
      <verse num="28">Afflict those who oppress and are insolent with pride.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001029"/>
      <verse num="29">Plant your people in your holy place, as Moses said.<q class="end-double" qid="81001029.1" from="81001024.1" to="81001029.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001030"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="30">Then the priests sang the hymns.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001031"/>
      <verse num="31">And when the materials of the sacrifice were consumed, Nehemiah ordered that the liquid that was left should be poured upon large stones.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001032"/>
      <verse num="32">When this was done, a flame blazed up; but when the light from the altar shone back, it went out.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001033"/>
      <verse num="33">When this matter became known, and it was reported to the king of the Persians that, in the place where the exiled priests had hidden the fire, the liquid had appeared with which Nehemiah and his associates had burned the materials of the sacrifice,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001034"/>
      <verse num="34">the king investigated the matter and enclosed the place and made it sacred.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001035"/>
      <verse num="35">And with those persons whom the king favored he exchanged many excellent gifts.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81001036"/>
      <verse num="36">Nehemiah and his associates called this <q class="begin-double" qid="81001036.1" from="81001036.1" to="81001036.2"/>nephthar,<q class="end-double" qid="81001036.2" from="81001036.1" to="81001036.2"/> which means purification, but by most people it is called naphtha.<note nid="n81001036.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002001"/>
    <chapter num="2">
      <heading>Jeremiah Hides the Tent, Ark, and Altar</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">One finds in the records that Jeremiah the prophet ordered those who were being deported to take some of the fire, as has been told,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002002"/>
      <verse num="2">and that the prophet, after giving them the law, instructed those who were being deported not to forget the commandments of the Lord or to be led astray in their thoughts upon seeing the gold and silver statues and their adornment.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002003"/>
      <verse num="3">And with other similar words he exhorted them that the law should not depart from their hearts.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002004"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="4">It was also in the writing that the prophet, having received an oracle, ordered that the tent and the ark should follow with him and that he went out to the mountain where Moses had gone up and had seen the inheritance of God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002005"/>
      <verse num="5">And Jeremiah came and found a cave, and he brought there the tent and the ark and the altar of incense, and he sealed up the entrance.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002006"/>
      <verse num="6">Some of those who followed him came up to mark the way, but could not find it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002007"/>
      <verse num="7">When Jeremiah learned of it, he rebuked them and declared: <q class="begin-double" qid="81002007.1" from="81002007.1" to="81002008.1"/>The place shall be unknown until God gathers his people together again and shows his mercy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002008"/>
      <verse num="8">And then the Lord will disclose these things, and the glory of the Lord and the cloud will appear, as they were shown in the case of Moses, and as Solomon asked that the place should be specially consecrated.<q class="end-double" qid="81002008.1" from="81002007.1" to="81002008.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002009"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="9">It was also made clear that being possessed of wisdom Solomon<note nid="n81002009.1"/> offered sacrifice for the dedication and completion of the temple.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002010"/>
      <verse num="10">Just as Moses prayed to the Lord, and fire came down from heaven and devoured the sacrifices, so also Solomon prayed, and the fire came down and consumed the whole burnt offerings.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002011"/>
      <verse num="11">And Moses said, <q class="begin-double" qid="81002011.1" from="81002011.1" to="81002011.2"/>They were consumed because the sin offering had not been eaten.<q class="end-double" qid="81002011.2" from="81002011.1" to="81002011.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002012"/>
      <verse num="12">Likewise Solomon also kept the eight days.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002013"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="13">The same things are reported in the records and in the memoirs of Nehemiah, and also that he founded a library and collected the books about the kings and prophets and the writings of David and letters of kings about votive offerings.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002014"/>
      <verse num="14">In the same way Judas also collected all the books that had been lost on account of the war that had come upon us, and they are in our possession.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002015"/>
      <verse num="15">So if you have need of them, send people to get them for you.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002016"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">Since, therefore, we are about to celebrate the purification, we write to you. Will you therefore please keep the days?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002017"/>
      <verse num="17">It is God who has saved all his people and has returned the inheritance to all, and the kingship and priesthood and consecration,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002018"/>
      <verse num="18">as he promised through the law. For we have hope in God that he will soon have mercy upon us and will gather us from everywhere under heaven into his holy place, for he has rescued us from great evils and has purified the place.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002019"/>
      <heading>Compiler&apos;s Preface</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">The story of Judas Maccabeus and his brothers and the purification of the great temple and the dedication of the altar</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002020"/>
      <verse num="20">and further the wars against Antiochus Epiphanes and his son Eupator</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002021"/>
      <verse num="21">and the appearances that came from heaven to those who fought zealously on behalf of Judaism, so that though few in number they seized the whole land and pursued the barbarian hordes</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002022"/>
      <verse num="22">and recovered the temple famous throughout the world and freed the city and restored the laws that were about to be abolished, while the Lord with great kindness became gracious to them&emdash;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002023"/>
      <verse num="23">all this, which has been set forth by Jason of Cyrene in five volumes, we shall attempt to condense into a single book.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002024"/>
      <verse num="24">For considering the flood of numerical data and the difficulty there is for those who wish to enter upon the narratives of history because of the mass of material,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002025"/>
      <verse num="25">we have aimed to please those who wish to read, to make it easy for those who are inclined to memorize and to profit all readers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002026"/>
      <verse num="26">For us who have undertaken the toil of abbreviating, it is no light matter but calls for sweat and loss of sleep,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002027"/>
      <verse num="27">just as it is not easy for one who prepares a banquet and seeks the benefit of others. However, to secure the gratitude of many we will gladly endure the uncomfortable toil,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002028"/>
      <verse num="28">leaving the responsibility for exact details to the compiler, while devoting our effort to arriving at the outlines of the condensation.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002029"/>
      <verse num="29">For as the master builder of a new house must be concerned with the whole construction, while the one who undertakes its painting and decoration has to consider only what is suitable for its adornment, such in my judgment is the case with us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002030"/>
      <verse num="30">It is the duty of the original historian to occupy the ground and to discuss matters from every side and to take trouble with details,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002031"/>
      <verse num="31">but the one who recasts the narrative should be allowed to fight for brevity of expression and to forego exhaustive treatment.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81002032"/>
      <verse num="32">At this point therefore let us begin our narrative, without adding further to what has already been said; for it is foolish to lengthen the preface while cutting short the history itself.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003001"/>
    <chapter num="3">
      <heading>Arrival of Heliodorus in Jerusalem</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">While the holy city was inhabited in unbroken peace and the laws were very well observed because of the piety of the high priest Onias and his hatred of wickedness,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003002"/>
      <verse num="2">it came about that the kings themselves honored the place and glorified the temple with the finest presents,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003003"/>
      <verse num="3">so that even King Seleucus of Asia defrayed from his own revenues all the expenses connected with the service of the sacrifices.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003004"/>
      <verse num="4">But a man named Simon, of the tribe of Benjamin, who had been made captain of the temple, had a disagreement with the high priest about the administration of the city market;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003005"/>
      <verse num="5">and when he could not prevail over Onias he went to Apollonius of Tarsus,<note nid="n81003005.1"/> who at that time was governor of Coelesyria and Phoenicia.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003006"/>
      <verse num="6">He reported to him that the treasury in Jerusalem was full of untold sums of money, so that the amount of the funds could not be reckoned and that they did not belong to the account of the sacrifices, but that it was possible for them to fall under the control of the king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003007"/>
      <verse num="7">When Apollonius met the king, he told him of the money about which he had been informed. The king<note nid="n81003007.1"/> chose Heliodorus, who was in charge of his affairs, and sent him with commands to effect the removal of the aforesaid money.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003008"/>
      <verse num="8">Heliodorus at once set out on his journey, ostensibly to make an inspection tour of the cities of Coelesyria and Phoenicia, but in fact to carry out the king&apos;s purpose.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003009"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="9">When he had arrived at Jerusalem and had been kindly welcomed by the high priest of<note nid="n81003009.1"/> the city, he told about the disclosure that had been made and stated why he had come, and he inquired whether this really was the situation.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003010"/>
      <verse num="10">The high priest explained that there were some deposits belonging to widows and orphans</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003011"/>
      <verse num="11">and also some money of Hyrcanus son of Tobias, a man of very prominent position, and that it totaled in all 400 talents of silver and 200 of gold. To such an extent the impious Simon had misrepresented the facts.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003012"/>
      <verse num="12">And he said that it was utterly impossible that wrong should be done to those people who had trusted in the holiness of the place and in the sanctity and inviolability of the temple that is honored throughout the whole world.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003013"/>
      <verse num="13">But Heliodorus, because of the king&apos;s commands that he had, said that this money must in any case be confiscated for the king&apos;s treasury.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003014"/>
      <verse num="14">So he set a day and went in to direct the inspection of these funds.<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>There was no little distress throughout the whole city.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003015"/>
      <verse num="15">The priests prostrated themselves before the altar in their priestly garments and called toward heaven upon him who had given the law about deposits, that he should keep them safe for those who had deposited them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003016"/>
      <verse num="16">To see the appearance of the high priest was to be wounded at heart, for his face and the change in his color disclosed the anguish of his soul.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003017"/>
      <verse num="17">For terror and bodily trembling had come over the man, which plainly showed to those who looked at him the pain lodged in his heart.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003018"/>
      <verse num="18">People also hurried out of their houses in crowds to make a general supplication because the Holy Place was about to be brought into contempt.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003019"/>
      <verse num="19">Women, girded with sackcloth under their breasts, thronged the streets. Some of the maidens who were kept indoors ran together to the gates, and some to the walls, while others peered out of the windows.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003020"/>
      <verse num="20">And holding up their hands to heaven, they all made entreaty.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003021"/>
      <verse num="21">There was something pitiable in the prostration of the whole populace and the anxiety of the high priest in his great anguish.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003022"/>
      <heading>The Lord Protects His Temple</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="22">While they were calling upon the almighty Lord that he would keep what had been entrusted safe and secure for those who had entrusted it,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003023"/>
      <verse num="23">Heliodorus went on with what had been decided.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003024"/>
      <verse num="24">But when he arrived at the treasury with his bodyguard, then and there the Sovereign of spirits and of all authority caused so great a manifestation that all who had been so bold as to accompany him were astounded by the power of God and became faint with terror.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003025"/>
      <verse num="25">For there appeared to them a magnificently caparisoned horse, with a rider of frightening appearance, and it rushed furiously at Heliodorus and struck at him with its front hoofs. Its rider was seen to have armor and weapons of gold.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003026"/>
      <verse num="26">Two young men also appeared to him, remarkably strong, gloriously beautiful and splendidly dressed, who stood on each side of him and scourged him continuously, inflicting many blows on him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003027"/>
      <verse num="27">When he suddenly fell to the ground and deep darkness came over him, his men took him up and put him on a stretcher</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003028"/>
      <verse num="28">and carried him away&emdash;this man who had just entered the aforesaid treasury with a great retinue and all his bodyguard but was now unable to help himself&emdash;and they recognized clearly the sovereign power of God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003029"/>
      <verse num="29">While he lay prostrate, speechless because of the divine intervention and deprived of any hope of recovery,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003030"/>
      <verse num="30">they praised the Lord who had acted marvelously for his own place. And the temple, which a little while before was full of fear and disturbance, was filled with joy and gladness, now that the almighty Lord had appeared.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003031"/>
      <heading>Onias Prays for Heliodorus</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="31">Quickly some of Heliodorus&apos; friends asked Onias to call upon the Most High and to grant life to one who was lying quite at his last breath.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003032"/>
      <verse num="32">And the high priest, fearing that the king might get the notion that some foul play had been perpetrated by the Jews with regard to Heliodorus, offered sacrifice for the man&apos;s recovery.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003033"/>
      <verse num="33">While the high priest was making the offering of atonement, the same young men appeared again to Heliodorus, dressed in the same clothing, and they stood and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="81003033.1" from="81003033.1" to="81003034.1"/>Be very grateful to Onias the high priest, since for his sake the Lord has granted you your life.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003034"/>
      <verse num="34">And see that you, who have been scourged by heaven, report to everyone the majestic power of God.<q class="end-double" qid="81003034.1" from="81003033.1" to="81003034.1"/> Having said this they vanished.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003035"/>
      <heading>Conversion of Heliodorus</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="35">Then Heliodorus offered sacrifice to the Lord and made very great vows to the Savior of his life, and having bidden Onias farewell, he marched off with his forces to the king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003036"/>
      <verse num="36">And he bore testimony to everyone concerning the deeds of the supreme God, which he had seen with his own eyes.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003037"/>
      <verse num="37">When the king asked Heliodorus what sort of person would be suitable to send on another mission to Jerusalem, he replied,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003038"/>
      <verse num="38"><q class="begin-double" qid="81003038.1" from="81003038.1" to="81003039.1"/>If you have any enemy or plotter against your government, send him there, for you will get him back thoroughly scourged, if he escapes at all, for there certainly is about the place some power of God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003039"/>
      <verse num="39">For he who has his dwelling in heaven watches over that place himself and brings it aid, and he strikes and destroys those who come to do it injury.<q class="end-double" qid="81003039.1" from="81003038.1" to="81003039.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81003040"/>
      <verse num="40">This was the outcome of the episode of Heliodorus and the protection of the treasury.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004001"/>
    <chapter num="4">
      <heading>Simon Accuses Onias</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">The previously mentioned Simon, who had informed about the money against<note nid="n81004001.1"/> his own country, slandered Onias, saying that it was he who had incited Heliodorus and had been the real cause of the misfortune.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004002"/>
      <verse num="2">He dared to designate as a plotter against the government the man who was the benefactor of the city, the protector of his compatriots, and a zealot for the laws.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004003"/>
      <verse num="3">When his hatred progressed to such a degree that even murders were committed by one of Simon&apos;s approved agents,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004004"/>
      <verse num="4">Onias recognized that the rivalry was serious and that Apollonius son of Menestheus<note nid="n81004004.1"/> and governor of Coelesyria and Phoenicia was intensifying the malice of Simon.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004005"/>
      <verse num="5">So he conveyed himself to the king, not accusing his fellow citizens but having in view the welfare, both public and private, of all the people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004006"/>
      <verse num="6">For he saw that without the king&apos;s attention public affairs could not again reach a peaceful settlement and that Simon would not stop his folly.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004007"/>
      <heading>Jason&apos;s Reforms</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">When Seleucus died and Antiochus who was called Epiphanes succeeded to the kingdom, Jason the brother of Onias obtained the high priesthood by corruption,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004008"/>
      <verse num="8">promising the king at an interview<note nid="n81004008.1"/> 360 talents of silver and, from another source of revenue, 80 talents.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004009"/>
      <verse num="9">In addition to this he promised to pay 150 more if permission were given to establish by his authority a gymnasium and a body of youth for it and to enroll the people of Jerusalem as citizens of Antioch.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004010"/>
      <verse num="10">When the king assented and Jason<note nid="n81004010.1"/> came to office, he at once shifted his compatriots over to the Greek way of life.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004011"/>
      <verse num="11">He set aside the existing royal concessions to the Jews, secured through John the father of Eupolemus, who went on the mission to establish friendship and alliance with the Romans; and he destroyed the lawful ways of living and introduced new customs contrary to the law.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004012"/>
      <verse num="12">For with alacrity he founded a gymnasium right under the citadel, and he induced the noblest of the young men<note nid="n81004012.1"/> to wear the athlete&apos;s cap.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004013"/>
      <verse num="13">There was such an extreme of hellenization and increase in the adoption of foreign ways because of the surpassing wickedness of Jason, who was ungodly and no true high priest,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004014"/>
      <verse num="14">that the priests were no longer intent upon their service at the altar. Despising the sanctuary and neglecting the sacrifices, they hastened to take part in the unlawful proceedings in the wrestling arena after the call to the discus,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004015"/>
      <verse num="15">disdaining the honors prized by their fathers and putting the highest value upon Greek forms of prestige.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004016"/>
      <verse num="16">For this reason heavy disaster overtook them, and those whose ways of living they admired and wished to imitate completely became their enemies and punished them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004017"/>
      <verse num="17">For it is no light thing to show irreverence to the divine laws&emdash;which later events will make clear.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004018"/>
      <heading>Jason Introduces Greek Customs</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">When the quadrennial games were being held at Tyre and the king was present,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004019"/>
      <verse num="19">the vile Jason sent envoys, chosen as being Antiochian citizens from Jerusalem, to carry 300 silver drachmas for the sacrifice to Hercules. Those who carried the money, however, thought best not to use it for sacrifice, because that was inappropriate, but to expend it for another purpose.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004020"/>
      <verse num="20">So this money was intended by the sender for the sacrifice to Hercules, but by the decision of its carriers it was applied to the construction of triremes.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004021"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="21">When Apollonius son of Menestheus was sent to Egypt for the coronation<note nid="n81004021.1"/> of Philometor as king, Antiochus learned that Philometor<note nid="n81004021.2"/> had become hostile to his government, and he took measures for his own security. Therefore upon arriving at Joppa he proceeded to Jerusalem.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004022"/>
      <verse num="22">He was welcomed magnificently by Jason and the city and ushered in with a blaze of torches and with shouts. Then he marched into Phoenicia.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004023"/>
      <heading>Menelaus Becomes High Priest</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="23">After a period of three years Jason sent Menelaus, the brother of the previously mentioned Simon, to carry the money to the king and to complete the records of essential business.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004024"/>
      <verse num="24">But he, when presented to the king, extolled him with an air of authority and secured the high priesthood for himself, outbidding Jason by 300 talents of silver.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004025"/>
      <verse num="25">After receiving the king&apos;s orders he returned, possessing no qualification for the high priesthood, but having the hot temper of a cruel tyrant and the rage of a savage wild beast.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004026"/>
      <verse num="26">So Jason, who after supplanting his own brother was supplanted by another man, was driven as a fugitive into the land of Ammon.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004027"/>
      <verse num="27">And Menelaus held the office, but he did not pay regularly any of the money promised to the king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004028"/>
      <verse num="28">When Sostratus the captain of the citadel kept requesting payment, for the collection of the revenue was his responsibility, the two of them were summoned by the king on account of this issue.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004029"/>
      <verse num="29">Menelaus left his own brother Lysimachus as deputy in the high priesthood, while Sostratus left Crates, the commander of the Cyprian troops.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004030"/>
      <heading>Murder of Onias</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="30">While such was the state of affairs, it happened that the people of Tarsus and of Mallus revolted because their cities had been given as a present to Antiochis, the king&apos;s concubine.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004031"/>
      <verse num="31">So the king went hastily to settle the trouble, leaving Andronicus, a man of high rank, to act as his deputy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004032"/>
      <verse num="32">But Menelaus, thinking he had obtained a suitable opportunity, stole some of the gold vessels of the temple and gave them to Andronicus; other vessels, as it happened, he had sold to Tyre and the neighboring cities.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004033"/>
      <verse num="33">When Onias became fully aware of these acts he publicly exposed them, having first withdrawn to a place of sanctuary at Daphne near Antioch.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004034"/>
      <verse num="34">Therefore Menelaus, taking Andronicus aside, urged him to kill Onias. Andronicus<note nid="n81004034.1"/> came to Onias and resorting to treachery offered him sworn pledges and gave him his right hand and in spite of Onias&apos; suspicion persuaded him to come out from the place of sanctuary; then, with no regard for justice, he immediately got rid of him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004035"/>
      <verse num="35">For this reason not only Jews, but many also of other nations, were grieved and displeased at the unjust murder of the man.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004036"/>
      <verse num="36">When the king returned from the region of Cilicia, the Jews in the<note nid="n81004036.1"/> city appealed to him with regard to the unreasonable murder of Onias, and the Greeks shared their hatred of the crime.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004037"/>
      <verse num="37">Therefore Antiochus was grieved at heart and filled with pity and wept because of the moderation and good conduct of the deceased;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004038"/>
      <verse num="38">and inflamed with anger, he immediately stripped off the purple robe from Andronicus, tore off his garments, and led him about the whole city to that very place where he had committed the outrage against Onias, and there he dispatched the bloodthirsty fellow. The Lord thus repaid him with the punishment he deserved.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004039"/>
      <heading>Unpopularity of Lysimachus and Menelaus</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="39">When many acts of sacrilege had been committed in the city by Lysimachus with the connivance of Menelaus, and when report of them had spread abroad, the populace gathered against Lysimachus, because many of the gold vessels had already been stolen.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004040"/>
      <verse num="40">And since the crowds were becoming aroused and filled with anger, Lysimachus armed about 3,000 men and launched an unjust attack, under the leadership of a certain Auranus, a man advanced in years and no less advanced in folly.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004041"/>
      <verse num="41">But when the Jews<note nid="n81004041.1"/> became aware of Lysimachus&apos; attack, some picked up stones, some blocks of wood, and others took handfuls of the ashes that were lying about and threw them in wild confusion at Lysimachus and his men.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004042"/>
      <verse num="42">As a result, they wounded many of them and killed some and put them all to flight; and the temple robber himself they killed close by the treasury.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004043"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="43">Charges were brought against Menelaus about this incident.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004044"/>
      <verse num="44">When the king came to Tyre, three men sent by the senate presented the case before him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004045"/>
      <verse num="45">But Menelaus, already as good as beaten, promised a substantial bribe to Ptolemy son of Dorymenes to win over the king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004046"/>
      <verse num="46">Therefore Ptolemy, taking the king aside into a colonnade as if for refreshment, induced the king to change his mind.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004047"/>
      <verse num="47">Menelaus, the cause of all the evil, he acquitted of the charges against him, while he sentenced to death those unfortunate men, who would have been freed uncondemned if they had pleaded even before Scythians.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004048"/>
      <verse num="48">And so those who had spoken for the city and the people and the holy vessels quickly suffered the unjust penalty.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004049"/>
      <verse num="49">Therefore even the Tyrians, showing their hatred of the crime, provided magnificently for their funeral.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81004050"/>
      <verse num="50">But Menelaus, because of the cupidity of those in power, remained in office, growing in wickedness, having become the chief plotter against his fellow citizens.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005001"/>
    <chapter num="5">
      <heading>Jason Tries to Regain Control</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">About this time Antiochus made his second invasion of Egypt.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005002"/>
      <verse num="2">And it happened that over all the city, for almost forty days, there appeared golden-clad horsemen charging through the air, in companies fully armed with lances and drawn swords&emdash;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005003"/>
      <verse num="3">troops of horsemen drawn up, attacks and counterattacks made on this side and on that, brandishing of shields, massing of spears, hurling of missiles, the flash of golden trappings, and armor of all sorts.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005004"/>
      <verse num="4">Therefore everyone prayed that the apparition might prove to have been a good omen.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">When a false rumor arose that Antiochus was dead, Jason took no less than 1,000 men and suddenly made an assault upon the city. When the troops upon the wall had been forced back and at last the city was being taken, Menelaus took refuge in the citadel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005006"/>
      <verse num="6">But Jason kept relentlessly slaughtering his fellow citizens, not realizing that success at the cost of one&apos;s kindred is the greatest misfortune, but imagining that he was setting up trophies of victory over enemies and not over compatriots.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005007"/>
      <verse num="7">He did not gain control of the government, however, and in the end got only disgrace from his conspiracy and fled again into the country of the Ammonites.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005008"/>
      <verse num="8">Finally he met a miserable end. Sentenced by Aretas the ruler of the Arabs, fleeing from city to city, pursued by all men, hated as a rebel against the laws, and abhorred as the executioner of his country and his fellow citizens, he was cast ashore in Egypt;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005009"/>
      <verse num="9">and he who had driven many from their own country into exile died in exile, having embarked to go to the Lacedaemonians in hope of finding protection because of their kinship.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005010"/>
      <verse num="10">He who had cast out many to lie unburied had no one to mourn for him; he had no funeral of any sort and no place in the tomb of his fathers.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005011"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="11">When news of what had happened reached the king, he took it to mean that Judea was in revolt. So, raging inwardly, he left Egypt and took the city by storm.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005012"/>
      <verse num="12">And he commanded his soldiers to cut down relentlessly everyone they met and to slay those who went into the houses.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005013"/>
      <verse num="13">Then there was killing of young and old, destruction of women and children, and slaughter of virgins and infants.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005014"/>
      <verse num="14">Within the total of three days 80,000 were destroyed, 40,000 in hand-to-hand fighting; and as many were sold into slavery as were slain.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005015"/>
      <heading>Pillage of the Temple</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="15">Not content with this, Antiochus<note nid="n81005015.1"/> dared to enter the holiest temple in all the world, guided by Menelaus, who had become a traitor both to the laws and to his country.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005016"/>
      <verse num="16">He took the holy vessels with his polluted hands and swept away with profane hands the votive offerings that other kings had made to enhance the glory and honor of the place.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005017"/>
      <verse num="17">Antiochus was elated in spirit and did not perceive that the Lord was angered for a little while because of the sins of those who dwelt in the city and that therefore he was disregarding the Holy Place.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005018"/>
      <verse num="18">But if it had not happened that they were involved in many sins, this man would have been scourged and turned back from his rash act as soon as he came forward, just as Heliodorus had been, whom King Seleucus sent to inspect the treasury.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005019"/>
      <verse num="19">But the Lord did not choose the nation for the sake of the Holy Place, but the place for the sake of the nation.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005020"/>
      <verse num="20">Therefore the place itself shared in the misfortunes that befell the nation and afterward participated in its benefits; and what was forsaken in the wrath of the Almighty was restored again in all its glory when the great Lord was reconciled.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005021"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="21">So Antiochus carried off 1,800 talents from the temple and hurried away to Antioch, thinking in his arrogance that he could sail on the land and walk on the sea, because his mind was elated.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005022"/>
      <verse num="22">And he left governors to afflict the people: at Jerusalem, Philip, by birth a Phrygian and in character more barbarous than the man who appointed him;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005023"/>
      <verse num="23">and at Gerizim, Andronicus; and besides these Menelaus, who lorded it over his fellow citizens worse than the others did. In his malice toward the Jewish citizens,<note nid="n81005023.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005024"/>
      <verse num="24">Antiochus sent Apollonius, the captain of the Mysians, with an army of 22,000 and commanded him to slay all the grown men and to sell the women and boys as slaves.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005025"/>
      <verse num="25">When this man arrived in Jerusalem, he pretended to be peaceably disposed and waited until the holy Sabbath day; then, finding the Jews not at work, he ordered his men to parade under arms.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005026"/>
      <verse num="26">He put to the sword all those who came out to see them, then rushed into the city with his armed men and killed great numbers of people.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81005027"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="27">But Judas Maccabeus, with about nine others, got away to the wilderness and kept himself and his companions alive in the mountains as wild animals do; they continued to live on what grew wild, so that they might not share in the defilement.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006001"/>
    <chapter num="6">
      <heading>Suppression of Judaism</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Not long after this, the king sent an Athenian senator<note nid="n81006001.1"/> to compel the Jews to forsake the laws of their fathers and cease to live by the laws of God</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006002"/>
      <verse num="2">and also to pollute the temple in Jerusalem and call it the temple of Olympian Zeus and to call the one in Gerizim the temple of Zeus the Friend of Strangers, as did the people who dwelt in that place.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006003"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="3">Harsh and utterly grievous was the onslaught of evil.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006004"/>
      <verse num="4">For the temple was filled with debauchery and reveling by the Gentiles, who dallied with prostitutes and had intercourse with women within the sacred precincts and besides brought in things for sacrifice that were unfit.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006005"/>
      <verse num="5">The altar was covered with abominable offerings that were forbidden by the laws.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006006"/>
      <verse num="6">No one could either keep the Sabbath or observe the feasts of his fathers or so much as confess to being a Jew.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006007"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">On the monthly celebration of the king&apos;s birthday, the Jews<note nid="n81006007.1"/> were taken, under bitter constraint, to partake of the sacrifices; and when the Feast of Dionysus came, they were compelled to walk in the procession in honor of Dionysus, wearing wreaths of ivy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006008"/>
      <verse num="8">At the suggestion of Ptolemy<note nid="n81006008.1"/> a decree was issued to the neighboring Greek cities, that they should adopt the same policy toward the Jews and make them partake of the sacrifices</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006009"/>
      <verse num="9">and should slay those who did not choose to change over to Greek customs. One could see, therefore, the misery that had come upon them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006010"/>
      <verse num="10">For example, two women were brought in for having circumcised their children. These women they publicly paraded about the city, with their babies hung at their breasts, and then hurled them down headlong from the wall.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006011"/>
      <verse num="11">Others, who had assembled in the caves nearby to observe the seventh day secretly, were betrayed to Philip and were all burned together, because their piety kept them from defending themselves, in view of their regard for that holiest day.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006012"/>
      <heading>Providential Significance of the Persecution</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="12">Now I urge those who read this book not to be depressed by such calamities, but to recognize that these punishments were designed not to destroy but to discipline our people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006013"/>
      <verse num="13">In fact, to punish the ungodly quickly rather than leave them alone for very long is a sign of great kindness.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006014"/>
      <verse num="14">For in the case of the other nations the Lord waits patiently to punish them until they have reached the full measure of their sins; but he does not deal in this way with us,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006015"/>
      <verse num="15">in order that he may not take vengeance on us afterward when our sins have reached their height.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006016"/>
      <verse num="16">Therefore he never withdraws his mercy from us. Though he disciplines us with calamities, he does not forsake his own people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006017"/>
      <verse num="17">Let what we have said serve as a reminder; we must go on briefly with the story.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006018"/>
      <heading>Martyrdom of Eleazar</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">Eleazar, one of the scribes in high position, a man now advanced in age and of noble presence, was being forced to open his mouth to eat swine&apos;s flesh.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006019"/>
      <verse num="19">But he, welcoming death with honor rather than life with pollution, went up to the rack of his own accord, spitting out the flesh,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006020"/>
      <verse num="20">as men ought to go who have the courage to refuse things that it is not right to taste, even for the natural love of life.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006021"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="21">Those who were in charge of that unlawful sacrifice took the man aside, because of their long acquaintance with him, and privately urged him to bring meat of his own providing, proper for him to use, and pretend that he was eating the flesh of the sacrificial meal that had been commanded by the king,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006022"/>
      <verse num="22">so that by doing this he might be saved from death and be treated kindly on account of his old friendship with them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006023"/>
      <verse num="23">But making a high resolve, worthy of his years and the dignity of his old age and the gray hairs that he had reached with distinction and his excellent life even from childhood, and moreover according to the holy God-given law, he declared himself quickly, telling them to send him to the grave.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006024"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="24"><q class="begin-double" qid="81006024.1" from="81006024.1" to="81006024.2"/>Such pretense is not worthy of our time of life,<q class="end-double" qid="81006024.2" from="81006024.1" to="81006024.2"/> he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="81006024.3" from="81006024.3" to="81006028.1"/>lest many of the young should suppose that Eleazar in his ninetieth year has gone over to an alien religion,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006025"/>
      <verse num="25">and through my pretense, for the sake of living a brief moment longer, they should be led astray because of me, while I defile and disgrace my old age.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006026"/>
      <verse num="26">For even if for the present I should avoid the punishment of men, yet whether I live or die I shall not escape the hands of the Almighty.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006027"/>
      <verse num="27">Therefore, by manfully giving up my life now, I will show myself worthy of my old age</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006028"/>
      <verse num="28">and leave to the young a noble example of how to die a good death willingly and nobly for the revered and holy laws.<q class="end-double" qid="81006028.1" from="81006024.3" to="81006028.1"/><end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>When he had said this, he went<note nid="n81006028.1"/> at once to the rack.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006029"/>
      <verse num="29">And those who a little before had acted toward him with good will now changed to ill will, because the words he had uttered were in their opinion sheer madness.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006030"/>
      <verse num="30">When he was about to die under the blows, he groaned aloud and said: <q class="begin-double" qid="81006030.1" from="81006030.1" to="81006030.2"/>It is clear to the Lord in his holy knowledge that, though I might have been saved from death, I am enduring terrible sufferings in my body under this beating, but in my soul I am glad to suffer these things because I fear him.<q class="end-double" qid="81006030.2" from="81006030.1" to="81006030.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81006031"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="31">So in this way he died, leaving in his death an example of nobility and a memorial of courage, not only to the young but to the great body of his nation.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007001"/>
    <chapter num="7">
      <heading>Martyrdom of Seven Brothers</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">It happened also that seven brothers and their mother were arrested and were being compelled by the king, under torture with whips and cords, to partake of unlawful swine&apos;s flesh.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007002"/>
      <verse num="2">One of them, acting as their spokesman, said, <q class="begin-double" qid="81007002.1" from="81007002.1" to="81007002.2"/>What do you intend to ask and learn from us? For we are ready to die rather than transgress the laws of our fathers.<q class="end-double" qid="81007002.2" from="81007002.1" to="81007002.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007003"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="3">The king fell into a rage and gave orders that pans and caldrons be heated.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007004"/>
      <verse num="4">These were heated immediately, and he commanded that the tongue of their spokesman be cut out and that they scalp him and cut off his hands and feet, while the rest of the brothers and the mother looked on.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007005"/>
      <verse num="5">When he was utterly helpless, the king<note nid="n81007005.1"/> ordered them to take him to the fire, still breathing, and to fry him in a pan. The smoke from the pan spread widely, but the brothers<note nid="n81007005.2"/> and their mother encouraged one another to die nobly, saying,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007006"/>
      <verse num="6"><q class="begin-double" qid="81007006.1" from="81007006.1" to="81007006.4"/>The Lord God is watching over us and in truth has compassion on us, as Moses declared in his song that bore witness against the people to their faces, when he said, <q class="begin-single" qid="81007006.2" from="81007006.2" to="81007006.3"/>And he will have compassion on his servants.<q class="end-single" qid="81007006.3" from="81007006.2" to="81007006.3"/><q class="end-double" qid="81007006.4" from="81007006.1" to="81007006.4"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007007"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">After the first brother had died in this way, they brought forward the second for their sport. They tore off the skin of his head with the hair and asked him, <q class="begin-double" qid="81007007.1" from="81007007.1" to="81007007.2"/>Will you eat rather than have your body punished limb by limb?<q class="end-double" qid="81007007.2" from="81007007.1" to="81007007.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007008"/>
      <verse num="8">He replied in the language of his fathers and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="81007008.1" from="81007008.1" to="81007008.2"/>No.<q class="end-double" qid="81007008.2" from="81007008.1" to="81007008.2"/> Therefore he in turn underwent tortures as the first brother had done.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007009"/>
      <verse num="9">And when he was at his last breath, he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="81007009.1" from="81007009.1" to="81007009.2"/>You accursed wretch, you dismiss us from this present life, but the King of the universe will raise us up to an everlasting renewal of life, because we have died for his laws.<q class="end-double" qid="81007009.2" from="81007009.1" to="81007009.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007010"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">After him, the third was the victim of their sport. When it was demanded, he quickly put out his tongue and courageously stretched forth his hands</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007011"/>
      <verse num="11">and said nobly, <q class="begin-double" qid="81007011.1" from="81007011.1" to="81007011.2"/>I got these from heaven, and because of his laws I disdain them, and from him I hope to get them back again.<q class="end-double" qid="81007011.2" from="81007011.1" to="81007011.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007012"/>
      <verse num="12">As a result the king himself and those with him were astonished at the young man&apos;s spirit, for he regarded his sufferings as nothing.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007013"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="13">When he too had died, they maltreated and tortured the fourth in the same way.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007014"/>
      <verse num="14">And when he was near death, he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="81007014.1" from="81007014.1" to="81007014.2"/>One cannot but choose to die at the hands of men and to cherish the hope that God gives of being raised again by him. But for you there will be no resurrection to life!<q class="end-double" qid="81007014.2" from="81007014.1" to="81007014.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007015"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="15">Next they brought forward the fifth and maltreated him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007016"/>
      <verse num="16">But he looked at the king<note nid="n81007016.1"/> and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="81007016.1" from="81007016.1" to="81007017.1"/>Because you have authority among men, mortal though you are, you do what you please. But do not think that God has forsaken our people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007017"/>
      <verse num="17">Keep on, then, and see his mighty power, when you and your descendants are in torment!<q class="end-double" qid="81007017.1" from="81007016.1" to="81007017.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007018"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">After him they brought forward the sixth. And when he was about to die, he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="81007018.1" from="81007018.1" to="81007019.1"/>Do not deceive yourself in vain. For we are suffering these things on our own account, because of our sins against our own God. Therefore<note nid="n81007018.1"/> astounding things have happened.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007019"/>
      <verse num="19">But do not think that you will go unpunished for having tried to fight against God!<q class="end-double" qid="81007019.1" from="81007018.1" to="81007019.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007020"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="20">The mother was especially admirable and worthy of honorable memory. Though she saw her seven sons perish within a single day, she bore it with good courage because of her hope in the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007021"/>
      <verse num="21">She encouraged each of them in the language of their fathers. Filled with a noble spirit, she fired her woman&apos;s reasoning with a man&apos;s courage and said to them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007022"/>
      <verse num="22"><q class="begin-double" qid="81007022.1" from="81007022.1" to="81007023.1"/>I do not know how you came into being in my womb. It was not I who gave you life and breath, nor I who set in order the elements within each of you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007023"/>
      <verse num="23">Therefore the Creator of the world, who shaped the beginning of mankind and devised the origin of all things, will in his mercy give life and breath back to you again, since you now forget yourselves for the sake of his laws.<q class="end-double" qid="81007023.1" from="81007022.1" to="81007023.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007024"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="24">Antiochus felt that he was being treated with contempt, and he was suspicious of her reproachful tone. The youngest brother being still alive, Antiochus<note nid="n81007024.1"/> not only appealed to him in words, but promised with oaths that he would make him rich and enviable if he would turn from the ways of his fathers and that he would take him for his friend and entrust him with public affairs.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007025"/>
      <verse num="25">Since the young man would not listen to him at all, the king called the mother to him and urged her to advise the youth to save himself.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007026"/>
      <verse num="26">After much urging on his part, she undertook to persuade her son.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007027"/>
      <verse num="27">But, leaning close to him, she spoke in their native tongue as follows, deriding the cruel tyrant: <q class="begin-double" qid="81007027.1" from="81007027.1" to="81007029.1"/>My son, have pity on me. I carried you nine months in my womb and nursed you for three years and have reared you and brought you up to this point in your life and have taken care of you.<note nid="n81007027.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007028"/>
      <verse num="28">I urge you, my child, to look at the heaven and the earth and see everything that is in them and recognize that not out of things that already existed did God make them, and so too the human race comes into being.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007029"/>
      <verse num="29">Do not fear this butcher, but prove worthy of your brothers. Accept death, so that in God&apos;s mercy I may get you back again along with your brothers.<q class="end-double" qid="81007029.1" from="81007027.1" to="81007029.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007030"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="30">Now as she was speaking, the young man said, <q class="begin-double" qid="81007030.1" from="81007030.1" to="81007038.1"/>What are you<note nid="n81007030.1"/> waiting for? I will not obey the king&apos;s command, but I obey the command of the law that was given to our fathers through Moses.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007031"/>
      <verse num="31">But you,<note nid="n81007031.1"/> who have contrived all sorts of evil against the Hebrews, will certainly not escape the hands of God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007032"/>
      <verse num="32">For we are suffering because of our own sins.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007033"/>
      <verse num="33">And if our living Lord is angry for a little while, to rebuke and discipline us, he will again be reconciled with his own servants.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007034"/>
      <verse num="34">But you, unholy wretch, you most defiled of all men, do not be elated in vain and puffed up by uncertain hopes, when you raise your hand against the children of heaven.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007035"/>
      <verse num="35">You have not yet escaped the judgment of the almighty, all-seeing God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007036"/>
      <verse num="36">For now our brothers after enduring a brief suffering have fallen to an ever-flowing life under God&apos;s covenant; but you, by the judgment of God, will receive just punishment for your arrogance.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007037"/>
      <verse num="37">I, like my brothers, give up body and life for the laws of our fathers, appealing to God to show mercy soon to our nation and by afflictions and plagues to make you confess that he alone is God</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007038"/>
      <verse num="38">and through me and my brothers to bring to an end the wrath of the Almighty that has justly fallen on our whole nation.<q class="end-double" qid="81007038.1" from="81007030.1" to="81007038.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007039"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="39">The king fell into a rage and handled him worse than the others, being exasperated at his scorn.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007040"/>
      <verse num="40">So he died in his integrity, putting his whole trust in the Lord.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007041"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="41">Last of all, the mother died, after her sons.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81007042"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="42">Let this be enough, then, about the eating of sacrifices and the extreme tortures.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008001"/>
    <chapter num="8">
      <heading>Revolt of Judas Maccabeus</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Judas, however, who was also called Maccabeus, and his companions secretly entered the villages and summoned their kinsmen and enlisted those who had continued in the Jewish faith, and so they gathered about 6,000 men.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008002"/>
      <verse num="2">They earnestly prayed to the Lord to look upon the people who were oppressed by all and to have pity on the temple that had been profaned by ungodly men</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008003"/>
      <verse num="3">and to have mercy on the city that was being destroyed and about to be leveled to the ground and to listen to the blood that cried out to him</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008004"/>
      <verse num="4">and to remember also the lawless destruction of the innocent babies and the blasphemies committed against his name and to show his hatred of evil.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">As soon as Maccabeus got his army organized, the Gentiles could not withstand him, for the wrath of the Lord had turned to mercy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008006"/>
      <verse num="6">Coming without warning, he would set fire to towns and villages. He captured strategic positions and put to flight not a few of the enemy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008007"/>
      <verse num="7">He found the nights most advantageous for such attacks. And talk of his valor spread everywhere.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008008"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="8">When Philip saw that the man was gaining ground little by little and that he was pushing ahead with more frequent successes, he wrote to Ptolemy, the governor of Coelesyria and Phoenicia, to come to the aid of the king&apos;s government.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008009"/>
      <verse num="9">And Ptolemy<note nid="n81008009.1"/> promptly appointed Nicanor son of Patroclus, one of the king&apos;s chief friends, and sent him, in command of no fewer than 20,000 Gentiles of all nations, to wipe out the whole race of Judea. He associated with him Gorgias, a general and a man of experience in military service.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008010"/>
      <verse num="10">Nicanor determined to make up for the king the tribute due to the Romans, 2,000 talents, by selling the captured Jews into slavery.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008011"/>
      <verse num="11">And he immediately sent to the cities on the seacoast, inviting them to buy Jewish slaves and promising to hand over ninety slaves for a talent, not expecting the judgment from the Almighty that was about to overtake him.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008012"/>
      <heading>Preparation for Battle</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="12">Word came to Judas concerning Nicanor&apos;s invasion; and when he told his companions of the arrival of the army,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008013"/>
      <verse num="13">those who were cowardly and distrustful of God&apos;s justice ran off and got away.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008014"/>
      <verse num="14">Others sold all their remaining property and at the same time asked the Lord to rescue those who had been sold by the ungodly Nicanor before he ever met them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008015"/>
      <verse num="15">if not for their own sake, yet for the sake of the covenants made with their fathers, and because he had called them by his holy and glorious name.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008016"/>
      <verse num="16">But Maccabeus gathered his men together, to the number of 6,000, and exhorted them not to be frightened by the enemy and not to fear the great multitude of Gentiles who were wickedly coming against them, but to fight nobly,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008017"/>
      <verse num="17">keeping before their eyes the lawless outrage that the Gentiles<note nid="n81008017.1"/> had committed against the Holy Place and the torture of the derided city and, besides, the overthrow of their ancestral way of life.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008018"/>
      <verse num="18"><q class="begin-double" qid="81008018.1" from="81008018.1" to="81008018.2"/>For they trust to arms and acts of daring,<q class="end-double" qid="81008018.2" from="81008018.1" to="81008018.2"/> he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="81008018.3" from="81008018.3" to="81008018.4"/>but we trust in the almighty God, who is able with a single nod to strike down those who are coming against us and even the whole world.<q class="end-double" qid="81008018.4" from="81008018.3" to="81008018.4"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008019"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">Moreover, he told them of the times when help came to their ancestors; both the time of Sennacherib, when 185,000 perished,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008020"/>
      <verse num="20">and the time of the battle with the Galatians that took place in Babylonia, when 8,000 in all went into the affair, with 4,000 Macedonians; and when the Macedonians were hard pressed, the 8,000, by the help that came to them from heaven, destroyed 120,000 and took much booty.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008021"/>
      <heading>Judas Defeats Nicanor</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="21">With these words he filled them with good courage and made them ready to die for their laws and their country; then he divided his army into four parts.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008022"/>
      <verse num="22">He appointed his brothers also, Simon and Joseph and Jonathan, each to command a division, putting 1,500 men under each.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008023"/>
      <verse num="23">He also read aloud from the holy book the words <q class="begin-double" qid="81008023.1" from="81008023.1" to="81008023.2"/>El-ezer,<q class="end-double" qid="81008023.2" from="81008023.1" to="81008023.2"/> thus giving the watchword, <q class="begin-double" qid="81008023.3" from="81008023.3" to="81008023.4"/>God&apos;s help<q class="end-double" qid="81008023.4" from="81008023.3" to="81008023.4"/>; then, leading the first division himself, he joined battle with Nicanor.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008024"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="24">With the Almighty as their ally, they killed more than 9,000 of the enemy and wounded and disabled most of Nicanor&apos;s army and forced them all to flee.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008025"/>
      <verse num="25">They captured the money of those who had come to buy them as slaves. After pursuing them for some distance, they were obliged to return because the hour was late.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008026"/>
      <verse num="26">For it was the day before the Sabbath, and for that reason they did not continue their pursuit.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008027"/>
      <verse num="27">And when they had collected the arms of the enemy and stripped them of their spoils, they kept the Sabbath, giving great praise and thanks to the Lord, who had preserved them for that day and allotted it to them as the beginning of mercy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008028"/>
      <verse num="28">After the Sabbath they gave some of the spoils to those who had been tortured and to the widows and orphans and distributed the rest among themselves and their children.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008029"/>
      <verse num="29">When they had done this, they made common supplication and begged the merciful Lord to be wholly reconciled with his servants.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008030"/>
      <heading>Judas Defeats Timothy and Bacchides</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="30">In encounters with the forces of Timothy and Bacchides they killed more than 20,000 of them and got possession of some exceedingly high strongholds, and they divided very much plunder, giving to those who had been tortured and to the orphans and widows and also to the aged shares equal to their own.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008031"/>
      <verse num="31">Collecting the arms of the enemy,<note nid="n81008031.1"/> they stored them all carefully in strategic places and carried the rest of the spoils to Jerusalem.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008032"/>
      <verse num="32">They killed the commander of Timothy&apos;s forces, a most unholy man and one who had greatly troubled the Jews.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008033"/>
      <verse num="33">While they were celebrating the victory in the city of their fathers, they burned those who had set fire to the sacred gates, and Callisthenes,<note nid="n81008033.1"/> who had fled into one little house; so these received the proper recompense for their impiety.<note nid="n81008033.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008034"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="34">The thrice-accursed Nicanor, who had brought 1,000 merchants to buy the Jews,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008035"/>
      <verse num="35">having been humbled with the help of the Lord by opponents whom he regarded as of the least account, took off his splendid uniform and made his way alone like a runaway slave across the country till he reached Antioch, having succeeded chiefly in the destruction of his own army!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81008036"/>
      <verse num="36">Thus he who had undertaken to secure tribute for the Romans by the capture of the people of Jerusalem proclaimed that the Jews had a Defender and that therefore the Jews were invulnerable, because they followed the laws ordained by him.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009001"/>
    <chapter num="9">
      <heading>Last Campaign of Antiochus Epiphanes</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">About that time, as it happened, Antiochus had retreated in disorder from the region of Persia.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009002"/>
      <verse num="2">For he had entered the city called Persepolis and attempted to rob the temples and control the city. Therefore the people rushed to the rescue with arms, and Antiochus and his men<note nid="n81009002.1"/> were defeated, with the result that Antiochus was put to flight by the inhabitants and beat a shameful retreat.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009003"/>
      <verse num="3">While he was in Ecbatana, news came to him of what had happened to Nicanor and the forces of Timothy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009004"/>
      <verse num="4">Transported with rage, he conceived the idea of turning upon the Jews the injury done by those who had put him to flight; so he ordered his charioteer to drive without stopping until he completed the journey. But the judgment of heaven rode with him! For in his arrogance he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="81009004.1" from="81009004.1" to="81009004.2"/>When I get there I will make Jerusalem a cemetery of Jews.<q class="end-double" qid="81009004.2" from="81009004.1" to="81009004.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">But the all-seeing Lord, the God of Israel, struck him an incurable and invisible blow. As soon as he ceased speaking he was seized with a pain in his bowels for which there was no relief and with sharp internal tortures&emdash;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009006"/>
      <verse num="6">and that very justly, for he had tortured the bowels of others with many and strange inflictions.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009007"/>
      <verse num="7">Yet he did not in any way stop his insolence, but was even more filled with arrogance, breathing fire in his rage against the Jews and giving orders to hasten the journey. And so it came about that he fell out of his chariot as it was rushing along, and the fall was so hard as to torture every limb of his body.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009008"/>
      <verse num="8">Thus he who had just been thinking in his superhuman arrogance that he could command the waves of the sea and imagining that he could weigh the high mountains in a balance was brought down to earth and carried in a litter, making the power of God manifest to all.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009009"/>
      <verse num="9">And so the ungodly man&apos;s body swarmed with worms, and while he was still living in anguish and pain, his flesh rotted away, and because of his stench the whole army felt revulsion at his decay.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009010"/>
      <verse num="10">Because of his intolerable stench no one was able to carry the man who a little while before had thought that he could touch the stars of heaven.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009011"/>
      <verse num="11">Then it was that, broken in spirit, he began to lose much of his arrogance and to come to his senses under the scourge of God, for he was tortured with pain every moment.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009012"/>
      <verse num="12">And when he could not endure his own stench, he uttered these words: <q class="begin-double" qid="81009012.1" from="81009012.1" to="81009012.2"/>It is right to be subject to God, and no mortal should think that he is equal to God.<q class="end-double" qid="81009012.2" from="81009012.1" to="81009012.2"/><note nid="n81009012.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009013"/>
      <heading>Antiochus Makes a Promise to God</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="13">Then the abominable fellow made a vow to the Lord, who would no longer have mercy on him, stating</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009014"/>
      <verse num="14">that the holy city, which he had been hastening to level to the ground and to make a cemetery, he was now declaring to be free;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009015"/>
      <verse num="15">and the Jews, whom he had not considered worth burying but had planned to throw out with their children to the beasts, for the birds to pick, he would make, all of them, equal to citizens of Athens;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009016"/>
      <verse num="16">and the holy sanctuary, which he had formerly plundered, he would adorn with the finest offerings; and the holy vessels he would give back, all of them, many times over; and the expenses incurred for the sacrifices he would provide from his own revenues;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009017"/>
      <verse num="17">and in addition to all this he also would become a Jew and would visit every inhabited place to proclaim the power of God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009018"/>
      <verse num="18">But when his sufferings did not in any way abate, for the judgment of God had justly come upon him, he gave up all hope for himself and wrote to the Jews the following letter, in the form of a supplication. This was its content:</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009019"/>
      <heading>Antiochus&apos; Letter and Death</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19"><q class="begin-double" qid="81009019.1" from="81009019.1" to="81009027.1"/>To his worthy Jewish citizens, Antiochus their king and general sends hearty greetings and good wishes for their health and prosperity.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009020"/>
      <verse num="20">If you and your children are well and your affairs are as you wish, I am glad. As my hope is in heaven,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009021"/>
      <verse num="21">I remember with affection your esteem and good will. On my way back from the region of Persia I suffered an annoying illness, and I have deemed it necessary to take thought for the general security of all.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009022"/>
      <verse num="22">I do not despair of my condition, for I have good hope of recovering from my illness,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009023"/>
      <verse num="23">but I observed that my father, on the occasions when he made expeditions into the upper country, appointed his successor,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009024"/>
      <verse num="24">so that, if anything unexpected happened or any unwelcome news came, the people throughout the realm would not be troubled, for they would know to whom the government was left.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009025"/>
      <verse num="25">Moreover, I understand how the princes along the borders and the neighbors to my kingdom keep watching for opportunities and waiting to see what will happen. So I have appointed my son Antiochus to be king, whom I have often entrusted and commended to most of you when I hastened off to the upper provinces; and I have written to him what is written here.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009026"/>
      <verse num="26">I therefore urge and entreat you to remember the public and private services rendered to you and to maintain your present good will, each of you, toward me and my son.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009027"/>
      <verse num="27">For I am sure that he will follow my policy and will treat you with moderation and kindness.<q class="end-double" qid="81009027.1" from="81009019.1" to="81009027.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009028"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="28">So the murderer and blasphemer, having endured the most intense suffering, such as he had inflicted on others, came to the end of his life by a most pitiable fate, among the mountains in a strange land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81009029"/>
      <verse num="29">And Philip, one of his courtiers, took his body home; then, fearing the son of Antiochus, he conveyed himself to Ptolemy Philometor in Egypt.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010001"/>
    <chapter num="10">
      <heading>Purification of the Temple</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Now Maccabeus and his followers, the Lord leading them on, recovered the temple and the city;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010002"/>
      <verse num="2">and they tore down the altars that had been built in the public square by the foreigners and also destroyed the sacred precincts.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010003"/>
      <verse num="3">They purified the sanctuary and made another altar of sacrifice; then, striking fire out of flint, they offered sacrifices, after a lapse of two years, and they burned incense and lighted lamps and set out the bread of the Presence.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010004"/>
      <verse num="4">And when they had done this, they fell prostrate and prayed earnestly to the Lord that they might never again fall into such misfortunes, but that, if they should ever sin, they might be disciplined by him with forbearance and not be handed over to blasphemous and barbarous nations.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010005"/>
      <verse num="5">It happened that on the same day on which the sanctuary had been profaned by the foreigners, the purification of the sanctuary took place, that is, on the twenty-fifth day of the same month, which was Chislev.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010006"/>
      <verse num="6">And they celebrated it for eight days with rejoicing, in the manner of the Feast of Booths, remembering how not long before, during the Feast of Booths, they had been wandering in the mountains and caves like wild animals.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010007"/>
      <verse num="7">Therefore bearing ivy-wreathed wands and beautiful branches and also fronds of palm, they offered hymns of thanksgiving to him who had given success to the purifying of his own Holy Place.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010008"/>
      <verse num="8">They decreed by public ordinance and referendum that the whole nation of the Jews should observe these days every year.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010009"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="9">Such then was the end of Antiochus, who was called Epiphanes.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010010"/>
      <heading>Accession of Antiochus Eupator</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">Now we will tell what took place under Antiochus Eupator, who was the son of that ungodly man, and will give a brief summary of the principal calamities of the wars.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010011"/>
      <verse num="11">This man, when he succeeded to the kingdom, appointed one Lysias to have charge of the government and to be chief governor of Coelesyria and Phoenicia.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010012"/>
      <verse num="12">Ptolemy, who was called Macron, took the lead in showing justice to the Jews because of the wrong that had been done to them and attempted to maintain peaceful relations with them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010013"/>
      <verse num="13">As a result he was accused before Eupator by the king&apos;s friends. He heard himself called a traitor at every turn, because he had abandoned Cyprus, which Philometor had entrusted to him, and had gone over to Antiochus Epiphanes. Unable to command the respect due his office,<note nid="n81010013.1"/> he took poison and ended his life.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010014"/>
      <heading>Campaign in Idumea</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="14">When Gorgias became governor of the region, he maintained a force of mercenaries and at every turn kept on warring against the Jews.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010015"/>
      <verse num="15">Besides this, the Idumeans, who had control of important strongholds, were harassing the Jews; they received those who were banished from Jerusalem and endeavored to keep up the war.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010016"/>
      <verse num="16">But Maccabeus and his men, after making solemn supplication and asking God to fight on their side, rushed to the strongholds of the Idumeans.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010017"/>
      <verse num="17">Attacking them vigorously, they gained possession of the places and beat off all who fought upon the wall and killed those whom they encountered, killing no fewer than 20,000.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010018"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">When no less than 9,000 took refuge in two very strong towers well equipped to withstand a siege,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010019"/>
      <verse num="19">Maccabeus left Simon and Joseph, and also Zacchaeus and his men, a force sufficient to besiege them; and he himself set off for places where he was more urgently needed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010020"/>
      <verse num="20">But the men with Simon, being lovers of money, were bribed by some of those who were in the towers and on receiving 70,000 drachmas let some of them slip away.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010021"/>
      <verse num="21">When word of what had happened came to Maccabeus, he gathered the leaders of the people and accused these men of having sold their brothers for money by setting their enemies free to fight against them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010022"/>
      <verse num="22">Then he killed these men who had turned traitor and immediately captured the two towers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010023"/>
      <verse num="23">Having success at arms in everything he undertook, he destroyed more than 20,000 in the two strongholds.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010024"/>
      <heading>Judas Defeats Timothy</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="24">Now Timothy, who had been defeated by the Jews before, gathered a tremendous force of mercenaries and collected the cavalry from Asia in no small number. He came on, intending to take Judea by storm.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010025"/>
      <verse num="25">As he drew near, Maccabeus and his men sprinkled dust upon their heads and girded their loins with sackcloth, in supplication to God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010026"/>
      <verse num="26">Falling upon the steps before the altar, they implored him to be gracious to them and to be an enemy to their enemies and an adversary to their adversaries, as the law declares.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010027"/>
      <verse num="27">And rising from their prayer they took up their arms and advanced a considerable distance from the city; and when they came near to the enemy they halted.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010028"/>
      <verse num="28">Just as dawn was breaking, the two armies joined battle, the one having as pledge of success and victory not only their valor but also their reliance upon the Lord, while the other made rage their leader in the fight.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010029"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="29">When the battle became fierce, there appeared to the enemy from heaven five resplendent men on horses with golden bridles, and they were leading the Jews.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010030"/>
      <verse num="30">Two of them took Maccabeus in their midst, and protecting him with their own armor and weapons, they kept him from being wounded. And they showered arrows and thunderbolts upon the enemy, so that, confused and blinded, they were thrown into disorder and cut to pieces.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010031"/>
      <verse num="31">And they slaughtered 20,500 men, plus 600 horsemen.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010032"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="32">Timothy himself fled to a stronghold called Gazara, especially well garrisoned, where Chaereas was commander.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010033"/>
      <verse num="33">Then Maccabeus and his men were glad, and they besieged the fort for four days.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010034"/>
      <verse num="34">The men within, relying on the strength of the place, blasphemed terribly and hurled out wicked words.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010035"/>
      <verse num="35">But at dawn of the fifth day, twenty young men in the army of Maccabeus, fired with anger because of the blasphemies, bravely stormed the wall and with savage fury cut down everyone they met.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010036"/>
      <verse num="36">Others who came up in the same way wheeled around against the defenders and set fire to the towers; they kindled fires and burned the blasphemers alive. Others broke open the gates and let in the rest of the force, and they occupied the city.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010037"/>
      <verse num="37">They killed Timothy, who was hidden in a cistern, and his brother Chaereas and Apollophanes.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81010038"/>
      <verse num="38">When they had accomplished these things, with hymns and thanksgivings they blessed the Lord who shows great kindness to Israel and gives them the victory.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011001"/>
    <chapter num="11">
      <heading>Lysias Besieges Beth-zur</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Very soon after this, Lysias, the king&apos;s guardian and kinsman, who was in charge of the government, being vexed at what had happened,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011002"/>
      <verse num="2">gathered about 80,000 men and all his cavalry and came against the Jews. He intended to make the city a home for Greeks</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011003"/>
      <verse num="3">and to levy tribute on the temple as he did on the sacred places of the other nations and to put up the high priesthood for sale every year.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011004"/>
      <verse num="4">He took no account whatever of the power of God, but was elated with his ten thousands of infantry and his thousands of cavalry and his eighty elephants.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011005"/>
      <verse num="5">Entering Judea, he approached Beth-zur, which was a fortified place about five leagues<note nid="n81011005.1"/> from Jerusalem, and pressed it hard.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011006"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="6">When Maccabeus and his men got word that Lysias<note nid="n81011006.1"/> was besieging the strongholds, they and all the people, with lamentations and tears, begged the Lord to send a good angel to save Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011007"/>
      <verse num="7">Maccabeus himself was the first to take up arms, and he urged the others to risk their lives with him to aid their brothers. Then they eagerly rushed off together.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011008"/>
      <verse num="8">And there, while they were still near Jerusalem, a horseman appeared at their head, clothed in white and brandishing weapons of gold.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011009"/>
      <verse num="9">And they all together praised the merciful God and were strengthened in heart, ready to assail not only men but the wildest beasts or walls of iron.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011010"/>
      <verse num="10">They advanced in battle order, having their heavenly ally, for the Lord had mercy on them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011011"/>
      <verse num="11">They hurled themselves like lions against the enemy and threw down 11,000 of them and 1,600 horsemen and forced all the rest to flee.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011012"/>
      <verse num="12">Most of those who got away were stripped and wounded, and Lysias himself escaped by fleeing in disgrace.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011013"/>
      <heading>Lysias Makes Peace with the Jews</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="13">And as he was not without intelligence, he pondered over the defeat that had befallen him and realized that the Hebrews were invincible because the mighty God fought on their side. So he sent to them</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011014"/>
      <verse num="14">and persuaded them to settle everything on just terms, promising that he would persuade the king, constraining him to be their friend.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011015"/>
      <verse num="15">Maccabeus, having regard for the common good, agreed to all that Lysias urged. For the king granted every request in behalf of the Jews that Maccabeus delivered to Lysias in writing.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011016"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">The letter written to the Jews by Lysias was to this effect:<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/><q class="begin-double" qid="81011016.1" from="81011016.1" to="81011021.1"/>Lysias to the people of the Jews, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011017"/>
      <verse num="17">John and Absalom, who were sent by you, have delivered your signed communication and have asked about the matters indicated therein.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011018"/>
      <verse num="18">I have informed the king of everything that needed to be brought before him, and he has agreed to what was possible.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011019"/>
      <verse num="19">If you will maintain your good will toward the government, I will endeavor for the future to help promote your welfare.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011020"/>
      <verse num="20">And concerning these matters and their details, I have ordered these men and my representatives to confer with you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011021"/>
      <verse num="21">Farewell. The 148th year,<note nid="n81011021.1"/> Dioscorinthius twenty-fourth.<q class="end-double" qid="81011021.1" from="81011016.1" to="81011021.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011022"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="22">The king&apos;s letter ran thus:<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/><q class="begin-double" qid="81011022.1" from="81011022.1" to="81011026.1"/>King Antiochus to his brother Lysias, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011023"/>
      <verse num="23">Now that our father has gone on to the gods, we desire that the subjects of the kingdom be undisturbed in caring for their own affairs.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011024"/>
      <verse num="24">We have heard that the Jews do not consent to our father&apos;s change to Greek customs but prefer their own way of living and ask that their own customs be allowed them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011025"/>
      <verse num="25">Accordingly, since we choose that this nation also be free from disturbance, our decision is that their temple be restored to them and that they live according to the customs of their ancestors.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011026"/>
      <verse num="26">You will do well, therefore, to send word to them and give them pledges of friendship, so that they may know our policy and be of good cheer and go on happily in the conduct of their own affairs.<q class="end-double" qid="81011026.1" from="81011022.1" to="81011026.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011027"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="27">To the nation the king&apos;s letter was as follows:<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/><q class="begin-double" qid="81011027.1" from="81011027.1" to="81011033.1"/>King Antiochus to the senate of the Jews and to the other Jews, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011028"/>
      <verse num="28">If you are well, it is as we desire. We also are in good health.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011029"/>
      <verse num="29">Menelaus has informed us that you wish to return home and look after your own affairs.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011030"/>
      <verse num="30">Therefore those who go home by the thirtieth day of Xanthicus will have our pledge of friendship and full permission</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011031"/>
      <verse num="31">for the Jews to enjoy their own food and laws, just as formerly, and none of them shall be molested in any way for what he may have done in ignorance.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011032"/>
      <verse num="32">And I have also sent Menelaus to encourage you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011033"/>
      <verse num="33">Farewell. The 148th year, Xanthicus fifteenth.<q class="end-double" qid="81011033.1" from="81011027.1" to="81011033.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011034"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="34">The Romans also sent them a letter, which read thus:<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/><q class="begin-double" qid="81011034.1" from="81011034.1" to="81011038.1"/>Quintus Memmius and Titus Manius, envoys of the Romans, to the people of the Jews, greeting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011035"/>
      <verse num="35">With regard to what Lysias the kinsman of the king has granted you, we also give consent.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011036"/>
      <verse num="36">But as to the matters that he decided are to be referred to the king, as soon as you have considered them, send someone promptly, so that we may make proposals appropriate for you. For we are on our way to Antioch.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011037"/>
      <verse num="37">Therefore make haste and send some men, so that we may know your disposition.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81011038"/>
      <verse num="38">Farewell. The 148th year, Xanthicus fifteenth.<q class="end-double" qid="81011038.1" from="81011034.1" to="81011038.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012001"/>
    <chapter num="12">
      <heading>Incidents at Joppa and Jamnia</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">When this agreement had been reached, Lysias returned to the king, and the Jews went about their farming.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012002"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="2">But some of the governors in various places, Timothy and Apollonius son of Gennaeus, as well as Hieronymus and Demophon and in addition to these Nicanor the governor of Cyprus, would not let them live quietly and in peace.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012003"/>
      <verse num="3">And the people of Joppa did so ungodly a deed as this: they invited the Jews who lived among them to embark, with their wives and children, on boats that they had provided, as though there were no ill will to the Jews;<note nid="n81012003.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012004"/>
      <verse num="4">and this was done by public vote of the city. And when they accepted, because they wished to live peaceably and suspected nothing, the men of Joppa<note nid="n81012004.1"/> took them out to sea and drowned them, not less than 200.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012005"/>
      <verse num="5">When Judas heard of the cruelty visited on his compatriots, he gave orders to his men</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012006"/>
      <verse num="6">and, calling upon God the righteous Judge, attacked the murderers of his kindred. He set fire to the harbor by night and burned the boats and massacred those who had taken refuge there.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012007"/>
      <verse num="7">Then, because the city&apos;s gates were closed, he withdrew, intending to come again and root out the whole community of Joppa.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012008"/>
      <verse num="8">But learning that the people in Jamnia meant in the same way to wipe out the Jews who were living among them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012009"/>
      <verse num="9">he attacked the people of Jamnia by night and set fire to the harbor and the fleet, so that the glow of the light was seen in Jerusalem, thirty miles<note nid="n81012009.1"/> distant.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012010"/>
      <heading>Campaign in Gilead</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">When they had gone more than a mile<note nid="n81012010.1"/> from there, on their march against Timothy, no fewer than 5,000 Arabs with 500 horsemen attacked them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012011"/>
      <verse num="11">After a hard fight Judas and his men won the victory, by the help of God. The defeated nomads begged Judas to grant them pledges of friendship, promising to give him livestock and to help his people<note nid="n81012011.1"/> in all other ways.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012012"/>
      <verse num="12">Judas, thinking that they might really be useful in many ways, agreed to make peace with them; and after receiving his pledges they went to their tents.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012013"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="13">He also attacked a certain city that was strongly fortified with earthworks<note nid="n81012013.1"/> and walls and inhabited by all sorts of Gentiles. Its name was Caspin.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012014"/>
      <verse num="14">And those who were within, relying on the strength of the walls and on their supply of provisions, behaved most insolently toward Judas and his men, railing at them and even blaspheming and saying unholy things.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012015"/>
      <verse num="15">But Judas and his men, calling upon the great Sovereign of the world, who without battering rams or engines of war overthrew Jericho in the days of Joshua, rushed furiously upon the walls.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012016"/>
      <verse num="16">They took the city by the will of God and slaughtered untold numbers, so that the adjoining lake, a quarter of a mile<note nid="n81012016.1"/> wide, appeared to be running over with blood.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012017"/>
      <heading>Judas Defeats Timothy&apos;s Army</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="17">When they had gone ninety-five miles<note nid="n81012017.1"/> from there, they came to Charax, to the Jews who are called Toubiani.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012018"/>
      <verse num="18">They did not find Timothy in that region, for he had by then departed from the region without accomplishing anything, though in one place he had left a very strong garrison.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012019"/>
      <verse num="19">Dositheus and Sosipater, who were captains under Maccabeus, marched out and destroyed those whom Timothy had left in the stronghold, more than 10,000 men.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012020"/>
      <verse num="20">But Maccabeus arranged his army in divisions, set men<note nid="n81012020.1"/> in command of the divisions, and hastened after Timothy, who had with him 120,000 infantry and 2,500 cavalry.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012021"/>
      <verse num="21">When Timothy learned of the approach of Judas, he sent off the women and the children and also the baggage to a place called Carnaim; for that place was hard to besiege and difficult of access because of the narrowness of all the approaches.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012022"/>
      <verse num="22">But when Judas&apos; first division appeared, terror and fear came over the enemy at the manifestation to them of him who sees all things; and they rushed off in flight and were swept on, this way and that, so that often they were injured by their own men and pierced by the points of their swords.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012023"/>
      <verse num="23">And Judas pressed the pursuit with the utmost vigor, putting the sinners to the sword, and destroyed as many as 30,000 men.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012024"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="24">Timothy himself fell into the hands of Dositheus and Sosipater and their men. With great guile he entreated them to let him go in safety, because he held the parents of most of them and the brothers of some, to whom no consideration would be shown.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012025"/>
      <verse num="25">And when with many words he had confirmed his solemn promise to restore them unharmed, they let him go, for the sake of saving their brothers.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012026"/>
      <heading>Judas Wins Other Victories</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="26">Then Judas<note nid="n81012026.1"/> marched against Carnaim and the temple of Atargatis and slaughtered 25,000 people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012027"/>
      <verse num="27">After the rout and destruction of these, he marched also against Ephron, a fortified city where there were multitudes of people of all nationalities.<note nid="n81012027.1"/> Stalwart young men took their stand before the walls and made a vigorous defense; and great stores of war engines and missiles were there.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012028"/>
      <verse num="28">But the Jews<note nid="n81012028.1"/> called upon the Sovereign who with power shatters the might of his enemies, and they got the city into their hands and killed as many as 25,000 of those who were within it.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012029"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="29">Setting out from there, they hastened to Scythopolis, which is seventy-five miles<note nid="n81012029.1"/> from Jerusalem.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012030"/>
      <verse num="30">But when the Jews who lived there bore witness to the good will that the people of Scythopolis had shown them and their kind treatment of them in times of misfortune,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012031"/>
      <verse num="31">they thanked them and exhorted them to be well disposed to their race in the future also. Then they went up to Jerusalem, as the Feast of Weeks was close at hand.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012032"/>
      <heading>Judas Defeats Gorgias</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="32">After the feast called Pentecost, they hastened against Gorgias, the governor of Idumea.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012033"/>
      <verse num="33">And he came out with 3,000 infantry and 400 cavalry.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012034"/>
      <verse num="34">When they joined battle, it happened that a few of the Jews fell.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012035"/>
      <verse num="35">But a certain Dositheus, one of Bacenor&apos;s men, who was on horseback and was a strong man, caught hold of Gorgias and, grasping his cloak, was dragging him off by main strength, wishing to take the accursed man alive, when one of the Thracian horsemen bore down upon him and cut off his arm; so Gorgias escaped and reached Marisa.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012036"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="36">As Esdris and his men had been fighting for a long time and were weary, Judas called upon the Lord to show himself their ally and leader in the battle.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012037"/>
      <verse num="37">In the language of their fathers he raised the battle cry, with hymns; then he charged against Gorgias&apos; men when they were not expecting it and put them to flight.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012038"/>
      <heading>Prayers for Those Killed in Battle</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="38">Then Judas assembled his army and went to the city of Adullam. As the seventh day was coming on, they purified themselves according to the custom, and they kept the Sabbath there.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012039"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="39">On the next day, as by that time it had become necessary, Judas and his men went to take up the bodies of the fallen and to bring them back to lie with their kinsmen in the sepulchers of their fathers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012040"/>
      <verse num="40">Then under the tunic of every one of the dead they found sacred tokens of the idols of Jamnia, which the law forbids the Jews to wear. And it became clear to all that this was why these men had fallen.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012041"/>
      <verse num="41">So they all blessed the ways of the Lord, the righteous Judge, who reveals the things that are hidden;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012042"/>
      <verse num="42">and they turned to prayer, imploring that the sin that had been committed might be wholly blotted out. And the noble Judas exhorted the people to keep themselves free from sin, for they had seen with their own eyes what had happened because of the sin of those who had fallen.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012043"/>
      <verse num="43">He also took up a collection, man by man, to the amount of 2,000 drachmas of silver and sent it to Jerusalem to provide for a sin offering. In doing this he acted very well and honorably, taking account of the resurrection.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012044"/>
      <verse num="44">For if he were not expecting that those who had fallen would rise again, it would have been superfluous and foolish to pray for the dead.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81012045"/>
      <verse num="45">But if he was looking to the splendid reward that is laid up for those who fall asleep in godliness, it was a holy and pious thought. Therefore he made atonement for the dead, that they might be delivered from their sin.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013001"/>
    <chapter num="13">
      <heading>Menelaus Put to Death</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">In the 149th year<note nid="n81013001.1"/> word came to Judas and his men that Antiochus Eupator was coming with a great army against Judea</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013002"/>
      <verse num="2">and with him Lysias, his guardian, who had charge of the government. Each of them had a Greek force of 110,000 infantry, 5,300 cavalry, 22 elephants, and 300 chariots armed with scythes.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013003"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="3">Menelaus also joined them and with utter hypocrisy urged Antiochus on, not for the sake of his country&apos;s welfare, but because he thought that he would be established in office.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013004"/>
      <verse num="4">But the King of kings aroused the anger of Antiochus against the scoundrel; and when Lysias informed him that this man was to blame for all the trouble, he ordered them to take him to Beroea and to put him to death by the method that is the custom in that place.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013005"/>
      <verse num="5">For there is a tower in that place, fifty cubits high, full of ashes, and it has a rim running around it that on all sides inclines precipitously into the ashes.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013006"/>
      <verse num="6">There they all push to destruction any man guilty of sacrilege or notorious for other crimes.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013007"/>
      <verse num="7">By such a fate it came about that Menelaus the lawbreaker died, without even burial in the earth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013008"/>
      <verse num="8">And this was eminently just; because he had committed many sins against the altar whose fire and ashes were holy, he met his death in ashes.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013009"/>
      <heading>Battle Near the City of Modein</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="9">The king with barbarous arrogance was coming to show the Jews things far worse than those<note nid="n81013009.1"/> that had been done in his father&apos;s time.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013010"/>
      <verse num="10">But when Judas heard of this, he ordered the people to call upon the Lord day and night, now if ever to help those who were on the point of being deprived of the law and their country and the holy temple</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013011"/>
      <verse num="11">and not to let the people who had just begun to revive fall into the hands of the blasphemous Gentiles.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013012"/>
      <verse num="12">When they had all joined in the same petition and had fervently prayed to the merciful Lord with weeping and fasting and lying prostrate for three days without ceasing, Judas exhorted them and ordered them to stand ready.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013013"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="13">After consulting privately with the elders, he determined to march out and decide the matter by the help of God before the king&apos;s army could enter Judea and get possession of the city.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013014"/>
      <verse num="14">So, committing the decision to the Creator of the world and exhorting his men to fight nobly to the death for the laws, temple, city, country, and commonwealth, he pitched his camp near Modein.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013015"/>
      <verse num="15">He gave his men the watchword, <q class="begin-double" qid="81013015.1" from="81013015.1" to="81013015.2"/>God&apos;s victory,<q class="end-double" qid="81013015.2" from="81013015.1" to="81013015.2"/> and with a picked force of the bravest young men, he attacked the king&apos;s pavilion at night and killed as many as 2,000 men in the camp and stabbed<note nid="n81013015.1"/> the leading elephant with its occupant.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013016"/>
      <verse num="16">In the end they filled the camp with terror and confusion and withdrew in triumph.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013017"/>
      <verse num="17">This happened, just as day was dawning, because the Lord&apos;s help protected him.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013018"/>
      <heading>Antiochus Makes a Treaty with the Jews</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">The king, having had a taste of the daring of the Jews, tried strategy in attacking their positions.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013019"/>
      <verse num="19">He advanced against Beth-zur, a strong fortress of the Jews, was turned back, attacked again,<note nid="n81013019.1"/> and was defeated.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013020"/>
      <verse num="20">Judas sent in to the garrison whatever was necessary.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013021"/>
      <verse num="21">But Rhodocus, a man from the ranks of the Jews, gave secret information to the enemy; he was sought for, caught, and put in prison.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013022"/>
      <verse num="22">The king negotiated a second time with the people in Beth-zur, gave pledges, received theirs, withdrew, attacked Judas and his men, was defeated.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013023"/>
      <verse num="23">He got word that Philip, who had been left in charge of the government, had revolted in Antioch; he was dismayed, called in the Jews, yielded and swore to observe all their rights, settled with them and offered sacrifice, honored the sanctuary and showed generosity to the Holy Place.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013024"/>
      <verse num="24">He received Maccabeus, left Hegemonides as governor from Ptolemais to Gerar,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013025"/>
      <verse num="25">and went to Ptolemais. The people of Ptolemais were indignant over the treaty; in fact they were so angry that they wanted to annul its terms.<note nid="n81013025.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81013026"/>
      <verse num="26">Lysias took the public platform, made the best possible defense, convinced them, appeased them, gained their good will, and set out for Antioch. This is how the king&apos;s attack and withdrawal turned out.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014001"/>
    <chapter num="14">
      <heading>Alcimus Speaks against Judas</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Three years later, word came to Judas and his men that Demetrius son of Seleucus had sailed into the harbor of Tripolis with a strong army and a fleet</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014002"/>
      <verse num="2">and had taken possession of the country, having made away with Antiochus and his guardian Lysias.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014003"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="3">Now a certain Alcimus, who had formerly been high priest but had willfully defiled himself in the times of separation,<note nid="n81014003.1"/> realized that there was no way for him to be safe or to have access again to the holy altar</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014004"/>
      <verse num="4">and went to King Demetrius in about the 151st year,<note nid="n81014004.1"/> presenting to him a crown of gold and a palm and besides these some of the customary olive branches from the temple. During that day he kept quiet.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014005"/>
      <verse num="5">But he found an opportunity that furthered his mad purpose when he was invited by Demetrius to a meeting of the council and was asked about the disposition and intentions of the Jews. He answered:</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014006"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="6"><q class="begin-double" qid="81014006.1" from="81014006.1" to="81014010.1"/>Those of the Jews who are called Hasideans, whose leader is Judas Maccabeus, are keeping up war and stirring up sedition and will not let the kingdom attain tranquility.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014007"/>
      <verse num="7">Therefore I have laid aside my ancestral glory&emdash;I mean the high priesthood&emdash;and have now come here,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014008"/>
      <verse num="8">first because I am genuinely concerned for the interests of the king, and second because I have regard also for my fellow citizens. For through the folly of those whom I have mentioned our whole nation is now in no small misfortune.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014009"/>
      <verse num="9">Since you are acquainted, O king, with the details of this matter, please take thought for our country and our hard-pressed nation with the gracious kindness that you show to all.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014010"/>
      <verse num="10">For as long as Judas lives, it is impossible for the government to find peace.<q class="end-double" qid="81014010.1" from="81014006.1" to="81014010.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014011"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="11">When he had said this, the rest of the king&apos;s friends, who were hostile to Judas, quickly inflamed Demetrius still more.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014012"/>
      <verse num="12">And he immediately chose Nicanor, who had been in command of the elephants, appointed him governor of Judea, and sent him off</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014013"/>
      <verse num="13">with orders to kill Judas and scatter those with him and to set up Alcimus as high priest of the great temple.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014014"/>
      <verse num="14">And the Gentiles throughout Judea, who had fled before<note nid="n81014014.1"/> Judas, flocked to join Nicanor, thinking that the misfortunes and calamities of the Jews would mean prosperity for themselves.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014015"/>
      <heading>Nicanor Makes Friends with Judas</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="15">When the Jews<note nid="n81014015.1"/> heard of Nicanor&apos;s coming and the gathering of the Gentiles, they sprinkled dust upon their heads and prayed to him who established his own people forever and always upholds his own heritage by manifesting himself.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014016"/>
      <verse num="16">At the command of the leader, they<note nid="n81014016.1"/> set out from there immediately and engaged them in battle at a village called Dessau.<note nid="n81014016.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014017"/>
      <verse num="17">Simon the brother of Judas had encountered Nicanor, but had been temporarily<note nid="n81014017.1"/> checked because of the sudden consternation created by the enemy.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014018"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">Nevertheless Nicanor, hearing of the valor of Judas and his men and their courage in battle for their country, shrank from deciding the issue by bloodshed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014019"/>
      <verse num="19">Therefore he sent Posidonius and Theodotus and Mattathias to give and receive pledges of friendship.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014020"/>
      <verse num="20">When the terms had been fully considered and the leader had informed the people, and it appeared that they were of one mind, they agreed to the covenant.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014021"/>
      <verse num="21">And the leaders<note nid="n81014021.1"/> set a day on which to meet by themselves. A chariot came forward from each army; seats of honor were set in place;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014022"/>
      <verse num="22">Judas posted armed men in readiness at key places to prevent sudden treachery on the part of the enemy; they held the proper conference.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014023"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="23">Nicanor stayed on in Jerusalem and did nothing out of the way, but dismissed the flocks of people that had gathered.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014024"/>
      <verse num="24">And he kept Judas always in his presence; he was warmly attached to the man.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014025"/>
      <verse num="25">And he urged him to marry and have children; so he married, settled down, and shared the common life.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014026"/>
      <heading>Nicanor Turns against Judas</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="26">But when Alcimus noticed their good will for one another, he took the covenant that had been made and went to Demetrius. He told him that Nicanor was disloyal to the government, for he had appointed that conspirator against the kingdom, Judas, to be his successor.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014027"/>
      <verse num="27">The king became excited and, provoked by the false accusations of that depraved man, wrote to Nicanor, stating that he was displeased with the covenant and commanding him to send Maccabeus to Antioch as a prisoner without delay.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014028"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="28">When this message came to Nicanor, he was troubled and grieved that he had to annul their agreement when the man had done no wrong.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014029"/>
      <verse num="29">Since it was not possible to oppose the king, he watched for an opportunity to accomplish this by a stratagem.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014030"/>
      <verse num="30">But Maccabeus, noticing that Nicanor was more austere in his dealings with him and was meeting him more rudely than had been his custom, concluded that this austerity did not spring from the best motives. So he gathered not a few of his men and went into hiding from Nicanor.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014031"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="31">When the latter became aware that he had been cleverly outwitted by the man, he went to the great<note nid="n81014031.1"/> and holy temple while the priests were offering the customary sacrifices and commanded them to hand the man over.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014032"/>
      <verse num="32">And when they declared on oath that they did not know where the man was whom he sought,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014033"/>
      <verse num="33">he stretched out his right hand toward the sanctuary and swore this oath: <q class="begin-double" qid="81014033.1" from="81014033.1" to="81014033.2"/>If you do not hand Judas over to me as a prisoner, I will level this precinct of God to the ground and tear down the altar, and I will build here a splendid temple to Dionysus.<q class="end-double" qid="81014033.2" from="81014033.1" to="81014033.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014034"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="34">Having said this, he went away. Then the priests stretched forth their hands toward heaven and called upon the constant Defender of our nation, in these words:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014035"/>
      <verse num="35"><q class="begin-double" qid="81014035.1" from="81014035.1" to="81014036.1"/>O Lord of all, who has need of nothing, you were pleased that there be a temple for your habitation among us;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014036"/>
      <verse num="36">so now, O Holy One, Lord of all holiness, keep undefiled forever this house that has been so recently purified.<q class="end-double" qid="81014036.1" from="81014035.1" to="81014036.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014037"/>
      <heading>Razis Dies for His Country</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="37">A certain Razis, one of the elders of Jerusalem, was denounced to Nicanor as a man who loved his fellow citizens and was very well thought of and for his good will was called father of the Jews.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014038"/>
      <verse num="38">For in former times, when there was no mingling with the Gentiles, he had been accused of Judaism, and for Judaism he had with all zeal risked body and life.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014039"/>
      <verse num="39">Nicanor, wishing to exhibit the enmity that he had for the Jews, sent more than 500 soldiers to arrest him;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014040"/>
      <verse num="40">for he thought that by arresting<note nid="n81014040.1"/> him he would do them an injury.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014041"/>
      <verse num="41">When the troops were about to capture the tower and were forcing the door of the courtyard, they ordered that fire be brought and the doors burned. Being surrounded, Razis<note nid="n81014041.1"/> fell upon his own sword,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014042"/>
      <verse num="42">preferring to die nobly rather than to fall into the hands of sinners and suffer outrages unworthy of his noble birth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014043"/>
      <verse num="43">But in the heat of the struggle he did not hit exactly, and the crowd was now rushing in through the doors. He bravely ran up on the wall and manfully threw himself down into the crowd.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014044"/>
      <verse num="44">But as they quickly drew back, a space opened, and he fell in the middle of the empty space.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014045"/>
      <verse num="45">Still alive and aflame with anger, he rose, and though his blood gushed forth and his wounds were severe he ran through the crowd; and standing upon a steep rock,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81014046"/>
      <verse num="46">with his blood now completely drained from him, he tore out his entrails, took them with both hands and hurled them at the crowd, calling upon the Lord of life and spirit to give them back to him again. This was the manner of his death.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015001"/>
    <chapter num="15">
      <heading>Nicanor&apos;s Arrogance</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">When Nicanor heard that Judas and his men were in the region of Samaria, he made plans to attack them with complete safety on the day of rest.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015002"/>
      <verse num="2">And when the Jews who were compelled to follow him said, <q class="begin-double" qid="81015002.1" from="81015002.1" to="81015002.2"/>Do not destroy so savagely and barbarously, but show respect for the day that he who sees all things has honored and hallowed above other days,<q class="end-double" qid="81015002.2" from="81015002.1" to="81015002.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015003"/>
      <verse num="3">the thrice-accursed wretch asked if there were a sovereign in heaven who had commanded the keeping of the Sabbath day.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015004"/>
      <verse num="4">And when they declared, <q class="begin-double" qid="81015004.1" from="81015004.1" to="81015004.2"/>It is the living Lord himself, the Sovereign in heaven, who ordered us to observe the seventh day,<q class="end-double" qid="81015004.2" from="81015004.1" to="81015004.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015005"/>
      <verse num="5">he replied, <q class="begin-double" qid="81015005.1" from="81015005.1" to="81015005.2"/>And I am a sovereign also, on earth, and I command you to take up arms and finish the king&apos;s business.<q class="end-double" qid="81015005.2" from="81015005.1" to="81015005.2"/> Nevertheless, he did not succeed in carrying out his abominable design.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015006"/>
      <heading>Judas Prepares the Jews for Battle</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="6">This Nicanor in his utter boastfulness and arrogance had determined to erect a public monument of victory over Judas and his men.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015007"/>
      <verse num="7">But Maccabeus did not cease to trust with all confidence that he would get help from the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015008"/>
      <verse num="8">And he exhorted his men not to fear the attack of the Gentiles, but to keep in mind the former times when help had come to them from heaven and now to look for the victory that the Almighty would give them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015009"/>
      <verse num="9">Encouraging them from the Law and the Prophets and reminding them also of the struggles they had won, he made them the more eager.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015010"/>
      <verse num="10">And when he had aroused their courage, he gave his orders, at the same time pointing out the perfidy of the Gentiles and their violation of oaths.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015011"/>
      <verse num="11">He armed each of them not so much with confidence in shields and spears as with the inspiration of brave words, and he cheered them all by relating a dream, a sort of vision,<note nid="n81015011.1"/> that was worthy of belief.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015012"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="12">What he saw was this: Onias, who had been high priest, a noble and good man, of modest bearing and gentle manner, one who spoke fittingly and had been trained from childhood in all that belongs to excellence, was praying with outstretched hands for the whole body of the Jews.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015013"/>
      <verse num="13">Then likewise a man appeared, distinguished by his gray hair and dignity and of marvelous majesty and authority.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015014"/>
      <verse num="14">And Onias spoke, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="81015014.1" from="81015014.1" to="81015014.2"/>This is a man who loves the brothers and prays much for the people and the holy city&emdash;Jeremiah the prophet of God.<q class="end-double" qid="81015014.2" from="81015014.1" to="81015014.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015015"/>
      <verse num="15">Jeremiah stretched out his right hand and gave to Judas a golden sword, and as he gave it he addressed him thus:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015016"/>
      <verse num="16"><q class="begin-double" qid="81015016.1" from="81015016.1" to="81015016.2"/>Take this holy sword, a gift from God, with which you will strike down your adversaries.<q class="end-double" qid="81015016.2" from="81015016.1" to="81015016.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015017"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="17">Encouraged by the words of Judas, so noble and so effective in arousing valor and awaking manliness in the souls of the young, they determined not to carry on a campaign<note nid="n81015017.1"/> but to attack bravely and to decide the matter by fighting hand to hand with all courage, because the city and the sanctuary and the temple were in danger.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015018"/>
      <verse num="18">Their concern for wives and children and also for brothers and relatives lay upon them less heavily; their greatest and first fear was for the consecrated sanctuary.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015019"/>
      <verse num="19">And those who had to remain in the city were in no little distress, being anxious over the encounter in the open country.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015020"/>
      <heading>Defeat and Death of Nicanor</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="20">When all were now looking forward to the coming decision, and the enemy was already close at hand with their army drawn up for battle, the elephants<note nid="n81015020.1"/> strategically stationed and the cavalry deployed on the flanks,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015021"/>
      <verse num="21">Maccabeus, perceiving the hosts that were before him and the varied supply of arms and the savagery of the elephants, stretched out his hands toward heaven and called upon the Lord who works wonders; for he knew that it is not by arms, but as the Lord<note nid="n81015021.1"/> decides, that he gains the victory for those who deserve it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015022"/>
      <verse num="22">And he called upon him in these words: <q class="begin-double" qid="81015022.1" from="81015022.1" to="81015024.1"/>O Lord, in the time of King Hezekiah of Judea you sent your angel, and he killed fully 185,000 in the camp of Sennacherib.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015023"/>
      <verse num="23">So now, O Sovereign of the heavens, send a good angel to carry terror and trembling before us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015024"/>
      <verse num="24">By the might of your arm may these blasphemers who come against your holy people be struck down.<q class="end-double" qid="81015024.1" from="81015022.1" to="81015024.1"/> With these words he ended his prayer.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015025"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="25">Nicanor and his men advanced with trumpets and battle songs;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015026"/>
      <verse num="26">and Judas and his men met the enemy in battle with invocation to God and prayers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015027"/>
      <verse num="27">So, fighting with their hands and praying to God in their hearts, they laid low no less than 35,000 men and were greatly gladdened by God&apos;s manifestation.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015028"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="28">When the action was over and they were returning with joy, they recognized Nicanor, lying dead, in full armor.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015029"/>
      <verse num="29">Then there was shouting and tumult, and they blessed the Sovereign Lord in the language of their fathers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015030"/>
      <verse num="30">And the man who was ever in body and soul the defender of his fellow citizens, the man who maintained his youthful good will toward his compatriots, ordered them to cut off Nicanor&apos;s head and arm and carry them to Jerusalem.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015031"/>
      <verse num="31">And when he arrived there and had called his compatriots together and stationed the priests before the altar, he sent for those who were in the citadel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015032"/>
      <verse num="32">He showed them the vile Nicanor&apos;s head and that profane man&apos;s arm, which had been boastfully stretched out against the holy house of the Almighty;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015033"/>
      <verse num="33">and he cut out the tongue of the ungodly Nicanor and said that he would give it piecemeal to the birds and hang up these rewards of his folly opposite the sanctuary.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015034"/>
      <verse num="34">And they all, looking to heaven, blessed the Lord who had manifested himself, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="81015034.1" from="81015034.1" to="81015034.2"/>Blessed is he who has kept his own place undefiled.<q class="end-double" qid="81015034.2" from="81015034.1" to="81015034.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015035"/>
      <verse num="35">And he hung Nicanor&apos;s head from the citadel, a clear and conspicuous sign to everyone of the help of the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015036"/>
      <verse num="36">And they all decreed by public vote never to let this day go unobserved, but to celebrate the thirteenth day of the twelfth month&emdash;which is called Adar in the Syrian language&emdash;the day before Mordecai&apos;s day.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015037"/>
      <heading>Compiler&apos;s Epilogue</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="37">This, then, is how matters turned out with Nicanor. And from that time the city has been in the possession of the Hebrews. So I too will here end my story.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015038"/>
      <verse num="38">If it is well told and to the point, that is what I myself desired; if it is poorly done and mediocre, that was the best I could do.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v81015039"/>
      <verse num="39">For just as it is harmful to drink wine alone or, again, to drink water alone, while wine mixed with water is sweet and delicious and enhances one&apos;s enjoyment, so also the style of the story delights the ears of those who read the work. And here will be the end.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
  </book>
</crossway-bible>
