<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" translation="English Standard Version" revision="2018-3-26" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
  <book title="3 Maccabees" num="85">
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001001"/>
    <chapter num="1">
      <heading>Battle of Raphia</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">When Philopator learned from those who returned that the regions that he had controlled had been seized by Antiochus, he gave orders to all his forces, both infantry and cavalry, took with him his sister Arsinoë, and marched out to the region near Raphia, where Antiochus<q class="end-single" qid="85001001.1"/> supporters were encamped.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001002"/>
      <verse num="2">But a certain Theodotus, determined to carry out the plot he had devised, took with him the best of the Ptolemaic soldiers<note nid="n85001002.1"/> that had been previously issued to him and crossed over by night to the tent of Ptolemy, intending single-handed to kill him and thereby end the war.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001003"/>
      <verse num="3">But Dositheus, known as son of Drimylus, a Jew by birth who later changed his religion and apostatized from the ancestral traditions, had led the king away and arranged that a certain insignificant man should sleep in the tent; and so it turned out that this man incurred the vengeance meant for the king.<note nid="n85001003.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001004"/>
      <verse num="4">When a bitter fight resulted, and matters were turning out rather in favor of Antiochus, Arsinoë went to the troops with wailing and tears, her hair all disheveled, and exhorted them to defend themselves and their children and wives bravely, promising to give them each two minas of gold if they won the battle.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001005"/>
      <verse num="5">And so it came about that the enemy was routed in the action, and many captives also were taken.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001006"/>
      <verse num="6">Now that he had foiled the plot, Ptolemy<note nid="n85001006.1"/> decided to visit the neighboring cities and encourage them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001007"/>
      <verse num="7">By doing this and by endowing their sacred enclosures with gifts, he strengthened the morale of his subjects.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001008"/>
      <heading>Philopator Attempts to Enter the Temple</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="8">Since the Jews had sent some of their council and elders to greet him, to bring him gifts of welcome, and to congratulate him on what had happened, he was all the more eager to visit them as soon as possible.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001009"/>
      <verse num="9">After he had arrived in Jerusalem, he offered sacrifice to the supreme<note nid="n85001009.1"/> God and made thank offerings and did what was fitting for the place. Then, upon entering the place and being impressed by its excellence and its beauty,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001010"/>
      <verse num="10">he marveled at the good order of the temple and conceived a desire to enter the Most Holy Place.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001011"/>
      <verse num="11">When they said that this was not permitted, because not even members of their own nation were allowed to enter, nor even all of the priests, but only the high priest who was preeminent over all, and he only once a year, the king was by no means persuaded.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001012"/>
      <verse num="12">Even after the law had been read to him, he did not cease to maintain that he ought to enter, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="85001012.1" from="85001012.1" to="85001012.2"/>Even if those men are deprived of this honor, I ought not to be.<q class="end-double" qid="85001012.2" from="85001012.1" to="85001012.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001013"/>
      <verse num="13">And he inquired why, when he entered every other temple,<note nid="n85001013.1"/> no one there had stopped him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001014"/>
      <verse num="14">And someone heedlessly said that it was wrong to take this as a sign in itself.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001015"/>
      <verse num="15"><q class="begin-double" qid="85001015.1" from="85001015.1" to="85001015.2"/>But since this has happened,<q class="end-double" qid="85001015.2" from="85001015.1" to="85001015.2"/> the king<note nid="n85001015.1"/> said, <q class="begin-double" qid="85001015.3" from="85001015.3" to="85001015.4"/>why should not I at least enter, whether they wish it or not?<q class="end-double" qid="85001015.4" from="85001015.3" to="85001015.4"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001016"/>
      <heading>Jewish Resistance to Ptolemy</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">Then the priests in all their vestments prostrated themselves and entreated the supreme God to aid in the present situation and to avert the violence of this evil design, and they filled the temple with cries and tears;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001017"/>
      <verse num="17">and those who remained behind in the city were agitated and hurried out, supposing that something mysterious was occurring.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001018"/>
      <verse num="18">The virgins who had been enclosed in their chambers rushed out with their mothers, sprinkled their hair with dust,<note nid="n85001018.1"/> and filled the streets with groans and lamentations.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001019"/>
      <verse num="19">Those women who had recently been arrayed for marriage abandoned the bridal chambers prepared for wedded union and, neglecting proper modesty, in a disorderly rush flocked together in the city.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001020"/>
      <verse num="20">Mothers and nurses abandoned even newborn children here and there, some in houses and some in the streets, and without a backward look they crowded together at the highest temple.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001021"/>
      <verse num="21">Various were the supplications of those gathered there because of what the king was profanely plotting.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001022"/>
      <verse num="22">In addition, the bolder of the citizens would not tolerate the completion of his plans or the fulfillment of his intended purpose.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001023"/>
      <verse num="23">They shouted to their fellows to take arms and die courageously for the ancestral law and created a considerable disturbance in the place; and being barely restrained by the old men<note nid="n85001023.1"/> and the elders, they resorted to the same posture of supplication as the others.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001024"/>
      <verse num="24">Meanwhile the crowd, as before, was engaged in prayer,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001025"/>
      <verse num="25">while the elders near the king tried in various ways to change his arrogant mind from the plan that he had conceived.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001026"/>
      <verse num="26">But he, in his arrogance, took heed of nothing and began now to approach, determined to bring the aforesaid plan to a conclusion.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001027"/>
      <verse num="27">When those who were around him observed this, they turned, together with our people, to call upon the one having all power to defend them in the present trouble and not to overlook this unlawful and haughty deed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001028"/>
      <verse num="28">The continuous, vehement, and concerted cry of the crowds<note nid="n85001028.1"/> resulted in an immense uproar;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85001029"/>
      <verse num="29">for it seemed that not only the people but also the walls and the whole earth around echoed, because indeed all at that time<note nid="n85001029.1"/> preferred death to the profanation of the place.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002001"/>
    <chapter num="2">
      <heading>Prayer of High Priest Simon</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Then the high priest Simon, facing the sanctuary, bending his knees and extending his hands with calm dignity, prayed as follows:<note nid="n85002001.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002002"/>
      <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="85002002.1" from="85002002.1" to="85002020.1"/>Lord, Lord, king of the heavens and sovereign of all creation, holy among the holy ones, the only ruler, almighty, give attention to us who are suffering grievously from an impious and profane man, puffed up in his audacity and power.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002003"/>
      <verse num="3">For you, the Creator of all things and the governor of all, are a just Ruler, and you judge those who have done anything in insolence and arrogance.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002004"/>
      <verse num="4">You destroyed those who in the past committed injustice, among whom were even giants who trusted in their strength and boldness, whom you destroyed by bringing upon them a boundless flood.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002005"/>
      <verse num="5">You consumed with fire and sulfur the people of Sodom who acted arrogantly, who were notorious for<note nid="n85002005.1"/> their vices; and you made them an example to those who should come afterward.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002006"/>
      <verse num="6">You made known your mighty power by inflicting many and varied punishments on the audacious pharaoh who had enslaved your holy people Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002007"/>
      <verse num="7">And when he pursued them with chariots and a mass of troops, you overwhelmed him in the depths of the sea, but carried through safely those who had put their confidence in you, the Ruler over the whole creation.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002008"/>
      <verse num="8">And when they had seen the works of your hands, they praised you, the Almighty.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002009"/>
      <verse num="9">You, O King, when you had created the boundless and immeasurable earth, chose this city and sanctified this place for your name, though you have no need of anything; and when you had glorified it by your magnificent self-manifestation,<note nid="n85002009.1"/> you made it a firm foundation for the glory of your great and honored name.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002010"/>
      <verse num="10">And because you love the house of Israel, you promised that if we should have reverses and tribulation should overtake us, you would listen to our petition when we come to this place and pray.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002011"/>
      <verse num="11">And indeed you are faithful and true.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002012"/>
      <verse num="12">And because oftentimes when our fathers were oppressed you helped them in their humiliation and rescued them from great evils,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002013"/>
      <verse num="13">see now, O holy King, that because of our many and great sins we are crushed with suffering, subjected to our enemies, and overtaken by helplessness.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002014"/>
      <verse num="14">In our downfall this audacious and profane man undertakes to violate the Holy Place on earth dedicated to your glorious name.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002015"/>
      <verse num="15">For your dwelling, the heaven of heavens, is unapproachable by man.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002016"/>
      <verse num="16">But because you graciously bestowed your glory upon your people Israel, you sanctified this place.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002017"/>
      <verse num="17">Do not punish us for the defilement committed by these men or call us to account for this profanation, lest the transgressors boast in their wrath or exult in the arrogance of their tongue, saying,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002018"/>
      <verse num="18"><q class="begin-single" qid="85002018.1" from="85002018.1" to="85002018.2"/>We have trampled down the house of the sanctuary as the houses of the idols<note nid="n85002018.1"/> are trampled down.<q class="end-single" qid="85002018.2" from="85002018.1" to="85002018.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002019"/>
      <verse num="19">Wipe away our sins and disperse our errors and reveal your mercy at this hour.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002020"/>
      <verse num="20">Speedily let your mercies overtake us and put praises in the mouth of those who are downcast and broken in spirit and give us peace.<q class="end-double" qid="85002020.1" from="85002002.1" to="85002020.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002021"/>
      <heading>God’s Punishment of Ptolemy</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="21">Thereupon God, who oversees all things, the first Father of all, holy among the holy ones, having heard the lawful supplication, scourged him who had exalted himself in insolence and audacity.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002022"/>
      <verse num="22">He shook him this way and that as a reed is shaken by the wind, so that he lay helpless on the ground and, besides being paralyzed in his limbs, was unable even to speak, since he was smitten<note nid="n85002022.1"/> by a righteous judgment.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002023"/>
      <verse num="23">Then both friends and bodyguards, seeing the severe punishment that had overtaken him and fearing lest he should lose his life, quickly dragged him out, panic-stricken in their exceedingly great fear.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002024"/>
      <verse num="24">After a while he recovered, and though he had been punished, he by no means repented, but went away uttering bitter threats.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002025"/>
      <heading>Hostile Measures against the Jews</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="25">When he arrived in Egypt, he increased in his deeds of malice, abetted by the previously mentioned drinking companions and comrades, who were strangers to everything just.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002026"/>
      <verse num="26">He was not content with his innumerable licentious deeds, but he also continued with such audacity that he framed evil reports in the various localities; and many of his friends, intently observing the king<q class="end-single" qid="85002026.1"/>s purpose, themselves also followed his will.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002027"/>
      <verse num="27">He proposed to inflict public disgrace upon the Jewish people,<note nid="n85002027.1"/> and he set up a stone<note nid="n85002027.2"/> on the tower in the courtyard with this inscription:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002028"/>
      <verse num="28"><q class="begin-double" qid="85002028.1" from="85002028.1" to="85002029.1"/>None of those who do not sacrifice shall enter their sanctuaries, and all Jews shall be subjected to a registration involving poll tax and to being sold off as slaves. Those who object to this are to be taken by force and put to death;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002029"/>
      <verse num="29">those who are registered are also to be branded on their bodies by fire with the ivy-leaf symbol of Dionysus, and they shall also be reduced to their former limited status.<q class="end-double" qid="85002029.1" from="85002028.1" to="85002029.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002030"/>
      <verse num="30">In order that he might not appear to be an enemy to all, he inscribed below: <q class="begin-double" qid="85002030.1" from="85002030.1" to="85002030.2"/>But if any of them prefer to join those who have been initiated into the mysteries, they shall have equal citizenship with the Alexandrians.<q class="end-double" qid="85002030.2" from="85002030.1" to="85002030.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002031"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="31">Now some, while apparently abhorring the price to be exacted for maintaining the religion of the city,<note nid="n85002031.1"/> readily gave themselves up, since they expected to enhance their reputation by their future association with the king.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002032"/>
      <verse num="32">But the majority acted firmly with a courageous spirit and did not depart from their religion; and by paying money in exchange for life they confidently attempted to save themselves from the registration.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85002033"/>
      <verse num="33">They remained resolutely hopeful of obtaining help, and they abhorred those who separated themselves from them, considering them to be enemies of the Jewish<note nid="n85002033.1"/> nation and depriving them of common fellowship and mutual help.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003001"/>
    <chapter num="3">
      <heading>The Jews and Their Neighbors</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">When the impious king comprehended this situation, he became so infuriated that not only was he enraged against those Jews who lived in Alexandria, but was still more bitterly hostile toward those in the countryside; and he ordered that all should promptly be gathered into one place and put to death by the cruelest means.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003002"/>
      <verse num="2">While these matters were being arranged, a hostile rumor was circulated against the Jewish<note nid="n85003002.1"/> nation by men who conspired to do them ill, a pretext being given by a report that they hindered others<note nid="n85003002.2"/> from the observance of their lawful customs.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003003"/>
      <verse num="3">The Jews, however, continued to maintain good will and unswerving loyalty toward the dynasty;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003004"/>
      <verse num="4">but because they worshiped God and conducted themselves by his law, they kept their separateness with respect to foods. For this reason they appeared hostile to some;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003005"/>
      <verse num="5">but since they adorned their style of life with the good deeds of upright people, they were established in good repute among all people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003006"/>
      <verse num="6">Nevertheless those of other races paid no heed to their good service to their nation, which was common talk among all;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003007"/>
      <verse num="7">instead they gossiped about the differences in worship and foods, alleging that these people were loyal neither to the king nor to his authorities, but were hostile and greatly opposed to his government. So they attached no ordinary reproach to them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003008"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="8">The Greeks in the city, though wronged in no way, when they saw an unexpected tumult around these people and the crowds that suddenly were forming, were not strong enough to help them, for they lived under tyranny. They tried to console them, being grieved at the situation, and expected that matters would change;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003009"/>
      <verse num="9">for such a great community ought not to be left to its fate in this way when it had committed no offense.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003010"/>
      <verse num="10">And already some of their neighbors and friends and business associates had taken some of them aside privately and were pledging to protect them and to exert more earnest efforts for their assistance.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003011"/>
      <heading>Ptolemy’s Decree to Arrest All Jews</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="11">Then the king, boastful of his present good fortune and not considering the might of the supreme<note nid="n85003011.1"/> God, but assuming that he would persevere constantly in his same purpose, wrote this letter against them:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003012"/>
      <verse num="12"><q class="begin-double" qid="85003012.1" from="85003012.1" to="85003029.1"/>King Ptolemy Philopator to his generals and soldiers in Egypt and all its districts, greetings and good health.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003013"/>
      <verse num="13">I myself and our government are faring well.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003014"/>
      <verse num="14">When our expedition took place in Asia, as you yourselves know, it was brought to conclusion, according to plan, by the gods<q class="end-single" qid="85003014.1"/> deliberate alliance with us in battle,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003015"/>
      <verse num="15">and we considered that we should not rule the nations inhabiting Coelesyria and Phoenicia by the power of the spear but should cherish them with clemency and great benevolence, gladly treating them well.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003016"/>
      <verse num="16">And when we had granted very great revenues to the temples in the cities, we came on to Jerusalem also and went up to honor the temple of those wicked people, who never cease from their folly.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003017"/>
      <verse num="17">They accepted our presence by word, but insincerely by deed, because when we proposed to enter their inner temple and honor it with magnificent and most beautiful offerings,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003018"/>
      <verse num="18">they were carried away by their traditional conceit and prevented us from entering; but they were spared the exercise of our power because of the benevolence that we have toward all.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003019"/>
      <verse num="19">By maintaining their manifest ill-will toward us, they become the only people among all nations who hold their heads high in defiance of kings and their own benefactors and are unwilling to regard any action as sincere.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003020"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="20"><q class="continue-double" qid="85003020.1" from="85003012.1" to="85003029.1"/>But we accommodated ourselves to their folly and, crossing again into Egypt after victory, greeted all nationals there with benevolence. We did as was proper,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003021"/>
      <verse num="21">among these things declaring amnesty toward their compatriots here. And both because of their alliance with us and the myriad affairs liberally entrusted to them from the beginning, we ventured to make a change, by deciding both to deem them worthy of Alexandrian citizenship and to make them participants in our regular religious rites.<note nid="n85003021.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003022"/>
      <verse num="22">But they took this in a contrary spirit and, in their innate malice, disdained what is good. Since they incline constantly to what is base,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003023"/>
      <verse num="23">they not only spurn the priceless citizenship, but also both by speech and by silence they abominate those few among them who are sincerely disposed toward us; in every situation, in accordance with their infamous way of life, they secretly suspect that we may soon alter our policy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003024"/>
      <verse num="24">Therefore, fully convinced by these indications that they are ill-disposed toward us in every way, we have taken precautions lest, if a sudden disorder should later arise against us, we should have these impious people behind our backs as traitors and barbarous enemies.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003025"/>
      <verse num="25">Therefore we have given orders that, as soon as this letter shall arrive, you are to send to us those who live among you, together with their wives and children, with insulting and harsh treatment, and bound securely with iron fetters, to suffer the sure and shameful death that suits enemies.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003026"/>
      <verse num="26">For when these all have been punished, we are sure that for the remaining time the government will be established for ourselves in good order and in the best state.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003027"/>
      <verse num="27">But whoever shelters any of the Jews, old people or children or even infants, will be tortured to death with the most hateful torments, together with his household.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003028"/>
      <verse num="28">Anyone willing to give information will receive the property of the one who incurs the punishment and also 2,000 drachmas from the royal treasury and will be awarded the crown of freedom.<note nid="n85003028.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003029"/>
      <verse num="29">Every place detected sheltering a Jew is to be made unapproachable and burned with fire and shall become useless for all time to any mortal creature.<q class="end-double" qid="85003029.1" from="85003012.1" to="85003029.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85003030"/>
      <verse num="30">The original of the letter was written in the above form.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004001"/>
    <chapter num="4">
      <heading>Jews Deported to Alexandria</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">In every place, then, where this decree arrived, a feast at public expense was arranged for the Gentiles with shouts and gladness, for the inveterate enmity that had been in their minds since long ago was now made evident and outspoken.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004002"/>
      <verse num="2">But among the Jews there was incessant mourning, lamentation, and tearful cries; everywhere their hearts were burning, and they groaned because of the unexpected destruction that had suddenly been decreed for them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004003"/>
      <verse num="3">What district or city or what habitable place at all or what streets were not filled with mourning and wailing for them?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004004"/>
      <verse num="4">For with such a harsh and ruthless spirit were they being sent off, all together, by the generals in the several cities, that at the sight of their unusual punishments, even some of their enemies, perceiving the common object of pity before their eyes and reflecting upon the uncertain outcome of life, shed tears at the most miserable expulsion of these people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004005"/>
      <verse num="5">For a multitude of gray-headed old men, sluggish of foot and bent with age, was being led away, forced to march at a swift pace by the violence with which they were driven in such a shameful manner.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004006"/>
      <verse num="6">And young women who had just entered the bridal chamber to share married life exchanged joy for wailing, their myrrh-perfumed hair sprinkled with ashes, and were carried away unveiled, all together raising a lament instead of a wedding song, as they were torn by the harsh treatment of the Gentiles.<note nid="n85004006.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004007"/>
      <verse num="7">In bonds and in public view they were violently dragged along as far as the place of embarkation.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004008"/>
      <verse num="8">Their husbands, in the prime of youth, their necks encircled with ropes instead of garlands, spent the remaining days of their marriage festival in lamentations instead of good cheer and youthful revelry, seeing the grave already lying open before them.<note nid="n85004008.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004009"/>
      <verse num="9">They were brought on board like wild animals, driven under the constraint of iron bonds; some were fastened by the neck to the benches of the boats, others had their feet secured by unbreakable fetters,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004010"/>
      <verse num="10">and in addition they were confined under a solid deck, so that with their eyes in total darkness, they should undergo treatment suiting traitors during the whole voyage.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004011"/>
      <heading>Jews Imprisoned at Schedia</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="11">When these men had been brought to the place called Schedia, and the voyage was concluded as the king had decreed, he commanded that they should be enclosed in the hippodrome that had been built with an immense perimeter wall in front of the city and that was well suited to make them an obvious spectacle to all coming back into the city and to those from the city<note nid="n85004011.1"/> going out into the country, so that they could neither communicate with the king<q class="end-single" qid="85004011.1"/>s forces nor in any way claim to be inside the circuit of the city.<note nid="n85004011.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004012"/>
      <verse num="12">And when this had happened, the king, hearing that the Jews<q class="end-single" qid="85004012.1"/> compatriots from the city frequently went out in secret to lament bitterly the ignoble misfortune of their brothers,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004013"/>
      <verse num="13">ordered in his rage that these men be dealt with in precisely the same fashion as the others, not omitting any detail of their punishment.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004014"/>
      <verse num="14">The entire race was to be registered individually, not for the hard labor that has been briefly mentioned before, but to be tortured with the outrages that he had ordered and at the end to be destroyed in the space of a single day.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004015"/>
      <verse num="15">The registration of these people was therefore conducted with bitter haste and zealous diligence from the rising of the sun till its setting, and though uncompleted it stopped after forty days.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004016"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">The king was greatly and continually filled with joy, organizing drinking parties in honor of all his idols, with a mind alienated from truth and with a profane mouth, praising deaf things that are unable even to communicate or to come to one<q class="end-single" qid="85004016.1"/>s help and uttering improper words against the supreme<note nid="n85004016.1"/> God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004017"/>
      <verse num="17">But after the previously mentioned interval of time the scribes declared to the king that they were no longer able to take the census of the Jews because of their innumerable multitude,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004018"/>
      <verse num="18">although most of them were still in the country, some still residing in their homes, and some at the place; the task was impossible for all the generals in Egypt.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004019"/>
      <verse num="19">After he had threatened them severely, charging that they had been bribed to contrive a means of escape, he was clearly convinced about the matter</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004020"/>
      <verse num="20">when they said and proved that both the paper<note nid="n85004020.1"/> and the pens they used for writing had already given out.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85004021"/>
      <verse num="21">But this was an act of the invincible providence of him who was aiding the Jews from heaven.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005001"/>
    <chapter num="5">
      <heading>Execution of the Jews Is Twice Thwarted</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Then the king, completely inflexible and filled with overpowering anger and wrath, summoned Hermon, keeper of the elephants,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005002"/>
      <verse num="2">and ordered him on the following day to drug all the elephants—500 in number—with large handfuls of frankincense and plenty of unmixed wine and to drive them in, maddened by the lavish abundance of liquor, so that the Jews might meet their doom.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005003"/>
      <verse num="3">When he had given these orders he returned to his feasting, together with those of his friends and of the army who were especially hostile toward the Jews.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005004"/>
      <verse num="4">And Hermon, keeper of the elephants, proceeded faithfully to carry out the orders.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005005"/>
      <verse num="5">The servants in charge of the Jews<note nid="n85005005.1"/> went out in the evening and set about binding the hands of the wretched people and making arrangements for their continued custody through the night, convinced that the whole nation would experience its final destruction.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005006"/>
      <verse num="6">For to the Gentiles it appeared that the Jews were left without any aid,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005007"/>
      <verse num="7">because in their bonds they were forcibly confined on every side. But with tears and an irrepressible voice they all called upon the almighty Lord and Ruler of all power, their merciful God and Father, praying</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005008"/>
      <verse num="8">that he avert with vengeance the unholy plot against them and in a glorious manifestation rescue them from the fate now prepared for them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005009"/>
      <verse num="9">So their entreaty continued to ascend fervently to heaven.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005010"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">Hermon, however, when he had drugged the pitiless elephants until they had been filled with a great abundance of wine and satiated with frankincense, presented himself at the courtyard early in the morning to report to the king about these preparations.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005011"/>
      <verse num="11">But the Lord<note nid="n85005011.1"/> sent upon the king a portion of sleep, that beneficence that from the beginning, night and day, is bestowed by him who grants it to whomever he wishes.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005012"/>
      <verse num="12">And by the action of the Lord he was overcome by so pleasant and deep a sleep<note nid="n85005012.1"/> that he quite failed in his lawless purpose and was completely frustrated in his inflexible plan.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005013"/>
      <verse num="13">Then the Jews, since they had escaped the appointed hour, began praising their holy God and again begged him who is easily reconciled to show the might of his all-powerful hand to the arrogant Gentiles.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005014"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="14">But now, since it was nearly the middle of the tenth hour, the person who was in charge of the invitations, seeing that the guests were assembled, approached the king and nudged him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005015"/>
      <verse num="15">And when he had with difficulty roused him, he pointed out that the hour of the banquet was already slipping by, and he gave him an account of the situation.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005016"/>
      <verse num="16">The king, after considering this, returned to his drinking and ordered those present for the banquet to recline opposite him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005017"/>
      <verse num="17">When this was done he began urging them to give themselves over to revelry and to make the present<note nid="n85005017.1"/> portion of the banquet joyful by celebrating all the more.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005018"/>
      <verse num="18">After the party had been going on for some time, the king summoned Hermon and with sharp threats demanded to know why the Jews had been allowed to remain alive through the present day.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005019"/>
      <verse num="19">But when he, with the corroboration of his friends, pointed out that while it was still night he had carried out completely the order given him,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005020"/>
      <verse num="20">the king,<note nid="n85005020.1"/> possessed by a savagery worse than that of Phalaris, said that the Jews<note nid="n85005020.2"/> could be thankful for today<q class="end-single" qid="85005020.1"/>s sleep, <q class="begin-double" qid="85005020.2" from="85005020.2" to="85005020.3"/>but,<q class="end-double" qid="85005020.3" from="85005020.2" to="85005020.3"/> he added, <q class="begin-double" qid="85005020.4" from="85005020.4" to="85005020.5"/>tomorrow without delay prepare the elephants in the same way for the destruction of the lawless Jews!<q class="end-double" qid="85005020.5" from="85005020.4" to="85005020.5"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005021"/>
      <verse num="21">When the king had spoken, all those present readily and joyfully with one accord gave their approval, and each departed to his own home.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005022"/>
      <verse num="22">But they did not so much employ the duration of the night in sleep as in devising all sorts of insults for those they thought to be doomed.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005023"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="23">Then, as soon as the cock had crowed in the early morning, Hermon, having equipped<note nid="n85005023.1"/> the beasts, began to move them along in the great colonnade.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005024"/>
      <verse num="24">The crowds of the city had been assembled for this most pitiful spectacle, and they were eagerly waiting for daybreak.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005025"/>
      <verse num="25">But the Jews, at their last gasp, since the time had run out, stretched their hands toward heaven and with most tearful supplication and mournful dirges implored the supreme<note nid="n85005025.1"/> God to help them again at once.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005026"/>
      <verse num="26">The rays of the sun were not yet shed abroad, and the king was still receiving his friends, when Hermon arrived and invited him to come out, indicating that what the king desired was ready for action.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005027"/>
      <verse num="27">But he, upon receiving the report and being struck by the unusual invitation to come out—since he had been completely overcome by incomprehension—inquired what the matter was for which this had been so zealously completed for him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005028"/>
      <verse num="28">This was the act of God who rules over all things, for he had implanted in the king<q class="end-single" qid="85005028.1"/>s mind a forgetfulness of the things he had previously devised.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005029"/>
      <verse num="29">Then Hermon and all the king<q class="end-single" qid="85005029.1"/>s friends pointed out that the beasts and the armed forces were ready, <q class="begin-double" qid="85005029.2" from="85005029.2" to="85005029.3"/>O king, according to your eager purpose.<q class="end-double" qid="85005029.3" from="85005029.2" to="85005029.3"/><note nid="n85005029.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005030"/>
      <verse num="30">But at these words he was filled with an overpowering wrath, because by the providence of God his whole mind had been deranged in regard to these matters; and with a threatening look he said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005031"/>
      <verse num="31"><q class="begin-double" qid="85005031.1" from="85005031.1" to="85005032.1"/>Were your parents or children present, I would have prepared them to be a rich feast for the savage beasts instead of the Jews, who give me no ground for complaint and have exhibited to an extraordinary degree a full and firm loyalty to my ancestors.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005032"/>
      <verse num="32">In fact you would have been deprived of life instead of these, were it not for an affection arising from our nurture in common and your usefulness.<q class="end-double" qid="85005032.1" from="85005031.1" to="85005032.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005033"/>
      <verse num="33">So Hermon suffered an unexpected and dangerous threat, and his eyes and his face showed his dismay.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005034"/>
      <verse num="34">The king<q class="end-single" qid="85005034.1"/>s friends one by one sullenly slipped away, and they<note nid="n85005034.1"/> dismissed the assembled people, each to his own occupation.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005035"/>
      <verse num="35">Then the Jews, upon hearing what the king had said, started praising the manifest Lord God, King of kings, since this also was his aid that they had received.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005036"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="36">The king, however, reconvened the party in the same manner and went about urging the guests to return to their celebrating.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005037"/>
      <verse num="37">After summoning Hermon he said in a threatening tone, <q class="begin-double" qid="85005037.1" from="85005037.1" to="85005038.1"/>How many times, you poor wretch, must I give you orders about these same things?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005038"/>
      <verse num="38">Equip<note nid="n85005038.1"/> the elephants now once more for the destruction of the Jews tomorrow!<q class="end-double" qid="85005038.1" from="85005037.1" to="85005038.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005039"/>
      <verse num="39">But the officials who were reclining at table with him, wondering at his instability of mind, began to object as follows:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005040"/>
      <verse num="40"><q class="begin-double" qid="85005040.1" from="85005040.1" to="85005041.1"/>O king, how long will you continue to test us, as though we are idiots, ordering now for a third time that they be destroyed and again revoking your decree in the matter?<note nid="n85005040.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005041"/>
      <verse num="41">As a result the city is in a tumult because of its expectation; it is crowded with masses of people and also in constant danger of being plundered.<q class="end-double" qid="85005041.1" from="85005040.1" to="85005041.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005042"/>
      <verse num="42">Upon this the king, a Phalaris in everything and filled with madness, took no account of the changes of mind that had come about within him for the protection of the Jews, and he firmly swore an irrevocable<note nid="n85005042.1"/> oath that he would send these people to death<note nid="n85005042.2"/> without delay, mangled by the knees and feet of the beasts,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005043"/>
      <verse num="43">and would also march against Judea and rapidly level it to the ground with fire and spear and by burning to the ground the temple <q class="begin-double" qid="85005043.1" from="85005043.1" to="85005043.2"/>inaccessible to us<q class="end-double" qid="85005043.2" from="85005043.1" to="85005043.2"/> would quickly render it forever empty of those who offered sacrifices there.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005044"/>
      <verse num="44">Then the friends and officers departed with great joy, and they confidently started posting the armed forces at the places in the city most favorable for keeping guard.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005045"/>
      <verse num="45">Now when the beasts had been brought virtually to a state of madness, so to speak, by the very fragrant draughts of wine mixed with frankincense and had been equipped with frightful devices, the elephant keeper</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005046"/>
      <verse num="46">entered at about dawn into the courtyard—the city now being filled with countless masses of people crowding their way into the hippodrome—and began urging the king on to the matter at hand.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005047"/>
      <verse num="47">So he, when he had filled his impious mind with a deep rage, rushed out in full force along with the beasts, wishing to witness, with invulnerable heart and with his own eyes, the grievous and pitiful destruction of the aforementioned people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005048"/>
      <verse num="48">And when the Jews saw the dust raised by the elephants going out at the gate and by the following armed forces, as well as by the trampling of the crowd, and heard the loud and tumultuous noise,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005049"/>
      <verse num="49">they thought that this was their last moment of life, the end of their most miserable suspense, and giving way to lamentation and groans they started kissing one another, embracing relatives and falling upon one another<q class="end-single" qid="85005049.1"/>s shoulders—parents and children, mothers and daughters, and others with babies at their breasts who were drawing their last milk.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005050"/>
      <verse num="50">Not only this, but when they considered the help that they had received before from heaven they prostrated themselves with one accord on the ground, removing the babies from their breasts,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85005051"/>
      <verse num="51">and cried out in a very loud voice, imploring the Ruler over every power to manifest himself and be merciful to them, as they stood now at the gates of death.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006001"/>
    <chapter num="6">
      <heading>Prayer of Eleazar</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Then a certain Eleazar, famous among the priests of the country, who had attained a ripe old age and throughout his life had been adorned with every virtue, directed the elders around him to cease calling upon the holy God and prayed as follows:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006002"/>
      <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="85006002.1" from="85006002.1" to="85006015.3"/>King of great power, almighty God Most High, governing all creation with mercy,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006003"/>
      <verse num="3">look upon the descendants of Abraham, O Father, upon the children of the consecrated Jacob, a people of your consecrated portion, foreigners in a foreign land who are perishing unjustly.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006004"/>
      <verse num="4">Pharaoh with his abundance of chariots, the former ruler of this Egypt, exalted with lawless insolence and boastful tongue, you destroyed together with his arrogant army by drowning them in the sea, manifesting the light of your mercy upon the nation of Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006005"/>
      <verse num="5">Sennacherib exulting in his countless forces, oppressive king of the Assyrians, who had already gained control of the whole world by the spear and was moving against your holy city, speaking grievous words with boasting and insolence, you, O Lord, broke in pieces, showing your power to many nations.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006006"/>
      <verse num="6">The three companions in Babylon who had voluntarily surrendered their lives to the flames so as not to serve vain things, you rescued unharmed, even to a hair, moistening the fiery furnace with dew and turning the flame against all their enemies.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006007"/>
      <verse num="7">Daniel, who through envious slanders was cast down into the ground to lions as food for wild beasts, you brought up to the light unharmed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006008"/>
      <verse num="8">And Jonah, wasting away in the belly of a huge, sea-born monster, you, Father, watched over and restored<note nid="n85006008.1"/> unharmed to all his family.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006009"/>
      <verse num="9">And now, you who hate insolence, all-merciful and protector of all, reveal yourself quickly to those of the nation of Israel<note nid="n85006009.1"/>—who are being outrageously treated by the abominable and lawless Gentiles.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006010"/>
      <verse num="10">Even if our lives have become entangled in impieties in our exile, rescue us from the hand of the enemy and destroy us, Lord, by whatever fate you choose.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006011"/>
      <verse num="11">Let not the empty-minded praise their empty idols<note nid="n85006011.1"/> at the destruction of your beloved people, saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="85006011.1" from="85006011.1" to="85006011.2"/>Not even their god has rescued them.<q class="end-single" qid="85006011.2" from="85006011.1" to="85006011.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006012"/>
      <verse num="12">But you, O Eternal One, who have all might and all power, look upon us now: have mercy upon us who by the senseless insolence of the lawless are being deprived of life in the manner of traitors.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006013"/>
      <verse num="13">And let the Gentiles cower today in fear of your invincible might, O honored one, who have power to save the nation of Jacob.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006014"/>
      <verse num="14">The whole throng of infants and their parents are entreating you with tears.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006015"/>
      <verse num="15">Let it be shown to all the Gentiles that you are with us, O Lord, and have not turned your face from us; but just as you have said, <q class="begin-single" qid="85006015.1" from="85006015.1" to="85006015.2"/>Not even when they were in the land of their enemies did I neglect them,<q class="end-single" qid="85006015.2" from="85006015.1" to="85006015.2"/> so accomplish it, O Lord.<q class="end-double" qid="85006015.3" from="85006002.1" to="85006015.3"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006016"/>
      <heading>Two Angels Rescue the Jews</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">Just as Eleazar was ending his prayer, the king arrived at the hippodrome with the beasts and all the arrogance of his power.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006017"/>
      <verse num="17">And when the Jews observed this they raised great cries to heaven so that even the nearby valleys resounded with them and brought an uncontrollable terror upon the army.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006018"/>
      <verse num="18">Then the most glorious, almighty, and true God revealed his holy face and opened the heavenly gates, from which two glorious angels of fearful aspect descended, visible to all but the Jews.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006019"/>
      <verse num="19">They opposed the power of the enemy and filled them with confusion and terror, binding them with immovable shackles.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006020"/>
      <verse num="20">Even the king began to shudder bodily, and he forgot his sullen insolence.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006021"/>
      <verse num="21">The beasts turned back upon the armed forces following them and began trampling and destroying them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006022"/>
      <verse num="22">Then the king<q class="end-single" qid="85006022.1"/>s anger was turned to pity and tears because of the things that he had devised beforehand.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006023"/>
      <verse num="23">For when he heard the shouting and saw them all fallen headlong to destruction, he wept and angrily threatened his friends, saying,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006024"/>
      <verse num="24"><q class="begin-double" qid="85006024.1" from="85006024.1" to="85006028.1"/>You are committing treason and surpassing tyrants in savagery; and even me, your benefactor, you are now attempting to deprive of dominion and life by secretly devising acts of no advantage to the kingdom.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006025"/>
      <verse num="25">Who is it that has taken each man from his home and senselessly gathered here those who faithfully have held the fortresses of our country?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006026"/>
      <verse num="26">Who is it that has so lawlessly encompassed with outrageous treatment those who from the beginning differed from<note nid="n85006026.1"/> all nations in their good will toward us and often have accepted willingly the worst of human dangers?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006027"/>
      <verse num="27">Loose and untie their unjust bonds! Send them back to their homes in peace, begging pardon for your former actions!<note nid="n85006027.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006028"/>
      <verse num="28">Release the sons of the almighty and living God of heaven, who from the time of our ancestors until now has granted an unimpeded and notable stability to our government.<q class="end-double" qid="85006028.1" from="85006024.1" to="85006028.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006029"/>
      <verse num="29">These then were the things he said; and the Jews, immediately released, began to bless their holy God and Savior, since they now had escaped death.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006030"/>
      <heading>The Jews Celebrate Their Deliverance</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="30">Then the king, when he had returned to the city, summoned the official in charge of the revenues and ordered him to provide to the Jews both wines and everything else needed for a festival of seven days, deciding that they should celebrate their rescue with all joyfulness in that same place in which they had expected to meet their destruction.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006031"/>
      <verse num="31">Accordingly those disgracefully treated and near to death<note nid="n85006031.1"/> or, rather, who stood at its very gates arranged for a banquet of deliverance instead of a bitter and lamentable death, and full of joy they apportioned to celebrants the place that had been prepared for their destruction and burial.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006032"/>
      <verse num="32">They ceased their chanting of dirges and took up the ancestral song, praising God, their Savior and worker of wonders.<note nid="n85006032.1"/> Putting an end to all mourning and wailing, they formed choruses<note nid="n85006032.2"/> as a sign of peaceful joy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006033"/>
      <verse num="33">Likewise also the king, after convening a great banquet to celebrate these events, gave thanks to heaven unceasingly and lavishly for the unexpected rescue that he<note nid="n85006033.1"/> had experienced.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006034"/>
      <verse num="34">And those who had previously believed that the Jews would be destroyed and become food for birds and had joyfully registered them groaned as they themselves were overcome by disgrace, and their fire-breathing boldness was ignominiously<note nid="n85006034.1"/> quenched.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006035"/>
      <verse num="35">But the Jews, when they had arranged the aforementioned choral group, as we have said before, passed the time in feasting to the accompaniment of joyous thanksgiving and psalms.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006036"/>
      <verse num="36">And when they had ordained a public rite for these things for the duration of their sojourning throughout their generations, they instituted the observance of the aforesaid days as a festival, not for drinking and gluttony, but because of the deliverance that had come to them through God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006037"/>
      <verse num="37">Then they petitioned the king, asking for dismissal to their homes.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006038"/>
      <verse num="38">So their registration was carried out from the twenty-fifth of Pachon to the fourth of Epeiph,<note nid="n85006038.1"/> for forty days; and their destruction was set for the fifth to the seventh of Epeiph,<note nid="n85006038.2"/> the three days</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006039"/>
      <verse num="39">in which the Lord of all most gloriously revealed his mercy and rescued them all together and unharmed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006040"/>
      <verse num="40">Then they feasted, provided with everything by the king, until the fourteenth day,<note nid="n85006040.1"/> on which also they made the petition for their dismissal.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85006041"/>
      <verse num="41">The king granted their request at once and wrote the following letter for them to the generals in the cities, magnanimously expressing his concern:</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007001"/>
    <chapter num="7">
      <heading>Ptolemy’s Letter on Behalf of the Jews</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1"><q class="begin-double" qid="85007001.1" from="85007001.1" to="85007009.1"/>King Ptolemy Philopator to the generals in Egypt and all in authority in his government, greetings and good health.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007002"/>
      <verse num="2">We ourselves and our children are faring well, the great God guiding our affairs according to our desire.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007003"/>
      <verse num="3">Certain of our friends, frequently urging us with malicious intent, persuaded us to gather together the Jews of the kingdom in a body and to punish them with barbarous penalties as traitors;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007004"/>
      <verse num="4">for they declared that our government would never be firmly established until this was accomplished, because of the ill-will that these people had toward all nations.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007005"/>
      <verse num="5">They also led them out with harsh treatment as slaves, or rather as traitors, and, girding themselves with a cruelty more savage than that of Scythian custom, they tried without any inquiry or examination to put them to death.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007006"/>
      <verse num="6">But we very severely threatened them for these acts, and in accordance with the clemency that we have toward all people we barely spared their lives. Since we have come to realize that the God of heaven surely shields the Jews, always fighting for them as a father does for his children,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007007"/>
      <verse num="7">and since we have taken into account the friendly and firm good will that they had toward us and our ancestors, we justly have acquitted them of every charge of whatever kind.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007008"/>
      <verse num="8">We also have ordered each and every one to return to his own home, with no one in any way<note nid="n85007008.1"/> doing them harm at all or reproaching them for the irrational things that have happened.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007009"/>
      <verse num="9">For you should know that if we devise any evil against them or cause them any grief at all, we always shall have not a mortal, but the Ruler over every power, the Most High God, as an antagonist to avenge such acts thoroughly and inescapably. Farewell.<q class="end-double" qid="85007009.1" from="85007001.1" to="85007009.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007010"/>
      <heading>The Jews Return Home with Joy</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">Upon receiving this letter the Jews did not immediately hurry to make their departure, but they requested of the king that at their own hands those of the Jewish nation who had willfully transgressed against the holy God and the law of God should receive the punishment they deserved.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007011"/>
      <verse num="11">For they declared that those who for the belly<q class="end-single" qid="85007011.1"/>s sake had transgressed the divine commandments would also never be favorably disposed toward the king<q class="end-single" qid="85007011.2"/>s government.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007012"/>
      <verse num="12">The king<note nid="n85007012.1"/> then, admitting and approving the truth of what they said, granted them a general license so that freely and without royal authority or supervision they might destroy those everywhere in his kingdom who had transgressed the law of God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007013"/>
      <verse num="13">When they had applauded him in fitting manner, their priests and the whole multitude shouted the hallelujah and joyfully departed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007014"/>
      <verse num="14">And so on their way they set about punishing and putting to death as public examples any whom they met of their compatriots who had become defiled.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007015"/>
      <verse num="15">In that day they put to death more than 300 men; and they kept the day as a joyful festival, since they had destroyed the profaners.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007016"/>
      <verse num="16">But those who had held fast to God even to death and had received the full enjoyment of deliverance began their departure from the city, crowned with all sorts of very fragrant flowers, joyfully and loudly giving thanks to the one God of their fathers, the eternal Savior<note nid="n85007016.1"/> of Israel, in words of praise and all kinds of melodious songs.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007017"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="17">When they had arrived at Ptolemais, called <q class="begin-double" qid="85007017.1" from="85007017.1" to="85007017.2"/>rose-bearing<q class="end-double" qid="85007017.2" from="85007017.1" to="85007017.2"/> because of a characteristic of the place, the fleet waited for them, in accord with the common desire, for seven days.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007018"/>
      <verse num="18">There they celebrated their deliverance,<note nid="n85007018.1"/> for the king had generously provided all things to them for their journey, to each as far as his own house.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007019"/>
      <verse num="19">And when they had landed in peace with appropriate thanksgiving, there too in like manner they decided to observe these days as a joyous festival during the time of their sojourning.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007020"/>
      <verse num="20">Then, after inscribing them as holy on a pillar and dedicating a place of prayer at the site of the festival, they departed unharmed, free, and overjoyed, since at the king<q class="end-single" qid="85007020.1"/>s command they had been brought safely by land and sea and river each to his own place.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007021"/>
      <verse num="21">They also possessed greater authority among their enemies than before, being held in honor and awe; and they were not subject at all to confiscation of their belongings by anyone.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007022"/>
      <verse num="22">Besides they all recovered all of their property, in accordance with the registration, so that those who held any restored it to them with extreme fear.<note nid="n85007022.1"/> So the supreme God perfectly performed great deeds for their deliverance.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v85007023"/>
      <verse num="23">Blessed be the Deliverer of Israel through all times! Amen.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
  </book>
</crossway-bible>
