<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible translation="English Standard Version" revision="2025-02-02" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
<book title="Judges" num="7">
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001001"/>
  <chapter num="1">
    <heading>The Continuing Conquest of Canaan</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">After the death of Joshua, the people of Israel <crossref let="a" cid="c07001001.1"/>inquired of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="b" cid="c07001001.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07001001.1" from="07001001.1" to="07001001.2"/>Who shall go up first for us against the Canaanites, to fight against them?<q class="end-double" qid="07001001.2" from="07001001.1" to="07001001.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001002"/>
    <verse num="2">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07001002.1" from="07001002.1" to="07001002.2"/>Judah shall go up; behold, I have given the land into his hand.<q class="end-double" qid="07001002.2" from="07001002.1" to="07001002.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001003"/>
    <verse num="3">And Judah said to Simeon his brother, <q class="begin-double" qid="07001003.1" from="07001003.1" to="07001003.2"/>Come up with me into the territory allotted to me, that we may fight against the Canaanites. <crossref let="c" cid="c07001003.1"/>And I likewise will go with you into the territory allotted to you.<q class="end-double" qid="07001003.2" from="07001003.1" to="07001003.2"/> So Simeon went with him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001004"/>
    <verse num="4">Then Judah went up and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave the Canaanites and the Perizzites into their hand, and they defeated 10,000 of them at Bezek.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001005"/>
    <verse num="5">They found Adoni-bezek at Bezek and fought against him and defeated the Canaanites and the Perizzites.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001006"/>
    <verse num="6">Adoni-bezek fled, but they pursued him and caught him and cut off his thumbs and his big toes.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001007"/>
    <verse num="7">And Adoni-bezek said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07001007.1" from="07001007.1" to="07001007.2"/>Seventy kings with their thumbs and their big toes cut off <crossref let="d" cid="c07001007.1"/>used to pick up scraps under my table. <crossref let="e" cid="c07001007.2"/>As I have done, so God has repaid me.<q class="end-double" qid="07001007.2" from="07001007.1" to="07001007.2"/> And they brought him to Jerusalem, and he died there.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="f" cid="c07001008.1"/>And the men of Judah fought against Jerusalem and captured it and struck it with the edge of the sword and set the city on fire.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001009"/>
    <verse num="9">And afterward the men of Judah went down to fight against the Canaanites who lived in <crossref let="g" cid="c07001009.1"/>the hill country, in the Negeb, and in <crossref let="g" cid="c07001009.2"/>the lowland.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="h" cid="c07001010.1"/>And Judah went against the Canaanites who lived in Hebron <crossref let="i" cid="c07001010.2"/>(now the name of Hebron was formerly Kiriath-arba), and they defeated <crossref let="j" cid="c07001010.3"/>Sheshai and Ahiman and Talmai.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11">From there they went against the inhabitants of Debir. The name of Debir was formerly Kiriath-sepher.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001012"/>
    <verse num="12">And Caleb said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07001012.1" from="07001012.1" to="07001012.2"/>He who attacks Kiriath-sepher and captures it, I will give him Achsah my daughter as wife.<q class="end-double" qid="07001012.2" from="07001012.1" to="07001012.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001013"/>
    <verse num="13">And Othniel the son of Kenaz, <crossref let="k" cid="c07001013.1"/>Caleb&apos;s younger brother, captured it. And he gave him Achsah his daughter as wife.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001014"/>
    <verse num="14">When she came to him, she urged him to ask her father for a field. And she dismounted from her donkey, and Caleb said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="07001014.1" from="07001014.1" to="07001014.2"/>What do you want?<q class="end-double" qid="07001014.2" from="07001014.1" to="07001014.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001015"/>
    <verse num="15">She said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07001015.1" from="07001015.1" to="07001015.2"/>Give me a blessing. Since you have given me the land of the Negeb, give me also springs of water.<q class="end-double" qid="07001015.2" from="07001015.1" to="07001015.2"/> And Caleb gave her the upper springs and the lower springs.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">And the descendants of the <crossref let="l" cid="c07001016.1"/>Kenite, Moses&apos; father-in-law, went up with the people of Judah <crossref let="m" cid="c07001016.2"/>from the city of palms into the wilderness of Judah, which lies in the Negeb near <crossref let="n" cid="c07001016.3"/>Arad, <crossref let="o" cid="c07001016.4"/>and they went and settled with the people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="p" cid="c07001017.1"/>And Judah went with Simeon his brother, and they defeated the Canaanites who inhabited Zephath and devoted it to destruction. So the name of the city was called <crossref let="q" cid="c07001017.2"/>Hormah.<note nid="n07001017.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001018"/>
    <verse num="18">Judah also <crossref let="r" cid="c07001018.1"/>captured Gaza with its territory, and Ashkelon with its territory, and Ekron with its territory.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001019"/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="p" cid="c07001019.1"/>And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was with Judah, and he took possession of the <crossref let="s" cid="c07001019.2"/>hill country, but he could not drive out the inhabitants of the plain because they had <crossref let="t" cid="c07001019.3"/>chariots of iron.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="u" cid="c07001020.1"/>And Hebron was given to Caleb, as Moses had said. And he drove out from it <crossref let="v" cid="c07001020.2"/>the three sons of Anak.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001021"/>
    <verse num="21">But the people of Benjamin did not drive out the Jebusites who lived in Jerusalem, <crossref let="w" cid="c07001021.1"/>so the Jebusites have lived with the people of Benjamin in Jerusalem to this day.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">The house of Joseph also went up against Bethel, <crossref let="x" cid="c07001022.1"/>and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was with them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001023"/>
    <verse num="23">And the house of Joseph scouted out Bethel. (<crossref let="y" cid="c07001023.1"/>Now the name of the city was formerly Luz.)</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001024"/>
    <verse num="24">And the spies saw a man coming out of the city, and they said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07001024.1" from="07001024.1" to="07001024.2"/>Please show us the way into the city, <crossref let="z" cid="c07001024.1"/>and we will deal kindly with you.<q class="end-double" qid="07001024.2" from="07001024.1" to="07001024.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001025"/>
    <verse num="25">And he showed them the way into the city. And they struck the city with the edge of the sword, but they let the man and all his family go.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001026"/>
    <verse num="26">And the man went to <crossref let="a" cid="c07001026.1"/>the land of the Hittites and built a city and called its name Luz. That is its name to this day.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001027"/>
    <heading>Failure to Complete the Conquest</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="27"><crossref let="b" cid="c07001027.1"/>Manasseh did not drive out the inhabitants of Beth-shean and its villages, or Taanach and its villages, or the inhabitants of Dor and its villages, or the inhabitants of Ibleam and its villages, or the inhabitants of Megiddo and its villages, for the Canaanites persisted in dwelling in that land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001028"/>
    <verse num="28">When Israel grew strong, they put the Canaanites to forced labor, but did not drive them out completely.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001029"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="c" cid="c07001029.1"/>And Ephraim did not drive out the Canaanites who lived in Gezer, so the Canaanites lived in Gezer among them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001030"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="30">Zebulun did not drive out the inhabitants of Kitron, or the inhabitants of <crossref let="d" cid="c07001030.1"/>Nahalol, so the Canaanites lived among them, but became subject to forced labor.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001031"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="31"><crossref let="e" cid="c07001031.1"/>Asher did not drive out the inhabitants of Acco, or the inhabitants of Sidon or of Ahlab or of Achzib or of Helbah or of Aphik or of Rehob,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001032"/>
    <verse num="32">so the Asherites lived among the Canaanites, the inhabitants of the land, for they did not drive them out.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001033"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="33">Naphtali did not drive out the inhabitants of <crossref let="f" cid="c07001033.1"/>Beth-shemesh, or the inhabitants of Beth-anath, so they lived among the Canaanites, the inhabitants of the land. Nevertheless, the inhabitants of Beth-shemesh and of Beth-anath became subject to forced labor for them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001034"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="34"><crossref let="g" cid="c07001034.1"/>The Amorites pressed the people of Dan back into the hill country, for they did not allow them to come down to the plain.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001035"/>
    <verse num="35">The Amorites persisted in dwelling in Mount Heres, <crossref let="h" cid="c07001035.1"/>in Aijalon, and in Shaalbim, but the hand of the house of Joseph rested heavily on them, and they became subject to forced labor.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07001036"/>
    <verse num="36">And the border of the Amorites ran from <crossref let="i" cid="c07001036.1"/>the ascent of Akrabbim, from Sela and upward.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002001"/>
  <chapter num="2">
    <heading>Israel&apos;s Disobedience</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Now the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> went up from Gilgal to <crossref let="j" cid="c07002001.1"/>Bochim. And he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07002001.1" from="07002001.1" to="07002003.1"/>I brought you up from Egypt and brought you into the land that I swore to give to your fathers. I said, <crossref let="k" cid="c07002001.2"/><q class="begin-single" qid="07002001.2" from="07002001.2" to="07002002.1"/>I will never break my covenant with you,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="l" cid="c07002002.1"/>and you shall make no covenant with the inhabitants of this land; <crossref let="m" cid="c07002002.2"/>you shall break down their altars.<q class="end-single" qid="07002002.1" from="07002001.2" to="07002002.1"/> But you have not obeyed my voice. What is this you have done?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002003"/>
    <verse num="3">So now I say, <crossref let="n" cid="c07002003.1"/>I will not drive them out before you, but they shall become <crossref let="o" cid="c07002003.2"/>thorns in your sides, and their gods shall be a snare to you.<q class="end-double" qid="07002003.1" from="07002001.1" to="07002003.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002004"/>
    <verse num="4">As soon as the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke these words to all the people of Israel, the people lifted up their voices and wept.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002005"/>
    <verse num="5">And they called the name of that place Bochim.<note nid="n07002005.1"/> And they sacrificed there to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002006"/>
    <heading>The Death of Joshua</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6">When Joshua dismissed the people, the people of Israel went each to his inheritance to take possession of the land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="p" cid="c07002007.1"/>And the people served the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders who outlived Joshua, who had seen all the great work that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had done for Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002008"/>
    <verse num="8">And Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, died at the age of 110 years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002009"/>
    <verse num="9">And they buried him within the boundaries of <crossref let="q" cid="c07002009.1"/>his inheritance in Timnath-heres, <crossref let="r" cid="c07002009.2"/>in the hill country of Ephraim, north of the mountain of Gaash.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002010"/>
    <verse num="10">And all that generation also were gathered to their fathers. And there arose another generation after them who did not know the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> or the work that he had done for Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002011"/>
    <heading>Israel&apos;s Unfaithfulness</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="s" cid="c07002011.1"/>And the people of Israel did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and served the Baals.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="t" cid="c07002012.1"/>And they abandoned the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers, who had brought them out of the land of Egypt. <crossref let="u" cid="c07002012.2"/>They went after other gods, from among the gods of the peoples who were around them, and <crossref let="v" cid="c07002012.3"/>bowed down to them. <crossref let="w" cid="c07002012.4"/>And they provoked the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to anger.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002013"/>
    <verse num="13">They abandoned the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="x" cid="c07002013.1"/>and served the Baals and the Ashtaroth.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002014"/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="y" cid="c07002014.1"/>So the anger of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was kindled against Israel, and he <crossref let="z" cid="c07002014.2"/>gave them over to plunderers, who plundered them. <crossref let="a" cid="c07002014.3"/>And he sold them into the hand of their surrounding enemies, <crossref let="b" cid="c07002014.4"/>so that they could no longer withstand their enemies.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002015"/>
    <verse num="15">Whenever they marched out, the hand of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was against them for harm, as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had warned, <crossref let="c" cid="c07002015.1"/>and as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had sworn to them. And they were in terrible distress.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002016"/>
    <heading>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> Raises Up Judges</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="d" cid="c07002016.1"/>Then the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> raised up judges, <crossref let="e" cid="c07002016.2"/>who saved them out of the hand of those who plundered them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002017"/>
    <verse num="17">Yet they did not listen to their judges, for <crossref let="f" cid="c07002017.1"/>they whored after other gods and bowed down to them. <crossref let="g" cid="c07002017.2"/>They soon turned aside from the way in which their fathers had walked, who had obeyed the commandments of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and they did not do so.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002018"/>
    <verse num="18">Whenever the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> raised up judges for them, <crossref let="h" cid="c07002018.1"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was with the judge, and he saved them from the hand of their enemies all the days of the judge. <crossref let="i" cid="c07002018.2"/>For the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was moved to pity by <crossref let="j" cid="c07002018.3"/>their groaning because of those who afflicted and oppressed them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002019"/>
    <verse num="19">But <crossref let="k" cid="c07002019.1"/>whenever the judge died, they turned back and were more corrupt than their fathers, going after other gods, serving them and bowing down to them. They did not drop any of their practices or their stubborn ways.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="l" cid="c07002020.1"/>So the anger of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was kindled against Israel, and he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07002020.1" from="07002020.1" to="07002022.1"/>Because this people <crossref let="m" cid="c07002020.2"/>have transgressed my covenant that I commanded their fathers and have not obeyed my voice,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002021"/>
    <verse num="21"><crossref let="n" cid="c07002021.1"/>I will no longer drive out before them any of the nations that Joshua left when he died,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002022"/>
    <verse num="22">in order <crossref let="o" cid="c07002022.1"/>to test Israel by them, whether they will take care to walk in the way of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> as their fathers did, or not.<q class="end-double" qid="07002022.1" from="07002020.1" to="07002022.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07002023"/>
    <verse num="23">So the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> left those nations, not driving them out quickly, and he did not give them into the hand of Joshua.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003001"/>
  <chapter num="3">
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="p" cid="c07003001.1"/>Now these are the nations that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> left, to test Israel by them, that is, all in Israel who had not experienced all the wars in Canaan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003002"/>
    <verse num="2">It was only in order that the generations of the people of Israel might know war, to teach war to those who had not known it before.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003003"/>
    <verse num="3">These are the nations: <crossref let="q" cid="c07003003.1"/>the five lords of the Philistines and all the Canaanites and the Sidonians and the Hivites who lived on Mount Lebanon, from Mount Baal-hermon as far as Lebo-hamath.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003004"/>
    <verse num="4">They were for <crossref let="r" cid="c07003004.1"/>the testing of Israel, to know whether Israel would obey the commandments of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, which he commanded their fathers by the hand of Moses.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003005"/>
    <verse num="5">So the people of Israel lived <crossref let="s" cid="c07003005.1"/>among the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Amorites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="t" cid="c07003006.1"/>And their daughters they took to themselves for wives, and their own daughters they gave to their sons, and they served their gods.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003007"/>
    <heading>Othniel</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="u" cid="c07003007.1"/>And the people of Israel did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. They forgot the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> their God and served the Baals and <crossref let="v" cid="c07003007.2"/>the Asheroth.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003008"/>
    <verse num="8">Therefore the anger of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was kindled against Israel, <crossref let="w" cid="c07003008.1"/>and he sold them into the hand of <crossref let="x" cid="c07003008.2"/>Cushan-rishathaim king of Mesopotamia. And the people of Israel served Cushan-rishathaim eight years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003009"/>
    <verse num="9">But when the people of Israel <crossref let="y" cid="c07003009.1"/>cried out to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> raised up a <crossref let="z" cid="c07003009.2"/>deliverer for the people of Israel, who saved them, <crossref let="a" cid="c07003009.3"/>Othniel the son of Kenaz, Caleb&apos;s younger brother.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="b" cid="c07003010.1"/>The Spirit of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was upon him, and he judged Israel. He went out to war, and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave Cushan-rishathaim king of Mesopotamia into his hand. And his hand prevailed over Cushan-rishathaim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="c" cid="c07003011.1"/>So the land had rest for forty years. Then Othniel the son of Kenaz died.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003012"/>
    <heading>Ehud</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="d" cid="c07003012.1"/>And the people of Israel again did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> strengthened Eglon <crossref let="e" cid="c07003012.2"/>the king of Moab against Israel, because they had done what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003013"/>
    <verse num="13">He gathered to himself the Ammonites and the <crossref let="f" cid="c07003013.1"/>Amalekites, and went and defeated Israel. And they took possession of <crossref let="g" cid="c07003013.2"/>the city of palms.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003014"/>
    <verse num="14">And the people of Israel served Eglon the king of Moab eighteen years.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">Then the people of Israel <crossref let="h" cid="c07003015.1"/>cried out to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> raised up for them <crossref let="h" cid="c07003015.2"/>a deliverer, Ehud, the son of Gera, the Benjaminite, <crossref let="i" cid="c07003015.3"/>a left-handed man. The people of Israel sent tribute by him to Eglon the king of Moab.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003016"/>
    <verse num="16">And Ehud made for himself a sword with two edges, a cubit<note nid="n07003016.1"/> in length, and he bound it on his right thigh under his clothes.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003017"/>
    <verse num="17">And he presented the tribute to Eglon king of Moab. Now Eglon was a very fat man.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003018"/>
    <verse num="18">And when Ehud had finished presenting the tribute, he sent away the people who carried the tribute.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003019"/>
    <verse num="19">But he himself turned back <crossref let="j" cid="c07003019.1"/>at the idols near Gilgal and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07003019.1" from="07003019.1" to="07003019.2"/>I have a secret message for you, O king.<q class="end-double" qid="07003019.2" from="07003019.1" to="07003019.2"/> And he commanded, <q class="begin-double" qid="07003019.3" from="07003019.3" to="07003019.4"/>Silence.<q class="end-double" qid="07003019.4" from="07003019.3" to="07003019.4"/> And all his attendants went out from his presence.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003020"/>
    <verse num="20">And Ehud came to him as he was sitting alone in his <crossref let="k" cid="c07003020.1"/>cool roof chamber. <crossref let="l" cid="c07003020.2"/>And Ehud said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07003020.1" from="07003020.1" to="07003020.2"/>I have a message from God for you.<q class="end-double" qid="07003020.2" from="07003020.1" to="07003020.2"/> And he arose from his seat.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003021"/>
    <verse num="21">And Ehud reached with his left hand, took the sword from his right thigh, and thrust it into his belly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003022"/>
    <verse num="22">And the hilt also went in after the blade, and the fat closed over the blade, for he did not pull the sword out of his belly; and the dung came out.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003023"/>
    <verse num="23">Then Ehud went out into the porch<note nid="n07003023.1"/> and closed the doors of the roof chamber behind him <crossref let="m" cid="c07003023.1"/>and locked them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003024"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24">When he had gone, the servants came, and when they saw that the doors of the roof chamber were locked, they thought, <crossref let="n" cid="c07003024.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07003024.1" from="07003024.1" to="07003024.2"/>Surely he is relieving himself in the closet of the cool chamber.<q class="end-double" qid="07003024.2" from="07003024.1" to="07003024.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003025"/>
    <verse num="25">And they waited till they were embarrassed. But when he still did not open the doors of the roof chamber, they took the key and opened them, and there lay their lord dead on the floor.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003026"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="26">Ehud escaped while they delayed, and he passed beyond <crossref let="o" cid="c07003026.1"/>the idols and escaped to Seirah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003027"/>
    <verse num="27">When he arrived, <crossref let="p" cid="c07003027.1"/>he sounded the trumpet in <crossref let="q" cid="c07003027.2"/>the hill country of Ephraim. Then the people of Israel went down with him from the hill country, and he was their leader.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003028"/>
    <verse num="28">And he said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07003028.1" from="07003028.1" to="07003028.2"/>Follow after me, <crossref let="r" cid="c07003028.1"/>for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has given your enemies the Moabites into your hand.<q class="end-double" qid="07003028.2" from="07003028.1" to="07003028.2"/> So they went down after him and seized <crossref let="s" cid="c07003028.2"/>the fords of the Jordan against the Moabites and did not allow anyone to pass over.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003029"/>
    <verse num="29">And they killed at that time about 10,000 of the Moabites, all strong, able-bodied men; not a man escaped.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003030"/>
    <verse num="30">So Moab was subdued that day under the hand of Israel. <crossref let="t" cid="c07003030.1"/>And the land had rest for eighty years.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07003031"/>
    <heading>Shamgar</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="31">After him was <crossref let="u" cid="c07003031.1"/>Shamgar the son of Anath, who killed 600 of the Philistines <crossref let="v" cid="c07003031.2"/>with an oxgoad, and he also <crossref let="w" cid="c07003031.3"/>saved Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004001"/>
  <chapter num="4">
    <heading>Deborah and Barak</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="x" cid="c07004001.1"/>And the people of Israel again did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> after Ehud died.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004002"/>
    <verse num="2">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="y" cid="c07004002.1"/>sold them into the hand of <crossref let="z" cid="c07004002.2"/>Jabin king of Canaan, who reigned in <crossref let="z" cid="c07004002.3"/>Hazor. The commander of his army was <crossref let="a" cid="c07004002.4"/>Sisera, who lived in <crossref let="b" cid="c07004002.5"/>Harosheth-hagoyim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004003"/>
    <verse num="3">Then the people of Israel <crossref let="c" cid="c07004003.1"/>cried out to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for help, for he had <crossref let="d" cid="c07004003.2"/>900 chariots of iron and he oppressed the people of Israel cruelly for twenty years.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">Now Deborah, a prophetess, the wife of Lappidoth, was judging Israel at that time.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004005"/>
    <verse num="5">She used to sit under the palm of Deborah between Ramah and Bethel in <crossref let="e" cid="c07004005.1"/>the hill country of Ephraim, and the people of Israel came up to her for judgment.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004006"/>
    <verse num="6">She sent and summoned <crossref let="f" cid="c07004006.1"/>Barak the son of Abinoam from <crossref let="g" cid="c07004006.2"/>Kedesh-naphtali and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07004006.1" from="07004006.1" to="07004007.2"/>Has not the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, commanded you, <q class="begin-single" qid="07004006.2" from="07004006.2" to="07004007.1"/>Go, gather your men at Mount <crossref let="h" cid="c07004006.3"/>Tabor, taking 10,000 from the people of Naphtali and the people of Zebulun.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004007"/>
    <verse num="7">And I will draw out Sisera, the general of Jabin&apos;s army, to meet you by <crossref let="i" cid="c07004007.1"/>the river Kishon with his chariots and his troops, <crossref let="j" cid="c07004007.2"/>and I will give him into your hand<q class="end-single" qid="07004007.1" from="07004006.2" to="07004007.1"/>?<q class="end-double" qid="07004007.2" from="07004006.1" to="07004007.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004008"/>
    <verse num="8">Barak said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="07004008.1" from="07004008.1" to="07004008.2"/>If you will go with me, I will go, but if you will not go with me, I will not go.<q class="end-double" qid="07004008.2" from="07004008.1" to="07004008.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004009"/>
    <verse num="9">And she said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07004009.1" from="07004009.1" to="07004009.2"/>I will surely go with you. Nevertheless, the road on which you are going will not lead to your glory, for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will <crossref let="k" cid="c07004009.1"/>sell Sisera into the hand of a woman.<q class="end-double" qid="07004009.2" from="07004009.1" to="07004009.2"/> Then Deborah arose and went with Barak to Kedesh.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004010"/>
    <verse num="10">And Barak called out <crossref let="l" cid="c07004010.1"/>Zebulun and Naphtali to Kedesh. And 10,000 men went up at his heels, and Deborah went up with him.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11">Now Heber <crossref let="m" cid="c07004011.1"/>the Kenite had separated from the Kenites, the descendants of <crossref let="n" cid="c07004011.2"/>Hobab the father-in-law of Moses, and had pitched his tent as far away as the oak in <crossref let="o" cid="c07004011.3"/>Zaanannim, which is near Kedesh.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">When Sisera was told that Barak the son of Abinoam had gone up to Mount Tabor,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004013"/>
    <verse num="13">Sisera called out all his chariots, <crossref let="p" cid="c07004013.1"/>900 chariots of iron, and all the men who were with him, from Harosheth-hagoyim to the river Kishon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004014"/>
    <verse num="14">And Deborah said to Barak, <q class="begin-double" qid="07004014.1" from="07004014.1" to="07004014.2"/>Up! For this is the day in which <crossref let="q" cid="c07004014.1"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has given Sisera into your hand. <crossref let="r" cid="c07004014.2"/>Does not the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> go out before you?<q class="end-double" qid="07004014.2" from="07004014.1" to="07004014.2"/> So Barak went down from Mount Tabor with 10,000 men following him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="s" cid="c07004015.1"/>And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> routed Sisera and all his chariots and all his army before Barak by the edge of the sword. And Sisera got down from his chariot and fled away on foot.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004016"/>
    <verse num="16">And Barak pursued the chariots and the army to Harosheth-hagoyim, and all the army of Sisera fell by the edge of the sword; not a man was left.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004017"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17">But Sisera fled away on foot to the tent of Jael, the wife of Heber the Kenite, for there was peace between Jabin the king of Hazor and the house of Heber the Kenite.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004018"/>
    <verse num="18">And Jael came out to meet Sisera and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07004018.1" from="07004018.1" to="07004018.2"/>Turn aside, my lord; turn aside to me; do not be afraid.<q class="end-double" qid="07004018.2" from="07004018.1" to="07004018.2"/> So he turned aside to her into the tent, and she covered him with a rug.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004019"/>
    <verse num="19">And he said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="07004019.1" from="07004019.1" to="07004019.2"/>Please give me a little water to drink, for I am thirsty.<q class="end-double" qid="07004019.2" from="07004019.1" to="07004019.2"/> So she opened <crossref let="t" cid="c07004019.1"/>a skin of milk and gave him a drink and covered him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004020"/>
    <verse num="20">And he said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="07004020.1" from="07004020.1" to="07004020.6"/>Stand at the opening of the tent, and if any man comes and asks you, <q class="begin-single" qid="07004020.2" from="07004020.2" to="07004020.3"/>Is anyone here?<q class="end-single" qid="07004020.3" from="07004020.2" to="07004020.3"/> say, <q class="begin-single" qid="07004020.4" from="07004020.4" to="07004020.5"/>No.<q class="end-single" qid="07004020.5" from="07004020.4" to="07004020.5"/><q class="end-double" qid="07004020.6" from="07004020.1" to="07004020.6"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004021"/>
    <verse num="21">But Jael the wife of Heber took a tent peg, and took a hammer in her hand. Then she went softly to him and drove the peg into his temple until it went down into the ground while he was lying fast asleep from weariness. So he died.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004022"/>
    <verse num="22">And behold, as Barak was pursuing Sisera, Jael went out to meet him and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07004022.1" from="07004022.1" to="07004022.2"/>Come, and I will show you the man whom you are seeking.<q class="end-double" qid="07004022.2" from="07004022.1" to="07004022.2"/> So he went in to her tent, and there lay Sisera dead, with the tent peg in his temple.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004023"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="23"><crossref let="u" cid="c07004023.1"/>So on that day God subdued Jabin the king of Canaan before the people of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07004024"/>
    <verse num="24">And the hand of the people of Israel pressed harder and harder against Jabin the king of Canaan, until they destroyed Jabin king of Canaan.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005001"/>
  <chapter num="5">
    <heading>The Song of Deborah and Barak</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="v" cid="c07005001.1"/>Then sang Deborah and Barak the son of Abinoam on that day:</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005002"/>
    <begin-block-indent/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="2">
        <begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="07005002.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/>That the leaders took the lead in Israel,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>that <crossref let="w" cid="c07005002.1"/>the people offered themselves willingly,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>bless the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>!<end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005003"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="3">
        <begin-line/><q class="continue-double" qid="07005003.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/>Hear, O kings; give ear, O princes;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> I will sing;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>I will make melody to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel.<end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005004"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="4">
        <begin-line/><q class="continue-double" qid="07005004.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/><span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="x" cid="c07005004.1"/>when you went out from Seir,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>when you marched from the region of Edom,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/><crossref let="y" cid="c07005004.2"/>the earth trembled<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>and the heavens dropped,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>yes, the clouds dropped water.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005005"/>
    <verse num="5">
        <begin-line/>The mountains <crossref let="z" cid="c07005005.1"/>quaked before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/><crossref let="a" cid="c07005005.2"/>even Sinai before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,<note nid="n07005005.1"/> the God of Israel.<end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005006"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="6">
        <begin-line/><q class="continue-double" qid="07005006.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/>In the days of <crossref let="b" cid="c07005006.1"/>Shamgar, son of Anath,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>in the days of <crossref let="c" cid="c07005006.2"/>Jael, <crossref let="d" cid="c07005006.3"/>the highways were abandoned,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>and travelers kept to the byways.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005007"/>
    <verse num="7">
        <begin-line/>The villagers ceased in Israel;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>they ceased to be until I arose;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>I, Deborah, arose as a mother in Israel.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005008"/>
    <verse num="8">
        <begin-line/><crossref let="e" cid="c07005008.1"/>When new gods were chosen,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>then war was in the gates.<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/><crossref let="f" cid="c07005008.2"/>Was shield or spear to be seen<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>among forty thousand in Israel?<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005009"/>
    <verse num="9">
        <begin-line/>My heart goes out to the commanders of Israel<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>who <crossref let="g" cid="c07005009.1"/>offered themselves willingly among the people.<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>Bless the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005010"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="10">
        <begin-line/><q class="continue-double" qid="07005010.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/>Tell of it, <crossref let="h" cid="c07005010.1"/>you who ride on white donkeys,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>you who sit on rich carpets<note nid="n07005010.1"/><end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>and you who walk by the way.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005011"/>
    <verse num="11">
        <begin-line/>To the sound of musicians<note nid="n07005011.1"/> at the watering places,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>there they repeat the righteous triumphs of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>the righteous triumphs of his villagers in Israel.<end-line/>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
        <begin-line/><q class="continue-double" qid="07005011.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/>Then down to the gates marched the people of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005012"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="12">
        <begin-line/><crossref let="i" cid="c07005012.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="07005012.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/>Awake, awake, Deborah!<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>Awake, awake, break out in a song!<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>Arise, Barak, <crossref let="j" cid="c07005012.2"/>lead away your captives,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>O son of Abinoam.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005013"/>
    <verse num="13">
        <begin-line/>Then down marched the remnant of the noble;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>the people of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> marched down for me against the mighty.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005014"/>
    <verse num="14">
        <begin-line/>From <crossref let="k" cid="c07005014.1"/>Ephraim their root <crossref let="l" cid="c07005014.2"/>they marched down into the valley,<note nid="n07005014.1"/><end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>following you, Benjamin, with your kinsmen;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>from <crossref let="m" cid="c07005014.3"/>Machir marched down the commanders,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>and from Zebulun those who bear the lieutenant&apos;s<note nid="n07005014.2"/> staff;<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005015"/>
    <verse num="15">
        <begin-line/>the princes of Issachar came with Deborah,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>and Issachar faithful to <crossref let="n" cid="c07005015.1"/>Barak;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>into the valley they rushed at his heels.<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>Among the clans of Reuben<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>there were great searchings of heart.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005016"/>
    <verse num="16">
        <begin-line/>Why did you sit still <crossref let="o" cid="c07005016.1"/>among the sheepfolds,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>to hear the whistling for the flocks?<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>Among the clans of Reuben<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>there were great searchings of heart.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005017"/>
    <verse num="17">
        <begin-line/><crossref let="p" cid="c07005017.1"/>Gilead stayed beyond the Jordan;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/><crossref let="q" cid="c07005017.2"/>and Dan, why did he stay with the ships?<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/><crossref let="r" cid="c07005017.3"/>Asher sat still <crossref let="s" cid="c07005017.4"/>at the coast of the sea,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>staying by his landings.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005018"/>
    <verse num="18">
        <begin-line/><crossref let="t" cid="c07005018.1"/>Zebulun is a people who risked their lives to the death;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/><crossref let="t" cid="c07005018.2"/>Naphtali, too, on the heights of the field.<end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005019"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="19">
        <begin-line/><q class="continue-double" qid="07005019.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/>The kings came, they fought;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>then fought the kings of Canaan,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>at <crossref let="u" cid="c07005019.1"/>Taanach, by the waters of <crossref let="v" cid="c07005019.2"/>Megiddo;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/><crossref let="w" cid="c07005019.3"/>they got no spoils of silver.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005020"/>
    <verse num="20">
        <begin-line/><crossref let="x" cid="c07005020.1"/>From heaven the stars fought,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>from their courses they fought against Sisera.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005021"/>
    <verse num="21">
        <begin-line/><crossref let="y" cid="c07005021.1"/>The torrent Kishon swept them away,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>the ancient torrent, the torrent Kishon.<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>March on, my soul, with might!<end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005022"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="22">
        <begin-line/><q class="continue-double" qid="07005022.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/>Then loud beat the horses&apos; hoofs<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>with the galloping, galloping of his steeds.<end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005023"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="23">
        <begin-line/><q class="continue-double" qid="07005023.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/>Curse Meroz, says the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>curse its inhabitants thoroughly,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/><crossref let="z" cid="c07005023.1"/>because they did not come to the help of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>to the help of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> against the mighty.<end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005024"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="24">
        <begin-line/><q class="continue-double" qid="07005024.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/>Most blessed of women be <crossref let="a" cid="c07005024.1"/>Jael,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>the wife of Heber the Kenite,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>of tent-dwelling women most blessed.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005025"/>
    <verse num="25">
        <begin-line/><crossref let="b" cid="c07005025.1"/>He asked for water and she gave him milk;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>she brought him curds in a noble&apos;s bowl.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005026"/>
    <verse num="26">
        <begin-line/><crossref let="c" cid="c07005026.1"/>She sent her hand to the tent peg<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>and her right hand to the workmen&apos;s mallet;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>she struck Sisera;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>she crushed his head;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>she shattered and pierced his temple.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005027"/>
    <verse num="27">
        <begin-line/>Between her feet<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>he sank, he fell, he lay still;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>between her feet<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>he sank, he fell;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>where he sank,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>there he fell&emdash;dead.<end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005028"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="28">
        <begin-line/><crossref let="d" cid="c07005028.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="07005028.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/>Out of the window she peered,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>the mother of Sisera wailed through <crossref let="e" cid="c07005028.2"/>the lattice:<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/><q class="begin-single" qid="07005028.2" from="07005028.2" to="07005028.3"/>Why is his chariot so long in coming?<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>Why tarry the hoofbeats of his chariots?<q class="end-single" qid="07005028.3" from="07005028.2" to="07005028.3"/><end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005029"/>
    <verse num="29">
        <begin-line/>Her wisest princesses answer,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>indeed, she answers herself,<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005030"/>
    <verse num="30">
        <begin-line/><q class="begin-single" qid="07005030.1" from="07005030.1" to="07005030.2"/>Have they not found and <crossref let="f" cid="c07005030.1"/>divided the spoil?&emdash;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>A womb or two for every man;<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>spoil of dyed materials for Sisera,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>spoil of dyed materials embroidered,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>two pieces of dyed work embroidered for the neck as spoil?<q class="end-single" qid="07005030.2" from="07005030.1" to="07005030.2"/><end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07005031"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="31">
        <begin-line/><crossref let="g" cid="c07005031.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="07005031.1" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/>So may all your enemies perish, O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>!<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>But your friends be <crossref let="h" cid="c07005031.2"/>like the sun <crossref let="i" cid="c07005031.3"/>as he rises in his might.<q class="end-double" qid="07005031.2" from="07005002.1" to="07005031.2"/><end-line/>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/><crossref let="j" cid="c07005031.4"/>And the land had rest for forty years.
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006001"/>
  <chapter num="6">
    <heading>Midian Oppresses Israel</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="k" cid="c07006001.1"/>The people of Israel did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave them into the hand of <crossref let="l" cid="c07006001.2"/>Midian seven years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006002"/>
    <verse num="2">And the hand of Midian overpowered Israel, and because of Midian the people of Israel made for themselves the dens that are in the mountains and <crossref let="m" cid="c07006002.1"/>the caves and the strongholds.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006003"/>
    <verse num="3">For whenever the Israelites planted crops, the Midianites and <crossref let="n" cid="c07006003.1"/>the Amalekites and <crossref let="o" cid="c07006003.2"/>the people of the East would come up against them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006004"/>
    <verse num="4">They would encamp against them <crossref let="p" cid="c07006004.1"/>and devour the produce of the land, as far as Gaza, and leave no sustenance in Israel and no sheep or ox or donkey.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006005"/>
    <verse num="5">For they would come up with their livestock and their tents; they would come <crossref let="q" cid="c07006005.1"/>like locusts in number&emdash;both they and their camels could not be counted&emdash;so that they laid waste the land as they came in.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006006"/>
    <verse num="6">And Israel was brought very low because of Midian. And the people of Israel <crossref let="r" cid="c07006006.1"/>cried out for help to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">When the people of Israel cried out to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> on account of the Midianites,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006008"/>
    <verse num="8">the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> sent a prophet to the people of Israel. And he said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07006008.1" from="07006008.1" to="07006010.3"/>Thus says the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel: <crossref let="s" cid="c07006008.1"/>I led you up from Egypt and brought you out of the house of slavery.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006009"/>
    <verse num="9">And I delivered you from the hand of the Egyptians and from the hand of all who oppressed you, and <crossref let="t" cid="c07006009.1"/>drove them out before you and gave you their land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006010"/>
    <verse num="10">And I said to you, <q class="begin-single" qid="07006010.1" from="07006010.1" to="07006010.2"/>I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God; <crossref let="u" cid="c07006010.1"/>you shall not fear the gods of the Amorites in whose land you dwell.<q class="end-single" qid="07006010.2" from="07006010.1" to="07006010.2"/> But you have not obeyed my voice.<q class="end-double" qid="07006010.3" from="07006008.1" to="07006010.3"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006011"/>
    <heading>The Call of Gideon</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11">Now the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> came and sat under the terebinth at Ophrah, which belonged to Joash <crossref let="v" cid="c07006011.1"/>the Abiezrite, while his son <crossref let="w" cid="c07006011.2"/>Gideon was beating out wheat in the winepress to hide it from the Midianites.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006012"/>
    <verse num="12">And <crossref let="x" cid="c07006012.1"/>the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> appeared to him and said to him, <crossref let="y" cid="c07006012.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07006012.1" from="07006012.1" to="07006012.2"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is with you, O mighty man of valor.<q class="end-double" qid="07006012.2" from="07006012.1" to="07006012.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006013"/>
    <verse num="13">And Gideon said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07006013.1" from="07006013.1" to="07006013.4"/>Please, my lord, if the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is with us, why then has all this happened to us? And where are <crossref let="z" cid="c07006013.1"/>all his wonderful deeds <crossref let="a" cid="c07006013.2"/>that our fathers recounted to us, saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="07006013.2" from="07006013.2" to="07006013.3"/>Did not the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> bring us up from Egypt?<q class="end-single" qid="07006013.3" from="07006013.2" to="07006013.3"/> But now the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has forsaken us and given us into the hand of Midian.<q class="end-double" qid="07006013.4" from="07006013.1" to="07006013.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006014"/>
    <verse num="14">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span><note nid="n07006014.1"/> turned to him and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07006014.1" from="07006014.1" to="07006014.2"/>Go in this might of yours and save Israel from the hand of Midian; <crossref let="b" cid="c07006014.1"/>do not I send you?<q class="end-double" qid="07006014.2" from="07006014.1" to="07006014.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006015"/>
    <verse num="15">And he said to him, <crossref let="c" cid="c07006015.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07006015.1" from="07006015.1" to="07006015.2"/>Please, Lord, how can I save Israel? Behold, <crossref let="d" cid="c07006015.2"/>my clan is the weakest in Manasseh, and I am the least in my father&apos;s house.<q class="end-double" qid="07006015.2" from="07006015.1" to="07006015.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006016"/>
    <verse num="16">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to him, <crossref let="e" cid="c07006016.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07006016.1" from="07006016.1" to="07006016.2"/>But I will be with you, and you shall strike the Midianites as one man.<q class="end-double" qid="07006016.2" from="07006016.1" to="07006016.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006017"/>
    <verse num="17">And he said to him, <crossref let="f" cid="c07006017.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07006017.1" from="07006017.1" to="07006018.1"/>If now I have found favor in your eyes, then <crossref let="g" cid="c07006017.2"/>show me a sign that it is you who speak with me.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006018"/>
    <verse num="18">Please <crossref let="h" cid="c07006018.1"/>do not depart from here until I come to you and bring out my present and set it before you.<q class="end-double" qid="07006018.1" from="07006017.1" to="07006018.1"/> And he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07006018.2" from="07006018.2" to="07006018.3"/>I will stay till you return.<q class="end-double" qid="07006018.3" from="07006018.2" to="07006018.3"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19">So Gideon went into his house <crossref let="i" cid="c07006019.1"/>and prepared a young goat and unleavened cakes from an ephah<note nid="n07006019.1"/> of flour. The meat he put in a basket, and the broth he put in a pot, and brought them to him under the terebinth and presented them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006020"/>
    <verse num="20">And the angel of God said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07006020.1" from="07006020.1" to="07006020.2"/>Take the meat and the unleavened cakes, and put them <crossref let="j" cid="c07006020.1"/>on this rock, and <crossref let="k" cid="c07006020.2"/>pour the broth over them.<q class="end-double" qid="07006020.2" from="07006020.1" to="07006020.2"/> And he did so.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006021"/>
    <verse num="21">Then the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> reached out the tip of the staff that was in his hand and touched the meat and the unleavened cakes. <crossref let="l" cid="c07006021.1"/>And fire sprang up from the rock and consumed the meat and the unleavened cakes. And the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> vanished from his sight.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006022"/>
    <verse num="22">Then Gideon perceived that he was the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. And Gideon said, <crossref let="m" cid="c07006022.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07006022.1" from="07006022.1" to="07006022.2"/>Alas, O Lord <span class="divine-name">God</span>! For now I have seen the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> face to face.<q class="end-double" qid="07006022.2" from="07006022.1" to="07006022.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006023"/>
    <verse num="23">But the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to him, <crossref let="n" cid="c07006023.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07006023.1" from="07006023.1" to="07006023.2"/>Peace be to you. Do not fear; you shall not die.<q class="end-double" qid="07006023.2" from="07006023.1" to="07006023.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006024"/>
    <verse num="24">Then Gideon built an altar there to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and called it, <crossref let="o" cid="c07006024.1"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> Is Peace. To this day it still stands at <crossref let="p" cid="c07006024.2"/>Ophrah, which belongs to the Abiezrites.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006025"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="25">That night the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07006025.1" from="07006025.1" to="07006026.1"/>Take your father&apos;s bull, and the second bull seven years old, and pull down the altar of Baal that your father has, and cut down <crossref let="q" cid="c07006025.1"/>the Asherah that is beside it</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006026"/>
    <verse num="26">and build an altar to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God on the top of the <crossref let="r" cid="c07006026.1"/>stronghold here, with stones laid in due order. Then take the second bull and offer it as a burnt offering with the wood of the Asherah that you shall cut down.<q class="end-double" qid="07006026.1" from="07006025.1" to="07006026.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006027"/>
    <verse num="27">So Gideon took ten men of his servants and did as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had told him. But because he was too afraid of his family and the men of the town to do it by day, he did it by night.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006028"/>
    <heading>Gideon Destroys the Altar of Baal</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="28">When the men of the town rose early in the morning, behold, the altar of Baal was broken down, and the Asherah beside it was cut down, and the second bull was offered on the altar that had been built.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006029"/>
    <verse num="29">And they said to one another, <q class="begin-double" qid="07006029.1" from="07006029.1" to="07006029.2"/>Who has done this thing?<q class="end-double" qid="07006029.2" from="07006029.1" to="07006029.2"/> And after they had searched and inquired, they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07006029.3" from="07006029.3" to="07006029.4"/>Gideon the son of Joash has done this thing.<q class="end-double" qid="07006029.4" from="07006029.3" to="07006029.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006030"/>
    <verse num="30">Then the men of the town said to Joash, <q class="begin-double" qid="07006030.1" from="07006030.1" to="07006030.2"/>Bring out your son, that he may die, for he has broken down the altar of Baal and cut down the Asherah beside it.<q class="end-double" qid="07006030.2" from="07006030.1" to="07006030.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006031"/>
    <verse num="31">But Joash said to all who stood against him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07006031.1" from="07006031.1" to="07006031.2"/>Will you contend for Baal? Or will you save him? Whoever contends for him shall be put to death by morning. If he is a god, let him contend for himself, because his altar has been broken down.<q class="end-double" qid="07006031.2" from="07006031.1" to="07006031.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006032"/>
    <verse num="32">Therefore on that day Gideon<note nid="n07006032.1"/> was called <crossref let="s" cid="c07006032.1"/>Jerubbaal, that is to say, <q class="begin-double" qid="07006032.1" from="07006032.1" to="07006032.2"/>Let Baal contend against him,<q class="end-double" qid="07006032.2" from="07006032.1" to="07006032.2"/> because he broke down his altar.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006033"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="33">Now <crossref let="t" cid="c07006033.1"/>all the Midianites and the Amalekites and the people of the East came together, and they crossed the Jordan and encamped in <crossref let="u" cid="c07006033.2"/>the Valley of Jezreel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006034"/>
    <verse num="34">But <crossref let="v" cid="c07006034.1"/>the Spirit of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> clothed Gideon, <crossref let="w" cid="c07006034.2"/>and he sounded the trumpet, and the Abiezrites were called out to follow him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006035"/>
    <verse num="35"><crossref let="x" cid="c07006035.1"/>And he sent messengers throughout all Manasseh, and they too were called out to follow him. <crossref let="x" cid="c07006035.2"/>And he sent messengers to Asher, Zebulun, and Naphtali, and they went up to meet them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006036"/>
    <heading>The Sign of the Fleece</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="36"><crossref let="y" cid="c07006036.1"/>Then Gideon said to God, <q class="begin-double" qid="07006036.1" from="07006036.1" to="07006037.1"/>If you will save Israel by my hand, as you have said,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006037"/>
    <verse num="37">behold, I am laying a fleece of wool on the threshing floor. If there is dew on the fleece alone, and it is dry on all the ground, then I shall know that you will save Israel by my hand, as you have said.<q class="end-double" qid="07006037.1" from="07006036.1" to="07006037.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006038"/>
    <verse num="38">And it was so. When he rose early next morning and squeezed the fleece, he wrung enough dew from the fleece to fill a bowl with water.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006039"/>
    <verse num="39">Then Gideon said to God, <crossref let="z" cid="c07006039.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07006039.1" from="07006039.1" to="07006039.2"/>Let not your anger burn against me; let me speak just once more. Please let me test just once more with the fleece. Please let it be dry on the fleece only, and on all the ground let there be dew.<q class="end-double" qid="07006039.2" from="07006039.1" to="07006039.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07006040"/>
    <verse num="40">And God did so that night; and it was dry on the fleece only, and on all the ground there was dew.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007001"/>
  <chapter num="7">
    <heading>Gideon&apos;s Three Hundred Men</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Then <crossref let="a" cid="c07007001.1"/>Jerubbaal (that is, Gideon) and all the people who were with him rose early and encamped beside <crossref let="b" cid="c07007001.2"/>the spring of Harod. And the camp of Midian was north of them, <crossref let="c" cid="c07007001.3"/>by the hill of Moreh, in the valley.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007002"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="2">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Gideon, <q class="begin-double" qid="07007002.1" from="07007002.1" to="07007003.3"/>The people with you are too many for me to give the Midianites into their hand, <crossref let="d" cid="c07007002.1"/>lest Israel boast over me, saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="07007002.2" from="07007002.2" to="07007002.3"/>My own hand has saved me.<q class="end-single" qid="07007002.3" from="07007002.2" to="07007002.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007003"/>
    <verse num="3">Now therefore proclaim in the ears of the people, saying, <crossref let="e" cid="c07007003.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="07007003.1" from="07007003.1" to="07007003.2"/>Whoever is fearful and trembling, let him return home and hurry away from Mount Gilead.<q class="end-single" qid="07007003.2" from="07007003.1" to="07007003.2"/><q class="end-double" qid="07007003.3" from="07007002.1" to="07007003.3"/> Then 22,000 of the people returned, and 10,000 remained.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Gideon, <q class="begin-double" qid="07007004.1" from="07007004.1" to="07007004.6"/>The people are still too many. Take them down to the water, and I will test them for you there, and anyone of whom I say to you, <q class="begin-single" qid="07007004.2" from="07007004.2" to="07007004.3"/>This one shall go with you,<q class="end-single" qid="07007004.3" from="07007004.2" to="07007004.3"/> shall go with you, and anyone of whom I say to you, <q class="begin-single" qid="07007004.4" from="07007004.4" to="07007004.5"/>This one shall not go with you,<q class="end-single" qid="07007004.5" from="07007004.4" to="07007004.5"/> shall not go.<q class="end-double" qid="07007004.6" from="07007004.1" to="07007004.6"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007005"/>
    <verse num="5">So he brought the people down to the water. And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Gideon, <q class="begin-double" qid="07007005.1" from="07007005.1" to="07007005.2"/>Every one who laps the water with his tongue, as a dog laps, you shall set by himself. Likewise, every one who kneels down to drink.<q class="end-double" qid="07007005.2" from="07007005.1" to="07007005.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007006"/>
    <verse num="6">And the number of those who lapped, putting their hands to their mouths, was 300 men, but all the rest of the people knelt down to drink water.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007007"/>
    <verse num="7">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Gideon, <crossref let="f" cid="c07007007.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07007007.1" from="07007007.1" to="07007007.2"/>With the 300 men who lapped I will save you and give the Midianites into your hand, and let all the others go every man to his home.<q class="end-double" qid="07007007.2" from="07007007.1" to="07007007.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007008"/>
    <verse num="8">So the people took provisions in their hands, and their trumpets. And he sent all the rest of Israel every man to his tent, but retained the 300 men. And the camp of Midian was below him <crossref let="g" cid="c07007008.1"/>in the valley.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007009"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9">That same <crossref let="h" cid="c07007009.1"/>night the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07007009.1" from="07007009.1" to="07007011.1"/>Arise, go down against the camp, <crossref let="i" cid="c07007009.2"/>for I have given it into your hand.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007010"/>
    <verse num="10">But if you are afraid to go down, go down to the camp with Purah your servant.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="j" cid="c07007011.1"/>And you shall hear what they say, and afterward your hands shall be strengthened to go down against the camp.<q class="end-double" qid="07007011.1" from="07007009.1" to="07007011.1"/> <crossref let="k" cid="c07007011.2"/>Then he went down with Purah his servant to the outposts of the armed men who were in the camp.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007012"/>
    <verse num="12">And the Midianites and the Amalekites and <crossref let="l" cid="c07007012.1"/>all the people of the East lay along the valley like locusts in abundance, and their camels were without number, <crossref let="m" cid="c07007012.2"/>as the sand that is on the seashore in abundance.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007013"/>
    <verse num="13">When Gideon came, behold, a man was telling a dream to his comrade. And he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07007013.1" from="07007013.1" to="07007013.2"/>Behold, I dreamed a dream, and behold, a cake of barley bread tumbled into the camp of Midian and came to the tent and struck it so that it fell and turned it upside down, so that the tent lay flat.<q class="end-double" qid="07007013.2" from="07007013.1" to="07007013.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007014"/>
    <verse num="14">And his comrade answered, <q class="begin-double" qid="07007014.1" from="07007014.1" to="07007014.2"/>This is no other than the sword of Gideon the son of Joash, a man of Israel; God has given into his hand Midian and all the camp.<q class="end-double" qid="07007014.2" from="07007014.1" to="07007014.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">As soon as Gideon heard the telling of the dream and its interpretation, he worshiped. And he returned to the camp of Israel and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07007015.1" from="07007015.1" to="07007015.2"/>Arise, for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has given the host of Midian into your hand.<q class="end-double" qid="07007015.2" from="07007015.1" to="07007015.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007016"/>
    <verse num="16">And he divided the 300 men into three companies and put trumpets into the hands of all of them and empty jars, with <crossref let="n" cid="c07007016.1"/>torches inside the jars.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007017"/>
    <verse num="17">And he said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07007017.1" from="07007017.1" to="07007018.3"/>Look at me, and do likewise. When I come to the outskirts of the camp, do as I do.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007018"/>
    <verse num="18">When I blow the trumpet, I and all who are with me, then blow the trumpets also on every side of all the camp and shout, <crossref let="o" cid="c07007018.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="07007018.1" from="07007018.1" to="07007018.2"/>For the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and for Gideon.<q class="end-single" qid="07007018.2" from="07007018.1" to="07007018.2"/><q class="end-double" qid="07007018.3" from="07007017.1" to="07007018.3"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007019"/>
    <heading>Gideon Defeats Midian</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19">So Gideon and the hundred men who were with him came to the outskirts of the camp at the beginning of the middle watch, when they had just set the watch. And they blew the trumpets and smashed the jars that were in their hands.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007020"/>
    <verse num="20">Then the three companies blew the trumpets and broke the jars. They held in their left hands the torches, and in their right hands the trumpets to blow. <crossref let="o" cid="c07007020.1"/>And they cried out, <q class="begin-double" qid="07007020.1" from="07007020.1" to="07007020.2"/>A sword for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and for Gideon!<q class="end-double" qid="07007020.2" from="07007020.1" to="07007020.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007021"/>
    <verse num="21">Every man stood in his place around the camp, <crossref let="p" cid="c07007021.1"/>and all the army ran. They cried out and fled.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007022"/>
    <verse num="22"><crossref let="q" cid="c07007022.1"/>When they blew the 300 trumpets, <crossref let="r" cid="c07007022.2"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> set <crossref let="s" cid="c07007022.3"/>every man&apos;s sword against his comrade and against all the army. And the army fled as far as Beth-shittah toward Zererah,<note nid="n07007022.1"/> as far as the border of Abel-meholah, by Tabbath.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007023"/>
    <verse num="23">And the men of Israel were called out from Naphtali and from Asher and from all Manasseh, and they pursued after Midian.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007024"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24"><crossref let="t" cid="c07007024.1"/>Gideon sent messengers throughout <crossref let="u" cid="c07007024.2"/>all the hill country of Ephraim, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="07007024.1" from="07007024.1" to="07007024.2"/>Come down against the Midianites and capture the waters against them, as far as <crossref let="v" cid="c07007024.3"/>Beth-barah, and also the Jordan.<q class="end-double" qid="07007024.2" from="07007024.1" to="07007024.2"/> So all the men of Ephraim were called out, and they captured the waters as far as Beth-barah, and also the Jordan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07007025"/>
    <verse num="25">And they captured <crossref let="w" cid="c07007025.1"/>the two princes of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb. They killed Oreb <crossref let="x" cid="c07007025.2"/>at the rock of Oreb, and Zeeb they killed at the winepress of Zeeb. Then they pursued Midian, and they brought the heads of Oreb and Zeeb to Gideon <crossref let="y" cid="c07007025.3"/>across the Jordan.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008001"/>
  <chapter num="8">
    <heading>Gideon Defeats Zebah and Zalmunna</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="z" cid="c07008001.1"/>Then the men of Ephraim said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008001.1" from="07008001.1" to="07008001.2"/>What is this that you have done to us, not to call us when you went to fight against Midian?<q class="end-double" qid="07008001.2" from="07008001.1" to="07008001.2"/> And they accused him fiercely.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008002"/>
    <verse num="2">And he said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008002.1" from="07008002.1" to="07008003.1"/>What have I done now in comparison with you? Is not <crossref let="a" cid="c07008002.1"/>the gleaning of the grapes of Ephraim better than the grape harvest of Abiezer?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008003"/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="b" cid="c07008003.1"/>God has given into your hands the princes of Midian, Oreb and Zeeb. What have I been able to do in comparison with you?<q class="end-double" qid="07008003.1" from="07008002.1" to="07008003.1"/> <crossref let="c" cid="c07008003.2"/>Then their anger<note nid="n07008003.1"/> against him subsided when he said this.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">And Gideon came to the Jordan and crossed over, he and <crossref let="d" cid="c07008004.1"/>the 300 men who were with him, exhausted yet pursuing.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008005"/>
    <verse num="5">So he said to the men of <crossref let="e" cid="c07008005.1"/>Succoth, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008005.1" from="07008005.1" to="07008005.2"/>Please give loaves of bread to the people who follow me, for they are exhausted, and I am pursuing after Zebah and Zalmunna, the kings of Midian.<q class="end-double" qid="07008005.2" from="07008005.1" to="07008005.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008006"/>
    <verse num="6">And the officials of Succoth said, <crossref let="f" cid="c07008006.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07008006.1" from="07008006.1" to="07008006.2"/>Are the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna already in your hand, <crossref let="g" cid="c07008006.2"/>that we should give bread to your army?<q class="end-double" qid="07008006.2" from="07008006.1" to="07008006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008007"/>
    <verse num="7">So Gideon said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008007.1" from="07008007.1" to="07008007.2"/>Well then, when the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has given Zebah and Zalmunna into my hand, <crossref let="h" cid="c07008007.1"/>I will flail your flesh with the thorns of the wilderness and with briers.<q class="end-double" qid="07008007.2" from="07008007.1" to="07008007.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008008"/>
    <verse num="8">And from there he went up to <crossref let="i" cid="c07008008.1"/>Penuel, and spoke to them in the same way, and the men of Penuel answered him as the men of Succoth had answered.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008009"/>
    <verse num="9">And he said to the men of Penuel, <crossref let="j" cid="c07008009.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07008009.1" from="07008009.1" to="07008009.2"/>When I come again in peace, <crossref let="k" cid="c07008009.2"/>I will break down this tower.<q class="end-double" qid="07008009.2" from="07008009.1" to="07008009.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">Now Zebah and Zalmunna were in Karkor with their army, about 15,000 men, all who were left of all the army of <crossref let="l" cid="c07008010.1"/>the people of the East, for there had fallen 120,000 men <crossref let="m" cid="c07008010.2"/>who drew the sword.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008011"/>
    <verse num="11">And Gideon went up by the way of the tent dwellers east of <crossref let="n" cid="c07008011.1"/>Nobah and Jogbehah and attacked the army, for the army felt <crossref let="o" cid="c07008011.2"/>secure.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008012"/>
    <verse num="12">And Zebah and Zalmunna fled, and he pursued them <crossref let="p" cid="c07008012.1"/>and captured the two kings of Midian, Zebah and Zalmunna, and he threw all the army into a panic.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">Then Gideon the son of Joash returned from the battle by the ascent of Heres.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008014"/>
    <verse num="14">And he captured a young man of Succoth and questioned him. And he wrote down for him the officials and elders of Succoth, seventy-seven men.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008015"/>
    <verse num="15">And he came to the men of Succoth and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008015.1" from="07008015.1" to="07008015.4"/>Behold Zebah and Zalmunna, about whom you taunted me, saying, <crossref let="q" cid="c07008015.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="07008015.2" from="07008015.2" to="07008015.3"/>Are the hands of Zebah and Zalmunna already in your hand, that we should give bread to your men who are exhausted?<q class="end-single" qid="07008015.3" from="07008015.2" to="07008015.3"/><q class="end-double" qid="07008015.4" from="07008015.1" to="07008015.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008016"/>
    <verse num="16">And he took the elders of the city, and he took thorns of the wilderness and briers and with them taught the men of Succoth a lesson.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="r" cid="c07008017.1"/>And he broke down the tower of Penuel and killed the men of the city.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18">Then he said to Zebah and Zalmunna, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008018.1" from="07008018.1" to="07008018.2"/>Where are the men whom you killed at <crossref let="s" cid="c07008018.1"/>Tabor?<q class="end-double" qid="07008018.2" from="07008018.1" to="07008018.2"/> They answered, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008018.3" from="07008018.3" to="07008018.4"/>As you are, so were they. Every one of them resembled the son of a king.<q class="end-double" qid="07008018.4" from="07008018.3" to="07008018.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008019"/>
    <verse num="19">And he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008019.1" from="07008019.1" to="07008019.2"/>They were my brothers, the sons of my mother. <crossref let="t" cid="c07008019.1"/>As the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> lives, if you had saved them alive, I would not kill you.<q class="end-double" qid="07008019.2" from="07008019.1" to="07008019.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008020"/>
    <verse num="20">So he said to Jether his firstborn, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008020.1" from="07008020.1" to="07008020.2"/>Rise and kill them!<q class="end-double" qid="07008020.2" from="07008020.1" to="07008020.2"/> But the young man did not draw his sword, for he was afraid, because he was still a young man.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008021"/>
    <verse num="21">Then Zebah and Zalmunna said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008021.1" from="07008021.1" to="07008021.2"/>Rise yourself and fall upon us, for as the man is, so is his strength.<q class="end-double" qid="07008021.2" from="07008021.1" to="07008021.2"/> And Gideon arose and <crossref let="u" cid="c07008021.1"/>killed Zebah and Zalmunna, and he took <crossref let="v" cid="c07008021.2"/>the crescent ornaments that were on the necks of their camels.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008022"/>
    <heading>Gideon&apos;s Ephod</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">Then the men of Israel said to Gideon, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008022.1" from="07008022.1" to="07008022.2"/>Rule over us, you and your son and your grandson also, for you have saved us from the hand of Midian.<q class="end-double" qid="07008022.2" from="07008022.1" to="07008022.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008023"/>
    <verse num="23">Gideon said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008023.1" from="07008023.1" to="07008023.2"/>I will not rule over you, and my son will not rule over you; <crossref let="w" cid="c07008023.1"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will rule over you.<q class="end-double" qid="07008023.2" from="07008023.1" to="07008023.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008024"/>
    <verse num="24">And Gideon said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008024.1" from="07008024.1" to="07008024.2"/>Let me make a request of you: every one of you give me the earrings from his spoil.<q class="end-double" qid="07008024.2" from="07008024.1" to="07008024.2"/> (For they had golden earrings, <crossref let="x" cid="c07008024.1"/>because they were Ishmaelites.)</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008025"/>
    <verse num="25">And they answered, <q class="begin-double" qid="07008025.1" from="07008025.1" to="07008025.2"/>We will willingly give them.<q class="end-double" qid="07008025.2" from="07008025.1" to="07008025.2"/> And they spread a cloak, and every man threw in it the earrings of his spoil.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008026"/>
    <verse num="26">And the weight of the golden earrings that he requested was 1,700 shekels<note nid="n07008026.1"/> of gold, besides <crossref let="y" cid="c07008026.1"/>the crescent ornaments and <crossref let="z" cid="c07008026.2"/>the pendants and the purple garments worn by the kings of Midian, and besides the collars that were around the necks of their camels.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008027"/>
    <verse num="27">And Gideon <crossref let="a" cid="c07008027.1"/>made an ephod of it and put it in his city, <crossref let="b" cid="c07008027.2"/>in Ophrah. And all Israel <crossref let="c" cid="c07008027.3"/>whored after it there, and it became a <crossref let="d" cid="c07008027.4"/>snare to Gideon and to his family.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008028"/>
    <verse num="28">So Midian was subdued before the people of Israel, and they raised their heads no more. <crossref let="e" cid="c07008028.1"/>And the land had rest for forty years in the days of Gideon.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008029"/>
    <heading>The Death of Gideon</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="f" cid="c07008029.1"/>Jerubbaal the son of Joash went and lived in his own house.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008030"/>
    <verse num="30">Now Gideon had <crossref let="g" cid="c07008030.1"/>seventy sons, his own offspring,<note nid="n07008030.1"/> for he had many wives.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008031"/>
    <verse num="31">And his concubine <crossref let="h" cid="c07008031.1"/>who was in Shechem also bore him a son, and he called his name Abimelech.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008032"/>
    <verse num="32">And Gideon the son of Joash died <crossref let="i" cid="c07008032.1"/>in a good old age and was buried in the tomb of Joash his father, <crossref let="j" cid="c07008032.2"/>at Ophrah of the Abiezrites.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008033"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="33"><crossref let="k" cid="c07008033.1"/>As soon as Gideon died, the people of Israel turned again and <crossref let="l" cid="c07008033.2"/>whored after the Baals and made <crossref let="m" cid="c07008033.3"/>Baal-berith their god.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008034"/>
    <verse num="34">And the people of Israel <crossref let="n" cid="c07008034.1"/>did not remember the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> their God, who had delivered them from the hand of all their enemies on every side,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07008035"/>
    <verse num="35"><crossref let="o" cid="c07008035.1"/>and they did not show steadfast love to the family of Jerubbaal (that is, Gideon) in return for all the good that he had done to Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009001"/>
  <chapter num="9">
    <heading>Abimelech&apos;s Conspiracy</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Now Abimelech the son of Jerubbaal went to Shechem to <crossref let="p" cid="c07009001.1"/>his mother&apos;s relatives and said to them and to the whole clan of his mother&apos;s family,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="07009002.1" from="07009002.1" to="07009002.4"/>Say in the ears of all the leaders of Shechem, <q class="begin-single" qid="07009002.2" from="07009002.2" to="07009002.3"/>Which is better for you, that all <crossref let="q" cid="c07009002.1"/>seventy of the sons of Jerubbaal rule over you, or that one rule over you?<q class="end-single" qid="07009002.3" from="07009002.2" to="07009002.3"/> Remember also that <crossref let="p" cid="c07009002.2"/>I am <crossref let="r" cid="c07009002.3"/>your bone and your flesh.<q class="end-double" qid="07009002.4" from="07009002.1" to="07009002.4"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009003"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3">And his mother&apos;s relatives spoke all these words on his behalf in the ears of all the leaders of Shechem, and their hearts inclined to follow Abimelech, for they said, <crossref let="s" cid="c07009003.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07009003.1" from="07009003.1" to="07009003.2"/>He is our brother.<q class="end-double" qid="07009003.2" from="07009003.1" to="07009003.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009004"/>
    <verse num="4">And they gave him seventy pieces of silver out of the house of <crossref let="t" cid="c07009004.1"/>Baal-berith with which Abimelech hired <crossref let="u" cid="c07009004.2"/>worthless and reckless fellows, who followed him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009005"/>
    <verse num="5">And he went to his father&apos;s house at <crossref let="v" cid="c07009005.1"/>Ophrah <crossref let="w" cid="c07009005.2"/>and killed his brothers the sons of Jerubbaal, seventy men, on one stone. But Jotham the youngest son of Jerubbaal was left, for he hid himself.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009006"/>
    <verse num="6">And all the leaders of Shechem came together, and all <crossref let="x" cid="c07009006.1"/>Beth-millo, and they went and made Abimelech king, by the oak of the pillar at Shechem.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">When it was told to Jotham, he went and stood on top of <crossref let="y" cid="c07009007.1"/>Mount Gerizim and cried aloud and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07009007.1" from="07009007.1" to="07009020.1"/>Listen to me, you leaders of Shechem, that God may listen to you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="z" cid="c07009008.1"/>The trees once went out to anoint a king over them, and they said to the olive tree, <crossref let="a" cid="c07009008.2"/><q class="begin-single" qid="07009008.1" from="07009008.1" to="07009008.2"/>Reign over us.<q class="end-single" qid="07009008.2" from="07009008.1" to="07009008.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009009"/>
    <verse num="9">But the olive tree said to them, <q class="begin-single" qid="07009009.1" from="07009009.1" to="07009009.2"/>Shall I leave my abundance, by which gods and men are honored, and go hold sway over the trees?<q class="end-single" qid="07009009.2" from="07009009.1" to="07009009.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009010"/>
    <verse num="10">And the trees said to the fig tree, <q class="begin-single" qid="07009010.1" from="07009010.1" to="07009010.2"/>You come and reign over us.<q class="end-single" qid="07009010.2" from="07009010.1" to="07009010.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009011"/>
    <verse num="11">But the fig tree said to them, <q class="begin-single" qid="07009011.1" from="07009011.1" to="07009011.2"/>Shall I leave my sweetness and my good fruit and go hold sway over the trees?<q class="end-single" qid="07009011.2" from="07009011.1" to="07009011.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009012"/>
    <verse num="12">And the trees said to the vine, <q class="begin-single" qid="07009012.1" from="07009012.1" to="07009012.2"/>You come and reign over us.<q class="end-single" qid="07009012.2" from="07009012.1" to="07009012.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009013"/>
    <verse num="13">But the vine said to them, <q class="begin-single" qid="07009013.1" from="07009013.1" to="07009013.2"/>Shall I leave my wine that <crossref let="b" cid="c07009013.1"/>cheers God and men and go hold sway over the trees?<q class="end-single" qid="07009013.2" from="07009013.1" to="07009013.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009014"/>
    <verse num="14">Then all the trees said to the bramble, <q class="begin-single" qid="07009014.1" from="07009014.1" to="07009014.2"/>You come and reign over us.<q class="end-single" qid="07009014.2" from="07009014.1" to="07009014.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009015"/>
    <verse num="15">And the bramble said to the trees, <q class="begin-single" qid="07009015.1" from="07009015.1" to="07009015.2"/>If in good faith you are anointing me king over you, then come and <crossref let="c" cid="c07009015.1"/>take refuge in my shade, but if not, <crossref let="d" cid="c07009015.2"/>let fire come out of the bramble and devour <crossref let="e" cid="c07009015.3"/>the cedars of Lebanon.<q class="end-single" qid="07009015.2" from="07009015.1" to="07009015.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16"><q class="continue-double" qid="07009016.1" from="07009007.1" to="07009020.1"/>Now therefore, if you acted in good faith and integrity when you made Abimelech king, and if you have dealt well with <crossref let="f" cid="c07009016.1"/>Jerubbaal and his house and have done to him <crossref let="g" cid="c07009016.2"/>as his deeds deserved&emdash;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009017"/>
    <verse num="17">for my father fought for you and risked his life and delivered you from the hand of Midian,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009018"/>
    <verse num="18">and you have risen up against my father&apos;s house this day <crossref let="h" cid="c07009018.1"/>and have killed his sons, seventy men on one stone, and have made <crossref let="i" cid="c07009018.2"/>Abimelech, the son of his female servant, king over the leaders of Shechem, <crossref let="j" cid="c07009018.3"/>because he is your relative&emdash;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009019"/>
    <verse num="19">if you then have acted in good faith and integrity with Jerubbaal and with his house this day, then <crossref let="k" cid="c07009019.1"/>rejoice in Abimelech, and let him also rejoice in you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009020"/>
    <verse num="20">But if not, <crossref let="l" cid="c07009020.1"/>let fire come out from Abimelech and devour the leaders of Shechem and Beth-millo; and let fire come out from the leaders of Shechem and from Beth-millo and devour Abimelech.<q class="end-double" qid="07009020.1" from="07009007.1" to="07009020.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009021"/>
    <verse num="21">And Jotham ran away and fled and went to <crossref let="m" cid="c07009021.1"/>Beer and lived there, because of Abimelech his brother.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009022"/>
    <heading>The Downfall of Abimelech</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">Abimelech ruled over Israel three years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009023"/>
    <verse num="23"><crossref let="n" cid="c07009023.1"/>And God sent an evil spirit between Abimelech and the leaders of Shechem, and the leaders of Shechem <crossref let="o" cid="c07009023.2"/>dealt treacherously with Abimelech,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009024"/>
    <verse num="24"><crossref let="p" cid="c07009024.1"/>that the violence done to the seventy sons of Jerubbaal might come, and their blood be laid on Abimelech their brother, who killed them, and on the men of Shechem, who strengthened his hands to kill his brothers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009025"/>
    <verse num="25">And the leaders of Shechem put men in ambush against him on the mountaintops, and they robbed all who passed by them along that way. And it was told to Abimelech.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009026"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="26">And Gaal the son of Ebed moved into Shechem with his relatives, and the leaders of Shechem put confidence in him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009027"/>
    <verse num="27">And they went out into the field and gathered the grapes from their vineyards and trod them and held a festival; and they went into <crossref let="q" cid="c07009027.1"/>the house of their god and ate and drank and reviled Abimelech.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009028"/>
    <verse num="28">And Gaal the son of Ebed said, <crossref let="r" cid="c07009028.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07009028.1" from="07009028.1" to="07009029.3"/>Who is Abimelech, and who are we of Shechem, that we should serve him? Is he not the son of Jerubbaal, and is not Zebul his officer? Serve the men of <crossref let="s" cid="c07009028.2"/>Hamor the father of Shechem; but why should we serve him?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009029"/>
    <verse num="29">Would that this people were under my hand! Then I would remove Abimelech. I would say<note nid="n07009029.1"/> to Abimelech, <q class="begin-single" qid="07009029.1" from="07009029.1" to="07009029.2"/>Increase your army, and come out.<q class="end-single" qid="07009029.2" from="07009029.1" to="07009029.2"/><q class="end-double" qid="07009029.3" from="07009028.1" to="07009029.3"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009030"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="30">When Zebul the ruler of the city heard the words of Gaal the son of Ebed, his anger was kindled.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009031"/>
    <verse num="31">And he sent messengers to Abimelech secretly,<note nid="n07009031.1"/> saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="07009031.1" from="07009031.1" to="07009033.1"/>Behold, Gaal the son of Ebed and his relatives have come to Shechem, and they are stirring up<note nid="n07009031.2"/> the city against you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009032"/>
    <verse num="32">Now therefore, go by night, you and the people who are with you, and set an ambush in the field.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009033"/>
    <verse num="33">Then in the morning, as soon as the sun is up, rise early and rush upon the city. And when he and the people who are with him come out against you, you may do to them <crossref let="t" cid="c07009033.1"/>as your hand finds to do.<q class="end-double" qid="07009033.1" from="07009031.1" to="07009033.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009034"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="34">So Abimelech and all the men who were with him rose up by night and set an ambush against Shechem in four companies.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009035"/>
    <verse num="35">And Gaal the son of Ebed went out and stood in the entrance of the gate of the city, and Abimelech and the people who were with him rose from the ambush.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009036"/>
    <verse num="36">And when Gaal saw the people, he said to Zebul, <q class="begin-double" qid="07009036.1" from="07009036.1" to="07009036.2"/>Look, people are coming down from <crossref let="u" cid="c07009036.1"/>the mountaintops!<q class="end-double" qid="07009036.2" from="07009036.1" to="07009036.2"/> And Zebul said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07009036.3" from="07009036.3" to="07009036.4"/>You mistake<note nid="n07009036.1"/> the shadow of the mountains for men.<q class="end-double" qid="07009036.4" from="07009036.3" to="07009036.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009037"/>
    <verse num="37">Gaal spoke again and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07009037.1" from="07009037.1" to="07009037.2"/>Look, people are coming down from the center of the land, and one company is coming from the direction of the Diviners&apos; Oak.<q class="end-double" qid="07009037.2" from="07009037.1" to="07009037.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009038"/>
    <verse num="38">Then Zebul said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07009038.1" from="07009038.1" to="07009038.4"/>Where is your mouth now, you who said, <crossref let="v" cid="c07009038.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="07009038.2" from="07009038.2" to="07009038.3"/>Who is Abimelech, that we should serve him?<q class="end-single" qid="07009038.3" from="07009038.2" to="07009038.3"/> Are not these the people whom you despised? Go out now and fight with them.<q class="end-double" qid="07009038.4" from="07009038.1" to="07009038.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009039"/>
    <verse num="39">And Gaal went out at the head of the leaders of Shechem and fought with Abimelech.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009040"/>
    <verse num="40">And Abimelech chased him, and he fled before him. And many fell wounded, up to the entrance of the gate.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009041"/>
    <verse num="41">And Abimelech lived at Arumah, and Zebul drove out Gaal and his relatives, so that they could not dwell at Shechem.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009042"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="42">On the following day, the people went out into the field, and Abimelech was told.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009043"/>
    <verse num="43">He took his people and divided them into three companies and set an ambush in the fields. And he looked and saw the people coming out of the city. So he rose against them and killed them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009044"/>
    <verse num="44">Abimelech and the company that was with him <crossref let="w" cid="c07009044.1"/>rushed forward and stood at the entrance of the gate of the city, while the two companies rushed upon all who were in the field and killed them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009045"/>
    <verse num="45">And Abimelech fought against the city all that day. He captured the city and killed the people who were in it, and <crossref let="x" cid="c07009045.1"/>he razed the city and <crossref let="y" cid="c07009045.2"/>sowed it with salt.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009046"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="46">When all the leaders of the Tower of Shechem heard of it, they entered <crossref let="z" cid="c07009046.1"/>the stronghold of the house of <crossref let="a" cid="c07009046.2"/>El-berith.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009047"/>
    <verse num="47">Abimelech was told that all the leaders of the Tower of Shechem were gathered together.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009048"/>
    <verse num="48">And Abimelech went up to Mount <crossref let="b" cid="c07009048.1"/>Zalmon, he and all the people who were with him. And Abimelech took an axe in his hand and cut down a bundle of brushwood and took it up and laid it on his shoulder. And he said to the men who were with him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07009048.1" from="07009048.1" to="07009048.2"/>What you have seen me do, hurry and do as I have done.<q class="end-double" qid="07009048.2" from="07009048.1" to="07009048.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009049"/>
    <verse num="49">So every one of the people cut down his bundle and following Abimelech put it against <crossref let="c" cid="c07009049.1"/>the stronghold, and they set the stronghold on fire over them, so that all the people of the Tower of Shechem also died, about 1,000 men and women.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009050"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="50">Then Abimelech went to Thebez and encamped against Thebez and captured it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009051"/>
    <verse num="51">But there was a strong tower within the city, and all the men and women and all the leaders of the city fled to it and shut themselves in, and they went up to the roof of the tower.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009052"/>
    <verse num="52">And Abimelech came to the tower and fought against it and drew near to the door of the tower to burn it with fire.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009053"/>
    <verse num="53"><crossref let="d" cid="c07009053.1"/>And a certain woman threw an upper millstone on Abimelech&apos;s head and crushed his skull.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009054"/>
    <verse num="54"><crossref let="e" cid="c07009054.1"/>Then he called quickly to the young man his armor-bearer and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07009054.1" from="07009054.1" to="07009054.4"/>Draw your sword and kill me, lest they say of me, <q class="begin-single" qid="07009054.2" from="07009054.2" to="07009054.3"/>A woman killed him.<q class="end-single" qid="07009054.3" from="07009054.2" to="07009054.3"/><q class="end-double" qid="07009054.4" from="07009054.1" to="07009054.4"/> And his young man thrust him through, and he died.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009055"/>
    <verse num="55">And when the men of Israel saw that Abimelech was dead, everyone departed to his home.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009056"/>
    <verse num="56"><crossref let="f" cid="c07009056.1"/>Thus God returned the evil of Abimelech, which he committed against his father in killing his seventy brothers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07009057"/>
    <verse num="57">And God also made all the evil of the men of Shechem return on their heads, and upon them came <crossref let="g" cid="c07009057.1"/>the curse of Jotham the son of Jerubbaal.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010001"/>
  <chapter num="10">
    <heading>Tola and Jair</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">After Abimelech there arose to <crossref let="h" cid="c07010001.1"/>save Israel Tola the son of Puah, son of Dodo, a man of Issachar, and he lived at Shamir in <crossref let="i" cid="c07010001.2"/>the hill country of Ephraim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010002"/>
    <verse num="2">And he judged Israel twenty-three years. Then he died and was buried at Shamir.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010003"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3">After him arose Jair the Gileadite, who judged Israel twenty-two years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010004"/>
    <verse num="4">And he had thirty sons who <crossref let="j" cid="c07010004.1"/>rode on thirty donkeys, and they had thirty cities, called Havvoth-jair to this day, <crossref let="k" cid="c07010004.2"/>which are in the land of Gilead.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010005"/>
    <verse num="5">And Jair died and was buried in Kamon.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010006"/>
    <heading>Further Disobedience and Oppression</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="l" cid="c07010006.1"/>The people of Israel again did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="m" cid="c07010006.2"/>and served the Baals and the Ashtaroth, the gods of Syria, <crossref let="n" cid="c07010006.3"/>the gods of Sidon, the gods of Moab, the gods of the Ammonites, and the gods of the Philistines. And they <crossref let="o" cid="c07010006.4"/>forsook the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and did not serve him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010007"/>
    <verse num="7">So the anger of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was kindled against Israel, and <crossref let="p" cid="c07010007.1"/>he sold them into the hand of the Philistines and into the hand of the Ammonites,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010008"/>
    <verse num="8">and they crushed and oppressed the people of Israel that year. For eighteen years they oppressed all the people of Israel who were beyond the Jordan in the land of the Amorites, which is in Gilead.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010009"/>
    <verse num="9">And the Ammonites crossed the Jordan to fight also against Judah and against Benjamin and against the house of Ephraim, so that Israel was severely distressed.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">And the people of Israel <crossref let="q" cid="c07010010.1"/>cried out to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="07010010.1" from="07010010.1" to="07010010.2"/>We have sinned against you, because <crossref let="r" cid="c07010010.2"/>we have forsaken our God and have served the Baals.<q class="end-double" qid="07010010.2" from="07010010.1" to="07010010.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010011"/>
    <verse num="11">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to the people of Israel, <q class="begin-double" qid="07010011.1" from="07010011.1" to="07010014.1"/>Did I not save you <crossref let="s" cid="c07010011.1"/>from the Egyptians and <crossref let="t" cid="c07010011.2"/>from the Amorites, <crossref let="u" cid="c07010011.3"/>from the Ammonites and <crossref let="v" cid="c07010011.4"/>from the Philistines?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010012"/>
    <verse num="12">The Sidonians also, and <crossref let="w" cid="c07010012.1"/>the Amalekites and the Maonites oppressed you, and you cried out to me, and I <crossref let="x" cid="c07010012.2"/>saved you out of their hand.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010013"/>
    <verse num="13">Yet you have <crossref let="y" cid="c07010013.1"/>forsaken me and served other gods; therefore I will save you no more.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010014"/>
    <verse num="14">Go and cry out <crossref let="z" cid="c07010014.1"/>to the gods whom you have chosen; let them save you in the time of your distress.<q class="end-double" qid="07010014.1" from="07010011.1" to="07010014.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010015"/>
    <verse num="15">And the people of Israel said to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <q class="begin-double" qid="07010015.1" from="07010015.1" to="07010015.2"/>We have sinned; do to us whatever seems good to you. Only please deliver us this day.<q class="end-double" qid="07010015.2" from="07010015.1" to="07010015.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010016"/>
    <verse num="16">So they put away the foreign gods from among them and served the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and <crossref let="a" cid="c07010016.1"/>he became impatient over the misery of Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010017"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17">Then the Ammonites were called to arms, and they encamped in Gilead. And the people of Israel came together, and they encamped at <crossref let="b" cid="c07010017.1"/>Mizpah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07010018"/>
    <verse num="18">And the people, the leaders of Gilead, said one to another, <q class="begin-double" qid="07010018.1" from="07010018.1" to="07010018.2"/>Who is the man who will begin to fight against the Ammonites? <crossref let="c" cid="c07010018.1"/>He shall be head over all the inhabitants of Gilead.<q class="end-double" qid="07010018.2" from="07010018.1" to="07010018.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011001"/>
  <chapter num="11">
    <heading>Jephthah Delivers Israel</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Now <crossref let="d" cid="c07011001.1"/>Jephthah the Gileadite was <crossref let="e" cid="c07011001.2"/>a mighty warrior, but he was the son of a prostitute. Gilead was the father of Jephthah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011002"/>
    <verse num="2">And Gilead&apos;s wife also bore him sons. And when his wife&apos;s sons grew up, they drove Jephthah out and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07011002.1" from="07011002.1" to="07011002.2"/>You shall not have an inheritance in our father&apos;s house, for you are the son of another woman.<q class="end-double" qid="07011002.2" from="07011002.1" to="07011002.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011003"/>
    <verse num="3">Then Jephthah fled from his brothers and lived in the land of <crossref let="f" cid="c07011003.1"/>Tob, and <crossref let="g" cid="c07011003.2"/>worthless fellows collected around Jephthah and went out with him.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">After a time the Ammonites made war against Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011005"/>
    <verse num="5">And when the Ammonites made war against Israel, the elders of Gilead went to bring Jephthah from the land of <crossref let="f" cid="c07011005.1"/>Tob.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011006"/>
    <verse num="6">And they said to Jephthah, <q class="begin-double" qid="07011006.1" from="07011006.1" to="07011006.2"/>Come and be our leader, that we may fight against the Ammonites.<q class="end-double" qid="07011006.2" from="07011006.1" to="07011006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011007"/>
    <verse num="7">But Jephthah said to the elders of Gilead, <q class="begin-double" qid="07011007.1" from="07011007.1" to="07011007.2"/>Did you not hate me and drive me out of my father&apos;s house? Why have you come to me now when you are in distress?<q class="end-double" qid="07011007.2" from="07011007.1" to="07011007.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011008"/>
    <verse num="8">And the elders of Gilead said to Jephthah, <q class="begin-double" qid="07011008.1" from="07011008.1" to="07011008.2"/>That is why we have turned to you now, that you may go with us and fight against the Ammonites and <crossref let="h" cid="c07011008.1"/>be our head over all the inhabitants of Gilead.<q class="end-double" qid="07011008.2" from="07011008.1" to="07011008.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011009"/>
    <verse num="9">Jephthah said to the elders of Gilead, <q class="begin-double" qid="07011009.1" from="07011009.1" to="07011009.2"/>If you bring me home again to fight against the Ammonites, and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gives them over to me, I will be your head.<q class="end-double" qid="07011009.2" from="07011009.1" to="07011009.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011010"/>
    <verse num="10">And the elders of Gilead said to Jephthah, <crossref let="i" cid="c07011010.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07011010.1" from="07011010.1" to="07011010.2"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will be witness between us, if we do not do as you say.<q class="end-double" qid="07011010.2" from="07011010.1" to="07011010.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011011"/>
    <verse num="11">So Jephthah went with the elders of Gilead, and the people <crossref let="j" cid="c07011011.1"/>made him head and leader over them. And Jephthah spoke all his words <crossref let="k" cid="c07011011.2"/>before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> at <crossref let="l" cid="c07011011.3"/>Mizpah.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">Then Jephthah sent messengers to the king of the Ammonites and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07011012.1" from="07011012.1" to="07011012.2"/>What do you have against me, that you have come to me to fight against my land?<q class="end-double" qid="07011012.2" from="07011012.1" to="07011012.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011013"/>
    <verse num="13">And the king of the Ammonites answered the messengers of Jephthah, <crossref let="m" cid="c07011013.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07011013.1" from="07011013.1" to="07011013.2"/>Because Israel on coming up from Egypt took away my land, from the <crossref let="n" cid="c07011013.2"/>Arnon to the <crossref let="o" cid="c07011013.3"/>Jabbok and to the Jordan; now therefore restore it peaceably.<q class="end-double" qid="07011013.2" from="07011013.1" to="07011013.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011014"/>
    <verse num="14">Jephthah again sent messengers to the king of the Ammonites</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011015"/>
    <verse num="15">and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07011015.1" from="07011015.1" to="07011027.1"/>Thus says Jephthah: <crossref let="p" cid="c07011015.1"/>Israel did not take away the land of Moab or the land of the Ammonites,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011016"/>
    <verse num="16">but when they came up from Egypt, Israel went through the wilderness <crossref let="q" cid="c07011016.1"/>to the Red Sea and <crossref let="r" cid="c07011016.2"/>came to Kadesh.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="s" cid="c07011017.1"/>Israel then sent messengers to the king of Edom, saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="07011017.1" from="07011017.1" to="07011017.2"/>Please let us pass through your land,<q class="end-single" qid="07011017.2" from="07011017.1" to="07011017.2"/> <crossref let="t" cid="c07011017.2"/>but the king of Edom would not listen. And they sent also to the king of Moab, but he would not consent. So Israel <crossref let="u" cid="c07011017.3"/>remained at Kadesh.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18"><q class="continue-double" qid="07011018.1" from="07011015.1" to="07011027.1"/>Then they journeyed through the wilderness and <crossref let="v" cid="c07011018.1"/>went around the land of Edom and the land of Moab and <crossref let="w" cid="c07011018.2"/>arrived on the east side of the land of Moab and <crossref let="x" cid="c07011018.3"/>camped on the other side of the Arnon. But they did not enter the territory of Moab, for the Arnon was the boundary of Moab.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011019"/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="y" cid="c07011019.1"/>Israel then sent messengers to Sihon king of the Amorites, king of Heshbon, and Israel said to him, <q class="begin-single" qid="07011019.1" from="07011019.1" to="07011019.2"/>Please let us pass through your land to our country,<q class="end-single" qid="07011019.2" from="07011019.1" to="07011019.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011020"/>
    <verse num="20">but Sihon did not trust Israel to pass through his territory, so Sihon gathered all his people together and encamped at Jahaz and fought with Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011021"/>
    <verse num="21">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, gave Sihon and all his people into the hand of Israel, and they defeated them. So Israel took possession of all the land of the Amorites, who inhabited that country.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011022"/>
    <verse num="22">And they took possession of all the territory of the Amorites from the Arnon to the Jabbok and from the wilderness to the Jordan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011023"/>
    <verse num="23">So then the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, dispossessed the Amorites from before his people Israel; and are you to take possession of them?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011024"/>
    <verse num="24">Will you not possess what <crossref let="z" cid="c07011024.1"/>Chemosh your god gives you to possess? <crossref let="a" cid="c07011024.2"/>And all that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God has dispossessed before us, we will possess.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011025"/>
    <verse num="25">Now are you any better than <crossref let="b" cid="c07011025.1"/>Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab? Did he ever contend against Israel, or did he ever go to war with them?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011026"/>
    <verse num="26">While Israel lived <crossref let="c" cid="c07011026.1"/>in Heshbon and its villages, and <crossref let="d" cid="c07011026.2"/>in Aroer and its villages, and in all the cities that are on the banks of the Arnon, 300 years, why did you not deliver them within that time?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011027"/>
    <verse num="27">I therefore have not sinned against you, and you do me wrong by making war on me. <crossref let="e" cid="c07011027.1"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the Judge, decide this day between the people of Israel and the people of Ammon.<q class="end-double" qid="07011027.1" from="07011015.1" to="07011027.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011028"/>
    <verse num="28">But the king of the Ammonites did not listen to the words of Jephthah that he sent to him.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011029"/>
    <heading>Jephthah&apos;s Tragic Vow</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="f" cid="c07011029.1"/>Then the Spirit of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was upon Jephthah, and he passed through Gilead and Manasseh and passed on to Mizpah of Gilead, and from Mizpah of Gilead he passed on to the Ammonites.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011030"/>
    <verse num="30">And Jephthah <crossref let="g" cid="c07011030.1"/>made a vow to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07011030.1" from="07011030.1" to="07011031.1"/>If you will give the Ammonites into my hand,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011031"/>
    <verse num="31">then whatever<note nid="n07011031.1"/> comes out from the doors of my house to meet me when I return in peace from the Ammonites <crossref let="h" cid="c07011031.1"/>shall be the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s, and <crossref let="i" cid="c07011031.2"/>I will offer it<note nid="n07011031.2"/> up for a burnt offering.<q class="end-double" qid="07011031.1" from="07011030.1" to="07011031.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011032"/>
    <verse num="32">So Jephthah crossed over to the Ammonites to fight against them, and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave them into his hand.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011033"/>
    <verse num="33">And he struck them from Aroer to the neighborhood of <crossref let="j" cid="c07011033.1"/>Minnith, twenty cities, and as far as Abel-keramim, with a great blow. So the Ammonites were subdued before the people of Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011034"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="34">Then Jephthah came to his home at <crossref let="k" cid="c07011034.1"/>Mizpah. And behold, his daughter came out to meet him <crossref let="l" cid="c07011034.2"/>with tambourines and with dances. She was his only child; besides her he had neither son nor daughter.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011035"/>
    <verse num="35">And as soon as he saw her, he tore his clothes and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07011035.1" from="07011035.1" to="07011035.2"/>Alas, my daughter! You have brought me very low, and you have become the cause of great trouble to me. For I have opened my mouth to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="m" cid="c07011035.1"/>and I cannot take back my vow.<q class="end-double" qid="07011035.2" from="07011035.1" to="07011035.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011036"/>
    <verse num="36">And she said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07011036.1" from="07011036.1" to="07011036.2"/>My father, you have opened your mouth to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>; do to me according to what has gone out of your mouth, now that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has avenged you on your enemies, on the Ammonites.<q class="end-double" qid="07011036.2" from="07011036.1" to="07011036.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011037"/>
    <verse num="37">So she said to her father, <q class="begin-double" qid="07011037.1" from="07011037.1" to="07011037.2"/>Let this thing be done for me: leave me alone two months, that I may go up and down on the mountains and weep for my virginity, I and my companions.<q class="end-double" qid="07011037.2" from="07011037.1" to="07011037.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011038"/>
    <verse num="38">So he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07011038.1" from="07011038.1" to="07011038.2"/>Go.<q class="end-double" qid="07011038.2" from="07011038.1" to="07011038.2"/> Then he sent her away for two months, and she departed, she and her companions, and wept for her virginity on the mountains.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011039"/>
    <verse num="39">And at the end of two months, she returned to her father, <crossref let="n" cid="c07011039.1"/>who did with her according to his vow that he had made. She had never known a man, and it became a custom in Israel</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07011040"/>
    <verse num="40">that the daughters of Israel went year by year to lament the daughter of Jephthah the Gileadite four days in the year.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012001"/>
  <chapter num="12">
    <heading>Jephthah&apos;s Conflict with Ephraim</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="o" cid="c07012001.1"/>The men of Ephraim were called to arms, and they crossed to Zaphon and said to Jephthah, <q class="begin-double" qid="07012001.1" from="07012001.1" to="07012001.2"/>Why did you cross over to fight against the Ammonites and did not call us to go with you? We will burn your house over you with fire.<q class="end-double" qid="07012001.2" from="07012001.1" to="07012001.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012002"/>
    <verse num="2">And Jephthah said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07012002.1" from="07012002.1" to="07012003.1"/>I and my people had a great dispute with the Ammonites, and when I called you, you did not save me from their hand.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012003"/>
    <verse num="3">And when I saw that you would not save me, <crossref let="p" cid="c07012003.1"/>I took my life in my hand and crossed over against the Ammonites, and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave them into my hand. Why then have you come up to me this day to fight against me?<q class="end-double" qid="07012003.1" from="07012002.1" to="07012003.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012004"/>
    <verse num="4">Then Jephthah gathered all the men of Gilead and fought with Ephraim. And the men of Gilead struck Ephraim, because they said, <crossref let="q" cid="c07012004.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07012004.1" from="07012004.1" to="07012004.2"/>You are fugitives of Ephraim, you Gileadites, in the midst of Ephraim and Manasseh.<q class="end-double" qid="07012004.2" from="07012004.1" to="07012004.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012005"/>
    <verse num="5">And the Gileadites captured <crossref let="r" cid="c07012005.1"/>the fords of the Jordan against the Ephraimites. And when any of the fugitives of Ephraim said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07012005.1" from="07012005.1" to="07012005.2"/>Let me go over,<q class="end-double" qid="07012005.2" from="07012005.1" to="07012005.2"/> the men of Gilead said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07012005.3" from="07012005.3" to="07012005.4"/>Are you an Ephraimite?<q class="end-double" qid="07012005.4" from="07012005.3" to="07012005.4"/> When he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07012005.5" from="07012005.5" to="07012005.6"/>No,<q class="end-double" qid="07012005.6" from="07012005.5" to="07012005.6"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012006"/>
    <verse num="6">they said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07012006.1" from="07012006.1" to="07012006.2"/>Then say Shibboleth,<q class="end-double" qid="07012006.2" from="07012006.1" to="07012006.2"/> and he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07012006.3" from="07012006.3" to="07012006.4"/>Sibboleth,<q class="end-double" qid="07012006.4" from="07012006.3" to="07012006.4"/> for he could not pronounce it right. Then they seized him and slaughtered him at <crossref let="r" cid="c07012006.1"/>the fords of the Jordan. At that time 42,000 of the Ephraimites fell.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">Jephthah judged Israel six years. Then Jephthah the Gileadite died and was buried in his city in Gilead.<note nid="n07012007.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012008"/>
    <heading>Ibzan, Elon, and Abdon</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">After him Ibzan of Bethlehem judged Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012009"/>
    <verse num="9">He had thirty sons, and thirty daughters he gave in marriage outside his clan, and thirty daughters he brought in from outside for his sons. And he judged Israel seven years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012010"/>
    <verse num="10">Then Ibzan died and was buried at Bethlehem.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11">After him Elon the Zebulunite judged Israel, and he judged Israel ten years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012012"/>
    <verse num="12">Then Elon the Zebulunite died and was buried at Aijalon in the land of Zebulun.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">After him Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite judged Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012014"/>
    <verse num="14">He had forty <crossref let="s" cid="c07012014.1"/>sons and thirty grandsons, who <crossref let="t" cid="c07012014.2"/>rode on seventy donkeys, and he judged Israel eight years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07012015"/>
    <verse num="15">Then Abdon the son of Hillel the Pirathonite died and was buried at Pirathon in the land of Ephraim, in the hill country of the Amalekites.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013001"/>
  <chapter num="13">
    <heading>The Birth of Samson</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">And the people of Israel again <crossref let="u" cid="c07013001.1"/>did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, so the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave them <crossref let="v" cid="c07013001.2"/>into the hand of the Philistines for forty years.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013002"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="2">There was a certain man of <crossref let="w" cid="c07013002.1"/>Zorah, of the tribe of the Danites, whose name was Manoah. <crossref let="x" cid="c07013002.2"/>And his wife was barren and had no children.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013003"/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="y" cid="c07013003.1"/>And the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> appeared to the woman and said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="07013003.1" from="07013003.1" to="07013005.1"/>Behold, you are barren and have not borne children, but you shall conceive and bear a son.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013004"/>
    <verse num="4">Therefore be careful <crossref let="z" cid="c07013004.1"/>and drink no wine or strong drink, and eat nothing unclean,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013005"/>
    <verse num="5">for behold, you shall conceive and bear a son. <crossref let="a" cid="c07013005.1"/>No razor shall come upon his head, for the child shall be <crossref let="z" cid="c07013005.2"/>a Nazirite to God from the womb, and he shall <crossref let="b" cid="c07013005.3"/>begin to save Israel from the hand of the Philistines.<q class="end-double" qid="07013005.1" from="07013003.1" to="07013005.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013006"/>
    <verse num="6">Then the woman came and told her husband, <crossref let="c" cid="c07013006.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07013006.1" from="07013006.1" to="07013007.3"/>A man of God came to me, and his appearance was like the appearance of the angel of God, very awesome. <crossref let="d" cid="c07013006.2"/>I did not ask him where he was from, and he did not tell me his name,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013007"/>
    <verse num="7">but he said to me, <crossref let="e" cid="c07013007.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="07013007.1" from="07013007.1" to="07013007.2"/>Behold, you shall conceive and bear a son. So then drink no wine or strong drink, and eat nothing unclean, for the child shall be a Nazirite to God from the womb to the day of his death.<q class="end-single" qid="07013007.2" from="07013007.1" to="07013007.2"/><q class="end-double" qid="07013007.3" from="07013006.1" to="07013007.3"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">Then Manoah prayed to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07013008.1" from="07013008.1" to="07013008.2"/>O Lord, please let the man of God whom you sent come again to us and teach us what we are to do with the child who will be born.<q class="end-double" qid="07013008.2" from="07013008.1" to="07013008.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013009"/>
    <verse num="9">And God listened to the voice of Manoah, and the angel of God came again to the woman as she sat in the field. But Manoah her husband was not with her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013010"/>
    <verse num="10">So the woman ran quickly and told her husband, <q class="begin-double" qid="07013010.1" from="07013010.1" to="07013010.2"/>Behold, the man who came to me the other day has appeared to me.<q class="end-double" qid="07013010.2" from="07013010.1" to="07013010.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013011"/>
    <verse num="11">And Manoah arose and went after his wife and came to the man and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07013011.1" from="07013011.1" to="07013011.2"/>Are you the man who spoke to this woman?<q class="end-double" qid="07013011.2" from="07013011.1" to="07013011.2"/> And he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07013011.3" from="07013011.3" to="07013011.4"/>I am.<q class="end-double" qid="07013011.4" from="07013011.3" to="07013011.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013012"/>
    <verse num="12">And Manoah said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07013012.1" from="07013012.1" to="07013012.2"/>Now when your words come true, <crossref let="f" cid="c07013012.1"/>what is to be the child&apos;s manner of life, and what is his mission?<q class="end-double" qid="07013012.2" from="07013012.1" to="07013012.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013013"/>
    <verse num="13">And the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Manoah, <q class="begin-double" qid="07013013.1" from="07013013.1" to="07013014.1"/>Of all that I said to the woman let her be careful.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013014"/>
    <verse num="14">She may not eat of anything that comes from the vine, <crossref let="g" cid="c07013014.1"/>neither let her drink wine or strong drink, or eat any unclean thing. All that I commanded her let her observe.<q class="end-double" qid="07013014.1" from="07013013.1" to="07013014.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">Manoah said to the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <q class="begin-double" qid="07013015.1" from="07013015.1" to="07013015.2"/>Please let us detain you and <crossref let="h" cid="c07013015.1"/>prepare a young goat for you.<q class="end-double" qid="07013015.2" from="07013015.1" to="07013015.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013016"/>
    <verse num="16">And the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Manoah, <q class="begin-double" qid="07013016.1" from="07013016.1" to="07013016.2"/>If you detain me, I will not eat of your food. But if you prepare a burnt offering, then offer it to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="07013016.2" from="07013016.1" to="07013016.2"/> (For Manoah did not know that he was the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.)</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013017"/>
    <verse num="17">And Manoah said to the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="i" cid="c07013017.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07013017.1" from="07013017.1" to="07013017.2"/>What is your name, so that, when your words come true, we may honor you?<q class="end-double" qid="07013017.2" from="07013017.1" to="07013017.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013018"/>
    <verse num="18">And the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to him, <crossref let="j" cid="c07013018.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07013018.1" from="07013018.1" to="07013018.2"/>Why do you ask my name, seeing <crossref let="k" cid="c07013018.2"/>it is wonderful?<q class="end-double" qid="07013018.2" from="07013018.1" to="07013018.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013019"/>
    <verse num="19">So <crossref let="l" cid="c07013019.1"/>Manoah took the young goat with the grain offering, and offered it on the rock to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, to the one who works<note nid="n07013019.1"/> wonders, and Manoah and his wife were watching.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013020"/>
    <verse num="20">And when the flame went up toward heaven from the altar, the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> went up in the flame of the altar. Now Manoah and his wife were watching, <crossref let="m" cid="c07013020.1"/>and they fell on their faces to the ground.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013021"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="21">The angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> appeared no more to Manoah and to his wife. <crossref let="n" cid="c07013021.1"/>Then Manoah knew that he was the angel of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013022"/>
    <verse num="22">And Manoah said to his wife, <crossref let="n" cid="c07013022.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07013022.1" from="07013022.1" to="07013022.2"/>We shall surely die, for we have seen God.<q class="end-double" qid="07013022.2" from="07013022.1" to="07013022.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013023"/>
    <verse num="23">But his wife said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07013023.1" from="07013023.1" to="07013023.2"/>If the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had meant to kill us, he would not have accepted a burnt offering and a grain offering at our hands, or shown us all these things, or now announced to us such things as these.<q class="end-double" qid="07013023.2" from="07013023.1" to="07013023.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013024"/>
    <verse num="24">And the woman bore a son and called his name Samson. <crossref let="o" cid="c07013024.1"/>And the young man grew, and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> blessed him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07013025"/>
    <verse num="25"><crossref let="p" cid="c07013025.1"/>And the Spirit of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> began to stir him in Mahaneh-dan, between <crossref let="q" cid="c07013025.2"/>Zorah and Eshtaol.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014001"/>
  <chapter num="14">
    <heading>Samson&apos;s Marriage</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="r" cid="c07014001.1"/>Samson went down to <crossref let="s" cid="c07014001.2"/>Timnah, and at Timnah he saw one of the daughters of the Philistines.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014002"/>
    <verse num="2">Then he came up and told his father and mother, <q class="begin-double" qid="07014002.1" from="07014002.1" to="07014002.2"/>I saw one of the daughters of the Philistines at Timnah. <crossref let="t" cid="c07014002.1"/>Now get her for me as my wife.<q class="end-double" qid="07014002.2" from="07014002.1" to="07014002.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014003"/>
    <verse num="3">But his father and mother said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07014003.1" from="07014003.1" to="07014003.2"/>Is there not a woman among the daughters <crossref let="u" cid="c07014003.1"/>of your relatives, or among all our people, that you must go to take a wife from the <crossref let="v" cid="c07014003.2"/>uncircumcised Philistines?<q class="end-double" qid="07014003.2" from="07014003.1" to="07014003.2"/> But Samson said to his father, <q class="begin-double" qid="07014003.3" from="07014003.3" to="07014003.4"/>Get her for me, for she is right in my eyes.<q class="end-double" qid="07014003.4" from="07014003.3" to="07014003.4"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">His father and mother did not know that it was <crossref let="w" cid="c07014004.1"/>from the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, for he was seeking an opportunity against the Philistines. <crossref let="x" cid="c07014004.2"/>At that time the Philistines ruled over Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014005"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5">Then Samson went down with his father and mother to Timnah, and they came to the vineyards of Timnah. And behold, a young lion came toward him roaring.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="y" cid="c07014006.1"/>Then the Spirit of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> rushed upon him, and although he had nothing in his hand, he tore the lion in pieces as one tears a young goat. But he did not tell his father or his mother what he had done.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014007"/>
    <verse num="7">Then he went down and talked with the woman, and she was right in Samson&apos;s eyes.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">After some days he returned to take her. And he turned aside to see the carcass of the lion, and behold, there was a swarm of bees in the body of the lion, and honey.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014009"/>
    <verse num="9">He scraped it out into his hands and went on, eating as he went. And he came to his father and mother and gave some to them, and they ate. But he did not tell them that he had scraped the honey from the carcass of the lion.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">His father went down to the woman, and Samson prepared a feast there, for so the young men used to do.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014011"/>
    <verse num="11">As soon as the people saw him, they brought thirty companions to be with him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014012"/>
    <verse num="12">And Samson said to them, <crossref let="z" cid="c07014012.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07014012.1" from="07014012.1" to="07014013.1"/>Let me now put a riddle to you. If you can tell me what it is, within <crossref let="a" cid="c07014012.2"/>the seven days of the feast, and find it out, then I will give you thirty linen garments and thirty <crossref let="b" cid="c07014012.3"/>changes of clothes,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014013"/>
    <verse num="13">but if you cannot tell me what it is, then you shall give me thirty linen garments and thirty changes of clothes.<q class="end-double" qid="07014013.1" from="07014012.1" to="07014013.1"/> And they said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07014013.2" from="07014013.2" to="07014013.3"/>Put your riddle, that we may hear it.<q class="end-double" qid="07014013.3" from="07014013.2" to="07014013.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014014"/>
    <verse num="14">And he said to them,
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
        <begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="07014014.1" from="07014014.1" to="07014014.2"/>Out of the eater came something to eat.<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>Out of the strong came something sweet.<q class="end-double" qid="07014014.2" from="07014014.1" to="07014014.2"/><end-line/>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/>And in three days they could not solve the riddle.
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">On the fourth<note nid="n07014015.1"/> day they said to Samson&apos;s wife, <crossref let="c" cid="c07014015.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07014015.1" from="07014015.1" to="07014015.2"/>Entice your husband to tell us what the riddle is, <crossref let="d" cid="c07014015.2"/>lest we burn you and your father&apos;s house with fire. Have you invited us here to impoverish us?<q class="end-double" qid="07014015.2" from="07014015.1" to="07014015.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014016"/>
    <verse num="16">And Samson&apos;s wife wept over him and said, <crossref let="e" cid="c07014016.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07014016.1" from="07014016.1" to="07014016.2"/>You only hate me; you do not love me. You have put a riddle to my people, and you have not told me what it is.<q class="end-double" qid="07014016.2" from="07014016.1" to="07014016.2"/> And he said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="07014016.3" from="07014016.3" to="07014016.4"/>Behold, I have not told my father nor my mother, and shall I tell you?<q class="end-double" qid="07014016.4" from="07014016.3" to="07014016.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014017"/>
    <verse num="17">She wept before him the seven days that their feast lasted, and on the seventh day he told her, because <crossref let="f" cid="c07014017.1"/>she pressed him hard. Then she told the riddle to her people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014018"/>
    <verse num="18">And the men of the city said to him on the seventh day before the sun went down,
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
        <begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="07014018.1" from="07014018.1" to="07014018.2"/>What is sweeter than honey?<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>What is stronger than a lion?<q class="end-double" qid="07014018.2" from="07014018.1" to="07014018.2"/><end-line/>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/>And he said to them,
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
        <begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="07014018.3" from="07014018.3" to="07014018.4"/>If you had not plowed with my heifer,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>you would not have found out my riddle.<q class="end-double" qid="07014018.4" from="07014018.3" to="07014018.4"/><end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <end-block-indent/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014019"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="g" cid="c07014019.1"/>And the Spirit of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> rushed upon him, and he went down to <crossref let="h" cid="c07014019.2"/>Ashkelon and struck down thirty men of the town and took their spoil and gave the garments to those who had told the riddle. In hot anger he went back to his father&apos;s house.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07014020"/>
    <verse num="20">And Samson&apos;s wife was given to <crossref let="i" cid="c07014020.1"/>his companion, <crossref let="j" cid="c07014020.2"/>who had been his best man.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015001"/>
  <chapter num="15">
    <heading>Samson Defeats the Philistines</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">After some days, at the time of wheat harvest, Samson went to visit his wife with <crossref let="k" cid="c07015001.1"/>a young goat. And he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015001.1" from="07015001.1" to="07015001.2"/>I will go in to my wife in the chamber.<q class="end-double" qid="07015001.2" from="07015001.1" to="07015001.2"/> But her father would not allow him to go in.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015002"/>
    <verse num="2">And her father said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015002.1" from="07015002.1" to="07015002.2"/>I really thought that you utterly hated her, <crossref let="l" cid="c07015002.1"/>so I gave her to your companion. Is not her younger sister more beautiful than she? Please take her instead.<q class="end-double" qid="07015002.2" from="07015002.1" to="07015002.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015003"/>
    <verse num="3">And Samson said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015003.1" from="07015003.1" to="07015003.2"/>This time I shall be innocent in regard to the Philistines, when I do them harm.<q class="end-double" qid="07015003.2" from="07015003.1" to="07015003.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015004"/>
    <verse num="4">So Samson went and caught 300 foxes and took torches. And he turned them tail to tail and put a torch between each pair of tails.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015005"/>
    <verse num="5">And when he had set fire to the torches, he let the foxes go into the standing grain of the Philistines and set fire to the stacked grain and the standing grain, as well as the olive orchards.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015006"/>
    <verse num="6">Then the Philistines said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015006.1" from="07015006.1" to="07015006.2"/>Who has done this?<q class="end-double" qid="07015006.2" from="07015006.1" to="07015006.2"/> And they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015006.3" from="07015006.3" to="07015006.4"/>Samson, the son-in-law of the Timnite, because he has taken his wife <crossref let="m" cid="c07015006.1"/>and given her to his companion.<q class="end-double" qid="07015006.4" from="07015006.3" to="07015006.4"/> And the Philistines came up and <crossref let="n" cid="c07015006.2"/>burned her and her father with fire.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015007"/>
    <verse num="7">And Samson said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015007.1" from="07015007.1" to="07015007.2"/>If this is what you do, I swear I will be avenged on you, and after that I will quit.<q class="end-double" qid="07015007.2" from="07015007.1" to="07015007.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015008"/>
    <verse num="8">And he struck them hip and thigh with a great blow, and he went down and stayed in the <crossref let="o" cid="c07015008.1"/>cleft of the rock of Etam.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015009"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9">Then the Philistines came up and encamped in Judah and <crossref let="p" cid="c07015009.1"/>made a raid on <crossref let="q" cid="c07015009.2"/>Lehi.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015010"/>
    <verse num="10">And the men of Judah said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015010.1" from="07015010.1" to="07015010.2"/>Why have you come up against us?<q class="end-double" qid="07015010.2" from="07015010.1" to="07015010.2"/> They said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015010.3" from="07015010.3" to="07015010.4"/>We have come up to bind Samson, to do to him as he did to us.<q class="end-double" qid="07015010.4" from="07015010.3" to="07015010.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015011"/>
    <verse num="11">Then 3,000 men of Judah went down to the cleft of the rock of Etam, and said to Samson, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015011.1" from="07015011.1" to="07015011.2"/>Do you not know that <crossref let="r" cid="c07015011.1"/>the Philistines are rulers over us? What then is this that you have done to us?<q class="end-double" qid="07015011.2" from="07015011.1" to="07015011.2"/> And he said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015011.3" from="07015011.3" to="07015011.4"/>As they did to me, so have I done to them.<q class="end-double" qid="07015011.4" from="07015011.3" to="07015011.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015012"/>
    <verse num="12">And they said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015012.1" from="07015012.1" to="07015012.2"/>We have come down to bind you, that we may give you into the hands of the Philistines.<q class="end-double" qid="07015012.2" from="07015012.1" to="07015012.2"/> And Samson said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015012.3" from="07015012.3" to="07015012.4"/>Swear to me that you will not attack me yourselves.<q class="end-double" qid="07015012.4" from="07015012.3" to="07015012.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015013"/>
    <verse num="13">They said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07015013.1" from="07015013.1" to="07015013.2"/>No; we will only bind you and give you into their hands. We will surely not kill you.<q class="end-double" qid="07015013.2" from="07015013.1" to="07015013.2"/> So they bound him with two <crossref let="s" cid="c07015013.1"/>new ropes and brought him up from the rock.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14">When he came to Lehi, the Philistines came shouting to meet him. <crossref let="t" cid="c07015014.1"/>Then the Spirit of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> rushed upon him, and the ropes that were on his arms became as flax that has caught fire, and his bonds melted off his hands.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015015"/>
    <verse num="15">And he found a fresh jawbone of a donkey, and put out his hand and took it, <crossref let="u" cid="c07015015.1"/>and with it he struck 1,000 men.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015016"/>
    <verse num="16">And Samson said,
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
        <begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="07015016.1" from="07015016.1" to="07015016.2"/>With the jawbone of a donkey,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>heaps upon heaps,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>with the jawbone of a donkey<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>have I struck down a thousand men.<q class="end-double" qid="07015016.2" from="07015016.1" to="07015016.2"/><end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <end-block-indent/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015017"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/>
    <verse num="17">As soon as he had finished speaking, he threw away the jawbone out of his hand. And that place <crossref let="v" cid="c07015017.1"/>was called Ramath-lehi.<note nid="n07015017.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18">And he was very thirsty, and he called upon the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and said, <crossref let="w" cid="c07015018.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07015018.1" from="07015018.1" to="07015018.2"/>You have granted this great salvation by the hand of your servant, and shall I now die of thirst and fall into the hands of the uncircumcised?<q class="end-double" qid="07015018.2" from="07015018.1" to="07015018.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015019"/>
    <verse num="19">And God split open the hollow place that is <crossref let="v" cid="c07015019.1"/>at Lehi, and water came out from it. And when he drank, <crossref let="x" cid="c07015019.2"/>his spirit returned, and he revived. Therefore the name of it was called En-hakkore;<note nid="n07015019.1"/> it is at Lehi to this day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07015020"/>
    <verse num="20">And he judged Israel <crossref let="y" cid="c07015020.1"/>in the days of the Philistines twenty years.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016001"/>
  <chapter num="16">
    <heading>Samson and Delilah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Samson went to <crossref let="z" cid="c07016001.1"/>Gaza, and there he saw a prostitute, and he went in to her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016002"/>
    <verse num="2">The Gazites were told, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016002.1" from="07016002.1" to="07016002.2"/>Samson has come here.<q class="end-double" qid="07016002.2" from="07016002.1" to="07016002.2"/> And they <crossref let="a" cid="c07016002.1"/>surrounded the place and set an ambush for him all night at the gate of the city. They kept quiet all night, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016002.3" from="07016002.3" to="07016002.4"/>Let us wait till the light of the morning; then we will kill him.<q class="end-double" qid="07016002.4" from="07016002.3" to="07016002.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016003"/>
    <verse num="3">But Samson lay till midnight, and at midnight he arose and took hold of the doors of the gate of the city and the two posts, and pulled them up, bar and all, and put them on his shoulders and carried them to the top of the hill that is in front of Hebron.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">After this he loved a woman in the Valley of Sorek, whose name was Delilah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016005"/>
    <verse num="5">And <crossref let="b" cid="c07016005.1"/>the lords of the Philistines came up to her and said to her, <crossref let="c" cid="c07016005.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07016005.1" from="07016005.1" to="07016005.2"/>Seduce him, and see where his great strength lies, and by what means we may overpower him, that we may bind him to <crossref let="d" cid="c07016005.3"/>humble him. And we will each give you 1,100 pieces of silver.<q class="end-double" qid="07016005.2" from="07016005.1" to="07016005.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016006"/>
    <verse num="6">So Delilah said to Samson, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016006.1" from="07016006.1" to="07016006.2"/>Please tell me where your great strength lies, and how you might be bound, that one could <crossref let="d" cid="c07016006.1"/>subdue you.<q class="end-double" qid="07016006.2" from="07016006.1" to="07016006.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">Samson said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016007.1" from="07016007.1" to="07016007.2"/>If they bind me with seven fresh bowstrings that have not been dried, <crossref let="e" cid="c07016007.1"/>then I shall become weak and be like any other man.<q class="end-double" qid="07016007.2" from="07016007.1" to="07016007.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016008"/>
    <verse num="8">Then the lords of the Philistines brought up to her seven fresh bowstrings that had not been dried, and she bound him with them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016009"/>
    <verse num="9">Now she had men lying in ambush in an inner chamber. And she said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016009.1" from="07016009.1" to="07016009.2"/>The Philistines are upon you, Samson!<q class="end-double" qid="07016009.2" from="07016009.1" to="07016009.2"/> But he snapped the bowstrings, as a thread of flax snaps when it touches the fire. So the secret of his strength was not known.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">Then Delilah said to Samson, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016010.1" from="07016010.1" to="07016010.2"/>Behold, you have mocked me and told me lies. Please tell me how you might be bound.<q class="end-double" qid="07016010.2" from="07016010.1" to="07016010.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016011"/>
    <verse num="11">And he said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016011.1" from="07016011.1" to="07016011.2"/>If they bind me with <crossref let="f" cid="c07016011.1"/>new ropes that have not been used, then I shall become weak and be like any other man.<q class="end-double" qid="07016011.2" from="07016011.1" to="07016011.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016012"/>
    <verse num="12">So Delilah took new ropes and bound him with them and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016012.1" from="07016012.1" to="07016012.2"/>The Philistines are upon you, Samson!<q class="end-double" qid="07016012.2" from="07016012.1" to="07016012.2"/> And the men lying in ambush were in an inner chamber. But he snapped the ropes off his arms like a thread.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">Then Delilah said to Samson, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016013.1" from="07016013.1" to="07016013.2"/>Until now you have mocked me and told me lies. Tell me how you might be bound.<q class="end-double" qid="07016013.2" from="07016013.1" to="07016013.2"/> And he said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016013.3" from="07016013.3" to="07016013.4"/>If you weave the seven locks of my head with the web and fasten it tight with the pin, then I shall become weak and be like any other man.<q class="end-double" qid="07016013.4" from="07016013.3" to="07016013.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016014"/>
    <verse num="14">So while he slept, Delilah took the seven locks of his head and wove them into the web.<note nid="n07016014.1"/> And she made them tight with the pin and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016014.1" from="07016014.1" to="07016014.2"/>The Philistines are upon you, Samson!<q class="end-double" qid="07016014.2" from="07016014.1" to="07016014.2"/> But he awoke from his sleep and pulled away the pin, the loom, and the web.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">And she said to him, <crossref let="g" cid="c07016015.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07016015.1" from="07016015.1" to="07016015.4"/>How can you say, <q class="begin-single" qid="07016015.2" from="07016015.2" to="07016015.3"/>I love you,<q class="end-single" qid="07016015.3" from="07016015.2" to="07016015.3"/> when your heart is not with me? You have mocked me these three times, and you have not told me where your great strength lies.<q class="end-double" qid="07016015.4" from="07016015.1" to="07016015.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016016"/>
    <verse num="16">And <crossref let="h" cid="c07016016.1"/>when she pressed him hard with her words day after day, and urged him, his soul was vexed to death.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016017"/>
    <verse num="17">And he told her all his heart, and said to her, <crossref let="i" cid="c07016017.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07016017.1" from="07016017.1" to="07016017.2"/>A razor has never come upon my head, for I have been a Nazirite to God from my mother&apos;s womb. If my head is shaved, then my strength will leave me, and I shall become weak and be like any other man.<q class="end-double" qid="07016017.2" from="07016017.1" to="07016017.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18">When Delilah saw that he had told her all his heart, she sent and called the lords of the Philistines, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016018.1" from="07016018.1" to="07016018.2"/>Come up again, for he has told me all his heart.<q class="end-double" qid="07016018.2" from="07016018.1" to="07016018.2"/> Then the lords of the Philistines came up to her and brought <crossref let="j" cid="c07016018.1"/>the money in their hands.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016019"/>
    <verse num="19">She made him sleep on her knees. And she called a man and had him shave off the seven locks of his head. Then she began <crossref let="k" cid="c07016019.1"/>to torment him, and his strength left him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016020"/>
    <verse num="20">And she said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016020.1" from="07016020.1" to="07016020.2"/>The Philistines are upon you, Samson!<q class="end-double" qid="07016020.2" from="07016020.1" to="07016020.2"/> And he awoke from his sleep and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016020.3" from="07016020.3" to="07016020.4"/>I will go out as at other times and shake myself free.<q class="end-double" qid="07016020.4" from="07016020.3" to="07016020.4"/> But he did not know that <crossref let="l" cid="c07016020.1"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had left him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016021"/>
    <verse num="21">And the Philistines seized him and gouged out his eyes and brought him down to Gaza and bound him with bronze shackles. <crossref let="m" cid="c07016021.1"/>And he ground at the mill in the prison.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016022"/>
    <verse num="22">But the hair of his head began to grow again after it had been shaved.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016023"/>
    <heading>The Death of Samson</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="23">Now the lords of the Philistines gathered to offer a great sacrifice to <crossref let="n" cid="c07016023.1"/>Dagon their god and to rejoice, and they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016023.1" from="07016023.1" to="07016023.2"/>Our god has given Samson our enemy into our hand.<q class="end-double" qid="07016023.2" from="07016023.1" to="07016023.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016024"/>
    <verse num="24">And when the people saw him, <crossref let="o" cid="c07016024.1"/>they praised their god. For they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016024.1" from="07016024.1" to="07016024.2"/>Our god has given our enemy into our hand, the ravager of our country, who has killed many of us.<q class="end-double" qid="07016024.2" from="07016024.1" to="07016024.2"/><note nid="n07016024.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016025"/>
    <verse num="25">And <crossref let="p" cid="c07016025.1"/>when their hearts were merry, they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016025.1" from="07016025.1" to="07016025.2"/>Call Samson, that he may entertain us.<q class="end-double" qid="07016025.2" from="07016025.1" to="07016025.2"/> So they called Samson out of the prison, and he entertained them. They made him stand between the pillars.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016026"/>
    <verse num="26">And Samson said to the young man who held him by the hand, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016026.1" from="07016026.1" to="07016026.2"/>Let me feel the pillars on which the house rests, that I may lean against them.<q class="end-double" qid="07016026.2" from="07016026.1" to="07016026.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016027"/>
    <verse num="27">Now the house was full of men and women. All the lords of the Philistines were there, and <crossref let="q" cid="c07016027.1"/>on the roof there were about 3,000 men and women, who looked on while Samson entertained.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016028"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="28">Then Samson called to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016028.1" from="07016028.1" to="07016028.2"/>O Lord <span class="divine-name">God</span>, <crossref let="r" cid="c07016028.1"/>please remember me and please strengthen me only this once, O God, that I may be avenged on the Philistines for my two eyes.<q class="end-double" qid="07016028.2" from="07016028.1" to="07016028.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016029"/>
    <verse num="29">And Samson grasped the two middle pillars on which the house rested, and he leaned his weight against them, his right hand on the one and his left hand on the other.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016030"/>
    <verse num="30">And Samson said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07016030.1" from="07016030.1" to="07016030.2"/>Let me die with the Philistines.<q class="end-double" qid="07016030.2" from="07016030.1" to="07016030.2"/> Then he bowed with all his strength, and the house fell upon the lords and upon all the people who were in it. So the dead whom he killed at his death were more than those whom he had killed during his life.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07016031"/>
    <verse num="31">Then his brothers and all his family came down and took him and brought him up and buried him <crossref let="s" cid="c07016031.1"/>between Zorah and Eshtaol in the tomb of Manoah his father. He had judged Israel twenty years.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017001"/>
  <chapter num="17">
    <heading>Micah and the Levite</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">There was a man of <crossref let="t" cid="c07017001.1"/>the hill country of Ephraim, whose name was Micah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017002"/>
    <verse num="2">And he said to his mother, <q class="begin-double" qid="07017002.1" from="07017002.1" to="07017002.2"/>The 1,100 pieces of silver that were taken from you, about which you uttered a curse, and also spoke it in my ears, behold, the silver is with me; I took it.<q class="end-double" qid="07017002.2" from="07017002.1" to="07017002.2"/> And his mother said, <crossref let="u" cid="c07017002.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07017002.3" from="07017002.3" to="07017002.4"/>Blessed be my son by the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="07017002.4" from="07017002.3" to="07017002.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017003"/>
    <verse num="3">And he restored the 1,100 pieces of silver to his mother. And his mother said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07017003.1" from="07017003.1" to="07017003.2"/>I dedicate the silver to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> from my hand for my son, to make <crossref let="v" cid="c07017003.1"/>a carved image and <crossref let="w" cid="c07017003.2"/>a metal image. Now therefore I will restore it to you.<q class="end-double" qid="07017003.2" from="07017003.1" to="07017003.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017004"/>
    <verse num="4">So when he restored the money to his mother, his mother <crossref let="x" cid="c07017004.1"/>took 200 pieces of silver and gave it to the silversmith, who made it into a carved image and a metal image. And it was in the house of Micah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017005"/>
    <verse num="5">And the man Micah had a shrine, and he made <crossref let="y" cid="c07017005.1"/>an ephod and <crossref let="z" cid="c07017005.2"/>household gods, and <crossref let="a" cid="c07017005.3"/>ordained<note nid="n07017005.1"/> one of his sons, who became his priest.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="b" cid="c07017006.1"/>In those days there was no king in Israel. <crossref let="c" cid="c07017006.2"/>Everyone did what was right in his own eyes.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">Now there was a young man of <crossref let="d" cid="c07017007.1"/>Bethlehem in Judah, of the family of Judah, who was a Levite, and he sojourned there.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017008"/>
    <verse num="8">And the man departed from the town of Bethlehem in Judah to sojourn where he could find a place. And as he journeyed, he came to <crossref let="e" cid="c07017008.1"/>the hill country of Ephraim to the house of Micah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017009"/>
    <verse num="9">And Micah said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07017009.1" from="07017009.1" to="07017009.2"/>Where do you come from?<q class="end-double" qid="07017009.2" from="07017009.1" to="07017009.2"/> And he said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07017009.3" from="07017009.3" to="07017009.4"/>I am a Levite of Bethlehem in Judah, and I am going to sojourn where I may find a place.<q class="end-double" qid="07017009.4" from="07017009.3" to="07017009.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017010"/>
    <verse num="10">And Micah said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07017010.1" from="07017010.1" to="07017010.2"/>Stay with me, and be to me <crossref let="f" cid="c07017010.1"/>a father and a priest, and I will give you ten pieces of silver a year and a suit of clothes and your living.<q class="end-double" qid="07017010.2" from="07017010.1" to="07017010.2"/> And the Levite went in.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017011"/>
    <verse num="11">And the Levite <crossref let="g" cid="c07017011.1"/>was content to dwell with the man, and the young man became to him like one of his sons.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017012"/>
    <verse num="12">And Micah <crossref let="h" cid="c07017012.1"/>ordained the Levite, and the young man <crossref let="i" cid="c07017012.2"/>became his priest, and was in the house of Micah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07017013"/>
    <verse num="13">Then Micah said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07017013.1" from="07017013.1" to="07017013.2"/>Now I know that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will prosper me, because I have a Levite as priest.<q class="end-double" qid="07017013.2" from="07017013.1" to="07017013.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018001"/>
  <chapter num="18">
    <heading>Danites Take the Levite and the Idol</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="j" cid="c07018001.1"/>In those days there was no king in Israel. And in those days <crossref let="k" cid="c07018001.2"/>the tribe of the people of Dan was seeking for itself an inheritance to dwell in, for until then no inheritance among the tribes of Israel had fallen to them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018002"/>
    <verse num="2">So the people of Dan sent five able men from the whole number of their tribe, <crossref let="l" cid="c07018002.1"/>from Zorah and from Eshtaol, <crossref let="m" cid="c07018002.2"/>to spy out the land and to explore it. And they said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07018002.1" from="07018002.1" to="07018002.2"/>Go and explore the land.<q class="end-double" qid="07018002.2" from="07018002.1" to="07018002.2"/> And they came <crossref let="n" cid="c07018002.3"/>to the hill country of Ephraim, to the house of Micah, and lodged there.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018003"/>
    <verse num="3">When they were by the house of Micah, they recognized the voice of the young Levite. And they turned aside and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07018003.1" from="07018003.1" to="07018003.2"/>Who brought you here? What are you doing in this place? What is your business here?<q class="end-double" qid="07018003.2" from="07018003.1" to="07018003.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018004"/>
    <verse num="4">And he said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07018004.1" from="07018004.1" to="07018004.2"/>This is how Micah dealt with me: <crossref let="o" cid="c07018004.1"/>he has hired me, and I have become his priest.<q class="end-double" qid="07018004.2" from="07018004.1" to="07018004.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018005"/>
    <verse num="5">And they said to him, <crossref let="p" cid="c07018005.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07018005.1" from="07018005.1" to="07018005.2"/>Inquire of God, please, that we may know whether the journey on which we are setting out will succeed.<q class="end-double" qid="07018005.2" from="07018005.1" to="07018005.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018006"/>
    <verse num="6">And the priest said to them, <crossref let="q" cid="c07018006.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07018006.1" from="07018006.1" to="07018006.2"/>Go in peace. The journey on which you go is under the eye of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="07018006.2" from="07018006.1" to="07018006.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">Then the five men departed and came to <crossref let="r" cid="c07018007.1"/>Laish and saw the people who were there, how they lived in security, after the manner of the Sidonians, <crossref let="s" cid="c07018007.2"/>quiet and unsuspecting, lacking<note nid="n07018007.1"/> nothing that is in the earth and possessing wealth, and how <crossref let="t" cid="c07018007.3"/>they were far from the Sidonians and had no dealings with anyone.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018008"/>
    <verse num="8">And when they came to their brothers at <crossref let="u" cid="c07018008.1"/>Zorah and Eshtaol, their brothers said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07018008.1" from="07018008.1" to="07018008.2"/>What do you report?<q class="end-double" qid="07018008.2" from="07018008.1" to="07018008.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018009"/>
    <verse num="9">They said, <crossref let="v" cid="c07018009.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07018009.1" from="07018009.1" to="07018010.1"/>Arise, and let us go up against them, for we have seen the land, and behold, it is very good. <crossref let="w" cid="c07018009.2"/>And will you do nothing? <crossref let="x" cid="c07018009.3"/>Do not be slow to go, to enter in and possess the land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018010"/>
    <verse num="10">As soon as you go, you will come to an <crossref let="y" cid="c07018010.1"/>unsuspecting people. The land is spacious, for God has given it into your hands, <crossref let="z" cid="c07018010.2"/>a place where there is no lack of anything that is in the earth.<q class="end-double" qid="07018010.1" from="07018009.1" to="07018010.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11">So 600 men of the tribe of Dan, <crossref let="a" cid="c07018011.1"/>armed with weapons of war, set out from Zorah and Eshtaol,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018012"/>
    <verse num="12">and went up and encamped at Kiriath-jearim in Judah. On this account that place is called <crossref let="b" cid="c07018012.1"/>Mahaneh-dan<note nid="n07018012.1"/> to this day; behold, it is west of <crossref let="c" cid="c07018012.2"/>Kiriath-jearim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018013"/>
    <verse num="13">And they passed on from there to <crossref let="d" cid="c07018013.1"/>the hill country of Ephraim, and came to the house of Micah.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14">Then the five men who had gone to scout out the country of Laish said to their brothers, <q class="begin-double" qid="07018014.1" from="07018014.1" to="07018014.2"/>Do you know that <crossref let="e" cid="c07018014.1"/>in these houses there are an ephod, household gods, a carved image, and a metal image? Now therefore consider what you will do.<q class="end-double" qid="07018014.2" from="07018014.1" to="07018014.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018015"/>
    <verse num="15">And they turned aside there and came to the house of the young Levite, at the home of Micah, and <crossref let="f" cid="c07018015.1"/>asked him about his welfare.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018016"/>
    <verse num="16">Now the 600 men of the Danites, <crossref let="g" cid="c07018016.1"/>armed with their weapons of war, stood by the entrance of the gate.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018017"/>
    <verse num="17">And <crossref let="h" cid="c07018017.1"/>the five men who had gone to scout out the land went up and entered and took <crossref let="i" cid="c07018017.2"/>the carved image, the ephod, the household gods, and the metal image, while the priest stood by the entrance of the gate with the 600 men armed with weapons of war.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018018"/>
    <verse num="18">And when these went into Micah&apos;s house and took <crossref let="i" cid="c07018018.1"/>the carved image, the ephod, the household gods, and the metal image, the priest said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07018018.1" from="07018018.1" to="07018018.2"/>What are you doing?<q class="end-double" qid="07018018.2" from="07018018.1" to="07018018.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018019"/>
    <verse num="19">And they said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07018019.1" from="07018019.1" to="07018019.2"/>Keep quiet; <crossref let="j" cid="c07018019.1"/>put your hand on your mouth and come with us and be to us <crossref let="k" cid="c07018019.2"/>a father and a priest. Is it better for you to be priest to the house of one man, or to be priest to a tribe and clan in Israel?<q class="end-double" qid="07018019.2" from="07018019.1" to="07018019.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018020"/>
    <verse num="20">And the priest&apos;s heart was glad. He took the ephod and the household gods and the carved image and went along with the people.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018021"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="21">So they turned and departed, putting the little ones and the livestock and <crossref let="l" cid="c07018021.1"/>the goods in front of them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018022"/>
    <verse num="22">When they had gone a distance from the home of Micah, the men who were in the houses near Micah&apos;s house were called out, and they overtook the people of Dan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018023"/>
    <verse num="23">And they shouted to the people of Dan, who turned around and said to Micah, <q class="begin-double" qid="07018023.1" from="07018023.1" to="07018023.2"/>What is the matter with you, that you come with such a company?<q class="end-double" qid="07018023.2" from="07018023.1" to="07018023.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018024"/>
    <verse num="24">And he said, <crossref let="m" cid="c07018024.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07018024.1" from="07018024.1" to="07018024.4"/>You take my gods that I made and the priest, and go away, and what have I left? How then do you ask me, <q class="begin-single" qid="07018024.2" from="07018024.2" to="07018024.3"/>What is the matter with you?<q class="end-single" qid="07018024.3" from="07018024.2" to="07018024.3"/><q class="end-double" qid="07018024.4" from="07018024.1" to="07018024.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018025"/>
    <verse num="25">And the people of Dan said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07018025.1" from="07018025.1" to="07018025.2"/>Do not let your voice be heard among us, lest angry fellows fall upon you, and you lose your life with the lives of your household.<q class="end-double" qid="07018025.2" from="07018025.1" to="07018025.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018026"/>
    <verse num="26">Then the people of Dan went their way. And when Micah saw that they were too strong for him, he turned and went back to his home.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018027"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="27">But the people of Dan took what Micah had made, and the priest who belonged to him, and they came to Laish, to a people <crossref let="n" cid="c07018027.1"/>quiet and unsuspecting, and <crossref let="o" cid="c07018027.2"/>struck them with the edge of the sword and burned the city with fire.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018028"/>
    <verse num="28">And there was no deliverer because it was <crossref let="p" cid="c07018028.1"/>far from Sidon, and they had no dealings with anyone. It was in the valley that belongs to <crossref let="q" cid="c07018028.2"/>Beth-rehob. Then they rebuilt the city and lived in it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018029"/>
    <verse num="29">And they named the city <crossref let="r" cid="c07018029.1"/>Dan, after the name of Dan their ancestor, who was born to Israel; but <crossref let="s" cid="c07018029.2"/>the name of the city was Laish at the first.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018030"/>
    <verse num="30">And the people of Dan set up the carved image for themselves, and Jonathan the son of Gershom, <crossref let="t" cid="c07018030.1"/>son of Moses,<note nid="n07018030.1"/> <crossref let="u" cid="c07018030.2"/>and his sons were priests to the tribe of the Danites until the day <crossref let="v" cid="c07018030.3"/>of the captivity of the land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07018031"/>
    <verse num="31">So they set up Micah&apos;s carved image that he made, <crossref let="w" cid="c07018031.1"/>as long as the house of God was at Shiloh.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019001"/>
  <chapter num="19">
    <heading>A Levite and His Concubine</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">In those days, <crossref let="x" cid="c07019001.1"/>when there was no king in Israel, a certain Levite was sojourning in the remote parts of <crossref let="y" cid="c07019001.2"/>the hill country of Ephraim, who took to himself a concubine from <crossref let="z" cid="c07019001.3"/>Bethlehem in Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019002"/>
    <verse num="2">And his concubine was unfaithful to<note nid="n07019002.1"/> him, and she went away from him to her father&apos;s house at Bethlehem in Judah, and was there some four months.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019003"/>
    <verse num="3">Then her husband arose and went after her, to speak kindly to her and bring her back. He had with him his servant and a couple of donkeys. And she brought him into her father&apos;s house. And when the girl&apos;s father saw him, he came with joy to meet him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019004"/>
    <verse num="4">And his father-in-law, the girl&apos;s father, made him stay, and he remained with him three days. So they ate and drank and spent the night there.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019005"/>
    <verse num="5">And on the fourth day they arose early in the morning, and he prepared to go, but the girl&apos;s father said to his son-in-law, <crossref let="a" cid="c07019005.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07019005.1" from="07019005.1" to="07019005.2"/>Strengthen your heart with a morsel of bread, and after that you may go.<q class="end-double" qid="07019005.2" from="07019005.1" to="07019005.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019006"/>
    <verse num="6">So the two of them sat and ate and drank together. And the girl&apos;s father said to the man, <q class="begin-double" qid="07019006.1" from="07019006.1" to="07019006.2"/>Be pleased to spend the night, and <crossref let="b" cid="c07019006.1"/>let your heart be merry.<q class="end-double" qid="07019006.2" from="07019006.1" to="07019006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019007"/>
    <verse num="7">And when the man rose up to go, his father-in-law pressed him, till he spent the night there again.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019008"/>
    <verse num="8">And on the fifth day he arose early in the morning to depart. And the girl&apos;s father said, <crossref let="c" cid="c07019008.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07019008.1" from="07019008.1" to="07019008.2"/>Strengthen your heart and wait until the day declines.<q class="end-double" qid="07019008.2" from="07019008.1" to="07019008.2"/> So they ate, both of them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019009"/>
    <verse num="9">And when the man and his concubine and his servant rose up to depart, his father-in-law, the girl&apos;s father, said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07019009.1" from="07019009.1" to="07019009.2"/>Behold, now the day has waned toward evening. Please, spend the night. Behold, the day draws to its close. Lodge here and let your heart be merry, and tomorrow you shall arise early in the morning for your journey, and go home.<q class="end-double" qid="07019009.2" from="07019009.1" to="07019009.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">But the man would not spend the night. He rose up and departed and arrived opposite <crossref let="d" cid="c07019010.1"/>Jebus (that is, Jerusalem). He had with him a couple of saddled donkeys, and his concubine was with him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019011"/>
    <verse num="11">When they were near Jebus, the day was nearly over, and the servant said to his master, <q class="begin-double" qid="07019011.1" from="07019011.1" to="07019011.2"/>Come now, let us turn aside to this city of the Jebusites and spend the night in it.<q class="end-double" qid="07019011.2" from="07019011.1" to="07019011.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019012"/>
    <verse num="12">And his master said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07019012.1" from="07019012.1" to="07019012.2"/>We will not turn aside into the city of foreigners, who do not belong to the people of Israel, but we will pass on to <crossref let="e" cid="c07019012.1"/>Gibeah.<q class="end-double" qid="07019012.2" from="07019012.1" to="07019012.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019013"/>
    <verse num="13">And he said to his young man, <q class="begin-double" qid="07019013.1" from="07019013.1" to="07019013.2"/>Come and let us draw near to one of these places and spend the night at Gibeah or at <crossref let="f" cid="c07019013.1"/>Ramah.<q class="end-double" qid="07019013.2" from="07019013.1" to="07019013.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019014"/>
    <verse num="14">So they passed on and went their way. And the sun went down on them near Gibeah, which belongs to Benjamin,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019015"/>
    <verse num="15">and they turned aside there, to go in and spend the night at Gibeah. And he went in and sat down in the open square of the city, <crossref let="g" cid="c07019015.1"/>for no one took them into his house to spend the night.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">And behold, an old man was coming from his work in the field at evening. The man was from <crossref let="h" cid="c07019016.1"/>the hill country of Ephraim, and he was sojourning in Gibeah. <crossref let="i" cid="c07019016.2"/>The men of the place were Benjaminites.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019017"/>
    <verse num="17">And he lifted up his eyes and saw the traveler in the open square of the city. And the old man said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07019017.1" from="07019017.1" to="07019017.2"/>Where are you going? And where do you come from?<q class="end-double" qid="07019017.2" from="07019017.1" to="07019017.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019018"/>
    <verse num="18">And he said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="07019018.1" from="07019018.1" to="07019019.1"/>We are passing from Bethlehem in Judah to the remote parts of the hill country of Ephraim, from which I come. I went to Bethlehem in Judah, and I am going <crossref let="j" cid="c07019018.1"/>to the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,<note nid="n07019018.1"/> <crossref let="g" cid="c07019018.2"/>but no one has taken me into his house.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019019"/>
    <verse num="19">We have straw and feed for our donkeys, with bread and wine for me and your female servant and the young man with your servants. <crossref let="k" cid="c07019019.1"/>There is no lack of anything.<q class="end-double" qid="07019019.1" from="07019018.1" to="07019019.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019020"/>
    <verse num="20">And the old man said, <crossref let="l" cid="c07019020.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07019020.1" from="07019020.1" to="07019020.2"/>Peace be to you; I will care for all your wants. <crossref let="m" cid="c07019020.2"/>Only, do not spend the night in the square.<q class="end-double" qid="07019020.2" from="07019020.1" to="07019020.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019021"/>
    <verse num="21">So he brought him into his house and gave the donkeys feed. <crossref let="n" cid="c07019021.1"/>And they washed their feet, and ate and drank.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019022"/>
    <heading>Gibeah&apos;s Crime</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">As they were <crossref let="o" cid="c07019022.1"/>making their hearts merry, behold, the men of the city, worthless fellows, <crossref let="p" cid="c07019022.2"/>surrounded the house, beating on the door. And they said to the old man, the master of the house, <q class="begin-double" qid="07019022.1" from="07019022.1" to="07019022.2"/>Bring out the man who came into your house, that we may know him.<q class="end-double" qid="07019022.2" from="07019022.1" to="07019022.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019023"/>
    <verse num="23">And the man, the master of the house, went out to them and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="07019023.1" from="07019023.1" to="07019024.1"/>No, my brothers, <crossref let="q" cid="c07019023.1"/>do not act so wickedly; since this man has come into my house, <crossref let="r" cid="c07019023.2"/>do not do this vile thing.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019024"/>
    <verse num="24"><crossref let="s" cid="c07019024.1"/>Behold, here are my virgin daughter and his concubine. Let me bring them out now. <crossref let="t" cid="c07019024.2"/>Violate them and do with them what seems good to you, but against this man <crossref let="r" cid="c07019024.3"/>do not do this outrageous thing.<q class="end-double" qid="07019024.1" from="07019023.1" to="07019024.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019025"/>
    <verse num="25">But the men would not listen to him. So the man seized his concubine and made her go out to them. And they knew her and abused her all night until the morning. And as the dawn began to break, they let her go.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019026"/>
    <verse num="26">And as morning appeared, the woman came and fell down at the door of the man&apos;s house where her master was, until it was light.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019027"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="27">And her master rose up in the morning, and when he opened the doors of the house and went out to go on his way, behold, there was his concubine lying at the door of the house, with her hands on the threshold.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019028"/>
    <verse num="28">He said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="07019028.1" from="07019028.1" to="07019028.2"/>Get up, let us be going.<q class="end-double" qid="07019028.2" from="07019028.1" to="07019028.2"/> <crossref let="u" cid="c07019028.1"/>But there was no answer. Then he put her on the donkey, and the man rose up and went away to his home.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019029"/>
    <verse num="29">And when he entered his house, he took a knife, and taking hold of his concubine he <crossref let="v" cid="c07019029.1"/>divided her, limb by limb, into twelve pieces, and sent her throughout all the territory of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07019030"/>
    <verse num="30"><crossref let="w" cid="c07019030.1"/>And all who saw it said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07019030.1" from="07019030.1" to="07019030.2"/>Such a thing has never happened or been seen from the day that the people of Israel came up out of the land of Egypt until this day; <crossref let="x" cid="c07019030.2"/>consider it, take counsel, and speak.<q class="end-double" qid="07019030.2" from="07019030.1" to="07019030.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020001"/>
  <chapter num="20">
    <heading>Israel&apos;s War with the Tribe of Benjamin</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Then <crossref let="y" cid="c07020001.1"/>all the people of Israel came out, <crossref let="z" cid="c07020001.2"/>from Dan to Beersheba, including the land of Gilead, and the congregation assembled as one man to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> at <crossref let="a" cid="c07020001.3"/>Mizpah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020002"/>
    <verse num="2">And the <crossref let="b" cid="c07020002.1"/>chiefs of all the people, of all the tribes of Israel, presented themselves in the assembly of the people of God, 400,000 men on foot <crossref let="c" cid="c07020002.2"/>that drew the sword.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020003"/>
    <verse num="3">(Now the people of Benjamin heard that the people of Israel had gone up to Mizpah.) And the people of Israel said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07020003.1" from="07020003.1" to="07020003.2"/>Tell us, how did this evil happen?<q class="end-double" qid="07020003.2" from="07020003.1" to="07020003.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020004"/>
    <verse num="4">And the Levite, the husband of the woman who was murdered, answered and said, <crossref let="d" cid="c07020004.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07020004.1" from="07020004.1" to="07020007.1"/>I came to Gibeah that belongs to Benjamin, I and my concubine, to spend the night.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020005"/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="e" cid="c07020005.1"/>And the leaders of Gibeah rose against me and surrounded the house against me by night. They meant to kill me, and they violated my concubine, and she is dead.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="f" cid="c07020006.1"/>So I took hold of my concubine and cut her in pieces and sent her throughout all the country of the inheritance of Israel, for they have committed abomination and <crossref let="g" cid="c07020006.2"/>outrage in Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020007"/>
    <verse num="7">Behold, you people of Israel, all of you, <crossref let="h" cid="c07020007.1"/>give your advice and counsel here.<q class="end-double" qid="07020007.1" from="07020004.1" to="07020007.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">And all the people arose as one man, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="07020008.1" from="07020008.1" to="07020010.1"/>None of us will go to his tent, and none of us will return to his house.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020009"/>
    <verse num="9">But now this is what we will do to Gibeah: we will go up against it by lot,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020010"/>
    <verse num="10">and we will take ten men of a hundred throughout all the tribes of Israel, and a hundred of a thousand, and a thousand of ten thousand, to bring provisions for the people, that when they come they may repay Gibeah of Benjamin for all the outrage that they have committed in Israel.<q class="end-double" qid="07020010.1" from="07020008.1" to="07020010.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020011"/>
    <verse num="11">So all the men of Israel gathered against the city, united as one man.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="i" cid="c07020012.1"/>And the tribes of Israel sent men through all the tribe of Benjamin, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="07020012.1" from="07020012.1" to="07020013.1"/>What evil is this that has taken place among you?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020013"/>
    <verse num="13">Now therefore give up the men, <crossref let="j" cid="c07020013.1"/>the worthless fellows in Gibeah, that we may put them to death <crossref let="k" cid="c07020013.2"/>and purge evil from Israel.<q class="end-double" qid="07020013.1" from="07020012.1" to="07020013.1"/> But the Benjaminites would not listen to the voice of their brothers, the people of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020014"/>
    <verse num="14">Then the people of Benjamin came together out of the cities to Gibeah to go out to battle against the people of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020015"/>
    <verse num="15">And the people of Benjamin mustered out of their cities on that day <crossref let="l" cid="c07020015.1"/>26,000 men <crossref let="m" cid="c07020015.2"/>who drew the sword, besides the inhabitants of Gibeah, who mustered 700 chosen men.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020016"/>
    <verse num="16">Among all these were 700 chosen men who were <crossref let="n" cid="c07020016.1"/>left-handed; every one could sling a stone at a hair and not miss.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020017"/>
    <verse num="17">And the men of Israel, apart from Benjamin, mustered <crossref let="m" cid="c07020017.1"/>400,000 men who drew the sword; all these were men of war.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18">The people of Israel arose and went up to <crossref let="o" cid="c07020018.1"/>Bethel and inquired of God, <crossref let="p" cid="c07020018.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07020018.1" from="07020018.1" to="07020018.2"/>Who shall go up first for us to fight against the people of Benjamin?<q class="end-double" qid="07020018.2" from="07020018.1" to="07020018.2"/> And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said, <crossref let="p" cid="c07020018.3"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07020018.3" from="07020018.3" to="07020018.4"/>Judah shall go up first.<q class="end-double" qid="07020018.4" from="07020018.3" to="07020018.4"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19">Then the people of Israel rose in the morning and encamped against Gibeah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020020"/>
    <verse num="20">And the men of Israel went out to fight against Benjamin, and the men of Israel drew up the battle line against them at Gibeah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020021"/>
    <verse num="21"><crossref let="q" cid="c07020021.1"/>The people of Benjamin came out of Gibeah and destroyed on that day 22,000 men of the Israelites.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020022"/>
    <verse num="22">But the people, the men of Israel, took courage, and again formed the battle line in the same place where they had formed it on the first day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020023"/>
    <verse num="23"><crossref let="r" cid="c07020023.1"/>And the people of Israel went up and wept before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> until the evening. And they inquired of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <q class="begin-double" qid="07020023.1" from="07020023.1" to="07020023.2"/>Shall we again draw near to fight against our brothers, the people of Benjamin?<q class="end-double" qid="07020023.2" from="07020023.1" to="07020023.2"/> And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07020023.3" from="07020023.3" to="07020023.4"/>Go up against them.<q class="end-double" qid="07020023.4" from="07020023.3" to="07020023.4"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020024"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24">So the people of Israel came near against the people of Benjamin the second day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020025"/>
    <verse num="25">And Benjamin <crossref let="s" cid="c07020025.1"/>went against them out of Gibeah the second day, and destroyed 18,000 men of the people of Israel. All these were men who <crossref let="t" cid="c07020025.2"/>drew the sword.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020026"/>
    <verse num="26">Then all the people of Israel, the whole army, went up and came to <crossref let="u" cid="c07020026.1"/>Bethel and wept. They sat there before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and fasted that day until evening, and offered burnt offerings and peace offerings before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020027"/>
    <verse num="27">And the people of Israel inquired of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="v" cid="c07020027.1"/>(for the ark of the covenant of God was there in those days,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020028"/>
    <verse num="28">and <crossref let="w" cid="c07020028.1"/>Phinehas the son of Eleazar, son of Aaron, <crossref let="x" cid="c07020028.2"/>ministered before it in those days), saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="07020028.1" from="07020028.1" to="07020028.2"/>Shall we go out once more to battle against our brothers, the people of Benjamin, or shall we cease?<q class="end-double" qid="07020028.2" from="07020028.1" to="07020028.2"/> And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07020028.3" from="07020028.3" to="07020028.4"/>Go up, for tomorrow I will give them into your hand.<q class="end-double" qid="07020028.4" from="07020028.3" to="07020028.4"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020029"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="y" cid="c07020029.1"/>So Israel set men in ambush around Gibeah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020030"/>
    <verse num="30">And the people of Israel went up against the people of Benjamin on the third day and set themselves in array against Gibeah, as at other times.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020031"/>
    <verse num="31">And the people of Benjamin went out against the people and were drawn away from the city. And as at other times they began to strike and kill some of the people in the highways, <crossref let="z" cid="c07020031.1"/>one of which goes up to <crossref let="a" cid="c07020031.2"/>Bethel and the other to Gibeah, and in the open country, about thirty men of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020032"/>
    <verse num="32">And the people of Benjamin said, <crossref let="b" cid="c07020032.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07020032.1" from="07020032.1" to="07020032.2"/>They are routed before us, as at the first.<q class="end-double" qid="07020032.2" from="07020032.1" to="07020032.2"/> But the people of Israel said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07020032.3" from="07020032.3" to="07020032.4"/>Let us flee and draw them away from the city to the highways.<q class="end-double" qid="07020032.4" from="07020032.3" to="07020032.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020033"/>
    <verse num="33">And all the men of Israel rose up out of their place and set themselves in array at Baal-tamar, and the men of Israel who were in ambush rushed out of their place from Maareh-geba.<note nid="n07020033.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020034"/>
    <verse num="34">And there came against Gibeah 10,000 chosen men out of all Israel, and the battle was hard, <crossref let="c" cid="c07020034.1"/>but the Benjaminites did not know that disaster was close upon them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020035"/>
    <verse num="35">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> defeated Benjamin before Israel, and the people of Israel destroyed 25,100 men of Benjamin that day. All these were men who <crossref let="d" cid="c07020035.1"/>drew the sword.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020036"/>
    <verse num="36">So the people of Benjamin saw that they were defeated.
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-paragraph/>The men of Israel gave ground to Benjamin, because they trusted the men in ambush whom they had set against Gibeah.
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020037"/>
    <verse num="37"><crossref let="e" cid="c07020037.1"/>Then the men in ambush hurried and rushed against Gibeah; the men in ambush moved out and struck all the city with the edge of the sword.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020038"/>
    <verse num="38">Now the appointed signal between the men of Israel and the men in the main ambush was that when they made a great cloud of smoke rise up out of the city</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020039"/>
    <verse num="39">the men of Israel should turn in battle. Now Benjamin had begun to strike and kill about thirty men of Israel. They said, <crossref let="f" cid="c07020039.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07020039.1" from="07020039.1" to="07020039.2"/>Surely they are defeated before us, as in the first battle.<q class="end-double" qid="07020039.2" from="07020039.1" to="07020039.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020040"/>
    <verse num="40">But when the signal began to rise out of the city in a column of smoke, the Benjaminites looked behind them, and behold, <crossref let="g" cid="c07020040.1"/>the whole of the city went up in smoke to heaven.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020041"/>
    <verse num="41">Then the men of Israel turned, and the men of Benjamin were dismayed, <crossref let="h" cid="c07020041.1"/>for they saw that disaster was close upon them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020042"/>
    <verse num="42">Therefore they turned their backs before the men of Israel in <crossref let="i" cid="c07020042.1"/>the direction of the wilderness, but the battle overtook them. And those who came out of the cities were destroying them in their midst.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020043"/>
    <verse num="43">Surrounding the Benjaminites, they pursued them and trod them down from Nohah<note nid="n07020043.1"/> as far as opposite Gibeah on the east.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020044"/>
    <verse num="44">Eighteen thousand men of Benjamin fell, all of them men of valor.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020045"/>
    <verse num="45">And they turned <crossref let="i" cid="c07020045.1"/>and fled toward the wilderness to the rock of <crossref let="j" cid="c07020045.2"/>Rimmon. Five thousand men of them were cut down in the highways. And they were pursued hard to Gidom, and 2,000 men of them were struck down.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020046"/>
    <verse num="46">So all who fell that day of Benjamin were 25,000 men who drew the sword, all of them men of valor.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020047"/>
    <verse num="47">But 600 men turned and <crossref let="i" cid="c07020047.1"/>fled toward the wilderness to the rock of <crossref let="j" cid="c07020047.2"/>Rimmon and remained at the rock of Rimmon four months.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07020048"/>
    <verse num="48">And the men of Israel turned back against the people of Benjamin and struck them with the edge of the sword, the city, men and beasts and all that they found. And all the towns that they found they set on fire.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021001"/>
  <chapter num="21">
    <heading>Wives Provided for the Tribe of Benjamin</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Now the men of Israel had sworn <crossref let="k" cid="c07021001.1"/>at Mizpah, <q class="begin-double" qid="07021001.1" from="07021001.1" to="07021001.2"/>No one of us shall give his daughter in marriage to Benjamin.<q class="end-double" qid="07021001.2" from="07021001.1" to="07021001.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021002"/>
    <verse num="2">And the people came to <crossref let="l" cid="c07021002.1"/>Bethel and sat there till evening before God, and they lifted up their voices and wept bitterly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021003"/>
    <verse num="3">And they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07021003.1" from="07021003.1" to="07021003.2"/>O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, why has this happened in Israel, that today there should be one tribe lacking in Israel?<q class="end-double" qid="07021003.2" from="07021003.1" to="07021003.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021004"/>
    <verse num="4">And the next day the people rose early and <crossref let="m" cid="c07021004.1"/>built there an altar and offered burnt offerings and peace offerings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021005"/>
    <verse num="5">And the people of Israel said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07021005.1" from="07021005.1" to="07021005.2"/>Which of all the tribes of Israel did not come up in the assembly to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>?<q class="end-double" qid="07021005.2" from="07021005.1" to="07021005.2"/> <crossref let="n" cid="c07021005.1"/>For they had taken a great oath concerning him who did not come up to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to Mizpah, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="07021005.3" from="07021005.3" to="07021005.4"/>He shall surely be put to death.<q class="end-double" qid="07021005.4" from="07021005.3" to="07021005.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021006"/>
    <verse num="6">And the people of Israel <crossref let="o" cid="c07021006.1"/>had compassion for Benjamin their brother and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07021006.1" from="07021006.1" to="07021007.1"/>One tribe is cut off from Israel this day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="p" cid="c07021007.1"/>What shall we do for wives for those who are left, since we have sworn by the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> that we will not give them any of our daughters for wives?<q class="end-double" qid="07021007.1" from="07021006.1" to="07021007.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">And they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07021008.1" from="07021008.1" to="07021008.2"/>What one is there of the tribes of Israel that did not come up to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to Mizpah?<q class="end-double" qid="07021008.2" from="07021008.1" to="07021008.2"/> And behold, no one had come to the camp from <crossref let="q" cid="c07021008.1"/>Jabesh-gilead, to the assembly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021009"/>
    <verse num="9">For when the people were mustered, behold, not one of the inhabitants of <crossref let="q" cid="c07021009.1"/>Jabesh-gilead was there.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021010"/>
    <verse num="10">So the congregation sent 12,000 of their bravest men there and commanded them, <crossref let="r" cid="c07021010.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07021010.1" from="07021010.1" to="07021011.1"/>Go and strike the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead with the edge of the sword; also the women and the little ones.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021011"/>
    <verse num="11">This is what you shall do: <crossref let="s" cid="c07021011.1"/>every male and every woman that has lain with a male you shall devote to destruction.<q class="end-double" qid="07021011.1" from="07021010.1" to="07021011.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021012"/>
    <verse num="12">And they found among the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead 400 young virgins who had not known a man by lying with him, and they brought them to the camp at <crossref let="t" cid="c07021012.1"/>Shiloh, which is in the land of Canaan.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">Then the whole congregation sent word to the people of Benjamin who were at the <crossref let="u" cid="c07021013.1"/>rock of Rimmon and <crossref let="v" cid="c07021013.2"/>proclaimed peace to them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021014"/>
    <verse num="14">And Benjamin returned at that time. And they gave them the women whom they had saved alive of the women of Jabesh-gilead, but they were not enough for them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021015"/>
    <verse num="15">And the people <crossref let="w" cid="c07021015.1"/>had compassion on Benjamin because the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had made a breach in the tribes of Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">Then the elders of the congregation said, <crossref let="x" cid="c07021016.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="07021016.1" from="07021016.1" to="07021016.2"/>What shall we do for wives for those who are left, since the women are destroyed out of Benjamin?<q class="end-double" qid="07021016.2" from="07021016.1" to="07021016.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021017"/>
    <verse num="17">And they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07021017.1" from="07021017.1" to="07021018.1"/>There must be an inheritance for the survivors of Benjamin, that a tribe not be blotted out from Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021018"/>
    <verse num="18">Yet we cannot give them wives from our daughters.<q class="end-double" qid="07021018.1" from="07021017.1" to="07021018.1"/> <crossref let="y" cid="c07021018.1"/>For the people of Israel had sworn, <q class="begin-double" qid="07021018.2" from="07021018.2" to="07021018.3"/>Cursed be he who gives a wife to Benjamin.<q class="end-double" qid="07021018.3" from="07021018.2" to="07021018.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021019"/>
    <verse num="19">So they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="07021019.1" from="07021019.1" to="07021019.2"/>Behold, there is the yearly feast of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> at Shiloh, which is north of Bethel, on the east of <crossref let="z" cid="c07021019.1"/>the highway that goes up from Bethel to Shechem, and south of Lebonah.<q class="end-double" qid="07021019.2" from="07021019.1" to="07021019.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021020"/>
    <verse num="20">And they commanded the people of Benjamin, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="07021020.1" from="07021020.1" to="07021022.3"/>Go and lie in ambush in the vineyards</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021021"/>
    <verse num="21">and watch. If the daughters of Shiloh come out to <crossref let="a" cid="c07021021.1"/>dance in the dances, then come out of the vineyards and snatch each man his wife from the daughters of Shiloh, and go to the land of Benjamin.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021022"/>
    <verse num="22">And when their fathers or their brothers come to complain to us, we will say to them, <q class="begin-single" qid="07021022.1" from="07021022.1" to="07021022.2"/>Grant them graciously to us, because we did not take for each man of them his wife in battle, neither did you give them to them, else you would now be guilty.<q class="end-single" qid="07021022.2" from="07021022.1" to="07021022.2"/><q class="end-double" qid="07021022.3" from="07021020.1" to="07021022.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021023"/>
    <verse num="23">And the people of Benjamin did so and took their wives, according to their number, from the dancers whom they carried off. Then they went and returned to their inheritance <crossref let="b" cid="c07021023.1"/>and rebuilt the towns and lived in them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021024"/>
    <verse num="24">And the people of Israel departed from there at that time, every man to his tribe and family, and they went out from there every man to his inheritance.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v07021025"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="25"><crossref let="c" cid="c07021025.1"/>In those days there was no king in Israel. Everyone did what was right in his own eyes.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
</book>
</crossway-bible>
