<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible translation="English Standard Version" revision="2025-02-02" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
<book title="2 Chronicles" num="14">
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001001"/>
  <chapter num="1">
    <heading>Solomon Worships at Gibeon</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="a" cid="c14001001.1"/>Solomon the son of David established himself in his kingdom, <crossref let="b" cid="c14001001.2"/>and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God was with him and made him exceedingly great.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001002"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="2">Solomon spoke to all Israel, to the <crossref let="c" cid="c14001002.1"/>commanders of thousands and of hundreds, to the judges, and to all the leaders in all Israel, the heads of fathers&apos; houses.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001003"/>
    <verse num="3">And Solomon, and all the assembly with him, went to <crossref let="d" cid="c14001003.1"/>the high place that was at Gibeon, <crossref let="e" cid="c14001003.2"/>for <crossref let="f" cid="c14001003.3"/>the tent of meeting of God, which Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had made in the wilderness, was there.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="g" cid="c14001004.1"/>(But David had brought up the ark of God from Kiriath-jearim to the place that David had prepared for it, for he had pitched a tent for it in Jerusalem.)</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001005"/>
    <verse num="5">Moreover, <crossref let="h" cid="c14001005.1"/>the bronze altar that <crossref let="i" cid="c14001005.2"/>Bezalel the son of Uri, son of Hur, had made, was there before the tabernacle of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. And Solomon and the assembly <crossref let="j" cid="c14001005.3"/>sought it<note nid="n14001005.1"/> out.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001006"/>
    <verse num="6">And Solomon went up there to the bronze altar before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, which was at the tent of meeting, <crossref let="k" cid="c14001006.1"/>and offered a thousand burnt offerings on it.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001007"/>
    <heading>Solomon Prays for Wisdom</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="l" cid="c14001007.1"/>In that night God appeared to Solomon, and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="14001007.1" from="14001007.1" to="14001007.2"/>Ask what I shall give you.<q class="end-double" qid="14001007.2" from="14001007.1" to="14001007.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001008"/>
    <verse num="8">And Solomon said to God, <q class="begin-double" qid="14001008.1" from="14001008.1" to="14001010.1"/>You have shown great and steadfast love to David my father, <crossref let="m" cid="c14001008.1"/>and have made me king in his place.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001009"/>
    <verse num="9">O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God, <crossref let="n" cid="c14001009.1"/>let your word to David my father be now fulfilled, for you have made me king over a people as numerous <crossref let="o" cid="c14001009.2"/>as the dust of the earth.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001010"/>
    <verse num="10">Give me now wisdom and knowledge to <crossref let="p" cid="c14001010.1"/>go out and come in before this people, for who can govern this people of yours, which is so great?<q class="end-double" qid="14001010.1" from="14001008.1" to="14001010.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001011"/>
    <verse num="11">God answered Solomon, <q class="begin-double" qid="14001011.1" from="14001011.1" to="14001012.1"/>Because this was in your heart, and you have not asked for <crossref let="q" cid="c14001011.1"/>possessions, wealth, honor, or the life of those who hate you, and have not even asked for long life, but have asked for wisdom and knowledge for yourself that you may govern my people over whom I have made you king,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001012"/>
    <verse num="12">wisdom and knowledge are granted to you. I will also give you <crossref let="q" cid="c14001012.1"/>riches, possessions, and honor, <crossref let="r" cid="c14001012.2"/>such as none of the kings had who were before you, and none after you shall have the like.<q class="end-double" qid="14001012.1" from="14001011.1" to="14001012.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001013"/>
    <verse num="13">So Solomon came from<note nid="n14001013.1"/> the <crossref let="s" cid="c14001013.1"/>high place at Gibeon, from before <crossref let="t" cid="c14001013.2"/>the tent of meeting, to Jerusalem. And he reigned over Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001014"/>
    <heading>Solomon Given Wealth</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="u" cid="c14001014.1"/>Solomon gathered together chariots and horsemen. <crossref let="v" cid="c14001014.2"/>He had 1,400 chariots and 12,000 horsemen, whom he stationed <crossref let="w" cid="c14001014.3"/>in the chariot cities and with the king in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001015"/>
    <verse num="15">And the king made silver and gold as common in Jerusalem as stone, and he made cedar as plentiful as the sycamore of the Shephelah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001016"/>
    <verse num="16">And Solomon&apos;s import of horses was from Egypt and Kue, and the king&apos;s traders would buy them from Kue for a price.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14001017"/>
    <verse num="17">They imported a chariot from Egypt for 600 shekels<note nid="n14001017.1"/> of silver, and a horse for 150. Likewise through them these were exported to all the kings of the Hittites and the kings of Syria.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002001"/>
  <chapter num="2">
    <heading>Preparing to Build the Temple</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><note nid="n14002001.1"/> <crossref let="x" cid="c14002001.1"/>Now Solomon purposed to build a temple for the name of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and a royal palace for himself.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002002"/>
    <verse num="2"><note nid="n14002002.1"/> <crossref let="y" cid="c14002002.1"/>And Solomon assigned 70,000 men to bear burdens and 80,000 to quarry in the hill country, and <crossref let="z" cid="c14002002.2"/>3,600 to oversee them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002003"/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="a" cid="c14002003.1"/>And Solomon sent word to Hiram the king of Tyre: <crossref let="b" cid="c14002003.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14002003.1" from="14002003.1" to="14002010.1"/>As you dealt with David my father and sent him cedar to build himself a house to dwell in, so deal with me.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002004"/>
    <verse num="4">Behold, I am about to build a house for the name of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> my God and dedicate it to him for the burning of <crossref let="c" cid="c14002004.1"/>incense of sweet spices before him, and for <crossref let="d" cid="c14002004.2"/>the regular arrangement of the showbread, and for <crossref let="e" cid="c14002004.3"/>burnt offerings morning and evening, <crossref let="f" cid="c14002004.4"/>on the Sabbaths and the new moons and the appointed feasts of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God, as ordained forever for Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002005"/>
    <verse num="5">The house that I am to build will be great, <crossref let="g" cid="c14002005.1"/>for our God is greater than all gods.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="h" cid="c14002006.1"/>But who is able to build him a house, since <crossref let="h" cid="c14002006.2"/>heaven, even highest heaven, cannot contain him? Who am I to build a house for him, except as a place to make offerings before him?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002007"/>
    <verse num="7">So now <crossref let="i" cid="c14002007.1"/>send me a man skilled to work in gold, silver, bronze, and iron, and in purple, crimson, and blue fabrics, trained also in engraving, to be with the skilled workers who are with me in Judah and Jerusalem, <crossref let="j" cid="c14002007.2"/>whom David my father provided.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002008"/>
    <verse num="8">Send me also cedar, cypress, and algum timber from Lebanon, for I know that <crossref let="k" cid="c14002008.1"/>your servants know how to cut timber in Lebanon. And my servants will be with your servants,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002009"/>
    <verse num="9">to prepare timber for me in abundance, for the house I am to build will be great and wonderful.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="l" cid="c14002010.1"/>I will give for your servants, the woodsmen who cut timber, 20,000 cors<note nid="n14002010.1"/> of crushed wheat, 20,000 cors of barley, 20,000 baths<note nid="n14002010.2"/> of wine, and 20,000 baths of oil.<q class="end-double" qid="14002010.1" from="14002003.1" to="14002010.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11">Then Hiram the king of Tyre answered in a letter that he sent to Solomon, <crossref let="m" cid="c14002011.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14002011.1" from="14002011.1" to="14002011.2"/>Because the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> loves his people, he has made you king over them.<q class="end-double" qid="14002011.2" from="14002011.1" to="14002011.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002012"/>
    <verse num="12">Hiram also said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14002012.1" from="14002012.1" to="14002016.1"/>Blessed be the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God of Israel, <crossref let="n" cid="c14002012.1"/>who made heaven and earth, who has given King David a wise son, who has discretion and understanding, <crossref let="o" cid="c14002012.2"/>who will build a temple for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and a royal palace for himself.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13"><q class="continue-double" qid="14002013.1" from="14002012.1" to="14002016.1"/>Now I have sent a skilled man, who has understanding, Huram-abi,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002014"/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="p" cid="c14002014.1"/>the son of a woman of the daughters of Dan, and his father was a man of Tyre. He is <crossref let="q" cid="c14002014.2"/>trained to work in gold, silver, bronze, iron, stone, and wood, and in purple, blue, and crimson fabrics and fine linen, and to do all sorts of engraving and execute any design that may be assigned him, with your craftsmen, the craftsmen of my lord, David your father.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002015"/>
    <verse num="15">Now therefore the wheat and barley, oil and wine, <crossref let="r" cid="c14002015.1"/>of which my lord has spoken, let him send to his servants.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002016"/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="s" cid="c14002016.1"/>And we will cut whatever timber you need from Lebanon and bring it to you in rafts by sea to <crossref let="t" cid="c14002016.2"/>Joppa, so that you may take it up to Jerusalem.<q class="end-double" qid="14002016.1" from="14002012.1" to="14002016.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002017"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17">Then Solomon counted all the resident aliens who were in the land of Israel, <crossref let="u" cid="c14002017.1"/>after the census of them that David his father had taken, and there were found 153,600.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14002018"/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="v" cid="c14002018.1"/>Seventy thousand of them he assigned to bear burdens, 80,000 to quarry in the hill country, and 3,600 as overseers to make the people work.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003001"/>
  <chapter num="3">
    <heading>Solomon Builds the Temple</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="w" cid="c14003001.1"/>Then Solomon began to build the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in Jerusalem <crossref let="x" cid="c14003001.2"/>on Mount Moriah, where the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span><note nid="n14003001.1"/> had appeared to David his father, at the place that David had appointed, <crossref let="y" cid="c14003001.3"/>on the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003002"/>
    <verse num="2">He began to build in the second month of the fourth year of his reign.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003003"/>
    <verse num="3">These are Solomon&apos;s <crossref let="z" cid="c14003003.1"/>measurements<note nid="n14003003.1"/> for building the house of God: <crossref let="a" cid="c14003003.2"/>the length, in cubits<note nid="n14003003.2"/> of the old standard, was sixty cubits, and the breadth twenty cubits.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003004"/>
    <verse num="4">The vestibule in front of the nave of the house was twenty cubits long, equal to the width of the house,<note nid="n14003004.1"/> and its height was 120 cubits. He overlaid it on the inside with pure gold.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003005"/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="b" cid="c14003005.1"/>The nave he lined with cypress and covered it with fine gold <crossref let="c" cid="c14003005.2"/>and made palms and chains on it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003006"/>
    <verse num="6">He adorned the house with settings of precious stones. The gold was gold of Parvaim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003007"/>
    <verse num="7">So he lined the house with gold&emdash;its beams, its thresholds, its walls, and its doors&emdash;<crossref let="c" cid="c14003007.1"/>and he carved cherubim on the walls.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="d" cid="c14003008.1"/>And he made the Most Holy Place. Its length, corresponding to the breadth of the house, was twenty cubits, and its breadth was twenty cubits. He overlaid it with 600 talents<note nid="n14003008.1"/> of fine gold.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003009"/>
    <verse num="9">The weight of gold for the nails was fifty shekels.<note nid="n14003009.1"/> And he overlaid <crossref let="e" cid="c14003009.1"/>the upper chambers with gold.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="f" cid="c14003010.1"/>In the Most Holy Place he made two cherubim of wood<note nid="n14003010.1"/> and overlaid<note nid="n14003010.2"/> them with gold.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003011"/>
    <verse num="11">The wings of the cherubim together extended twenty cubits: one wing of the one, of five cubits, touched the wall of the house, and its other wing, of five cubits, touched the wing of the other cherub;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003012"/>
    <verse num="12">and of this cherub, one wing, of five cubits, touched the wall of the house, and the other wing, also of five cubits, was joined to the wing of the first cherub.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003013"/>
    <verse num="13">The wings of these cherubim extended twenty cubits. The cherubim<note nid="n14003013.1"/> stood on their feet, <crossref let="g" cid="c14003013.1"/>facing the nave.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003014"/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="h" cid="c14003014.1"/>And he made the veil of blue and purple and crimson fabrics and fine linen, and he worked cherubim on it.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="i" cid="c14003015.1"/>In front of the house he made two pillars thirty-five cubits high, with a capital of five cubits on the top of each.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003016"/>
    <verse num="16">He made chains like a necklace<note nid="n14003016.1"/> and put them on the tops of the pillars, and he made a hundred pomegranates and put them on the chains.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14003017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="j" cid="c14003017.1"/>He set up the pillars in front of the temple, one on the south, the other on the north; that on the south he called Jachin, and that on the north Boaz.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004001"/>
  <chapter num="4">
    <heading>The Temple&apos;s Furnishings</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">He made <crossref let="k" cid="c14004001.1"/>an altar of bronze, twenty cubits<note nid="n14004001.1"/> long and twenty cubits wide and ten cubits high.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="l" cid="c14004002.1"/>Then he made the sea of cast metal. It was round, ten cubits from brim to brim, and five cubits high, and a line of thirty cubits measured its circumference.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004003"/>
    <verse num="3">Under it were figures of gourds,<note nid="n14004003.1"/> for ten cubits, compassing the sea all around. The gourds were in two rows, cast with it when it was cast.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004004"/>
    <verse num="4">It stood on twelve oxen, three facing north, three facing west, three facing south, and three facing east. The sea was set on them, and all their rear parts were inward.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004005"/>
    <verse num="5">Its thickness was a handbreadth.<note nid="n14004005.1"/> And its brim was made like the brim of a cup, like the flower of a lily. <crossref let="m" cid="c14004005.1"/>It held 3,000 baths.<note nid="n14004005.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="n" cid="c14004006.1"/>He also made ten basins in which to wash, and set five on the south side, and five on the north side. In these they were to rinse off what was used for the burnt offering, and the sea was for the priests to wash in.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">And he made ten golden lampstands <crossref let="o" cid="c14004007.1"/>as prescribed, and set them in the temple, five on the south side and five on the north.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="p" cid="c14004008.1"/>He also made ten tables and placed them in the temple, five on the south side and five on the north. And he made a hundred basins of gold.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004009"/>
    <verse num="9">He made <crossref let="q" cid="c14004009.1"/>the court of the priests <crossref let="r" cid="c14004009.2"/>and the great court and doors for the court and overlaid their doors with bronze.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="s" cid="c14004010.1"/>And he set the sea at the southeast corner of the house.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11"><crossrefs><crossref let="t" cid="c14004011.1"/><crossref let="u" cid="c14004011.2"/></crossrefs>Hiram also made the pots, the shovels, and the basins. <crossref let="u" cid="c14004011.3"/>So Hiram finished the work that he did for King Solomon on the house of God:</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004012"/>
    <verse num="12">the two pillars, <crossref let="v" cid="c14004012.1"/>the bowls, and the two capitals on the top of the pillars; and the two latticeworks to cover the two bowls of the capitals that were on the top of the pillars;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="w" cid="c14004013.1"/>and the 400 pomegranates for the two latticeworks, two rows of pomegranates for each latticework, to cover the two bowls of the capitals that were on the pillars.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004014"/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="n" cid="c14004014.1"/>He made the stands also, and the basins on the stands,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004015"/>
    <verse num="15">and the one sea, and the twelve oxen underneath it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004016"/>
    <verse num="16">The pots, the shovels, <crossref let="x" cid="c14004016.1"/>the forks, and all the equipment for these <crossrefs><crossref let="t" cid="c14004016.2"/><crossref let="y" cid="c14004016.3"/></crossrefs>Huram-abi made of burnished bronze for King Solomon for the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004017"/>
    <verse num="17">In the plain of the Jordan the king cast them, in the clay ground between Succoth and Zeredah.<note nid="n14004017.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004018"/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="z" cid="c14004018.1"/>Solomon made all these things in great quantities, for the weight of the bronze was not sought.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19">So Solomon made all the vessels that were in the house of God: the golden altar, <crossref let="a" cid="c14004019.1"/>the tables for the bread of the Presence,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004020"/>
    <verse num="20">the lampstands and their lamps of pure gold <crossref let="b" cid="c14004020.1"/>to burn before the inner sanctuary, as prescribed;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004021"/>
    <verse num="21">the flowers, the lamps, and the tongs, of purest gold;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14004022"/>
    <verse num="22">the snuffers, basins, dishes for incense, and fire pans, of pure gold, and the sockets<note nid="n14004022.1"/> of the temple, for the inner doors to the Most Holy Place and for the doors of the nave of the temple were of gold.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005001"/>
  <chapter num="5">
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="c" cid="c14005001.1"/>Thus all the work that Solomon did for the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was finished. And Solomon brought in the things that David his father had dedicated, and stored the silver, the gold, and all the vessels in the treasuries of the house of God.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005002"/>
    <heading>The Ark Brought to the Temple</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="2">Then Solomon assembled the elders of Israel and all the heads of the tribes, the leaders of the fathers&apos; houses of the people of Israel, in Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of the covenant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> out of <crossref let="d" cid="c14005002.1"/>the city of David, which is Zion.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005003"/>
    <verse num="3">And all the men of Israel assembled before the king at the feast that is in the seventh month.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005004"/>
    <verse num="4">And all the elders of Israel came, <crossref let="e" cid="c14005004.1"/>and the Levites took up the ark.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005005"/>
    <verse num="5">And they brought up the ark, the tent of meeting, and all the holy vessels that were in the tent; <crossref let="f" cid="c14005005.1"/>the Levitical priests brought them up.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005006"/>
    <verse num="6">And King Solomon and all the congregation of Israel, who had assembled before him, were before the ark, sacrificing so many sheep and oxen that they could not be counted or numbered.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005007"/>
    <verse num="7">Then the priests brought the ark of the covenant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to its place, in the inner sanctuary of the house, in the Most Holy Place, underneath the wings of the cherubim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005008"/>
    <verse num="8">The cherubim spread out their wings over the place of the ark, so that the cherubim made a covering above the ark and its poles.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005009"/>
    <verse num="9">And the poles were so long that the ends of the poles were seen <crossref let="g" cid="c14005009.1"/>from the Holy Place before the inner sanctuary, but they could not be seen from outside. And they are<note nid="n14005009.1"/> there to this day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005010"/>
    <verse num="10">There was nothing in the ark except the two tablets <crossref let="h" cid="c14005010.1"/>that Moses put there at Horeb, where the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> made a covenant with the people of Israel, when they came out of Egypt.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005011"/>
    <verse num="11">And when the priests came out of the Holy Place (for all the priests who were present had consecrated themselves, without regard to <crossref let="i" cid="c14005011.1"/>their divisions,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005012"/>
    <verse num="12">and all the Levitical <crossref let="j" cid="c14005012.1"/>singers, <crossref let="k" cid="c14005012.2"/>Asaph, <crossref let="l" cid="c14005012.3"/>Heman, and Jeduthun, their sons and kinsmen, arrayed in fine linen, with <crossref let="m" cid="c14005012.4"/>cymbals, harps, and lyres, stood east of the altar with 120 <crossref let="n" cid="c14005012.5"/>priests who were trumpeters;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005013"/>
    <verse num="13">and it was the duty of the trumpeters and singers to make themselves heard in unison in praise and thanksgiving to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>), and when the song was raised, <crossref let="o" cid="c14005013.1"/>with trumpets and cymbals and other musical instruments, in praise to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
        <begin-line/><crossref let="p" cid="c14005013.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14005013.1" from="14005013.1" to="14005013.2"/>For he is good,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>for his steadfast love endures forever,<q class="end-double" qid="14005013.2" from="14005013.1" to="14005013.2"/><end-line/>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/>the house, the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, was filled with a cloud,
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14005014"/>
    <verse num="14">so that the priests could not stand to minister because of the cloud, <crossref let="q" cid="c14005014.1"/>for the glory of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> filled the house of God.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006001"/>
  <chapter num="6">
    <heading>Solomon Blesses the People</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="r" cid="c14006001.1"/>Then Solomon said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14006001.1" from="14006001.1" to="14006002.1"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has said that he would dwell in thick darkness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006002"/>
    <verse num="2">But I have built you <crossref let="s" cid="c14006002.1"/>an exalted house, a place for you to dwell in forever.<q class="end-double" qid="14006002.1" from="14006001.1" to="14006002.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006003"/>
    <verse num="3">Then the king turned around and blessed all the assembly of Israel, while all the assembly of Israel stood.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006004"/>
    <verse num="4">And he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14006004.1" from="14006004.1" to="14006011.1"/>Blessed be the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, who with his hand has fulfilled what he promised with his mouth to David my father, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006005"/>
    <verse num="5"><q class="begin-single" qid="14006005.1" from="14006005.1" to="14006006.1"/>Since the day that I brought my people out of the land of Egypt, I chose no city out of all the tribes of Israel in which to build a house, that my name might be there, and I chose no man as prince over my people Israel;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="t" cid="c14006006.1"/>but I have chosen Jerusalem that my name may be there, <crossref let="u" cid="c14006006.2"/>and I have chosen David to be over my people Israel.<q class="end-single" qid="14006006.1" from="14006005.1" to="14006006.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="v" cid="c14006007.1"/>Now it was in the heart of David my father to build a house for the name of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006008"/>
    <verse num="8">But the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to David my father, <q class="begin-single" qid="14006008.1" from="14006008.1" to="14006009.1"/>Whereas <crossref let="v" cid="c14006008.1"/>it was in your heart to build a house for my name, you did well that it was in your heart.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006009"/>
    <verse num="9">Nevertheless, it is not you who shall build the house, but your son who shall be born to you shall build the house for my name.<q class="end-single" qid="14006009.1" from="14006008.1" to="14006009.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006010"/>
    <verse num="10">Now the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has fulfilled his promise that he made. For I have risen in the place of David my father and sit on the throne of Israel, as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> promised, and I have built the house for the name of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006011"/>
    <verse num="11">And there I have set the ark, <crossref let="w" cid="c14006011.1"/>in which is the covenant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> that he made with the people of Israel.<q class="end-double" qid="14006011.1" from="14006004.1" to="14006011.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006012"/>
    <heading>Solomon&apos;s Prayer of Dedication</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">Then Solomon stood before the altar of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in the presence of all the assembly of Israel and spread out his hands.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="x" cid="c14006013.1"/>Solomon had made a bronze platform five cubits<note nid="n14006013.1"/> long, five cubits wide, and three cubits high, and had set it in the court, and he stood on it. <crossref let="y" cid="c14006013.2"/>Then he knelt on his knees in the presence of all the assembly of Israel, and spread out his hands toward heaven,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006014"/>
    <verse num="14">and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14006014.1" from="14006014.1" to="14006042.1"/>O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, God of Israel, <crossref let="z" cid="c14006014.1"/>there is no God like you, in heaven or on earth, <crossref let="a" cid="c14006014.2"/>keeping covenant and showing steadfast love to your servants who walk before you with all their heart,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="b" cid="c14006015.1"/>who have kept with your servant David my father what you declared to him. You spoke with your mouth, and with your hand have fulfilled it this day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006016"/>
    <verse num="16">Now therefore, O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, God of Israel, keep for your servant David my father what you have promised him, saying, <crossref let="c" cid="c14006016.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="14006016.1" from="14006016.1" to="14006016.2"/>You shall not lack a man to sit before me on the throne of Israel, <crossref let="d" cid="c14006016.2"/>if only your sons pay close attention to their way, to walk in my law as you have walked before me.<q class="end-single" qid="14006016.2" from="14006016.1" to="14006016.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006017"/>
    <verse num="17">Now therefore, O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, God of Israel, let your word be confirmed, which you have spoken to your servant David.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18"><q class="continue-double" qid="14006018.1" from="14006014.1" to="14006042.1"/>But will God indeed dwell with man on the earth? Behold, <crossref let="e" cid="c14006018.1"/>heaven and the highest heaven cannot contain you, how much less this house that I have built!</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006019"/>
    <verse num="19">Yet have regard to the prayer of your servant and to his plea, O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> my God, listening to the cry and to the prayer that your servant prays before you,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="f" cid="c14006020.1"/>that your eyes may be open day and night toward this house, the place where you have promised to set your name, that you may listen to the prayer that your servant offers toward this place.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006021"/>
    <verse num="21">And listen to the pleas of your servant and of your people Israel, when they pray toward this place. And listen from heaven your dwelling place, <crossref let="g" cid="c14006021.1"/>and when you hear, forgive.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22"><q class="continue-double" qid="14006022.1" from="14006014.1" to="14006042.1"/>If a man sins against his neighbor and is made to take an oath and comes and swears his oath before your altar in this house,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006023"/>
    <verse num="23">then hear from heaven and act and judge your servants, repaying the guilty by bringing his conduct on his own head, and vindicating the righteous by rewarding him according to his righteousness.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006024"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24"><q class="continue-double" qid="14006024.1" from="14006014.1" to="14006042.1"/>If your people Israel are defeated before the enemy because they have sinned against you, and they turn again and acknowledge your name and pray and plead with you in this house,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006025"/>
    <verse num="25"><crossref let="g" cid="c14006025.1"/>then hear from heaven and forgive the sin of your people Israel and bring them again to the land that you gave to them and to their fathers.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006026"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="26"><crossref let="h" cid="c14006026.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="14006026.1" from="14006014.1" to="14006042.1"/>When heaven is shut up and there is no rain because they have sinned against you, if they pray toward this place and acknowledge your name and turn from their sin, when you afflict<note nid="n14006026.1"/> them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006027"/>
    <verse num="27"><crossref let="g" cid="c14006027.1"/>then hear in heaven and forgive the sin of your servants, your people Israel, when you teach them the good way<note nid="n14006027.1"/> in which they should walk, and grant rain upon your land, which you have given to your people as an inheritance.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006028"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="28"><crossref let="i" cid="c14006028.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="14006028.1" from="14006014.1" to="14006042.1"/>If there is famine in the land, if there is pestilence or blight or mildew or locust or caterpillar, if their enemies besiege them in the land at their gates, whatever plague, whatever sickness there is,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006029"/>
    <verse num="29">whatever prayer, whatever plea is made by any man or by all your people Israel, each knowing his own affliction and his own sorrow and stretching out his hands toward this house,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006030"/>
    <verse num="30"><crossref let="g" cid="c14006030.1"/>then hear from heaven your dwelling place and forgive and render to each whose heart you know, according to all his ways, <crossref let="j" cid="c14006030.2"/>for you, you only, know the hearts of the children of mankind,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006031"/>
    <verse num="31">that they may fear you and walk in your ways all the days that they live in the land that you gave to our fathers.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006032"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="32"><q class="continue-double" qid="14006032.1" from="14006014.1" to="14006042.1"/>Likewise, when a foreigner, who is not of your people Israel, comes from a far country for the sake of your great name and your mighty hand and your outstretched arm, when he comes and prays toward this house,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006033"/>
    <verse num="33">hear from heaven your dwelling place and do according to all for which the foreigner calls to you, in order that all the peoples of the earth may know your name and fear you, as do your people Israel, and that they may know that this house <crossref let="k" cid="c14006033.1"/>that I have built is called by your name.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006034"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="34"><q class="continue-double" qid="14006034.1" from="14006014.1" to="14006042.1"/>If your people go out to battle against their enemies, by whatever way you shall send them, and they pray to you toward this city that you have chosen and the house that I have built for your name,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006035"/>
    <verse num="35">then hear from heaven their prayer and their plea, and maintain their cause.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006036"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="36"><q class="continue-double" qid="14006036.1" from="14006014.1" to="14006042.1"/>If they sin against you&emdash;<crossref let="l" cid="c14006036.1"/>for there is no one who does not sin&emdash;and you are angry with them and give them to an enemy, so that they are carried away captive to a land far or near,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006037"/>
    <verse num="37">yet if they turn their heart in the land to which they have been carried captive, and repent and plead with you in the land of their captivity, saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="14006037.1" from="14006037.1" to="14006037.2"/>We have sinned and have acted perversely and wickedly,<q class="end-single" qid="14006037.2" from="14006037.1" to="14006037.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006038"/>
    <verse num="38">if they repent with all their heart and with all their soul in the land of their captivity to which they were carried captive, and pray toward their land, which you gave to their fathers, the city that you have chosen and the house that I have built for your name,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006039"/>
    <verse num="39">then hear from heaven your dwelling place their prayer and their pleas, and maintain their cause and forgive your people who have sinned against you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006040"/>
    <verse num="40">Now, O my God, <crossref let="m" cid="c14006040.1"/>let your eyes be open <crossref let="n" cid="c14006040.2"/>and your ears attentive to the prayer of this place.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006041"/>
    <begin-block-indent/>
    <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
    <verse num="41">
        <begin-line/><q class="continue-double" qid="14006041.1" from="14006014.1" to="14006042.1"/>And now arise, O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God, and go to your <crossref let="o" cid="c14006041.1"/>resting place,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>you and the ark of your might.<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>Let your priests, O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God, be <crossref let="p" cid="c14006041.2"/>clothed with salvation,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>and let your saints <crossref let="q" cid="c14006041.3"/>rejoice in your goodness.<end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14006042"/>
    <verse num="42">
        <begin-line/>O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God, <crossref let="r" cid="c14006042.1"/>do not turn away the face of your anointed one!<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/><crossref let="s" cid="c14006042.2"/>Remember your steadfast love for David your servant.<q class="end-double" qid="14006042.1" from="14006014.1" to="14006042.1"/><end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <end-block-indent/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007001"/>
  <chapter num="7">
    <heading>Fire from Heaven</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="t" cid="c14007001.1"/>As soon as Solomon finished his prayer, <crossref let="u" cid="c14007001.2"/>fire came down from heaven and consumed the burnt offering and the sacrifices, <crossref let="v" cid="c14007001.3"/>and the glory of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> filled the temple.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007002"/>
    <verse num="2">And the priests could not enter the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, because the glory of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> filled the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s house.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007003"/>
    <verse num="3">When all the people of Israel saw the fire come down and the glory of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> on the temple, they bowed down with their faces to the ground on the pavement and worshiped and gave thanks to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="14007003.1" from="14007003.1" to="14007003.2"/>For he is good, <crossref let="w" cid="c14007003.1"/>for his steadfast love endures forever.<q class="end-double" qid="14007003.2" from="14007003.1" to="14007003.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007004"/>
    <heading>The Dedication of the Temple</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="x" cid="c14007004.1"/>Then the king and all the people offered sacrifice before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007005"/>
    <verse num="5">King Solomon offered as a sacrifice 22,000 oxen and 120,000 sheep. So the king and all the people dedicated the house of God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007006"/>
    <verse num="6">The priests stood at their posts; <crossref let="y" cid="c14007006.1"/>the Levites also, with the instruments for music to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> that King David had made for giving thanks to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&emdash;<crossref let="w" cid="c14007006.2"/>for his steadfast love endures forever&emdash;whenever David offered praises by their ministry;<note nid="n14007006.1"/> <crossref let="z" cid="c14007006.3"/>opposite them the priests sounded trumpets, and all Israel stood.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="a" cid="c14007007.1"/>And Solomon consecrated the middle of the court that was before the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, for there he offered the burnt offering and the fat of the peace offerings, because the bronze altar Solomon had made could not hold the burnt offering and the grain offering and the fat.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">At that time Solomon held the feast for seven days, and all Israel with him, a very great assembly, from <crossref let="b" cid="c14007008.1"/>Lebo-hamath to the <crossref let="c" cid="c14007008.2"/>Brook of Egypt.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007009"/>
    <verse num="9">And on the eighth day they held a solemn assembly, for they had kept the dedication of the altar seven days and the feast seven days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007010"/>
    <verse num="10">On the twenty-third day of the seventh month he sent the people away to their homes, joyful and glad of heart for the prosperity<note nid="n14007010.1"/> that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had granted to David and to Solomon and to Israel his people.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007011"/>
    <heading>If My People Pray</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="d" cid="c14007011.1"/>Thus Solomon finished the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and the king&apos;s house. All that Solomon had planned to do in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and in his own house he successfully accomplished.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007012"/>
    <verse num="12">Then the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> appeared to Solomon in the night and said to him: <q class="begin-double" qid="14007012.1" from="14007012.1" to="14007022.3"/>I have heard your prayer <crossref let="e" cid="c14007012.1"/>and have chosen this place for myself as a house of sacrifice.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="f" cid="c14007013.1"/>When I shut up the heavens so that there is no rain, or command the locust to devour the land, or send pestilence among my people,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007014"/>
    <verse num="14">if my people who are called by my name <crossref let="g" cid="c14007014.1"/>humble themselves, and pray and seek my face and turn from their wicked ways, then I will hear from heaven and will forgive their sin and heal their land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="h" cid="c14007015.1"/>Now my eyes will be open and my ears attentive to the prayer that is made in this place.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007016"/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="e" cid="c14007016.1"/>For now I have chosen and consecrated this house that my name may be there forever. My eyes and my heart will be there for all time.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007017"/>
    <verse num="17">And as for you, if you will walk before me as David your father walked, doing according to all that I have commanded you and keeping my statutes and my rules,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007018"/>
    <verse num="18">then I will establish your royal throne, as I covenanted with David your father, saying, <crossref let="i" cid="c14007018.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="14007018.1" from="14007018.1" to="14007018.2"/>You shall not lack a man to rule Israel.<q class="end-single" qid="14007018.2" from="14007018.1" to="14007018.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="j" cid="c14007019.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="14007019.1" from="14007012.1" to="14007022.3"/>But if you<note nid="n14007019.1"/> turn aside and forsake my statutes and my commandments that I have set before you, and go and serve other gods and worship them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="k" cid="c14007020.1"/>then I will pluck you<note nid="n14007020.1"/> up from my land that I have given you, and this house that I have consecrated for my name, I will cast out of my sight, and I will make it <crossref let="l" cid="c14007020.2"/>a proverb and a byword among all peoples.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007021"/>
    <verse num="21">And at this house, which was exalted, everyone passing by will be astonished and say, <crossref let="m" cid="c14007021.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="14007021.1" from="14007021.1" to="14007021.2"/>Why has the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> done thus to this land and to this house?<q class="end-single" qid="14007021.2" from="14007021.1" to="14007021.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14007022"/>
    <verse num="22">Then they will say, <q class="begin-single" qid="14007022.1" from="14007022.1" to="14007022.2"/>Because they abandoned the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers who brought them out of the land of Egypt, and laid hold on other gods and worshiped them and served them. Therefore he has brought all this disaster on them.<q class="end-single" qid="14007022.2" from="14007022.1" to="14007022.2"/><q class="end-double" qid="14007022.3" from="14007012.1" to="14007022.3"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008001"/>
  <chapter num="8">
    <heading>Solomon&apos;s Accomplishments</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="n" cid="c14008001.1"/>At the end of twenty years, in which Solomon had built the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and his own house,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008002"/>
    <verse num="2">Solomon rebuilt the cities that Hiram had given to him, and settled the people of Israel in them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008003"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3">And Solomon went to Hamath-zobah and took it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008004"/>
    <verse num="4">He built Tadmor in the wilderness and all the store cities that he built in Hamath.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008005"/>
    <verse num="5">He also built <crossref let="o" cid="c14008005.1"/>Upper Beth-horon and Lower Beth-horon, <crossref let="p" cid="c14008005.2"/>fortified cities <crossref let="p" cid="c14008005.3"/>with walls, gates, and bars,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008006"/>
    <verse num="6">and Baalath, and all the store cities that Solomon had and all the cities for his chariots and the cities for his horsemen, and whatever Solomon desired to build in Jerusalem, in Lebanon, and in all the land of his dominion.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="q" cid="c14008007.1"/>All the people who were left of the Hittites, the Amorites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites, who were not of Israel,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008008"/>
    <verse num="8">from their descendants who were left after them in the land, whom the people of Israel had not destroyed&emdash;these Solomon drafted <crossref let="r" cid="c14008008.1"/>as forced labor, and so they are to this day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008009"/>
    <verse num="9">But of the people of Israel Solomon made no slaves for his work; they were soldiers, and his officers, the commanders of his chariots, and his horsemen.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008010"/>
    <verse num="10">And these were the chief officers of King Solomon, 250, who exercised authority over the people.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="s" cid="c14008011.1"/>Solomon brought Pharaoh&apos;s daughter up from the city of David to the house that he had built for her, for he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14008011.1" from="14008011.1" to="14008011.2"/>My wife shall not live in the house of David king of Israel, for the places to which the ark of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has come are holy.<q class="end-double" qid="14008011.2" from="14008011.1" to="14008011.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">Then Solomon offered up burnt offerings to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> on the altar of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="t" cid="c14008012.1"/>that he had built before the vestibule,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="u" cid="c14008013.1"/>as the duty of each day required, offering <crossref let="v" cid="c14008013.2"/>according to the commandment of Moses for the Sabbaths, the new moons, and the <crossref let="w" cid="c14008013.3"/>three annual feasts&emdash;the Feast of Unleavened Bread, the Feast of Weeks, and the Feast of Booths.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008014"/>
    <verse num="14">According to the ruling of David his father, he appointed <crossref let="x" cid="c14008014.1"/>the divisions of the priests for their service, <crossref let="y" cid="c14008014.2"/>and the Levites for their offices of praise and <crossref let="z" cid="c14008014.3"/>ministry before the priests <crossref let="u" cid="c14008014.4"/>as the duty of each day required, and <crossref let="a" cid="c14008014.5"/>the gatekeepers in their divisions at each gate, for so David <crossref let="b" cid="c14008014.6"/>the man of God had commanded.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008015"/>
    <verse num="15">And they did not turn aside from what the king had commanded the priests and Levites concerning any matter and concerning the treasuries.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">Thus was accomplished all the work of Solomon from<note nid="n14008016.1"/> the day the foundation of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was laid until it was finished. So the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was completed.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008017"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17">Then Solomon went to <crossref let="c" cid="c14008017.1"/>Ezion-geber and <crossref let="d" cid="c14008017.2"/>Eloth on the shore of the sea, in the land of Edom.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14008018"/>
    <verse num="18">And Hiram sent to him by the hand of his servants ships and servants familiar with the sea, and they went to Ophir together with the servants of Solomon and brought from there <crossref let="e" cid="c14008018.1"/>450 talents<note nid="n14008018.1"/> of gold and brought it to King Solomon.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009001"/>
  <chapter num="9">
    <heading>The Queen of Sheba</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="f" cid="c14009001.1"/>Now when <crossref let="g" cid="c14009001.2"/>the queen of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon, she came to Jerusalem to test him with hard questions, having a very great retinue and camels bearing spices and very much gold and precious stones. And when she came to Solomon, she told him all that was on her mind.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009002"/>
    <verse num="2">And Solomon answered all her questions. There was nothing hidden from Solomon that he could not explain to her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009003"/>
    <verse num="3">And when <crossref let="g" cid="c14009003.1"/>the queen of Sheba had seen the wisdom of Solomon, the house that he had built,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009004"/>
    <verse num="4">the food of his table, the seating of his officials, and the attendance of his servants, and their clothing, his cupbearers, and their clothing, and his burnt offerings that he offered at the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, there was no more breath in her.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009005"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5">And she said to the king, <q class="begin-double" qid="14009005.1" from="14009005.1" to="14009008.1"/>The report was true that I heard in my own land of your words and of your wisdom,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009006"/>
    <verse num="6">but I did not believe the<note nid="n14009006.1"/> reports until I came and my own eyes had seen it. And behold, half the greatness of your wisdom was not told me; you surpass the report that I heard.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009007"/>
    <verse num="7">Happy are your men! Happy are these your servants, who continually stand before you and hear your wisdom!</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009008"/>
    <verse num="8">Blessed be the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God, who has delighted in you <crossref let="h" cid="c14009008.1"/>and set you on his throne as king for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God! <crossref let="i" cid="c14009008.2"/>Because your God loved Israel and would establish them forever, he has made you king over them, that you may execute justice and righteousness.<q class="end-double" qid="14009008.1" from="14009005.1" to="14009008.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009009"/>
    <verse num="9">Then she gave the king 120 talents<note nid="n14009009.1"/> of gold, and a very great quantity of spices, and precious stones. There were no spices such as those that the queen of Sheba gave to King Solomon.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">Moreover, the servants of Hiram and the servants of Solomon, <crossref let="j" cid="c14009010.1"/>who brought gold from Ophir, brought algum wood and precious stones.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009011"/>
    <verse num="11">And the king made from the algum wood <crossref let="k" cid="c14009011.1"/>supports for the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and for the king&apos;s house, lyres also and harps for the singers. There never was seen the like of them before in the land of Judah.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">And King Solomon gave to the queen of Sheba all that she desired, whatever she asked <crossref let="l" cid="c14009012.1"/>besides what she had brought to the king. So she turned and went back to her own land with her servants.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009013"/>
    <heading>Solomon&apos;s Wealth</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="m" cid="c14009013.1"/>Now the weight of gold that came to Solomon in one year was 666 talents of gold,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009014"/>
    <verse num="14">besides that which the explorers and merchants brought. <crossref let="n" cid="c14009014.1"/>And all the kings of Arabia and the governors of the land brought gold and silver to Solomon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009015"/>
    <verse num="15">King Solomon made 200 large shields of beaten gold; 600 shekels<note nid="n14009015.1"/> of beaten gold went into each shield.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009016"/>
    <verse num="16">And he made 300 shields of beaten gold; <crossref let="o" cid="c14009016.1"/>300 shekels of gold went into each shield; and the king put them in the House of the Forest of Lebanon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009017"/>
    <verse num="17">The king also made a great ivory throne and overlaid it with pure gold.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009018"/>
    <verse num="18">The throne had six steps and a footstool of gold, which were attached to the throne, and on each side of the seat were armrests and two lions standing beside the armrests,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009019"/>
    <verse num="19">while twelve lions stood there, one on each end of a step on the six steps. Nothing like it was ever made for any kingdom.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009020"/>
    <verse num="20">All King Solomon&apos;s drinking vessels were of gold, and all the vessels of the House of the Forest of Lebanon were of pure gold. Silver was not considered as anything in the days of Solomon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009021"/>
    <verse num="21">For the king&apos;s ships went to <crossref let="p" cid="c14009021.1"/>Tarshish with the servants of Hiram. Once every three years the ships of Tarshish used to come bringing gold, silver, ivory, apes, and peacocks.<note nid="n14009021.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">Thus King Solomon <crossref let="q" cid="c14009022.1"/>excelled all the kings of the earth in riches and in wisdom.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009023"/>
    <verse num="23">And all the kings of the earth sought the presence of Solomon to hear his wisdom, which God had put into his mind.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009024"/>
    <verse num="24">Every one of them brought his present, articles of silver and of gold, garments, myrrh,<note nid="n14009024.1"/> spices, horses, and mules, so much year by year.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009025"/>
    <verse num="25">And Solomon had <crossref let="r" cid="c14009025.1"/>4,000 stalls for horses and chariots, and 12,000 horsemen, whom he stationed in the chariot cities and with the king in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009026"/>
    <verse num="26"><crossref let="s" cid="c14009026.1"/>And he ruled over all the kings <crossref let="t" cid="c14009026.2"/>from the Euphrates<note nid="n14009026.1"/> to the land of the Philistines and to the border of Egypt.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009027"/>
    <verse num="27"><crossref let="u" cid="c14009027.1"/>And the king made silver as common in Jerusalem as stone, and he made cedar as plentiful as the sycamore of the Shephelah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009028"/>
    <verse num="28"><crossref let="v" cid="c14009028.1"/>And horses were imported for Solomon from Egypt and from all lands.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009029"/>
    <heading>Solomon&apos;s Death</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="w" cid="c14009029.1"/>Now the rest of the acts of Solomon, from <crossref let="x" cid="c14009029.2"/>first to last, are they not written in the history of <crossref let="y" cid="c14009029.3"/>Nathan the prophet, and in the prophecy of <crossref let="z" cid="c14009029.4"/>Ahijah the Shilonite, and in the visions of <crossref let="a" cid="c14009029.5"/>Iddo <crossref let="b" cid="c14009029.6"/>the seer concerning Jeroboam the son of Nebat?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009030"/>
    <verse num="30">Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel forty years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14009031"/>
    <verse num="31">And Solomon slept with his fathers and was buried in <crossref let="c" cid="c14009031.1"/>the city of David his father, and Rehoboam his son reigned in his place.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010001"/>
  <chapter num="10">
    <heading>The Revolt Against Rehoboam</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="d" cid="c14010001.1"/>Rehoboam went to Shechem, for all Israel had come to Shechem to make him king.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010002"/>
    <verse num="2">And as soon as Jeroboam the son of Nebat heard of it (for he was in Egypt, <crossref let="e" cid="c14010002.1"/>where he had fled from King Solomon), then Jeroboam returned from Egypt.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010003"/>
    <verse num="3">And they sent and called him. And Jeroboam and all Israel came and said to Rehoboam,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="f" cid="c14010004.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14010004.1" from="14010004.1" to="14010004.2"/>Your father made our yoke heavy. Now therefore lighten the hard service of your father and his heavy yoke on us, and we will serve you.<q class="end-double" qid="14010004.2" from="14010004.1" to="14010004.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010005"/>
    <verse num="5">He said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="14010005.1" from="14010005.1" to="14010005.2"/>Come to me again in three days.<q class="end-double" qid="14010005.2" from="14010005.1" to="14010005.2"/> So the people went away.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6">Then King Rehoboam took counsel with the old men,<note nid="n14010006.1"/> who had stood before Solomon his father while he was yet alive, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="14010006.1" from="14010006.1" to="14010006.2"/>How do you advise me to answer this people?<q class="end-double" qid="14010006.2" from="14010006.1" to="14010006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010007"/>
    <verse num="7">And they said to him, <crossref let="g" cid="c14010007.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14010007.1" from="14010007.1" to="14010007.2"/>If you will be good to this people and please them and speak good words to them, then they will be your servants forever.<q class="end-double" qid="14010007.2" from="14010007.1" to="14010007.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010008"/>
    <verse num="8">But he abandoned the counsel that the old men gave him, and took counsel with the young men who had grown up with him and stood before him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010009"/>
    <verse num="9">And he said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="14010009.1" from="14010009.1" to="14010009.4"/>What do you advise that we answer this people who have said to me, <q class="begin-single" qid="14010009.2" from="14010009.2" to="14010009.3"/>Lighten the yoke that your father put on us<q class="end-single" qid="14010009.3" from="14010009.2" to="14010009.3"/>?<q class="end-double" qid="14010009.4" from="14010009.1" to="14010009.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010010"/>
    <verse num="10">And the young men who had grown up with him said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="14010010.1" from="14010010.1" to="14010011.2"/>Thus shall you speak to the people who said to you, <q class="begin-single" qid="14010010.2" from="14010010.2" to="14010010.3"/>Your father made our yoke heavy, but you lighten it for us<q class="end-single" qid="14010010.3" from="14010010.2" to="14010010.3"/>; thus shall you say to them, <q class="begin-single" qid="14010010.4" from="14010010.4" to="14010011.1"/>My little finger is thicker than my father&apos;s thighs.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010011"/>
    <verse num="11">And now, whereas my father laid on you a heavy yoke, I will add to your yoke. My father disciplined you with whips, but I will discipline you with scorpions.<q class="end-single" qid="14010011.1" from="14010010.4" to="14010011.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="14010011.2" from="14010010.1" to="14010011.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">So Jeroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam the third day, as the king said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14010012.1" from="14010012.1" to="14010012.2"/>Come to me again the third day.<q class="end-double" qid="14010012.2" from="14010012.1" to="14010012.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010013"/>
    <verse num="13">And the king answered them harshly; and forsaking the counsel of the old men,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010014"/>
    <verse num="14">King Rehoboam spoke to them according to the counsel of the young men, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="14010014.1" from="14010014.1" to="14010014.2"/>My father made your yoke heavy, but I will add to it. My father disciplined you with whips, but I will discipline you with scorpions.<q class="end-double" qid="14010014.2" from="14010014.1" to="14010014.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010015"/>
    <verse num="15">So the king did not listen to the people, for it was a turn of affairs brought about by God that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> might fulfill his word, <crossref let="h" cid="c14010015.1"/>which he spoke by Ahijah the Shilonite to Jeroboam the son of Nebat.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">And when all Israel saw that the king did not listen to them, the people answered the king, <q class="begin-double" qid="14010016.1" from="14010016.1" to="14010016.2"/>What portion have we in David? We have no inheritance in the son of Jesse. <crossref let="i" cid="c14010016.1"/>Each of you to your tents, O Israel! Look now to your own house, David.<q class="end-double" qid="14010016.2" from="14010016.1" to="14010016.2"/> So all Israel went to their tents.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010017"/>
    <verse num="17">But Rehoboam reigned over the people of Israel who lived in the cities of Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010018"/>
    <verse num="18">Then King Rehoboam sent <crossref let="j" cid="c14010018.1"/>Hadoram,<note nid="n14010018.1"/> who was taskmaster over the forced labor, and the people of Israel stoned him to death with stones. And King Rehoboam quickly mounted his chariot to flee to Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14010019"/>
    <verse num="19">So Israel has been in rebellion against the house of David to this day.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011001"/>
  <chapter num="11">
    <heading>Rehoboam Secures His Kingdom</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="k" cid="c14011001.1"/>When Rehoboam came to Jerusalem, he assembled the house of Judah and Benjamin, 180,000 chosen warriors, to fight against Israel, to restore the kingdom to Rehoboam.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011002"/>
    <verse num="2">But the word of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> came to <crossref let="l" cid="c14011002.1"/>Shemaiah the man of God:</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011003"/>
    <verse num="3"><q class="begin-double" qid="14011003.1" from="14011003.1" to="14011004.3"/>Say to Rehoboam the son of Solomon, king of Judah, and to all Israel in Judah and Benjamin,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011004"/>
    <verse num="4"><q class="begin-single" qid="14011004.1" from="14011004.1" to="14011004.2"/>Thus says the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, You shall not go up or fight against <crossref let="m" cid="c14011004.1"/>your relatives. Return every man to his home, for this thing is from me.<q class="end-single" qid="14011004.2" from="14011004.1" to="14011004.2"/><q class="end-double" qid="14011004.3" from="14011003.1" to="14011004.3"/> So they listened to the word of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and returned and did not go against Jeroboam.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011005"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5">Rehoboam lived in Jerusalem, and he built <crossref let="n" cid="c14011005.1"/>cities for defense in Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011006"/>
    <verse num="6">He built Bethlehem, Etam, Tekoa,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011007"/>
    <verse num="7">Beth-zur, Soco, Adullam,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011008"/>
    <verse num="8">Gath, <crossref let="o" cid="c14011008.1"/>Mareshah, Ziph,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011009"/>
    <verse num="9">Adoraim, Lachish, Azekah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011010"/>
    <verse num="10">Zorah, Aijalon, and Hebron, fortified cities that are in Judah and in Benjamin.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011011"/>
    <verse num="11">He made the fortresses strong, and put commanders in them, and stores of food, oil, and wine.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011012"/>
    <verse num="12">And he put shields and spears in all the cities and made them very strong. So he held Judah and Benjamin.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011013"/>
    <heading>Priests and Levites Come to Jerusalem</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">And the priests and the Levites who were in all Israel presented themselves to him from all places where they lived.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011014"/>
    <verse num="14">For the Levites left <crossref let="p" cid="c14011014.1"/>their common lands and their holdings and came to Judah and Jerusalem, <crossref let="q" cid="c14011014.2"/>because Jeroboam and his sons cast them out from serving as priests of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011015"/>
    <verse num="15">and he appointed his own <crossref let="r" cid="c14011015.1"/>priests for the high places and for the goat idols and for <crossref let="s" cid="c14011015.2"/>the calves that he had made.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011016"/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="t" cid="c14011016.1"/>And those who had set their hearts to seek the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God of Israel came after them from all the tribes of Israel to Jerusalem to sacrifice to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="u" cid="c14011017.1"/>They strengthened the kingdom of Judah, and for three years they made Rehoboam the son of Solomon secure, for they walked for three years in the way of David and Solomon.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011018"/>
    <heading>Rehoboam&apos;s Family</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18">Rehoboam took as wife Mahalath the daughter of Jerimoth the son of David, and of Abihail the daughter of <crossref let="v" cid="c14011018.1"/>Eliab the son of Jesse,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011019"/>
    <verse num="19">and she bore him sons, Jeush, Shemariah, and Zaham.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011020"/>
    <verse num="20">After her he took <crossref let="w" cid="c14011020.1"/>Maacah the daughter of Absalom, who bore him <crossref let="x" cid="c14011020.2"/>Abijah, Attai, Ziza, and Shelomith.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011021"/>
    <verse num="21">Rehoboam loved Maacah the daughter of Absalom above all his wives and concubines (he took eighteen wives and sixty concubines, and fathered twenty-eight sons and sixty daughters).</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011022"/>
    <verse num="22"><crossref let="y" cid="c14011022.1"/>And Rehoboam appointed <crossref let="x" cid="c14011022.2"/>Abijah the son of Maacah as chief prince among his brothers, for he intended to make him king.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14011023"/>
    <verse num="23">And he dealt wisely and distributed some of his sons through all the districts of Judah and Benjamin, in all the fortified cities, and he gave them abundant provisions and procured wives for them.<note nid="n14011023.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012001"/>
  <chapter num="12">
    <heading>Egypt Plunders Jerusalem</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="z" cid="c14012001.1"/>When the rule of Rehoboam was established <crossref let="a" cid="c14012001.2"/>and he was strong, <crossref let="b" cid="c14012001.3"/>he abandoned the law of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and all Israel with him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="c" cid="c14012002.1"/>In the fifth year of King Rehoboam, because they had been unfaithful to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="d" cid="c14012002.2"/>Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012003"/>
    <verse num="3">with 1,200 chariots and 60,000 horsemen. And the people were without number who came with him from Egypt&emdash;<crossref let="e" cid="c14012003.1"/>Libyans, Sukkiim, and Ethiopians.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012004"/>
    <verse num="4">And he took <crossref let="f" cid="c14012004.1"/>the fortified cities of Judah and came as far as Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012005"/>
    <verse num="5">Then <crossref let="g" cid="c14012005.1"/>Shemaiah the prophet came to Rehoboam and to the princes of Judah, who had gathered at Jerusalem because of Shishak, and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="14012005.1" from="14012005.1" to="14012005.4"/>Thus says the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="h" cid="c14012005.2"/><q class="begin-single" qid="14012005.2" from="14012005.2" to="14012005.3"/>You abandoned me, so I have abandoned you to the hand of Shishak.<q class="end-single" qid="14012005.3" from="14012005.2" to="14012005.3"/><q class="end-double" qid="14012005.4" from="14012005.1" to="14012005.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012006"/>
    <verse num="6">Then the princes of <crossref let="i" cid="c14012006.1"/>Israel and the king humbled themselves and said, <crossref let="j" cid="c14012006.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14012006.1" from="14012006.1" to="14012006.2"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is righteous.<q class="end-double" qid="14012006.2" from="14012006.1" to="14012006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012007"/>
    <verse num="7">When the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> saw that they humbled themselves, the word of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> came to Shemaiah: <crossref let="k" cid="c14012007.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14012007.1" from="14012007.1" to="14012008.1"/>They have humbled themselves. I will not destroy them, but I will grant them some deliverance, <crossref let="l" cid="c14012007.2"/>and my wrath shall not be poured out on Jerusalem by the hand of Shishak.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012008"/>
    <verse num="8">Nevertheless, they shall be servants to him, <crossref let="m" cid="c14012008.1"/>that they may know my service and the service of the kingdoms of the countries.<q class="end-double" qid="14012008.1" from="14012007.1" to="14012008.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012009"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="n" cid="c14012009.1"/>So Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem. He took away the treasures of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and the treasures of the king&apos;s house. He took away everything. He also took away <crossref let="o" cid="c14012009.2"/>the shields of gold that Solomon had made,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012010"/>
    <verse num="10">and King Rehoboam made in their place shields of bronze and committed them to the hands of the officers of the guard, who kept the door of the king&apos;s house.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012011"/>
    <verse num="11">And as often as the king went into the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the guard came and carried them and brought them back to the guardroom.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012012"/>
    <verse num="12">And when <crossref let="p" cid="c14012012.1"/>he humbled himself the wrath of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> turned from him, so as not to make a complete destruction. Moreover, <crossref let="q" cid="c14012012.2"/>conditions were good<note nid="n14012012.1"/> in Judah.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="r" cid="c14012013.1"/>So King Rehoboam grew strong in Jerusalem and reigned. Rehoboam was forty-one years old when he began to reign, and he reigned seventeen years in Jerusalem, the city that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel to put his name there. His mother&apos;s name was Naamah the Ammonite.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012014"/>
    <verse num="14">And he did evil, <crossref let="s" cid="c14012014.1"/>for he did not set his heart to seek the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="t" cid="c14012015.1"/>Now the acts of Rehoboam, <crossref let="u" cid="c14012015.2"/>from first to last, are they not written in the chronicles of <crossref let="v" cid="c14012015.3"/>Shemaiah the prophet and of <crossref let="w" cid="c14012015.4"/>Iddo <crossref let="x" cid="c14012015.5"/>the seer?<note nid="n14012015.1"/> There were continual wars between Rehoboam and Jeroboam.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14012016"/>
    <verse num="16">And Rehoboam slept with his fathers and was buried in the city of David, and <crossref let="y" cid="c14012016.1"/>Abijah<note nid="n14012016.1"/> his son reigned in his place.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013001"/>
  <chapter num="13">
    <heading>Abijah Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="z" cid="c14013001.1"/>In the eighteenth year of King Jeroboam, <crossref let="y" cid="c14013001.2"/>Abijah began to reign over Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013002"/>
    <verse num="2">He reigned for three years in Jerusalem. His mother&apos;s name was <crossref let="a" cid="c14013002.1"/>Micaiah<note nid="n14013002.1"/> the daughter of Uriel of Gibeah.
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-paragraph/><crossref let="b" cid="c14013002.2"/>Now there was war between Abijah and Jeroboam.
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013003"/>
    <verse num="3">Abijah went out to battle, having an army of valiant men of war, 400,000 chosen men. And Jeroboam <crossref let="c" cid="c14013003.1"/>drew up his line of battle against him with 800,000 chosen mighty warriors.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013004"/>
    <verse num="4">Then Abijah stood up on Mount <crossref let="d" cid="c14013004.1"/>Zemaraim that is in <crossref let="e" cid="c14013004.2"/>the hill country of Ephraim and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14013004.1" from="14013004.1" to="14013012.1"/>Hear me, O Jeroboam and all Israel!</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013005"/>
    <verse num="5">Ought you not to know that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God of Israel <crossref let="f" cid="c14013005.1"/>gave the kingship over Israel forever to David and his sons by <crossref let="g" cid="c14013005.2"/>a covenant of salt?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013006"/>
    <verse num="6">Yet Jeroboam the son of Nebat, a servant of Solomon the son of David, rose up <crossref let="h" cid="c14013006.1"/>and rebelled against his lord,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013007"/>
    <verse num="7">and certain <crossref let="i" cid="c14013007.1"/>worthless scoundrels<note nid="n14013007.1"/> gathered about him and defied Rehoboam the son of Solomon, when Rehoboam was <crossref let="j" cid="c14013007.2"/>young and irresolute<note nid="n14013007.2"/> and could not withstand them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8"><q class="continue-double" qid="14013008.1" from="14013004.1" to="14013012.1"/>And now you think to withstand the kingdom of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in the hand of the sons of David, because you are a great multitude and have with you <crossref let="k" cid="c14013008.1"/>the golden calves that Jeroboam made you for gods.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="l" cid="c14013009.1"/>Have you not driven out the priests of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the sons of Aaron, and the Levites, and made priests for yourselves like the peoples of other lands? Whoever comes <crossref let="m" cid="c14013009.2"/>for ordination<note nid="n14013009.1"/> with a young bull or seven rams becomes a priest of what are <crossref let="n" cid="c14013009.3"/>not gods.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013010"/>
    <verse num="10">But as for us, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is our God, and we have not forsaken him. We have priests ministering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> who are sons of Aaron, and Levites for their service.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013011"/>
    <verse num="11">They offer to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="o" cid="c14013011.1"/>every morning and every evening burnt offerings and incense of sweet spices, set out <crossref let="p" cid="c14013011.2"/>the showbread on the table of pure gold, <crossref let="q" cid="c14013011.3"/>and care for the golden lampstand that its lamps may <crossref let="r" cid="c14013011.4"/>burn every evening. For we <crossref let="s" cid="c14013011.5"/>keep the charge of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God, but you have forsaken him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013012"/>
    <verse num="12">Behold, God is with us at our head, and his priests <crossref let="t" cid="c14013012.1"/>with their battle trumpets to sound the call to battle against you. O sons of Israel, <crossref let="u" cid="c14013012.2"/>do not fight against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of your fathers, for you cannot succeed.<q class="end-double" qid="14013012.1" from="14013004.1" to="14013012.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">Jeroboam had sent <crossref let="v" cid="c14013013.1"/>an ambush around to come upon them from behind. Thus his troops<note nid="n14013013.1"/> were in front of Judah, and the ambush was behind them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013014"/>
    <verse num="14">And when Judah looked, behold, the battle was in front of and behind them. <crossref let="w" cid="c14013014.1"/>And they cried to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and the priests <crossref let="t" cid="c14013014.2"/>blew the trumpets.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013015"/>
    <verse num="15">Then the men of Judah raised the battle shout. And when the men of Judah shouted, <crossref let="x" cid="c14013015.1"/>God defeated Jeroboam and all Israel before Abijah and Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013016"/>
    <verse num="16">The men of Israel fled before Judah, <crossref let="y" cid="c14013016.1"/>and God gave them into their hand.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013017"/>
    <verse num="17">Abijah and his people struck them with great force, so there fell slain of Israel 500,000 chosen men.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013018"/>
    <verse num="18">Thus the men of Israel were subdued at that time, and the men of Judah prevailed, <crossref let="z" cid="c14013018.1"/>because they relied on the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013019"/>
    <verse num="19">And Abijah pursued Jeroboam <crossref let="a" cid="c14013019.1"/>and took cities from him, Bethel with its villages and Jeshanah with its villages and <crossref let="b" cid="c14013019.2"/>Ephron<note nid="n14013019.1"/> with its villages.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013020"/>
    <verse num="20">Jeroboam did not recover his power in the days of Abijah. <crossref let="c" cid="c14013020.1"/>And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> struck him down, <crossref let="d" cid="c14013020.2"/>and he died.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013021"/>
    <verse num="21">But Abijah grew mighty. And he took fourteen wives and had twenty-two sons and sixteen daughters.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14013022"/>
    <verse num="22">The rest of the acts of Abijah, his ways and his sayings, are written in the <crossref let="e" cid="c14013022.1"/>story of the prophet <crossref let="f" cid="c14013022.2"/>Iddo.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014001"/>
  <chapter num="14">
    <heading>Asa Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><note nid="n14014001.1"/> <crossref let="g" cid="c14014001.1"/>Abijah slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city of David. And Asa his son reigned in his place. In his days the land had rest for ten years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014002"/>
    <verse num="2"><note nid="n14014002.1"/> And Asa did what was good and right in the eyes of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014003"/>
    <verse num="3">He took away the foreign altars <crossref let="h" cid="c14014003.1"/>and the high places and broke down <crossref let="i" cid="c14014003.2"/>the pillars and cut down the <crossref let="j" cid="c14014003.3"/>Asherim</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014004"/>
    <verse num="4">and commanded Judah to seek the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers, and to keep the law and the commandment.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014005"/>
    <verse num="5">He also took out of all the cities of Judah <crossref let="h" cid="c14014005.1"/>the high places and the <crossref let="k" cid="c14014005.2"/>incense altars. And the kingdom had rest under him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014006"/>
    <verse num="6">He built <crossref let="l" cid="c14014006.1"/>fortified cities in Judah, for the land had rest. He had no war in those years, <crossref let="m" cid="c14014006.2"/>for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave him peace.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014007"/>
    <verse num="7">And he said to Judah, <q class="begin-double" qid="14014007.1" from="14014007.1" to="14014007.2"/>Let us build these cities and surround them with <crossref let="n" cid="c14014007.1"/>walls and towers, gates and bars. The land is still ours, because we have sought the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God. We have sought him, <crossref let="m" cid="c14014007.2"/>and he has given us peace on every side.<q class="end-double" qid="14014007.2" from="14014007.1" to="14014007.2"/> So they built and prospered.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014008"/>
    <verse num="8">And Asa had an army of <crossref let="o" cid="c14014008.1"/>300,000 from Judah, armed with large shields and spears, and 280,000 men from Benjamin that carried shields and drew bows. All these were mighty men of valor.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014009"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9">Zerah <crossref let="p" cid="c14014009.1"/>the Ethiopian came out against them with an army of a million men and 300 chariots, and came as far as <crossref let="q" cid="c14014009.2"/>Mareshah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014010"/>
    <verse num="10">And Asa went out to meet him, and <crossref let="r" cid="c14014010.1"/>they drew up their lines of battle in the Valley of Zephathah at <crossref let="q" cid="c14014010.2"/>Mareshah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014011"/>
    <verse num="11">And Asa <crossref let="s" cid="c14014011.1"/>cried to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God, <q class="begin-double" qid="14014011.1" from="14014011.1" to="14014011.2"/>O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, there is none like you to help, between the mighty and the weak. Help us, O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God, <crossref let="t" cid="c14014011.2"/>for we rely on you, <crossref let="u" cid="c14014011.3"/>and in your name we have come against this multitude. O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, you are our God; let not man prevail against you.<q class="end-double" qid="14014011.2" from="14014011.1" to="14014011.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="v" cid="c14014012.1"/>So the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> defeated the Ethiopians before Asa and before Judah, and the Ethiopians fled.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014013"/>
    <verse num="13">Asa and the people who were with him pursued them as far as <crossref let="w" cid="c14014013.1"/>Gerar, and the Ethiopians fell until none remained alive, for they were broken before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and his army. The men of Judah<note nid="n14014013.1"/> carried away very much spoil.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014014"/>
    <verse num="14">And they attacked all the cities around <crossref let="w" cid="c14014014.1"/>Gerar, <crossref let="x" cid="c14014014.2"/>for the fear of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was upon them. They plundered all the cities, for there was much plunder in them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14014015"/>
    <verse num="15">And they struck down the tents of those who had livestock and carried away sheep in abundance and camels. Then they returned to Jerusalem.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015001"/>
  <chapter num="15">
    <heading>Asa&apos;s Religious Reforms</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="y" cid="c14015001.1"/>The Spirit of God came<note nid="n14015001.1"/> upon Azariah the son of Oded,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015002"/>
    <verse num="2">and he went out to meet Asa and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="14015002.1" from="14015002.1" to="14015007.1"/>Hear me, Asa, and all Judah and Benjamin: <crossref let="z" cid="c14015002.1"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is with you while you are with him. <crossref let="a" cid="c14015002.2"/>If you seek him, he will be found by you, <crossref let="b" cid="c14015002.3"/>but if you forsake him, he will forsake you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015003"/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="c" cid="c14015003.1"/>For a long time Israel was without the true God, and without a teaching priest and without law,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="d" cid="c14015004.1"/>but when in their distress they turned to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, and sought him, he was found by them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015005"/>
    <verse num="5">In those times there was no peace <crossref let="e" cid="c14015005.1"/>to him who went out or to him who came in, for great disturbances afflicted all the inhabitants of the lands.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015006"/>
    <verse num="6">They were broken in pieces. Nation was crushed by nation and city by city, for God troubled them with every sort of distress.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="f" cid="c14015007.1"/>But you, take courage! Do not let your hands be weak, <crossref let="g" cid="c14015007.2"/>for your work shall be rewarded.<q class="end-double" qid="14015007.1" from="14015002.1" to="14015007.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">As soon as Asa heard these words, <crossref let="h" cid="c14015008.1"/>the prophecy of Azariah the son of Oded, he took courage and put away the detestable idols from all the land of Judah and Benjamin and from <crossref let="i" cid="c14015008.2"/>the cities that he had taken in <crossref let="j" cid="c14015008.3"/>the hill country of Ephraim, and he repaired the altar of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="k" cid="c14015008.4"/>that was in front of the vestibule of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<note nid="n14015008.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015009"/>
    <verse num="9">And he gathered all Judah and Benjamin, <crossref let="l" cid="c14015009.1"/>and those from Ephraim, Manasseh, and Simeon who were residing with them, for great numbers had deserted to him from Israel when they saw that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God was with him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015010"/>
    <verse num="10">They were gathered at Jerusalem in the third month of the fifteenth year of the reign of Asa.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015011"/>
    <verse num="11">They sacrificed to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> on that day <crossref let="m" cid="c14015011.1"/>from the spoil that they had brought 700 oxen and 7,000 sheep.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="n" cid="c14015012.1"/>And they entered into a covenant to seek the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers, with all their heart and with all their soul,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015013"/>
    <verse num="13">but that whoever would not seek the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, <crossref let="o" cid="c14015013.1"/>should be put to death, whether young or old, man or woman.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015014"/>
    <verse num="14">They swore an oath to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> with a loud voice and with shouting and with trumpets and with horns.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015015"/>
    <verse num="15">And all Judah rejoiced over the oath, for they had sworn with all their heart and had sought him with their whole desire, and he was found by them, <crossref let="p" cid="c14015015.1"/>and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave them rest all around.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="q" cid="c14015016.1"/>Even Maacah, <crossref let="r" cid="c14015016.2"/>his mother, King Asa removed from being queen mother because she had made a detestable image <crossref let="s" cid="c14015016.3"/>for Asherah. Asa cut down her image, <crossref let="t" cid="c14015016.4"/>crushed it, and burned it at the brook Kidron.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="u" cid="c14015017.1"/>But the high places were not taken out of Israel. Nevertheless, the heart of Asa was wholly true all his days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015018"/>
    <verse num="18">And he brought into the house of God the sacred gifts of his father and his own sacred gifts, silver, and gold, and vessels.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14015019"/>
    <verse num="19">And there was no more war until the thirty-fifth year of the reign of Asa.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016001"/>
  <chapter num="16">
    <heading>Asa&apos;s Last Years</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="v" cid="c14016001.1"/>In the <crossref let="w" cid="c14016001.2"/>thirty-sixth year of the reign of Asa, Baasha king of Israel went up against Judah and built Ramah, <crossref let="x" cid="c14016001.3"/>that he might permit no one to go out or come in to Asa king of Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016002"/>
    <verse num="2">Then Asa took silver and gold from the treasures of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and the king&apos;s house and sent them to Ben-hadad king of Syria, who lived in Damascus, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016003"/>
    <verse num="3"><q class="begin-double" qid="14016003.1" from="14016003.1" to="14016003.2"/>There is a covenant<note nid="n14016003.1"/> between me and you, as there was between my father and your father. Behold, I am sending to you silver and gold. Go, break your covenant with Baasha king of Israel, that he may withdraw from me.<q class="end-double" qid="14016003.2" from="14016003.1" to="14016003.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016004"/>
    <verse num="4">And Ben-hadad listened to King Asa and sent the commanders of his armies against the cities of Israel, and they conquered Ijon, Dan, Abel-maim, and all the <crossref let="y" cid="c14016004.1"/>store cities of Naphtali.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016005"/>
    <verse num="5">And when Baasha heard of it, he stopped building Ramah and let his work cease.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016006"/>
    <verse num="6">Then King Asa took all Judah, and they carried away the stones of Ramah and its timber, with which Baasha had been building, and with them he built Geba and Mizpah.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">At that time <crossref let="z" cid="c14016007.1"/>Hanani <crossref let="a" cid="c14016007.2"/>the seer came to Asa king of Judah and said to him, <crossref let="b" cid="c14016007.3"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14016007.1" from="14016007.1" to="14016009.1"/>Because you relied on the king of Syria, and did not rely on the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God, the army of the king of Syria has escaped you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016008"/>
    <verse num="8">Were not <crossref let="c" cid="c14016008.1"/>the Ethiopians and <crossref let="d" cid="c14016008.2"/>the Libyans a huge army with very many chariots and horsemen? Yet <crossref let="e" cid="c14016008.3"/>because you relied on the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, he gave them into your hand.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="f" cid="c14016009.1"/>For the eyes of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> run to and fro throughout the whole earth, to give strong support to those <crossref let="g" cid="c14016009.2"/>whose heart is blameless<note nid="n14016009.1"/> toward him. <crossref let="h" cid="c14016009.3"/>You have done foolishly in this, for from now on <crossref let="i" cid="c14016009.4"/>you will have wars.<q class="end-double" qid="14016009.1" from="14016007.1" to="14016009.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016010"/>
    <verse num="10">Then Asa was angry with the seer and put him <crossref let="j" cid="c14016010.1"/>in the stocks in prison, for he was in a rage with him because of this. And Asa inflicted cruelties upon some of the people at the same time.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="k" cid="c14016011.1"/>The acts of Asa, from first to last, are written in the Book of the Kings of Judah and Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016012"/>
    <verse num="12">In the thirty-ninth year of his reign Asa was diseased in his feet, and his disease became severe. Yet even in his disease he did not seek the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, but sought help from physicians.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016013"/>
    <verse num="13">And Asa slept with his fathers, dying in the forty-first year of his reign.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14016014"/>
    <verse num="14">They buried him in the tomb that he had cut for himself in the city of David. They laid him on a bier <crossref let="l" cid="c14016014.1"/>that had been filled with various kinds of spices prepared by the perfumer&apos;s art, <crossref let="m" cid="c14016014.2"/>and they made a very great fire in his honor.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017001"/>
  <chapter num="17">
    <heading>Jehoshaphat Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Jehoshaphat his son reigned in his place and strengthened himself against Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017002"/>
    <verse num="2">He placed forces in all the <crossref let="n" cid="c14017002.1"/>fortified cities of Judah and set garrisons in the land of Judah, and in the cities of Ephraim <crossref let="o" cid="c14017002.2"/>that Asa his father had captured.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017003"/>
    <verse num="3">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was with Jehoshaphat, because he walked in the earlier ways of his father David. He did not seek the Baals,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017004"/>
    <verse num="4">but sought the God of his father and walked in his commandments, <crossref let="p" cid="c14017004.1"/>and not according to the practices of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017005"/>
    <verse num="5">Therefore the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> established the kingdom in his hand. And all Judah <crossref let="q" cid="c14017005.1"/>brought tribute to Jehoshaphat, <crossref let="r" cid="c14017005.2"/>and he had great riches and honor.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017006"/>
    <verse num="6">His heart was courageous in the ways of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. And furthermore, <crossref let="s" cid="c14017006.1"/>he took the high places and the Asherim out of Judah.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">In the third year of his reign he sent his officials, Ben-hail, Obadiah, Zechariah, Nethanel, and Micaiah, <crossref let="t" cid="c14017007.1"/>to teach in the cities of Judah;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="u" cid="c14017008.1"/>and with them the Levites, Shemaiah, Nethaniah, Zebadiah, Asahel, Shemiramoth, Jehonathan, Adonijah, Tobijah, and Tobadonijah; and with these Levites, the priests Elishama and Jehoram.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017009"/>
    <verse num="9">And <crossref let="t" cid="c14017009.1"/>they taught in Judah, having the Book of the Law of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> with them. They went about through all the cities of Judah and taught among the people.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="v" cid="c14017010.1"/>And the fear of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> fell upon all the kingdoms of the lands that were around Judah, and they made no war against Jehoshaphat.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017011"/>
    <verse num="11">Some of the Philistines <crossref let="w" cid="c14017011.1"/>brought Jehoshaphat presents and silver for tribute, and the Arabians also brought him 7,700 rams and 7,700 goats.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017012"/>
    <verse num="12">And Jehoshaphat grew steadily greater. He built in Judah fortresses and store cities,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017013"/>
    <verse num="13">and he had large supplies in the cities of Judah. He had soldiers, mighty men of valor, in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017014"/>
    <verse num="14">This was the muster of them by fathers&apos; houses: Of Judah, the commanders of thousands: Adnah the commander, with 300,000 mighty men of valor;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017015"/>
    <verse num="15">and next to him Jehohanan the commander, with 280,000;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017016"/>
    <verse num="16">and next to him Amasiah the son of Zichri, <crossref let="x" cid="c14017016.1"/>a volunteer for the service of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, with 200,000 mighty men of valor.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017017"/>
    <verse num="17">Of Benjamin: Eliada, a mighty man of valor, with 200,000 men <crossref let="y" cid="c14017017.1"/>armed with bow and shield;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017018"/>
    <verse num="18">and next to him Jehozabad with 180,000 armed for war.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14017019"/>
    <verse num="19">These were in the service of the king, besides <crossref let="z" cid="c14017019.1"/>those whom the king had placed in the fortified cities throughout all Judah.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018001"/>
  <chapter num="18">
    <heading>Jehoshaphat Allies with Ahab</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Now Jehoshaphat <crossref let="a" cid="c14018001.1"/>had great riches and honor, <crossref let="b" cid="c14018001.2"/>and he made a marriage alliance with Ahab.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="c" cid="c14018002.1"/>After some years he went down to Ahab in Samaria. And Ahab killed an abundance of sheep and oxen for him and for the people who were with him, and induced him to go up against Ramoth-gilead.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018003"/>
    <verse num="3">Ahab king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat king of Judah, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018003.1" from="14018003.1" to="14018003.2"/>Will you go with me to Ramoth-gilead?<q class="end-double" qid="14018003.2" from="14018003.1" to="14018003.2"/> He answered him, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018003.3" from="14018003.3" to="14018003.4"/>I am as you are, my people as your people. We will be with you in the war.<q class="end-double" qid="14018003.4" from="14018003.3" to="14018003.4"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">And Jehoshaphat said to the king of Israel, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018004.1" from="14018004.1" to="14018004.2"/>Inquire first for the word of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="14018004.2" from="14018004.1" to="14018004.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018005"/>
    <verse num="5">Then the king of Israel gathered the prophets together, four hundred men, and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018005.1" from="14018005.1" to="14018005.2"/>Shall we go to battle against Ramoth-gilead, or shall I refrain?<q class="end-double" qid="14018005.2" from="14018005.1" to="14018005.2"/> And they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018005.3" from="14018005.3" to="14018005.4"/>Go up, for God will give it into the hand of the king.<q class="end-double" qid="14018005.4" from="14018005.3" to="14018005.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018006"/>
    <verse num="6">But Jehoshaphat said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018006.1" from="14018006.1" to="14018006.2"/>Is there not here another prophet of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> of whom we may inquire?<q class="end-double" qid="14018006.2" from="14018006.1" to="14018006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018007"/>
    <verse num="7">And the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018007.1" from="14018007.1" to="14018007.2"/>There is yet one man by whom we may inquire of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, Micaiah the son of Imlah; but I hate him, for he never prophesies good concerning me, but always evil.<q class="end-double" qid="14018007.2" from="14018007.1" to="14018007.2"/> And Jehoshaphat said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018007.3" from="14018007.3" to="14018007.4"/>Let not the king say so.<q class="end-double" qid="14018007.4" from="14018007.3" to="14018007.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018008"/>
    <verse num="8">Then the king of Israel summoned an officer and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018008.1" from="14018008.1" to="14018008.2"/>Bring quickly Micaiah the son of Imlah.<q class="end-double" qid="14018008.2" from="14018008.1" to="14018008.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018009"/>
    <verse num="9">Now the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah were sitting on their thrones, arrayed in their robes. And they were sitting at the threshing floor <crossref let="d" cid="c14018009.1"/>at the entrance of the gate of Samaria, and all the prophets were prophesying before them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018010"/>
    <verse num="10">And Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah made for himself horns of iron and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018010.1" from="14018010.1" to="14018010.4"/>Thus says the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <q class="begin-single" qid="14018010.2" from="14018010.2" to="14018010.3"/>With these you shall push the Syrians until they are destroyed.<q class="end-single" qid="14018010.3" from="14018010.2" to="14018010.3"/><q class="end-double" qid="14018010.4" from="14018010.1" to="14018010.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018011"/>
    <verse num="11">And all the prophets prophesied so and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018011.1" from="14018011.1" to="14018011.2"/>Go up to Ramoth-gilead and triumph. The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will give it into the hand of the king.<q class="end-double" qid="14018011.2" from="14018011.1" to="14018011.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">And the messenger who went to summon Micaiah said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018012.1" from="14018012.1" to="14018012.2"/>Behold, the words of the prophets with one accord are favorable to the king. Let your word be like the word of one of them, and speak favorably.<q class="end-double" qid="14018012.2" from="14018012.1" to="14018012.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018013"/>
    <verse num="13">But Micaiah said, <crossref let="e" cid="c14018013.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14018013.1" from="14018013.1" to="14018013.2"/>As the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> lives, <crossref let="f" cid="c14018013.2"/>what my God says, that I will speak.<q class="end-double" qid="14018013.2" from="14018013.1" to="14018013.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018014"/>
    <verse num="14">And when he had come to the king, the king said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018014.1" from="14018014.1" to="14018014.2"/>Micaiah, shall we go to Ramoth-gilead to battle, or shall I refrain?<q class="end-double" qid="14018014.2" from="14018014.1" to="14018014.2"/> And he answered, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018014.3" from="14018014.3" to="14018014.4"/>Go up and triumph; they will be given into your hand.<q class="end-double" qid="14018014.4" from="14018014.3" to="14018014.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018015"/>
    <verse num="15">But the king said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018015.1" from="14018015.1" to="14018015.2"/>How many times shall I make you swear that you speak to me nothing but the truth in the name of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>?<q class="end-double" qid="14018015.2" from="14018015.1" to="14018015.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018016"/>
    <verse num="16">And he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018016.1" from="14018016.1" to="14018016.4"/>I saw all Israel scattered on the mountains, <crossref let="g" cid="c14018016.1"/>as sheep that have no shepherd. And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said, <q class="begin-single" qid="14018016.2" from="14018016.2" to="14018016.3"/>These have no master; let each return to his home in peace.<q class="end-single" qid="14018016.3" from="14018016.2" to="14018016.3"/><q class="end-double" qid="14018016.4" from="14018016.1" to="14018016.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018017"/>
    <verse num="17">And the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018017.1" from="14018017.1" to="14018017.2"/>Did I not tell you that he would not prophesy good concerning me, but evil?<q class="end-double" qid="14018017.2" from="14018017.1" to="14018017.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018018"/>
    <verse num="18">And Micaiah said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018018.1" from="14018018.1" to="14018022.1"/>Therefore hear the word of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>: <crossref let="h" cid="c14018018.1"/>I saw the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> sitting on his throne, and all the host of heaven standing on his right hand and on his left.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018019"/>
    <verse num="19">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said, <q class="begin-single" qid="14018019.1" from="14018019.1" to="14018019.2"/>Who will entice Ahab the king of Israel, that he may go up and fall at Ramoth-gilead?<q class="end-single" qid="14018019.2" from="14018019.1" to="14018019.2"/> And one said one thing, and another said another.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018020"/>
    <verse num="20">Then a spirit came forward and stood before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="14018020.1" from="14018020.1" to="14018020.2"/>I will entice him.<q class="end-single" qid="14018020.2" from="14018020.1" to="14018020.2"/> And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to him, <q class="begin-single" qid="14018020.3" from="14018020.3" to="14018020.4"/>By what means?<q class="end-single" qid="14018020.4" from="14018020.3" to="14018020.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018021"/>
    <verse num="21">And he said, <q class="begin-single" qid="14018021.1" from="14018021.1" to="14018021.2"/>I will go out, and will be <crossref let="i" cid="c14018021.1"/>a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets.<q class="end-single" qid="14018021.2" from="14018021.1" to="14018021.2"/> And he said, <q class="begin-single" qid="14018021.3" from="14018021.3" to="14018021.4"/>You are to entice him, and you shall succeed; go out and do so.<q class="end-single" qid="14018021.4" from="14018021.3" to="14018021.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018022"/>
    <verse num="22">Now therefore behold, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has put a lying spirit in the mouth of these your prophets. The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has declared disaster concerning you.<q class="end-double" qid="14018022.1" from="14018018.1" to="14018022.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018023"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="23">Then Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah came near <crossref let="j" cid="c14018023.1"/>and struck Micaiah on the cheek and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018023.1" from="14018023.1" to="14018023.2"/>Which way did the Spirit of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> go from me to speak to you?<q class="end-double" qid="14018023.2" from="14018023.1" to="14018023.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018024"/>
    <verse num="24">And Micaiah said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018024.1" from="14018024.1" to="14018024.2"/>Behold, you shall see on that day when you go into an inner chamber to hide yourself.<q class="end-double" qid="14018024.2" from="14018024.1" to="14018024.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018025"/>
    <verse num="25">And the king of Israel said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018025.1" from="14018025.1" to="14018026.3"/>Seize Micaiah and take him back to Amon <crossref let="k" cid="c14018025.1"/>the governor of the city and to Joash the king&apos;s son,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018026"/>
    <verse num="26">and say, <q class="begin-single" qid="14018026.1" from="14018026.1" to="14018026.2"/>Thus says the king, <crossref let="l" cid="c14018026.1"/>Put this fellow in prison and feed him with meager rations of bread and water until I return in peace.<q class="end-single" qid="14018026.2" from="14018026.1" to="14018026.2"/><q class="end-double" qid="14018026.3" from="14018025.1" to="14018026.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018027"/>
    <verse num="27">And Micaiah said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018027.1" from="14018027.1" to="14018027.2"/>If you return in peace, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has not spoken by me.<q class="end-double" qid="14018027.2" from="14018027.1" to="14018027.2"/> And he said, <crossref let="m" cid="c14018027.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14018027.3" from="14018027.3" to="14018027.4"/>Hear, all you peoples!<q class="end-double" qid="14018027.4" from="14018027.3" to="14018027.4"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018028"/>
    <heading>The Defeat and Death of Ahab</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="28">So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah went up to Ramoth-gilead.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018029"/>
    <verse num="29">And the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018029.1" from="14018029.1" to="14018029.2"/>I will disguise myself and go into battle, but you wear your robes.<q class="end-double" qid="14018029.2" from="14018029.1" to="14018029.2"/> And the king of Israel disguised himself, and they went into battle.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018030"/>
    <verse num="30">Now the king of Syria had commanded the captains of his chariots, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018030.1" from="14018030.1" to="14018030.2"/>Fight with neither small nor great, but only with the king of Israel.<q class="end-double" qid="14018030.2" from="14018030.1" to="14018030.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018031"/>
    <verse num="31">As soon as the captains of the chariots saw Jehoshaphat, they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018031.1" from="14018031.1" to="14018031.2"/>It is the king of Israel.<q class="end-double" qid="14018031.2" from="14018031.1" to="14018031.2"/> So they turned to fight against him. And Jehoshaphat cried out, and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> helped him; God drew them away from him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018032"/>
    <verse num="32">For as soon as the captains of the chariots saw that it was not the king of Israel, they turned back from pursuing him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018033"/>
    <verse num="33">But a certain man drew his bow at random<note nid="n14018033.1"/> and struck the king of Israel between the scale armor and the breastplate. Therefore he said to the driver of his chariot, <q class="begin-double" qid="14018033.1" from="14018033.1" to="14018033.2"/>Turn around and carry me out of the battle, for I am wounded.<q class="end-double" qid="14018033.2" from="14018033.1" to="14018033.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14018034"/>
    <verse num="34">And the battle continued that day, and the king of Israel was propped up in his chariot facing the Syrians until evening. Then at sunset he died.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14019001"/>
  <chapter num="19">
    <heading>Jehoshaphat&apos;s Reforms</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Jehoshaphat the king of Judah returned in safety to his house in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14019002"/>
    <verse num="2">But <crossref let="n" cid="c14019002.1"/>Jehu the son of <crossref let="o" cid="c14019002.2"/>Hanani <crossref let="p" cid="c14019002.3"/>the seer went out to meet him and said to King Jehoshaphat, <q class="begin-double" qid="14019002.1" from="14019002.1" to="14019003.1"/>Should you <crossref let="q" cid="c14019002.4"/>help the wicked and love those who hate the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>? Because of this, <crossref let="r" cid="c14019002.5"/>wrath has gone out against you from the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14019003"/>
    <verse num="3">Nevertheless, <crossref let="s" cid="c14019003.1"/>some good is found in you, for <crossref let="t" cid="c14019003.2"/>you destroyed the Asheroth out of the land, and have <crossref let="u" cid="c14019003.3"/>set your heart to seek God.<q class="end-double" qid="14019003.1" from="14019002.1" to="14019003.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14019004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">Jehoshaphat lived at Jerusalem. And he went out again among the people, from Beersheba to <crossref let="v" cid="c14019004.1"/>the hill country of Ephraim, and brought them back to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14019005"/>
    <verse num="5">He appointed <crossref let="w" cid="c14019005.1"/>judges in the land in all <crossref let="x" cid="c14019005.2"/>the fortified cities of Judah, city by city,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14019006"/>
    <verse num="6">and said to the judges, <q class="begin-double" qid="14019006.1" from="14019006.1" to="14019007.1"/>Consider what you do, <crossref let="y" cid="c14019006.1"/>for you judge not for man but for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. He is with you in giving judgment.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14019007"/>
    <verse num="7">Now then, let the fear of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> be upon you. Be careful what you do, for <crossref let="z" cid="c14019007.1"/>there is no injustice with the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God, <crossref let="a" cid="c14019007.2"/>or partiality or taking bribes.<q class="end-double" qid="14019007.1" from="14019006.1" to="14019007.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14019008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">Moreover, in Jerusalem Jehoshaphat <crossref let="b" cid="c14019008.1"/>appointed certain Levites and priests and heads of families of Israel, <crossref let="y" cid="c14019008.2"/>to give judgment for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and to decide disputed cases. They had their seat at Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14019009"/>
    <verse num="9">And he charged them: <crossref let="c" cid="c14019009.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14019009.1" from="14019009.1" to="14019011.1"/>Thus you shall do in the fear of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, in faithfulness, <crossref let="d" cid="c14019009.2"/>and with your whole heart:</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14019010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="e" cid="c14019010.1"/>whenever a case comes to you from your brothers who live in their cities, concerning bloodshed, law or commandment, statutes or rules, then you shall warn them, that they may not incur guilt before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and <crossref let="f" cid="c14019010.2"/>wrath may not come upon you and your brothers. Thus you shall do, and you will not incur guilt.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14019011"/>
    <verse num="11">And behold, Amariah the chief priest is over you <crossref let="g" cid="c14019011.1"/>in all matters of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>; and Zebadiah the son of Ishmael, the governor of the house of Judah, in all the king&apos;s matters, and the Levites will serve you as officers. <crossref let="h" cid="c14019011.2"/>Deal courageously, and may the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> be with the upright!<q class="end-double" qid="14019011.1" from="14019009.1" to="14019011.1"/><note nid="n14019011.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020001"/>
  <chapter num="20">
    <heading>Jehoshaphat&apos;s Prayer</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">After this <crossref let="i" cid="c14020001.1"/>the Moabites and Ammonites, and with them some of the Meunites,<note nid="n14020001.1"/> came against Jehoshaphat for battle.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020002"/>
    <verse num="2">Some men came and told Jehoshaphat, <q class="begin-double" qid="14020002.1" from="14020002.1" to="14020002.2"/>A great multitude is coming against you from Edom,<note nid="n14020002.1"/> from beyond the sea; and, behold, they are in <crossref let="j" cid="c14020002.1"/>Hazazon-tamar<q class="end-double" qid="14020002.2" from="14020002.1" to="14020002.2"/> (that is, <crossref let="k" cid="c14020002.2"/>Engedi).</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020003"/>
    <verse num="3">Then Jehoshaphat was afraid and set his face <crossref let="l" cid="c14020003.1"/>to seek the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and <crossref let="m" cid="c14020003.2"/>proclaimed a fast throughout all Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020004"/>
    <verse num="4">And Judah assembled to seek help from the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>; from all the cities of Judah they came to seek the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020005"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5">And Jehoshaphat stood in the assembly of Judah and Jerusalem, in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, before the new court,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020006"/>
    <verse num="6">and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14020006.1" from="14020006.1" to="14020012.1"/>O <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, God of our fathers, are you not <crossref let="n" cid="c14020006.1"/>God in heaven? You <crossref let="o" cid="c14020006.2"/>rule over all the kingdoms of the nations. <crossref let="p" cid="c14020006.3"/>In your hand are power and might, so that none is able to withstand you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020007"/>
    <verse num="7">Did you not, our God, <crossref let="q" cid="c14020007.1"/>drive out the inhabitants of this land before your people Israel, and give it forever to the descendants of <crossref let="r" cid="c14020007.2"/>Abraham your friend?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020008"/>
    <verse num="8">And they have lived in it and have built for you in it a sanctuary for your name, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="s" cid="c14020009.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="14020009.1" from="14020009.1" to="14020009.2"/>If disaster comes upon us, the sword, judgment,<note nid="n14020009.1"/> or pestilence, or famine, <crossref let="t" cid="c14020009.2"/>we will stand before this house and before you&emdash;<crossref let="u" cid="c14020009.3"/>for your name is in this house&emdash;and cry out to you in our affliction, and you will hear and save.<q class="end-single" qid="14020009.2" from="14020009.1" to="14020009.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020010"/>
    <verse num="10">And now behold, the men of <crossref let="v" cid="c14020010.1"/>Ammon and Moab and <crossref let="w" cid="c14020010.2"/>Mount Seir, whom <crossref let="x" cid="c14020010.3"/>you would not let Israel invade when they came from the land of Egypt, <crossref let="y" cid="c14020010.4"/>and whom they avoided and did not destroy&emdash;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020011"/>
    <verse num="11">behold, they reward us <crossref let="z" cid="c14020011.1"/>by coming to drive us out of your possession, which you have given us to inherit.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020012"/>
    <verse num="12">O our God, will you not <crossref let="a" cid="c14020012.1"/>execute judgment on them? For we are powerless against this great horde that is coming against us. We do not know what to do, but <crossref let="b" cid="c14020012.2"/>our eyes are on you.<q class="end-double" qid="14020012.1" from="14020006.1" to="14020012.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">Meanwhile all Judah stood before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, with their little ones, their wives, and their children.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020014"/>
    <verse num="14">And <crossref let="c" cid="c14020014.1"/>the Spirit of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> came<note nid="n14020014.1"/> upon Jahaziel the son of Zechariah, son of Benaiah, son of Jeiel, son of Mattaniah, a Levite of the sons of Asaph, in the midst of the assembly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020015"/>
    <verse num="15">And he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14020015.1" from="14020015.1" to="14020017.2"/>Listen, all Judah and inhabitants of Jerusalem and King Jehoshaphat: Thus says the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to you, <crossref let="d" cid="c14020015.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="14020015.2" from="14020015.2" to="14020017.1"/>Do not be afraid and do not be dismayed at this great horde, <crossref let="e" cid="c14020015.2"/>for the battle is not yours but God&apos;s.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020016"/>
    <verse num="16">Tomorrow go down against them. Behold, they will come up by the ascent of Ziz. You will find them at the end of <crossref let="f" cid="c14020016.1"/>the valley, east of the wilderness of Jeruel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="g" cid="c14020017.1"/>You will not need to fight in this battle. Stand firm, hold your position, and see the salvation of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> on your behalf, O Judah and Jerusalem.<q class="end-single" qid="14020017.1" from="14020015.2" to="14020017.1"/> <crossref let="d" cid="c14020017.2"/>Do not be afraid and do not be dismayed. Tomorrow go out against them, <crossref let="h" cid="c14020017.3"/>and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will be with you.<q class="end-double" qid="14020017.2" from="14020015.1" to="14020017.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18">Then Jehoshaphat <crossref let="i" cid="c14020018.1"/>bowed his head with his face to the ground, and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem fell down before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, worshiping the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020019"/>
    <verse num="19">And the Levites, of the <crossref let="j" cid="c14020019.1"/>Kohathites and the <crossref let="k" cid="c14020019.2"/>Korahites, stood up to praise the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, with a very loud voice.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020020"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20">And they rose early in the morning and went out into <crossref let="l" cid="c14020020.1"/>the wilderness of Tekoa. And when they went out, Jehoshaphat stood and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14020020.1" from="14020020.1" to="14020020.2"/>Hear me, Judah and inhabitants of Jerusalem! <crossref let="m" cid="c14020020.2"/>Believe in the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God, and you will be established; believe his prophets, and you will succeed.<q class="end-double" qid="14020020.2" from="14020020.1" to="14020020.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020021"/>
    <verse num="21">And when he had taken counsel with the people, he appointed those who were to sing to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and praise him <crossref let="n" cid="c14020021.1"/>in holy attire, as they went before the army, and say,
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
        <begin-line/><crossref let="o" cid="c14020021.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14020021.1" from="14020021.1" to="14020021.2"/>Give thanks to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>for his steadfast love endures forever.<q class="end-double" qid="14020021.2" from="14020021.1" to="14020021.2"/><end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <end-block-indent/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020022"/>
    <begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/>
    <verse num="22">And when they began to sing and praise, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> set <crossref let="p" cid="c14020022.1"/>an ambush against the men of <crossref let="q" cid="c14020022.2"/>Ammon, Moab, and Mount Seir, who had come against Judah, so that they were routed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020023"/>
    <verse num="23">For the men of Ammon and Moab rose against the inhabitants of Mount Seir, devoting them to destruction, and when they had made an end of the inhabitants of Seir, <crossref let="r" cid="c14020023.1"/>they all helped to destroy one another.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020024"/>
    <heading>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> Delivers Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24">When Judah came to the watchtower of the wilderness, they looked toward the horde, and behold, there<note nid="n14020024.1"/> were dead bodies lying on the ground; none had escaped.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020025"/>
    <verse num="25">When Jehoshaphat and his people came to take their spoil, they found among them, in great numbers, goods, clothing, and precious things, which they took for themselves until they could carry no more. They were three days in taking the spoil, it was so much.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020026"/>
    <verse num="26">On the fourth day they assembled in the Valley of Beracah,<note nid="n14020026.1"/> for there they blessed the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. Therefore the name of that place has been called the Valley of Beracah to this day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020027"/>
    <verse num="27">Then they returned, every man of Judah and Jerusalem, and Jehoshaphat at their head, returning to Jerusalem with joy, <crossref let="s" cid="c14020027.1"/>for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had made them rejoice over their enemies.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020028"/>
    <verse num="28">They came to Jerusalem with harps and lyres and trumpets, to the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020029"/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="t" cid="c14020029.1"/>And the fear of God came on all the kingdoms of the countries when they heard that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had fought against the enemies of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020030"/>
    <verse num="30">So the realm of Jehoshaphat was quiet, <crossref let="u" cid="c14020030.1"/>for his God gave him rest all around.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020031"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="31"><crossref let="v" cid="c14020031.1"/>Thus Jehoshaphat reigned over Judah. He was thirty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned twenty-five years in Jerusalem. His mother&apos;s name was Azubah the daughter of Shilhi.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020032"/>
    <verse num="32">He walked in the way of Asa his father and did not turn aside from it, doing what was right in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020033"/>
    <verse num="33"><crossref let="w" cid="c14020033.1"/>The high places, however, were not taken away; <crossref let="x" cid="c14020033.2"/>the people had not yet set their hearts upon the God of their fathers.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020034"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="34">Now the rest of the acts of Jehoshaphat, from first to last, are written in the chronicles of <crossref let="y" cid="c14020034.1"/>Jehu the son of Hanani, <crossref let="z" cid="c14020034.2"/>which are recorded in the Book of the Kings of Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020035"/>
    <heading>The End of Jehoshaphat&apos;s Reign</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="35"><crossref let="a" cid="c14020035.1"/>After this Jehoshaphat king of Judah joined with Ahaziah king of Israel, who acted wickedly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020036"/>
    <verse num="36">He joined him in building ships to go to <crossref let="b" cid="c14020036.1"/>Tarshish, and they built the ships in Ezion-geber.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14020037"/>
    <verse num="37">Then Eliezer the son of Dodavahu of Mareshah prophesied against Jehoshaphat, saying, <crossref let="c" cid="c14020037.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14020037.1" from="14020037.1" to="14020037.2"/>Because you have joined with Ahaziah, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will destroy what you have made.<q class="end-double" qid="14020037.2" from="14020037.1" to="14020037.2"/> And the ships were wrecked and were not able to go to Tarshish.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021001"/>
  <chapter num="21">
    <heading>Jehoram Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="d" cid="c14021001.1"/>Jehoshaphat slept with his fathers and was buried with his fathers in the city of David, and Jehoram his son reigned in his place.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021002"/>
    <verse num="2">He had brothers, the sons of Jehoshaphat: Azariah, Jehiel, Zechariah, Azariah, Michael, and Shephatiah; all these were the sons of Jehoshaphat king of <crossref let="e" cid="c14021002.1"/>Israel.<note nid="n14021002.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021003"/>
    <verse num="3">Their father gave them great gifts of silver, gold, and valuable possessions, together with <crossref let="f" cid="c14021003.1"/>fortified cities in Judah, but he gave the kingdom to Jehoram, because he was the firstborn.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021004"/>
    <verse num="4">When Jehoram had ascended the throne of his father and was established, he killed all his brothers with the sword, and also some of the princes of <crossref let="e" cid="c14021004.1"/>Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021005"/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="g" cid="c14021005.1"/>Jehoram was <crossref let="h" cid="c14021005.2"/>thirty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned eight years in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="i" cid="c14021006.1"/>And he walked in the way of the kings of Israel, as the house of Ahab had done, for <crossref let="j" cid="c14021006.2"/>the daughter of Ahab was his wife. And he did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021007"/>
    <verse num="7">Yet the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was not willing to destroy the house of David, because of the covenant that he had made with David, and since he had promised to give <crossref let="k" cid="c14021007.1"/>a lamp to him and to his sons forever.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">In his days Edom revolted from the <crossref let="l" cid="c14021008.1"/>rule of Judah and set up a king of their own.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021009"/>
    <verse num="9">Then Jehoram passed over with his commanders and all his chariots, and he rose by night and struck the Edomites who had surrounded him and his chariot commanders.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021010"/>
    <verse num="10">So Edom revolted from <crossref let="m" cid="c14021010.1"/>the rule of Judah to this day. At that time Libnah also revolted from his rule, because he had forsaken the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of his fathers.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11">Moreover, he made high places in the hill country of Judah and led the inhabitants of Jerusalem <crossref let="n" cid="c14021011.1"/>into whoredom and made Judah go astray.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021012"/>
    <verse num="12">And a letter came to him from Elijah the prophet, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="14021012.1" from="14021012.1" to="14021015.2"/>Thus says the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of David your father, <crossref let="o" cid="c14021012.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="14021012.2" from="14021012.2" to="14021015.1"/>Because you have not walked in the ways of Jehoshaphat your father, or <crossref let="p" cid="c14021012.2"/>in the ways of Asa king of Judah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="i" cid="c14021013.1"/>but have walked in the way of the kings of Israel and have enticed Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem <crossref let="n" cid="c14021013.2"/>into whoredom, <crossref let="q" cid="c14021013.3"/>as the house of Ahab led Israel into whoredom, and also you <crossref let="r" cid="c14021013.4"/>have killed your brothers, of your father&apos;s house, who were better than you,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021014"/>
    <verse num="14">behold, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will bring a great plague on your people, your children, your wives, and all your possessions,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021015"/>
    <verse num="15">and you yourself will have a severe sickness <crossref let="s" cid="c14021015.1"/>with a disease of your bowels, until your bowels come out because of the disease, day by day.<q class="end-single" qid="14021015.1" from="14021012.2" to="14021015.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="14021015.2" from="14021012.1" to="14021015.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="t" cid="c14021016.1"/>And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> stirred up against Jehoram the anger<note nid="n14021016.1"/> of the Philistines and of <crossref let="u" cid="c14021016.2"/>the Arabians who are near the Ethiopians.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021017"/>
    <verse num="17">And they came up against Judah and invaded it and carried away all the possessions they found that belonged to the king&apos;s house, and also his sons and his wives, so that no son was left to him except <crossref let="v" cid="c14021017.1"/>Jehoahaz, his youngest son.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18">And after all this the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> struck him <crossref let="w" cid="c14021018.1"/>in his bowels with an incurable disease.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021019"/>
    <verse num="19">In the course of time, at the end of two years, his bowels came out because of the disease, and he died in great agony. His people made no fire in his honor, <crossref let="x" cid="c14021019.1"/>like the fires made for his fathers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14021020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="y" cid="c14021020.1"/>He was thirty-two years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eight years in Jerusalem. And he departed <crossref let="z" cid="c14021020.2"/>with no one&apos;s regret. <crossref let="a" cid="c14021020.3"/>They buried him in the city of David, but not in the tombs of the kings.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14022001"/>
  <chapter num="22">
    <heading>Ahaziah Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="b" cid="c14022001.1"/>And the inhabitants of Jerusalem made Ahaziah, his youngest son, king in his place, for the band of men that came with <crossref let="c" cid="c14022001.2"/>the Arabians to the camp had killed all the older sons. So Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah reigned.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14022002"/>
    <verse num="2">Ahaziah was twenty-two<note nid="n14022002.1"/> years old when he began to reign, and he reigned one year in Jerusalem. His mother&apos;s name was Athaliah, <crossref let="d" cid="c14022002.1"/>the granddaughter of Omri.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14022003"/>
    <verse num="3">He also walked in the ways of the house of Ahab, for his mother was his counselor in doing wickedly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14022004"/>
    <verse num="4">He did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, as the house of Ahab had done. For after the death of his father they were his counselors, to his undoing.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14022005"/>
    <verse num="5">He even followed their counsel and went with Jehoram the son of Ahab king of Israel to make war against Hazael king of Syria at Ramoth-gilead. And the Syrians wounded Joram,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14022006"/>
    <verse num="6">and he returned to be healed in Jezreel of the wounds that he had received at Ramah, when he fought against Hazael king of Syria. And Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah went down to see Joram the son of Ahab in Jezreel, because he was wounded.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14022007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">But it was ordained by<note nid="n14022007.1"/> God that the downfall of Ahaziah should come about through his going to visit Joram. For when he came there, <crossref let="e" cid="c14022007.1"/>he went out with Jehoram to meet Jehu the son of Nimshi, <crossref let="f" cid="c14022007.2"/>whom the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had anointed to destroy the house of Ahab.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14022008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="g" cid="c14022008.1"/>And when Jehu was <crossref let="h" cid="c14022008.2"/>executing judgment on the house of Ahab, he met the princes of Judah and the sons of Ahaziah&apos;s brothers, who attended Ahaziah, and he killed them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14022009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="i" cid="c14022009.1"/>He searched for Ahaziah, and he was captured while hiding in Samaria, and he was brought to Jehu and put to death. <crossref let="j" cid="c14022009.2"/>They buried him, for they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14022009.1" from="14022009.1" to="14022009.2"/>He is the grandson of Jehoshaphat, <crossref let="k" cid="c14022009.3"/>who sought the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> with all his heart.<q class="end-double" qid="14022009.2" from="14022009.1" to="14022009.2"/> And the house of Ahaziah had no one able to rule the kingdom.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14022010"/>
    <heading>Athaliah Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="l" cid="c14022010.1"/>Now when Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah saw that her son was dead, she arose and destroyed all the royal family of the house of Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14022011"/>
    <verse num="11">But Jehoshabeath,<note nid="n14022011.1"/> the daughter of the king, took Joash the son of Ahaziah and stole him away from among the king&apos;s sons who were about to be put to death, and she put him and his nurse in a bedroom. Thus Jehoshabeath, the daughter of King Jehoram and wife of Jehoiada the priest, because she was a sister of Ahaziah, hid him<note nid="n14022011.2"/> from Athaliah, so that she did not put him to death.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14022012"/>
    <verse num="12">And he remained with them six years, hidden in the house of God, while Athaliah reigned over the land.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023001"/>
  <chapter num="23">
    <heading>Joash Made King</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="m" cid="c14023001.1"/>But in the seventh year Jehoiada took courage and entered into a covenant with the commanders of hundreds, Azariah the son of Jeroham, Ishmael the son of Jehohanan, Azariah the son of Obed, Maaseiah the son of Adaiah, and Elishaphat the son of Zichri.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023002"/>
    <verse num="2">And they went about through <crossref let="n" cid="c14023002.1"/>Judah and gathered the Levites from all the cities of Judah, and the heads of fathers&apos; houses of Israel, and they came to Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023003"/>
    <verse num="3">And all the assembly made a covenant with the king in the house of God. And Jehoiada<note nid="n14023003.1"/> said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="14023003.1" from="14023003.1" to="14023007.1"/>Behold, the king&apos;s son! Let him reign, <crossref let="o" cid="c14023003.1"/>as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke concerning the sons of David.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023004"/>
    <verse num="4">This is the thing that you shall do: <crossref let="p" cid="c14023004.1"/>of you priests and Levites who come off duty on the Sabbath, one third shall be gatekeepers,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023005"/>
    <verse num="5">and one third shall be at the king&apos;s house and one third at the Gate of the Foundation. And all the people shall be in the courts of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023006"/>
    <verse num="6">Let no one enter the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> except the priests <crossref let="q" cid="c14023006.1"/>and ministering Levites. They may enter, for they are holy, but all the people shall keep the charge of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023007"/>
    <verse num="7">The Levites shall surround the king, each with his weapons in his hand. And whoever enters the house shall be put to death. Be with the king when he comes in and when he goes out.<q class="end-double" qid="14023007.1" from="14023003.1" to="14023007.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">The Levites and all Judah did according to all that Jehoiada the priest commanded, and they each brought his men, who were to go off duty on the Sabbath, with those who were to come on duty on the Sabbath, for Jehoiada the priest did not dismiss <crossref let="r" cid="c14023008.1"/>the divisions.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023009"/>
    <verse num="9">And Jehoiada the priest gave to the captains the spears and the large and small shields that had been King David&apos;s, which were in the house of God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023010"/>
    <verse num="10">And he set all the people as a guard for the king, every man with his weapon in his hand, from the south side of the house to the north side of the house, around the altar and the house.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023011"/>
    <verse num="11">Then they brought out the king&apos;s son and put the crown on him and gave him <crossref let="s" cid="c14023011.1"/>the testimony. And they proclaimed him king, and Jehoiada and his sons anointed him, and they said, <crossref let="t" cid="c14023011.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14023011.1" from="14023011.1" to="14023011.2"/>Long live the king.<q class="end-double" qid="14023011.2" from="14023011.1" to="14023011.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023012"/>
    <heading>Athaliah Executed</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">When Athaliah heard the noise of the people running and praising the king, she went into the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to the people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023013"/>
    <verse num="13">And when she looked, there was the king standing by his pillar at the entrance, and the captains and the trumpeters beside the king, and all the people of the land rejoicing and blowing trumpets, and the singers with their musical instruments leading in the celebration. And Athaliah tore her clothes and cried, <q class="begin-double" qid="14023013.1" from="14023013.1" to="14023013.2"/>Treason! Treason!<q class="end-double" qid="14023013.2" from="14023013.1" to="14023013.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023014"/>
    <verse num="14">Then Jehoiada the priest brought out the captains who were set over the army, saying to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="14023014.1" from="14023014.1" to="14023014.2"/>Bring her out between the ranks, and anyone who follows her is to be put to death with the sword.<q class="end-double" qid="14023014.2" from="14023014.1" to="14023014.2"/> For the priest said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14023014.3" from="14023014.3" to="14023014.4"/>Do not put her to death in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="14023014.4" from="14023014.3" to="14023014.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023015"/>
    <verse num="15">So they laid hands on her,<note nid="n14023015.1"/> and she went into the entrance of <crossref let="u" cid="c14023015.1"/>the horse gate of the king&apos;s house, and they put her to death there.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023016"/>
    <heading>Jehoiada&apos;s Reforms</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">And Jehoiada made a covenant between himself and all the people and the king that they should be the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023017"/>
    <verse num="17">Then all the people went to the house of Baal and tore it down; his altars and his images they broke in pieces, <crossref let="v" cid="c14023017.1"/>and they killed Mattan the priest of Baal before the altars.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023018"/>
    <verse num="18">And Jehoiada posted watchmen for the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> under the direction of <crossref let="w" cid="c14023018.1"/>the Levitical priests and the Levites <crossref let="x" cid="c14023018.2"/>whom David had organized to be in charge of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, to offer burnt offerings to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="y" cid="c14023018.3"/>as it is written in the Law of Moses, with rejoicing and with singing, <crossref let="z" cid="c14023018.4"/>according to the order of David.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023019"/>
    <verse num="19">He stationed <crossref let="a" cid="c14023019.1"/>the gatekeepers at the gates of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> so that no one should enter who was in any way unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023020"/>
    <verse num="20">And he took the captains, the nobles, the governors of the people, and all the people of the land, and they brought the king down from the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, marching <crossref let="b" cid="c14023020.1"/>through the upper gate to the king&apos;s house. And they set the king on the royal throne.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14023021"/>
    <verse num="21">So all the people of the land rejoiced, and the city was quiet after Athaliah had been put to death with the sword.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024001"/>
  <chapter num="24">
    <heading>Joash Repairs the Temple</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="c" cid="c14024001.1"/>Joash<note nid="n14024001.1"/> was seven years old when he began to reign, and he reigned forty years in Jerusalem. His mother&apos;s name was Zibiah of Beersheba.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="d" cid="c14024002.1"/>And Joash did what was right in the eyes of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> all the days of Jehoiada the priest.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024003"/>
    <verse num="3">Jehoiada got for him two wives, and he had sons and daughters.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">After this Joash <crossref let="e" cid="c14024004.1"/>decided to <crossref let="f" cid="c14024004.2"/>restore the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024005"/>
    <verse num="5">And he gathered the priests and the Levites and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="14024005.1" from="14024005.1" to="14024005.2"/>Go out to the cities of <crossref let="g" cid="c14024005.1"/>Judah and gather from all Israel money to repair the house of your God from year to year, and see that you act quickly.<q class="end-double" qid="14024005.2" from="14024005.1" to="14024005.2"/> But the Levites did not act quickly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024006"/>
    <verse num="6">So the king summoned Jehoiada the chief and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="14024006.1" from="14024006.1" to="14024006.2"/>Why have you not required the Levites to bring in from Judah and Jerusalem <crossref let="h" cid="c14024006.1"/>the tax levied by Moses, the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and the congregation of Israel for <crossref let="i" cid="c14024006.2"/>the tent of testimony?<q class="end-double" qid="14024006.2" from="14024006.1" to="14024006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024007"/>
    <verse num="7">For <crossref let="j" cid="c14024007.1"/>the sons of Athaliah, that wicked woman, had broken into the house of God, and had also used all <crossref let="k" cid="c14024007.2"/>the dedicated things of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for the Baals.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">So the king commanded, and they made a chest and set it outside the gate of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024009"/>
    <verse num="9">And <crossref let="l" cid="c14024009.1"/>proclamation was made throughout Judah and Jerusalem to bring in for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="h" cid="c14024009.2"/>the tax that Moses the servant of God laid on Israel in the wilderness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024010"/>
    <verse num="10">And all the princes and all the people rejoiced and brought their tax and dropped it into the chest until they had finished.<note nid="n14024010.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024011"/>
    <verse num="11">And whenever the chest was brought to the king&apos;s officers by the Levites, when they saw that there was much money in it, the king&apos;s secretary and the officer of the chief priest would come and empty the chest and take it and return it to its place. Thus they did day after day, and collected money in abundance.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024012"/>
    <verse num="12">And the king and Jehoiada gave it to those who had charge of the work of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and they hired masons and carpenters to restore the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and also workers in iron and bronze to repair the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024013"/>
    <verse num="13">So those who were engaged in the work labored, and the repairing went forward in their hands, and they restored the house of God to its proper condition and strengthened it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024014"/>
    <verse num="14">And when they had finished, they brought the rest of the money before the king and Jehoiada, and with it <crossref let="m" cid="c14024014.1"/>were made utensils for the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, both for the service and for the burnt offerings, and dishes for incense and vessels of gold and silver. And they offered burnt offerings in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> regularly all the days of Jehoiada.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">But Jehoiada grew old and full of days, and died. He was 130 years old at his death.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024016"/>
    <verse num="16">And they buried him in the city of David among the kings, because he had done good in Israel, and toward God and his house.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024017"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17">Now after the death of Jehoiada the princes of Judah came and paid homage to the king. Then the king listened to them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024018"/>
    <verse num="18">And they abandoned the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers, and served <crossref let="o" cid="c14024018.1"/>the Asherim and the idols. And <crossref let="p" cid="c14024018.2"/>wrath came upon Judah and Jerusalem for this guilt of theirs.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024019"/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="q" cid="c14024019.1"/>Yet he sent prophets among them to bring them back to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. <crossref let="r" cid="c14024019.2"/>These testified against them, but they would not pay attention.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024020"/>
    <heading>Joash&apos;s Treachery</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="s" cid="c14024020.1"/>Then the Spirit of God clothed Zechariah <crossref let="t" cid="c14024020.2"/>the son of Jehoiada the priest, and he stood above the people, and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="14024020.1" from="14024020.1" to="14024020.4"/>Thus says God, <crossref let="u" cid="c14024020.3"/><q class="begin-single" qid="14024020.2" from="14024020.2" to="14024020.3"/>Why do you break the commandments of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, so that you cannot prosper? <crossref let="v" cid="c14024020.4"/>Because you have forsaken the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, he has forsaken you.<q class="end-single" qid="14024020.3" from="14024020.2" to="14024020.3"/><q class="end-double" qid="14024020.4" from="14024020.1" to="14024020.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024021"/>
    <verse num="21">But <crossref let="w" cid="c14024021.1"/>they conspired against him, <crossref let="x" cid="c14024021.2"/>and by command of the king they stoned him with stones in the court of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024022"/>
    <verse num="22">Thus Joash the king did not remember the kindness that Jehoiada, Zechariah&apos;s father, had shown him, but killed his son. And when he was dying, he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14024022.1" from="14024022.1" to="14024022.2"/>May the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> see <crossref let="y" cid="c14024022.1"/>and avenge!<q class="end-double" qid="14024022.2" from="14024022.1" to="14024022.2"/><note nid="n14024022.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024023"/>
    <heading>Joash Assassinated</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="23">At the end of the year <crossref let="z" cid="c14024023.1"/>the army of the Syrians came up against Joash. They came to Judah and Jerusalem and destroyed all the princes of the people from among the people and sent all their spoil to the king of Damascus.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024024"/>
    <verse num="24">Though the army of the Syrians had come with few men, <crossref let="a" cid="c14024024.1"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> delivered into their hand a very great army, <crossref let="v" cid="c14024024.2"/>because Judah<note nid="n14024024.1"/> had forsaken the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers. Thus they <crossref let="b" cid="c14024024.3"/>executed judgment on Joash.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024025"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="25">When they had departed from him, leaving him <crossref let="c" cid="c14024025.1"/>severely wounded, <crossref let="d" cid="c14024025.2"/>his servants conspired against him because of the blood of <crossref let="e" cid="c14024025.3"/>the son<note nid="n14024025.1"/> of Jehoiada the priest, and killed him on his bed. So he died, and they buried him in the city of David, <crossref let="f" cid="c14024025.4"/>but they did not bury him in the tombs of the kings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024026"/>
    <verse num="26">Those who conspired against him were Zabad the son of Shimeath the Ammonite, and Jehozabad the son of Shimrith the Moabite.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14024027"/>
    <verse num="27">Accounts of his sons and of the many oracles against him and of <crossref let="g" cid="c14024027.1"/>the rebuilding<note nid="n14024027.1"/> of the house of God are written in the <crossref let="h" cid="c14024027.2"/>Story<note nid="n14024027.2"/> of the Book of the Kings. And Amaziah his son reigned in his place.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025001"/>
  <chapter num="25">
    <heading>Amaziah Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="i" cid="c14025001.1"/>Amaziah was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother&apos;s name was Jehoaddan of Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025002"/>
    <verse num="2">And he did what was right in the eyes of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="j" cid="c14025002.1"/>yet not with a whole heart.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025003"/>
    <verse num="3">And as soon as the royal power was firmly his, he killed his servants who had struck down the king his father.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025004"/>
    <verse num="4">But he did not put their children to death, according to what is written in the Law, in the Book of Moses, where the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded, <crossref let="k" cid="c14025004.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14025004.1" from="14025004.1" to="14025004.2"/>Fathers shall not die because of their children, nor children die because of their fathers, but each one shall die for his own sin.<q class="end-double" qid="14025004.2" from="14025004.1" to="14025004.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025005"/>
    <heading>Amaziah&apos;s Victories</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5">Then Amaziah assembled the men of Judah and set them by fathers&apos; houses under commanders of thousands and of hundreds for all Judah and Benjamin. He mustered those <crossref let="l" cid="c14025005.1"/>twenty years old and upward, and found that they were <crossref let="m" cid="c14025005.2"/>300,000 choice men, fit for war, <crossref let="n" cid="c14025005.3"/>able to handle spear and shield.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025006"/>
    <verse num="6">He hired also 100,000 mighty men of valor from Israel for 100 talents<note nid="n14025006.1"/> of silver.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025007"/>
    <verse num="7">But <crossref let="o" cid="c14025007.1"/>a man of God came to him and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14025007.1" from="14025007.1" to="14025008.1"/>O king, do not let the army of Israel go with you, for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is not with Israel, with all these Ephraimites.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025008"/>
    <verse num="8">But go, act, be strong for the battle. Why should you suppose that God will cast you down before the enemy? <crossref let="p" cid="c14025008.1"/>For God has power to help or to cast down.<q class="end-double" qid="14025008.1" from="14025007.1" to="14025008.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025009"/>
    <verse num="9">And Amaziah said to the man of God, <q class="begin-double" qid="14025009.1" from="14025009.1" to="14025009.2"/>But what shall we do about the hundred talents that I have given to the army of Israel?<q class="end-double" qid="14025009.2" from="14025009.1" to="14025009.2"/> The man of God answered, <q class="begin-double" qid="14025009.3" from="14025009.3" to="14025009.4"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is able to give you much more than this.<q class="end-double" qid="14025009.4" from="14025009.3" to="14025009.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025010"/>
    <verse num="10">Then Amaziah discharged the army that had come to him from Ephraim to go home again. And they became very angry with Judah and returned home in fierce anger.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025011"/>
    <verse num="11">But Amaziah took courage and led out his people and went to the <crossref let="q" cid="c14025011.1"/>Valley of Salt and struck down <crossref let="r" cid="c14025011.2"/>10,000 men of Seir.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025012"/>
    <verse num="12">The men of Judah captured another 10,000 alive and took them to the top of a rock and threw them down from the top of the rock, and they were all dashed to pieces.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025013"/>
    <verse num="13">But the men of the army whom Amaziah sent back, not letting them go with him to battle, raided the cities of Judah, <crossref let="s" cid="c14025013.1"/>from Samaria to Beth-horon, and struck down 3,000 people in them and took much spoil.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025014"/>
    <heading>Amaziah&apos;s Idolatry</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14">After Amaziah came from striking down the Edomites, <crossref let="t" cid="c14025014.1"/>he brought the gods <crossref let="r" cid="c14025014.2"/>of the men of Seir and set them up as his gods and worshiped them, making offerings to them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025015"/>
    <verse num="15">Therefore the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was angry with Amaziah and sent to him a prophet, who said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="14025015.1" from="14025015.1" to="14025015.2"/>Why have you sought the gods of a people <crossref let="u" cid="c14025015.1"/>who did not deliver their own people from your hand?<q class="end-double" qid="14025015.2" from="14025015.1" to="14025015.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025016"/>
    <verse num="16">But as he was speaking, the king said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="14025016.1" from="14025016.1" to="14025016.2"/>Have we made you a royal counselor? Stop! Why should you be struck down?<q class="end-double" qid="14025016.2" from="14025016.1" to="14025016.2"/> So the prophet stopped, but said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14025016.3" from="14025016.3" to="14025016.4"/>I know that <crossref let="v" cid="c14025016.1"/>God has determined to destroy you, because you have done this and have not listened to my counsel.<q class="end-double" qid="14025016.4" from="14025016.3" to="14025016.4"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025017"/>
    <heading>Israel Defeats Amaziah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="w" cid="c14025017.1"/>Then Amaziah king of Judah took counsel and sent to Joash the son of Jehoahaz, son of Jehu, king of Israel, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="14025017.1" from="14025017.1" to="14025017.2"/>Come, let us look one another in the face.<q class="end-double" qid="14025017.2" from="14025017.1" to="14025017.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025018"/>
    <verse num="18">And Joash the king of Israel sent word to Amaziah king of Judah, <crossref let="x" cid="c14025018.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14025018.1" from="14025018.1" to="14025019.3"/>A thistle on Lebanon sent to a cedar on Lebanon, saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="14025018.2" from="14025018.2" to="14025018.3"/>Give your daughter to my son for a wife,<q class="end-single" qid="14025018.3" from="14025018.2" to="14025018.3"/> and a wild beast of Lebanon passed by and trampled down the thistle.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025019"/>
    <verse num="19">You say, <q class="begin-single" qid="14025019.1" from="14025019.1" to="14025019.2"/>See, I<note nid="n14025019.1"/> have struck down Edom,<q class="end-single" qid="14025019.2" from="14025019.1" to="14025019.2"/> and <crossref let="y" cid="c14025019.1"/>your heart has lifted you up in boastfulness. But now stay at home. Why should you provoke trouble so that you fall, you and Judah with you?<q class="end-double" qid="14025019.3" from="14025018.1" to="14025019.3"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025020"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20">But Amaziah would not listen, for it was of God, in order that he might give them into the hand of their enemies, <crossref let="z" cid="c14025020.1"/>because they had sought the gods of Edom.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025021"/>
    <verse num="21">So Joash king of Israel went up, and he and Amaziah king of Judah faced one another in battle at Beth-shemesh, which belongs to Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025022"/>
    <verse num="22">And Judah was defeated by Israel, and every man fled to his home.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025023"/>
    <verse num="23">And Joash king of Israel captured Amaziah king of Judah, the son of Joash, son of <crossref let="a" cid="c14025023.1"/>Ahaziah, at Beth-shemesh, and brought him to Jerusalem and broke down the wall of Jerusalem for 400 cubits,<note nid="n14025023.1"/> from <crossref let="b" cid="c14025023.2"/>the Ephraim Gate to the Corner Gate.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025024"/>
    <verse num="24">And he seized all the gold and silver, and all the vessels that were found in the house of God, in the care of <crossref let="c" cid="c14025024.1"/>Obed-edom. He seized also the treasuries of the king&apos;s house, also hostages, and he returned to Samaria.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025025"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="25"><crossref let="d" cid="c14025025.1"/>Amaziah the son of Joash, king of Judah, lived fifteen years after the death of Joash the son of Jehoahaz, king of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025026"/>
    <verse num="26">Now the rest of the deeds of Amaziah, from first to last, are they not written in the Book of the Kings of Judah and Israel?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025027"/>
    <verse num="27">From the time when he turned away from the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> they made a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem, and he fled to Lachish. But they sent after him to Lachish and put him to death there.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14025028"/>
    <verse num="28">And they brought him upon horses, and he was buried with his fathers in the city of David.<note nid="n14025028.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026001"/>
  <chapter num="26">
    <heading>Uzziah Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">And all the people of Judah took Uzziah, who was sixteen years old, and made him king instead of his father Amaziah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026002"/>
    <verse num="2">He built Eloth and restored it to Judah, after the king slept with his fathers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026003"/>
    <verse num="3">Uzziah was <crossref let="e" cid="c14026003.1"/>sixteen years old when he began to reign, and he reigned fifty-two years in Jerusalem. His mother&apos;s name was Jecoliah of Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026004"/>
    <verse num="4">And he did what was right in the eyes of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, according to all that his father Amaziah had done.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026005"/>
    <verse num="5">He set himself to seek God <crossref let="f" cid="c14026005.1"/>in the days of Zechariah, <crossref let="g" cid="c14026005.2"/>who instructed him in the fear of God, and as long as he sought the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, God made him prosper.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6">He went out and <crossref let="h" cid="c14026006.1"/>made war against the Philistines and broke through the wall of Gath and the wall of Jabneh and the wall of Ashdod, and he built cities in the territory of Ashdod and elsewhere among the Philistines.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026007"/>
    <verse num="7">God helped him <crossref let="i" cid="c14026007.1"/>against the Philistines and against the Arabians who lived in Gurbaal and against the <crossref let="j" cid="c14026007.2"/>Meunites.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026008"/>
    <verse num="8">The Ammonites <crossref let="k" cid="c14026008.1"/>paid tribute to Uzziah, and his fame spread even to the border of Egypt, for he became very strong.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026009"/>
    <verse num="9">Moreover, Uzziah built towers in Jerusalem at <crossref let="l" cid="c14026009.1"/>the Corner Gate and at <crossref let="m" cid="c14026009.2"/>the Valley Gate and at <crossref let="n" cid="c14026009.3"/>the Angle, and fortified them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026010"/>
    <verse num="10">And he built towers in the wilderness and <crossref let="o" cid="c14026010.1"/>cut out many cisterns, for he had large herds, both in the Shephelah and in the plain, and he had farmers and vinedressers in the hills and in the fertile lands, for he loved the soil.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026011"/>
    <verse num="11">Moreover, Uzziah had an army of soldiers, fit for war, in divisions according to the numbers in the muster made by Jeiel the secretary and Maaseiah the officer, under the direction of Hananiah, one of the king&apos;s commanders.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026012"/>
    <verse num="12">The whole number of the heads of fathers&apos; houses of mighty men of valor was 2,600.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026013"/>
    <verse num="13">Under their command was an army of <crossref let="p" cid="c14026013.1"/>307,500, who could make war with mighty power, to help the king against the enemy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026014"/>
    <verse num="14">And Uzziah prepared for all the army shields, spears, helmets, <crossref let="q" cid="c14026014.1"/>coats of mail, bows, and stones for slinging.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026015"/>
    <verse num="15">In Jerusalem he made machines, invented by skillful men, to be on the towers and the corners, to shoot arrows and great stones. And his fame spread far, for he was marvelously helped, till he was strong.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026016"/>
    <heading>Uzziah&apos;s Pride and Punishment</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">But when <crossref let="r" cid="c14026016.1"/>he was strong, <crossref let="s" cid="c14026016.2"/>he grew proud, to his destruction. For he was unfaithful to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God and entered the temple of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to burn incense on the altar of incense.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026017"/>
    <verse num="17">But <crossref let="t" cid="c14026017.1"/>Azariah the priest went in after him, with eighty priests of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> who were men of valor,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026018"/>
    <verse num="18">and they withstood King Uzziah and said to him, <crossref let="u" cid="c14026018.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14026018.1" from="14026018.1" to="14026018.2"/>It is not for you, Uzziah, to burn incense to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="v" cid="c14026018.2"/>but for the priests, the sons of Aaron, who are consecrated to burn incense. Go out of the sanctuary, for you have done wrong, and it will bring you no honor from the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God.<q class="end-double" qid="14026018.2" from="14026018.1" to="14026018.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026019"/>
    <verse num="19">Then Uzziah was angry. Now he had a censer in his hand to burn incense, and when he became angry with the priests, <crossref let="w" cid="c14026019.1"/>leprosy<note nid="n14026019.1"/> broke out on his forehead in the presence of the priests in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, by the altar of incense.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026020"/>
    <verse num="20">And Azariah the chief priest and all the priests looked at him, and behold, he was leprous in his forehead! And they rushed him out quickly, and he himself hurried to go out, because the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had struck him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026021"/>
    <verse num="21"><crossref let="x" cid="c14026021.1"/>And King Uzziah was a leper to the day of his death, and being a leper lived <crossref let="y" cid="c14026021.2"/>in a separate house, for he was excluded from the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. And Jotham his son was over the king&apos;s household, governing the people of the land.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">Now the rest of the acts of Uzziah, from first to last, <crossref let="z" cid="c14026022.1"/>Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz wrote.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14026023"/>
    <verse num="23">And Uzziah slept with his fathers, and they buried him with his fathers in the burial field that belonged to the kings, for they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14026023.1" from="14026023.1" to="14026023.2"/>He is a leper.<q class="end-double" qid="14026023.2" from="14026023.1" to="14026023.2"/> And Jotham his son reigned in his place.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14027001"/>
  <chapter num="27">
    <heading>Jotham Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="a" cid="c14027001.1"/>Jotham was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. His mother&apos;s name was Jerushah the daughter of Zadok.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14027002"/>
    <verse num="2">And he did what was right in the eyes of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> according to all that his father Uzziah had done, <crossref let="b" cid="c14027002.1"/>except he did not enter the temple of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. But the people still followed corrupt practices.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14027003"/>
    <verse num="3">He built the upper gate of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and did much building on the wall of <crossref let="c" cid="c14027003.1"/>Ophel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14027004"/>
    <verse num="4">Moreover, he built cities in the hill country of Judah, and forts and towers on the wooded hills.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14027005"/>
    <verse num="5">He fought with the king of the Ammonites and prevailed against them. And the Ammonites gave him that year 100 talents<note nid="n14027005.1"/> of silver, and 10,000 cors<note nid="n14027005.2"/> of wheat and 10,000 of barley. The Ammonites paid him the same amount in the second and the third years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14027006"/>
    <verse num="6">So Jotham became mighty, because he ordered his ways before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14027007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="d" cid="c14027007.1"/>Now the rest of the acts of Jotham, and all his wars and his ways, behold, they are written in the Book of the Kings of Israel and Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14027008"/>
    <verse num="8">He was <crossref let="e" cid="c14027008.1"/>twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14027009"/>
    <verse num="9">And Jotham slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city of David, and Ahaz his son reigned in his place.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028001"/>
  <chapter num="28">
    <heading>Ahaz Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="f" cid="c14028001.1"/>Ahaz was twenty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. And he did not do what was right in the eyes of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, as his father David had done,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028002"/>
    <verse num="2">but he walked in the ways of the kings of Israel. He even made <crossref let="g" cid="c14028002.1"/>metal images for <crossref let="h" cid="c14028002.2"/>the Baals,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028003"/>
    <verse num="3">and <crossref let="i" cid="c14028003.1"/>he made offerings in the <crossref let="j" cid="c14028003.2"/>Valley of the Son of Hinnom and <crossref let="k" cid="c14028003.3"/>burned his sons as an offering,<note nid="n14028003.1"/> according to <crossref let="l" cid="c14028003.4"/>the abominations of the nations whom the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> drove out before the people of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028004"/>
    <verse num="4">And he sacrificed and <crossref let="i" cid="c14028004.1"/>made offerings on the high places and on the hills and under every green tree.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028005"/>
    <heading>Judah Defeated</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="m" cid="c14028005.1"/>Therefore the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God gave him into the hand of the king of Syria, who defeated him and took captive a great number of his people and brought them to Damascus. He was also given into the hand of the king of Israel, who struck him with great force.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028006"/>
    <verse num="6">For <crossref let="n" cid="c14028006.1"/>Pekah the son of Remaliah killed 120,000 from Judah in one day, all of them men of valor, because they had forsaken the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028007"/>
    <verse num="7">And Zichri, a mighty man of Ephraim, killed Maaseiah the king&apos;s son and Azrikam the commander of the palace and Elkanah the next in authority to the king.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">The men of Israel took captive 200,000 <crossref let="o" cid="c14028008.1"/>of their relatives, women, sons, and daughters. They also took much spoil from them and brought the spoil to Samaria.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028009"/>
    <verse num="9">But a prophet of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was there, whose name was Oded, and he went out to meet the army that came to Samaria and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="14028009.1" from="14028009.1" to="14028011.1"/>Behold, because the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of your fathers, <crossref let="p" cid="c14028009.1"/>was angry with Judah, he gave them into your hand, but you have killed them in a rage <crossref let="q" cid="c14028009.2"/>that has reached up to heaven.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028010"/>
    <verse num="10">And now you intend to subjugate the people of Judah and Jerusalem, male and female, as your slaves. Have you not sins of your own against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028011"/>
    <verse num="11">Now hear me, and send back the captives <crossref let="o" cid="c14028011.1"/>from your relatives whom you have taken, for the fierce wrath of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is upon you.<q class="end-double" qid="14028011.1" from="14028009.1" to="14028011.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">Certain chiefs also of the men of Ephraim, Azariah the son of Johanan, Berechiah the son of Meshillemoth, Jehizkiah the son of Shallum, and Amasa the son of Hadlai, stood up against those who were coming from the war</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028013"/>
    <verse num="13">and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="14028013.1" from="14028013.1" to="14028013.2"/>You shall not bring the captives in here, for you propose to bring upon us guilt against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in addition to our present sins and guilt. For our guilt is already great, and there is fierce wrath against Israel.<q class="end-double" qid="14028013.2" from="14028013.1" to="14028013.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028014"/>
    <verse num="14">So the armed men left the captives and the spoil before the princes and all the assembly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028015"/>
    <verse num="15">And <crossref let="r" cid="c14028015.1"/>the men who have been mentioned by name rose and took the captives, and with the spoil they clothed all who were naked among them. They clothed them, gave them sandals, <crossref let="s" cid="c14028015.2"/>provided them with food and drink, and anointed them, and carrying all the feeble among them on donkeys, they brought them to their kinsfolk at Jericho, <crossref let="t" cid="c14028015.3"/>the city of palm trees. Then they returned to Samaria.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="u" cid="c14028016.1"/>At that time King Ahaz sent to the king<note nid="n14028016.1"/> of Assyria for help.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028017"/>
    <verse num="17">For the Edomites had again invaded and defeated Judah and carried away captives.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028018"/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="v" cid="c14028018.1"/>And the Philistines had made raids on <crossref let="w" cid="c14028018.2"/>the cities in the Shephelah and the Negeb of Judah, and had taken Beth-shemesh, Aijalon, Gederoth, Soco <crossref let="x" cid="c14028018.3"/>with its villages, Timnah with its villages, and Gimzo with its villages. And they settled there.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028019"/>
    <verse num="19">For the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> humbled Judah because of Ahaz king of Israel, for he had made <crossref let="y" cid="c14028019.1"/>Judah act sinfully<note nid="n14028019.1"/> and had been very unfaithful to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028020"/>
    <verse num="20">So <crossref let="z" cid="c14028020.1"/>Tiglath-pileser<note nid="n14028020.1"/> king of Assyria came against him and afflicted him instead of strengthening him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028021"/>
    <verse num="21"><crossref let="a" cid="c14028021.1"/>For Ahaz took a portion from the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and the house of the king and of the princes, and gave tribute to the king of Assyria, but it did not help him.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028022"/>
    <heading>Ahaz&apos;s Idolatry</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">In the time of his distress he became yet more faithless to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&emdash;this same King Ahaz.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028023"/>
    <verse num="23">For <crossref let="b" cid="c14028023.1"/>he sacrificed to the gods of Damascus that had defeated him and said, <crossref let="c" cid="c14028023.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14028023.1" from="14028023.1" to="14028023.2"/>Because the gods of the kings of Syria helped them, I will sacrifice to them that they may help me.<q class="end-double" qid="14028023.2" from="14028023.1" to="14028023.2"/> But they were the ruin of him and of all Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028024"/>
    <verse num="24">And Ahaz gathered together the vessels of the house of God and <crossref let="d" cid="c14028024.1"/>cut in pieces the vessels of the house of God, and he shut up the doors of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and he made himself <crossref let="e" cid="c14028024.2"/>altars in every corner of Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028025"/>
    <verse num="25">In every city of Judah he made high places to <crossref let="f" cid="c14028025.1"/>make offerings to other gods, provoking to anger the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of his fathers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028026"/>
    <verse num="26"><crossref let="g" cid="c14028026.1"/>Now the rest of his acts and all his ways, from first to last, behold, they are written in the Book of the Kings of Judah and Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14028027"/>
    <verse num="27">And Ahaz slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city, in Jerusalem, for <crossref let="h" cid="c14028027.1"/>they did not bring him into the tombs of the kings of Israel. And Hezekiah his son reigned in his place.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029001"/>
  <chapter num="29">
    <heading>Hezekiah Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="j" cid="c14029001.1"/>Hezekiah began to reign when he was twenty-five years old, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother&apos;s name was Abijah<note nid="n14029001.1"/> the daughter of <crossref let="k" cid="c14029001.2"/>Zechariah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029002"/>
    <verse num="2">And he did what was right in the eyes of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, according to all that David his father had done.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029003"/>
    <heading>Hezekiah Cleanses the Temple</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3">In the first year of his reign, in the first month, he <crossref let="l" cid="c14029003.1"/>opened the doors of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and repaired them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029004"/>
    <verse num="4">He brought in the priests and the Levites and assembled them in the square on the east</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029005"/>
    <verse num="5">and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="14029005.1" from="14029005.1" to="14029011.1"/>Hear me, Levites! Now <crossref let="m" cid="c14029005.1"/>consecrate yourselves, and consecrate the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of your fathers, and carry out the filth<note nid="n14029005.1"/> from the Holy Place.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029006"/>
    <verse num="6">For our fathers have been unfaithful and have done what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God. They have forsaken him and <crossref let="n" cid="c14029006.1"/>have turned away their faces from the habitation of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and turned their backs.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029007"/>
    <verse num="7">They also <crossref let="o" cid="c14029007.1"/>shut the doors of the vestibule and put out the lamps and have not burned incense or offered burnt offerings in the Holy Place to the God of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029008"/>
    <verse num="8">Therefore <crossref let="p" cid="c14029008.1"/>the wrath of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> came on Judah and Jerusalem, and he has made them <crossref let="q" cid="c14029008.2"/>an object of horror, of astonishment, <crossref let="r" cid="c14029008.3"/>and of hissing, as you see with your own eyes.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029009"/>
    <verse num="9">For behold, <crossref let="s" cid="c14029009.1"/>our fathers have fallen by the sword, and our sons and our daughters and our wives are in captivity for this.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029010"/>
    <verse num="10">Now <crossref let="t" cid="c14029010.1"/>it is in my heart <crossref let="u" cid="c14029010.2"/>to make a covenant with the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, in order that his fierce anger may turn away from us.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029011"/>
    <verse num="11">My sons, do not now be negligent, <crossref let="v" cid="c14029011.1"/>for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has chosen you to stand in his presence, to minister to him and to be his ministers and make offerings to him.<q class="end-double" qid="14029011.1" from="14029005.1" to="14029011.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">Then the Levites arose, <crossref let="w" cid="c14029012.1"/>Mahath the son of Amasai, and Joel the son of Azariah, of the sons of <crossref let="x" cid="c14029012.2"/>the Kohathites; and of the sons of <crossref let="x" cid="c14029012.3"/>Merari, Kish the son of Abdi, and Azariah the son of Jehallelel; and of the <crossref let="x" cid="c14029012.4"/>Gershonites, Joah the son of Zimmah, and Eden the son of Joah;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029013"/>
    <verse num="13">and of the sons of <crossref let="y" cid="c14029013.1"/>Elizaphan, Shimri and Jeuel; and of the sons of <crossref let="z" cid="c14029013.2"/>Asaph, Zechariah and Mattaniah;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029014"/>
    <verse num="14">and of the sons of <crossref let="a" cid="c14029014.1"/>Heman, Jehuel and Shimei; and of the sons of <crossref let="b" cid="c14029014.2"/>Jeduthun, Shemaiah and Uzziel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029015"/>
    <verse num="15">They gathered their brothers and <crossref let="c" cid="c14029015.1"/>consecrated themselves and went in as the king had commanded, <crossref let="d" cid="c14029015.2"/>by the words of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="e" cid="c14029015.3"/>to cleanse the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029016"/>
    <verse num="16">The priests went into the inner part of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to cleanse it, and they brought out all the uncleanness that they found in the temple of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> into the court of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. And the Levites took it and carried it out to <crossref let="f" cid="c14029016.1"/>the brook Kidron.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029017"/>
    <verse num="17">They began to consecrate <crossref let="g" cid="c14029017.1"/>on the first day of the first month, and on the eighth day of the month they came to the vestibule of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. Then for eight days they consecrated the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and on the sixteenth day of the first month they finished.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029018"/>
    <verse num="18">Then they went in to Hezekiah the king and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="14029018.1" from="14029018.1" to="14029019.1"/>We have cleansed all the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the altar of burnt offering and all its utensils, and the table for the showbread and all its utensils.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029019"/>
    <verse num="19">All the utensils <crossref let="h" cid="c14029019.1"/>that King Ahaz discarded in his reign when he was faithless, we have made ready and consecrated, and behold, they are before the altar of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="14029019.1" from="14029018.1" to="14029019.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029020"/>
    <heading>Hezekiah Restores Temple Worship</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20">Then Hezekiah the king rose early and gathered the officials of the city and went up to the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029021"/>
    <verse num="21">And they brought seven bulls, seven rams, seven lambs, and seven male goats <crossref let="i" cid="c14029021.1"/>for a sin offering for the kingdom and for the sanctuary and for Judah. And he commanded the priests, the sons of Aaron, to offer them on the altar of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029022"/>
    <verse num="22">So they slaughtered the bulls, and the priests received the blood <crossref let="j" cid="c14029022.1"/>and threw it against the altar. And they slaughtered the rams, and their blood was thrown against the altar. And they slaughtered the lambs, and their blood was thrown against the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029023"/>
    <verse num="23">Then the goats for the sin offering were brought to the king and the assembly, <crossref let="k" cid="c14029023.1"/>and they laid their hands on them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029024"/>
    <verse num="24">and the priests slaughtered them and made a sin offering with their blood on the altar, <crossref let="l" cid="c14029024.1"/>to make atonement for all Israel. For the king commanded that the burnt offering and the sin offering should be made for all Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029025"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="25"><crossref let="m" cid="c14029025.1"/>And he stationed the Levites in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> with cymbals, harps, and lyres, <crossref let="n" cid="c14029025.2"/>according to the commandment of David and of Gad <crossref let="o" cid="c14029025.3"/>the king&apos;s seer and of <crossref let="p" cid="c14029025.4"/>Nathan the prophet, for the commandment was from the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> through his prophets.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029026"/>
    <verse num="26">The Levites stood with <crossref let="q" cid="c14029026.1"/>the instruments of David, <crossref let="r" cid="c14029026.2"/>and the priests with the trumpets.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029027"/>
    <verse num="27">Then Hezekiah commanded that the burnt offering be offered on the altar. And when the burnt offering began, <crossref let="s" cid="c14029027.1"/>the song to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> began also, and the trumpets, accompanied by the instruments of David king of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029028"/>
    <verse num="28">The whole assembly worshiped, and the singers sang, and the trumpeters sounded. All this continued until the burnt offering was finished.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029029"/>
    <verse num="29">When the offering was finished, <crossref let="t" cid="c14029029.1"/>the king and all who were present with him bowed themselves and worshiped.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029030"/>
    <verse num="30">And Hezekiah the king and the officials commanded the Levites to sing praises to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> with the words of David and of Asaph the seer. And they sang praises with gladness, and they bowed down and worshiped.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029031"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="31">Then Hezekiah said, <crossref let="u" cid="c14029031.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14029031.1" from="14029031.1" to="14029031.2"/>You have now consecrated yourselves to<note nid="n14029031.1"/> the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. Come near; bring sacrifices and thank offerings to the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="14029031.2" from="14029031.1" to="14029031.2"/> And the assembly brought sacrifices and thank offerings, and all who were <crossref let="v" cid="c14029031.2"/>of a willing heart brought burnt offerings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029032"/>
    <verse num="32">The number of the burnt offerings that the assembly brought was 70 bulls, 100 rams, and 200 lambs; all these were for a burnt offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029033"/>
    <verse num="33">And the consecrated offerings were 600 bulls and 3,000 sheep.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029034"/>
    <verse num="34">But the priests were too few and could not flay all the burnt offerings, so until other priests had consecrated themselves, <crossref let="w" cid="c14029034.1"/>their brothers the Levites helped them, until the work was finished&emdash;<crossref let="x" cid="c14029034.2"/>for the Levites were more upright in heart than the priests in consecrating themselves.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029035"/>
    <verse num="35">Besides the great number of burnt offerings, there was <crossref let="y" cid="c14029035.1"/>the fat of the peace offerings, and there were <crossref let="z" cid="c14029035.2"/>the drink offerings for the burnt offerings. Thus the service of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was restored.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14029036"/>
    <verse num="36">And Hezekiah and all the people rejoiced because God had provided for the people, for the thing came about suddenly.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030001"/>
  <chapter num="30">
    <heading>Passover Celebrated</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Hezekiah sent to all Israel and Judah, and wrote letters also to Ephraim and Manasseh, that they should come to the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> at Jerusalem to keep the Passover to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030002"/>
    <verse num="2">For the king and his princes and all the assembly in Jerusalem had taken counsel to keep the Passover <crossref let="a" cid="c14030002.1"/>in the second month&emdash;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030003"/>
    <verse num="3">for they could not keep it <crossref let="b" cid="c14030003.1"/>at that time <crossref let="c" cid="c14030003.2"/>because the priests had not consecrated themselves in sufficient number, nor had the people assembled in Jerusalem&emdash;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030004"/>
    <verse num="4">and the plan seemed right to the king and all the assembly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030005"/>
    <verse num="5">So they decreed to make a proclamation throughout all Israel, <crossref let="d" cid="c14030005.1"/>from Beersheba to Dan, that the people should come and keep the Passover to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, at Jerusalem, for they had not kept it as often as prescribed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="e" cid="c14030006.1"/>So couriers went throughout all Israel and Judah with letters from the king and his princes, as the king had commanded, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="14030006.1" from="14030006.1" to="14030009.1"/>O people of Israel, <crossref let="f" cid="c14030006.2"/>return to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, that he may turn again to the remnant of you who have escaped from the hand of <crossref let="g" cid="c14030006.3"/>the kings of Assyria.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="h" cid="c14030007.1"/>Do not be like your fathers and your brothers, who were faithless to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God of their fathers, so that he made them a desolation, as you see.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="i" cid="c14030008.1"/>Do not now be stiff-necked as your fathers were, but yield yourselves to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and come to his sanctuary, which he has consecrated forever, and serve the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God, <crossref let="j" cid="c14030008.2"/>that his fierce anger may turn away from you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030009"/>
    <verse num="9">For <crossref let="f" cid="c14030009.1"/>if you return to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, your brothers and your children <crossref let="k" cid="c14030009.2"/>will find compassion with their captors and return to this land. For <crossref let="l" cid="c14030009.3"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God is gracious and merciful and will not turn away his face from you, <crossref let="m" cid="c14030009.4"/>if you return to him.<q class="end-double" qid="14030009.1" from="14030006.1" to="14030009.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="e" cid="c14030010.1"/>So the couriers went from city to city through the country of <crossref let="n" cid="c14030010.2"/>Ephraim and Manasseh, and as far as Zebulun, but <crossref let="o" cid="c14030010.3"/>they laughed them to scorn and mocked them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030011"/>
    <verse num="11">However, <crossref let="p" cid="c14030011.1"/>some men of Asher, of Manasseh, and of Zebulun humbled themselves and came to Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030012"/>
    <verse num="12">The hand of God was also on Judah to give them one heart to do what the king and the princes commanded <crossref let="q" cid="c14030012.1"/>by the word of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">And many people came together in Jerusalem to keep the Feast of Unleavened Bread <crossref let="r" cid="c14030013.1"/>in the second month, a very great assembly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030014"/>
    <verse num="14">They set to work and removed <crossref let="s" cid="c14030014.1"/>the altars that were in Jerusalem, and all the altars for burning incense they took away <crossref let="t" cid="c14030014.2"/>and threw into the brook Kidron.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="u" cid="c14030015.1"/>And they slaughtered the Passover lamb on the fourteenth day of the second month. <crossref let="v" cid="c14030015.2"/>And the priests and the Levites were ashamed, <crossref let="w" cid="c14030015.3"/>so that they consecrated themselves and brought burnt offerings into the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030016"/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="x" cid="c14030016.1"/>They took their accustomed posts according to the Law of Moses <crossref let="y" cid="c14030016.2"/>the man of God. The priests threw the blood that they received from the hand of the Levites.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030017"/>
    <verse num="17">For there were many in the assembly who had not consecrated themselves. Therefore the Levites had to slaughter the Passover lamb for everyone who was not clean, to consecrate it to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030018"/>
    <verse num="18">For a majority of the people, <crossref let="z" cid="c14030018.1"/>many of them from Ephraim, Manasseh, Issachar, and Zebulun, had not cleansed themselves, yet they ate the Passover otherwise <crossref let="a" cid="c14030018.2"/>than as prescribed. For Hezekiah had prayed for them, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="14030018.1" from="14030018.1" to="14030019.1"/>May the good <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> pardon everyone</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030019"/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="b" cid="c14030019.1"/>who sets his heart to seek God, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of his fathers, even though not according to the sanctuary&apos;s rules of cleanness.<q class="end-double" qid="14030019.1" from="14030018.1" to="14030019.1"/><note nid="n14030019.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030020"/>
    <verse num="20">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> heard Hezekiah and healed the people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030021"/>
    <verse num="21">And the people of Israel who were present at Jerusalem kept <crossref let="c" cid="c14030021.1"/>the Feast of Unleavened Bread seven days with great gladness, and the Levites and the priests praised the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> day by day, singing with all their might<note nid="n14030021.1"/> to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030022"/>
    <verse num="22">And Hezekiah spoke <crossref let="d" cid="c14030022.1"/>encouragingly to all the Levites who showed good skill in the service of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. So they ate the food of the festival for seven days, sacrificing <crossref let="e" cid="c14030022.2"/>peace offerings and giving thanks to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030023"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="23">Then the whole assembly agreed together to keep the feast <crossref let="f" cid="c14030023.1"/>for another seven days. So they kept it for another seven days with gladness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030024"/>
    <verse num="24">For Hezekiah king of Judah <crossref let="g" cid="c14030024.1"/>gave the assembly 1,000 bulls and 7,000 sheep for offerings, and the princes gave the assembly 1,000 bulls and 10,000 sheep. And the priests <crossref let="h" cid="c14030024.2"/>consecrated themselves in great numbers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030025"/>
    <verse num="25">The whole assembly of Judah, and the priests and the Levites, <crossref let="i" cid="c14030025.1"/>and the whole assembly that came out of Israel, and the sojourners who came out of the land of Israel, and the sojourners who lived in Judah, rejoiced.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030026"/>
    <verse num="26">So there was great joy in Jerusalem, for <crossref let="j" cid="c14030026.1"/>since the time of Solomon the son of David king of Israel there had been nothing like this in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14030027"/>
    <verse num="27">Then <crossref let="k" cid="c14030027.1"/>the priests and the Levites arose and <crossref let="l" cid="c14030027.2"/>blessed the people, and their voice was heard, and their prayer came to <crossref let="m" cid="c14030027.3"/>his holy habitation in heaven.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031001"/>
  <chapter num="31">
    <heading>Hezekiah Organizes the Priests</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Now when all this was finished, all Israel who were present went out to the cities of Judah and <crossref let="n" cid="c14031001.1"/>broke in pieces the <crossref let="o" cid="c14031001.2"/>pillars and cut down <crossref let="p" cid="c14031001.3"/>the Asherim and broke down the high places and the altars throughout all Judah and Benjamin, and in Ephraim and Manasseh, until they had destroyed them all. Then all the people of Israel returned to their cities, every man to his possession.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031002"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="2">And Hezekiah appointed <crossref let="q" cid="c14031002.1"/>the divisions of the priests and of the Levites, division by division, each according to his service, the priests and the Levites, <crossref let="r" cid="c14031002.2"/>for burnt offerings and peace offerings, to minister in the gates of the camp of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and to give thanks and praise.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031003"/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="s" cid="c14031003.1"/>The contribution of the king from his own possessions was for the burnt offerings: the burnt offerings of morning and evening, and the burnt offerings for the Sabbaths, the new moons, and the appointed feasts, <crossref let="t" cid="c14031003.2"/>as it is written in the Law of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031004"/>
    <verse num="4">And he commanded the people who lived in Jerusalem to give <crossref let="u" cid="c14031004.1"/>the portion due to the priests and the Levites, that they might give themselves to the Law of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031005"/>
    <verse num="5">As soon as the command was spread abroad, the people of Israel gave in abundance the firstfruits of grain, wine, oil, honey, and of all the produce of the field. And they brought in abundantly <crossref let="v" cid="c14031005.1"/>the tithe of everything.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031006"/>
    <verse num="6">And the people of Israel and Judah who lived in the cities of Judah also brought in the tithe of cattle and sheep, and <crossref let="w" cid="c14031006.1"/>the tithe of the dedicated things that had been dedicated to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> their God, and laid them in heaps.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031007"/>
    <verse num="7">In the third month they began to pile up the heaps, and finished them in the seventh month.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031008"/>
    <verse num="8">When Hezekiah and the princes came and saw the heaps, they blessed the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and his people Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031009"/>
    <verse num="9">And Hezekiah questioned the priests and the Levites about the heaps.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031010"/>
    <verse num="10">Azariah the chief priest, who was <crossref let="x" cid="c14031010.1"/>of the house of Zadok, answered him, <q class="begin-double" qid="14031010.1" from="14031010.1" to="14031010.2"/>Since they began to bring the contributions into the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, we have eaten and had enough and have plenty left, <crossref let="y" cid="c14031010.2"/>for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has blessed his people, so that we have this large amount left.<q class="end-double" qid="14031010.2" from="14031010.1" to="14031010.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11">Then Hezekiah commanded them to prepare <crossref let="z" cid="c14031011.1"/>chambers in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and they prepared them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031012"/>
    <verse num="12">And they faithfully brought in the contributions, the tithes, and the dedicated things. The chief officer <crossref let="a" cid="c14031012.1"/>in charge of them was Conaniah the Levite, with <crossref let="b" cid="c14031012.2"/>Shimei his brother as second,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="b" cid="c14031013.1"/>while Jehiel, Azaziah, Nahath, Asahel, Jerimoth, Jozabad, Eliel, Ismachiah, <crossref let="b" cid="c14031013.2"/>Mahath, and Benaiah were overseers assisting Conaniah and Shimei his brother, by the appointment of Hezekiah the king and <crossref let="x" cid="c14031013.3"/>Azariah the chief officer of the house of God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031014"/>
    <verse num="14">And Kore the son of Imnah the Levite, keeper of the east gate, was over the freewill offerings to God, to apportion the contribution reserved for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and the most holy offerings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="b" cid="c14031015.1"/>Eden, Miniamin, Jeshua, Shemaiah, Amariah, and Shecaniah were faithfully assisting him in <crossref let="d" cid="c14031015.2"/>the cities of the priests, to distribute the portions to their brothers, old and young alike, by divisions,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031016"/>
    <verse num="16">except those enrolled by genealogy, males from three years old and upward&emdash;all who entered the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="e" cid="c14031016.1"/>as the duty of each day required&emdash;for their service according to their offices, by their divisions.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031017"/>
    <verse num="17">The enrollment of the priests was according to their fathers&apos; houses; that of the Levites <crossref let="f" cid="c14031017.1"/>from twenty years old and upward was according to their offices, by their divisions.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031018"/>
    <verse num="18">They were enrolled with all their little children, their wives, their sons, and their daughters, the whole assembly, for they were faithful in keeping themselves holy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031019"/>
    <verse num="19">And for the sons of Aaron, the priests, who were in the fields of common land belonging to their cities, there were men in the several cities who were <crossref let="g" cid="c14031019.1"/>designated by name to distribute portions to every male among the priests and to everyone among the Levites who was enrolled.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031020"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20">Thus Hezekiah did throughout all Judah, <crossref let="h" cid="c14031020.1"/>and he did what was good and right and faithful before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14031021"/>
    <verse num="21">And every work that he undertook in the service of the house of God and in accordance with the law and the commandments, seeking his God, he did with all his heart, and prospered.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032001"/>
  <chapter num="32">
    <heading>Sennacherib Invades Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="i" cid="c14032001.1"/>After these things and these acts of faithfulness, Sennacherib king of Assyria came and invaded Judah and encamped against the fortified cities, thinking to win them for himself.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032002"/>
    <verse num="2">And when Hezekiah saw that Sennacherib had come and intended to fight against Jerusalem,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032003"/>
    <verse num="3">he planned with his officers and his mighty men to stop the water of the springs that were outside the city; and they helped him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032004"/>
    <verse num="4">A great many people were gathered, and they stopped all the springs and <crossref let="j" cid="c14032004.1"/>the brook that flowed through the land, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="14032004.1" from="14032004.1" to="14032004.2"/>Why should the kings of Assyria come and find much water?<q class="end-double" qid="14032004.2" from="14032004.1" to="14032004.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032005"/>
    <verse num="5">He set to work resolutely and built up <crossref let="k" cid="c14032005.1"/>all the wall that was broken down and raised towers upon it,<note nid="n14032005.1"/> and outside it he built another wall, and he strengthened the <crossref let="l" cid="c14032005.2"/>Millo in the city of David. He also made weapons and shields in abundance.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032006"/>
    <verse num="6">And he set combat commanders over the people and gathered them together to him in the square at the gate of the city and spoke <crossref let="m" cid="c14032006.1"/>encouragingly to them, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="n" cid="c14032007.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14032007.1" from="14032007.1" to="14032008.1"/>Be strong and courageous. <crossref let="o" cid="c14032007.2"/>Do not be afraid or dismayed before the king of Assyria and all the horde that is with him, <crossref let="p" cid="c14032007.3"/>for there are more with us than with him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032008"/>
    <verse num="8">With him is <crossref let="q" cid="c14032008.1"/>an arm of flesh, <crossref let="r" cid="c14032008.2"/>but with us is the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God, to help us and to fight our battles.<q class="end-double" qid="14032008.1" from="14032007.1" to="14032008.1"/> And the people took confidence from the words of Hezekiah king of Judah.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032009"/>
    <heading>Sennacherib Blasphemes</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9">After this, Sennacherib king of Assyria, who was besieging Lachish with all his forces, sent his servants to Jerusalem to Hezekiah king of Judah and to all the people of Judah who were in Jerusalem, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032010"/>
    <verse num="10"><q class="begin-double" qid="14032010.1" from="14032010.1" to="14032015.2"/>Thus says Sennacherib king of Assyria, <q class="begin-single" qid="14032010.2" from="14032010.2" to="14032015.1"/>On what are you trusting, that you endure the siege in Jerusalem?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032011"/>
    <verse num="11">Is not Hezekiah misleading you, that he may give you over to die by famine and by thirst, when he tells you, <q class="begin-inner-double" qid="14032011.1" from="14032011.1" to="14032011.2"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God will deliver us from the hand of the king of Assyria<q class="end-inner-double" qid="14032011.2" from="14032011.1" to="14032011.2"/>?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="s" cid="c14032012.1"/>Has not this same Hezekiah taken away his high places and his altars and commanded Judah and Jerusalem, <q class="begin-inner-double" qid="14032012.1" from="14032012.1" to="14032012.2"/>Before one altar you shall worship, and on it you shall burn your sacrifices<q class="end-inner-double" qid="14032012.2" from="14032012.1" to="14032012.2"/>?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032013"/>
    <verse num="13">Do you not know what I and my fathers have done to all the peoples of other lands? Were the gods of the nations of those lands at all able to deliver their lands out of my hand?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032014"/>
    <verse num="14">Who among all the gods of those nations that my fathers devoted to destruction was able to deliver his people from my hand, that your God should be able to deliver you from my hand?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032015"/>
    <verse num="15">Now, therefore, do not let Hezekiah deceive you or mislead you in this fashion, and do not believe him, for no god of any nation or kingdom has been able to deliver his people from my hand or from the hand of my fathers. How much less will your God deliver you out of my hand!<q class="end-single" qid="14032015.1" from="14032010.2" to="14032015.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="14032015.2" from="14032010.1" to="14032015.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">And his servants said still more against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God and against his servant Hezekiah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032017"/>
    <verse num="17">And he wrote letters to cast contempt on the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, and to speak against him, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="14032017.1" from="14032017.1" to="14032017.2"/>Like the gods of the nations of the lands who have not delivered their people from my hands, so the God of Hezekiah will not deliver his people from my hand.<q class="end-double" qid="14032017.2" from="14032017.1" to="14032017.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032018"/>
    <verse num="18">And they shouted it with a loud voice in the language of Judah to the people of Jerusalem who were on the wall, to frighten and terrify them, in order that they might take the city.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032019"/>
    <verse num="19">And they spoke of the God of Jerusalem as they spoke of the gods of the peoples of the earth, which are the work of men&apos;s hands.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032020"/>
    <heading>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> Delivers Jerusalem</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20">Then Hezekiah the king and Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz, prayed because of this and cried to heaven.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032021"/>
    <verse num="21">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> sent an angel, who cut off all the mighty warriors and commanders and officers in the camp of the king of Assyria. So he returned with <crossref let="t" cid="c14032021.1"/>shame of face to his own land. And when he came into the house of his god, some of his own sons struck him down there with the sword.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032022"/>
    <verse num="22">So the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> saved Hezekiah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem from the hand of Sennacherib king of Assyria and from the hand of all his enemies, and he provided for them on every side.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032023"/>
    <verse num="23">And many <crossref let="u" cid="c14032023.1"/>brought gifts to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to Jerusalem and precious things to Hezekiah king of Judah, so that he was exalted in the sight of all nations from that time onward.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032024"/>
    <heading>Hezekiah&apos;s Pride and Achievements</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24"><crossref let="v" cid="c14032024.1"/>In those days Hezekiah became sick and was at the point of death, and he prayed to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and he answered him and gave him a sign.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032025"/>
    <verse num="25">But Hezekiah <crossref let="w" cid="c14032025.1"/>did not make return according to the benefit done to him, for <crossref let="x" cid="c14032025.2"/>his heart was proud. Therefore <crossref let="y" cid="c14032025.3"/>wrath came upon him and Judah and Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032026"/>
    <verse num="26">But Hezekiah <crossref let="z" cid="c14032026.1"/>humbled himself for the pride of his heart, both he and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that the wrath of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> did not come upon them in the days of Hezekiah.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032027"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="27">And Hezekiah had very great riches and honor, and he made for himself treasuries for silver, for gold, for precious stones, for spices, for shields, and for all kinds of <crossref let="a" cid="c14032027.1"/>costly vessels;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032028"/>
    <verse num="28">storehouses also for the yield of grain, wine, and oil; and stalls for all kinds of cattle, and sheepfolds.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032029"/>
    <verse num="29">He likewise provided cities for himself, and flocks and herds in abundance, for God had given him very great possessions.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032030"/>
    <verse num="30">This same Hezekiah <crossref let="b" cid="c14032030.1"/>closed the upper outlet of the waters of <crossref let="c" cid="c14032030.2"/>Gihon and directed them down to the west side of the city of David. And Hezekiah prospered in all his works.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032031"/>
    <verse num="31">And so in the matter of the envoys of the princes of Babylon, <crossref let="d" cid="c14032031.1"/>who had been sent to him to inquire about <crossref let="e" cid="c14032031.2"/>the sign that had been done in the land, God left him to himself, <crossref let="f" cid="c14032031.3"/>in order to test him and to know all that was in his heart.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032032"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="32">Now the rest of the acts of Hezekiah and his good deeds, behold, they are written <crossref let="g" cid="c14032032.1"/>in the vision of Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz, <crossref let="h" cid="c14032032.2"/>in the Book of the Kings of Judah and Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14032033"/>
    <verse num="33">And Hezekiah slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the <crossref let="i" cid="c14032033.1"/>upper part of the tombs of the sons of David, and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem did him honor at his death. And Manasseh his son reigned in his place.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033001"/>
  <chapter num="33">
    <heading>Manasseh Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="j" cid="c14033001.1"/>Manasseh was twelve years old when he began to reign, and he reigned fifty-five years in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033002"/>
    <verse num="2">And he did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, according to <crossref let="k" cid="c14033002.1"/>the abominations of the nations whom the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> drove out before the people of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033003"/>
    <verse num="3">For he rebuilt the high places <crossref let="l" cid="c14033003.1"/>that his father Hezekiah had broken down, and he erected altars to the Baals, and made <crossref let="m" cid="c14033003.2"/>Asheroth, and worshiped all the host of heaven and served them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033004"/>
    <verse num="4">And he built altars in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, of which the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had said, <crossref let="n" cid="c14033004.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14033004.1" from="14033004.1" to="14033004.2"/>In Jerusalem shall my name be forever.<q class="end-double" qid="14033004.2" from="14033004.1" to="14033004.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033005"/>
    <verse num="5">And he built altars for all the host of heaven in <crossref let="o" cid="c14033005.1"/>the two courts of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="p" cid="c14033006.1"/>And he burned his sons as an offering <crossref let="q" cid="c14033006.2"/>in the Valley of the Son of Hinnom, and <crossref let="r" cid="c14033006.3"/>used fortune-telling and omens and sorcery, and dealt with <crossref let="s" cid="c14033006.4"/>mediums and with necromancers. He did much evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, provoking him to anger.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033007"/>
    <verse num="7">And <crossref let="t" cid="c14033007.1"/>the carved image of the idol that he had made he set in the house of God, of which God said to David and to Solomon his son, <q class="begin-double" qid="14033007.1" from="14033007.1" to="14033008.1"/>In this house, and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, <crossref let="n" cid="c14033007.2"/>I will put my name forever,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033008"/>
    <verse num="8">and I will no more remove the foot of Israel from the land <crossref let="u" cid="c14033008.1"/>that I appointed for your fathers, if only they will be careful to do all that I have commanded them, all the law, the statutes, and the rules given through Moses.<q class="end-double" qid="14033008.1" from="14033007.1" to="14033008.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033009"/>
    <verse num="9">Manasseh led Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem astray, to do more evil than the nations whom the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> destroyed before the people of Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033010"/>
    <heading>Manasseh&apos;s Repentance</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Manasseh and to his people, but they paid no attention.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="v" cid="c14033011.1"/>Therefore the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> brought upon them the commanders of the army of the king of Assyria, who captured Manasseh with hooks and <crossref let="w" cid="c14033011.2"/>bound him with chains of bronze and brought him to Babylon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033012"/>
    <verse num="12">And when he was in distress, he entreated the favor of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God <crossref let="x" cid="c14033012.1"/>and humbled himself greatly before the God of his fathers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033013"/>
    <verse num="13">He prayed to him, and <crossref let="y" cid="c14033013.1"/>God was moved by his entreaty and heard his plea and brought him again to Jerusalem into his kingdom. <crossref let="z" cid="c14033013.2"/>Then Manasseh knew that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was God.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14">Afterward he built an outer wall for the city of David west of <crossref let="a" cid="c14033014.1"/>Gihon, in the valley, and for the entrance into <crossref let="b" cid="c14033014.2"/>the Fish Gate, and carried it around <crossref let="c" cid="c14033014.3"/>Ophel, and raised it to a very great height. He also put commanders of the army in all the fortified cities in Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033015"/>
    <verse num="15">And <crossref let="d" cid="c14033015.1"/>he took away the foreign gods and the idol from the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and all the altars that he had built on the mountain of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and in Jerusalem, and he threw them outside of the city.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033016"/>
    <verse num="16">He also restored the altar of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and offered on it sacrifices of peace offerings and of thanksgiving, and he commanded Judah to serve the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="e" cid="c14033017.1"/>Nevertheless, the people still sacrificed at the high places, but only to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> their God.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18">Now the rest of the acts of Manasseh, and <crossref let="f" cid="c14033018.1"/>his prayer to his God, and the words of <crossref let="g" cid="c14033018.2"/>the seers who spoke to him in the name of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, behold, they are in the <crossref let="h" cid="c14033018.3"/>Chronicles of the Kings of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033019"/>
    <verse num="19">And his prayer, and how <crossref let="y" cid="c14033019.1"/>God was moved by his entreaty, and all his sin and his faithlessness, and the sites <crossref let="i" cid="c14033019.2"/>on which he built high places and set up the <crossref let="i" cid="c14033019.3"/>Asherim and the images, before <crossref let="x" cid="c14033019.4"/>he humbled himself, behold, they are written in the Chronicles of the Seers.<note nid="n14033019.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033020"/>
    <verse num="20">So Manasseh slept with his fathers, and they buried him in his house, and Amon his son reigned in his place.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033021"/>
    <heading>Amon&apos;s Reign and Death</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="21"><crossref let="j" cid="c14033021.1"/>Amon was twenty-two years old when he began to reign, and he reigned two years in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033022"/>
    <verse num="22">And he did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, as Manasseh his father had done. Amon sacrificed to all the images <crossref let="k" cid="c14033022.1"/>that Manasseh his father had made, and served them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033023"/>
    <verse num="23">And he did not humble himself before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="l" cid="c14033023.1"/>as Manasseh his father had humbled himself, but this Amon incurred guilt more and more.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033024"/>
    <verse num="24">And his servants conspired against him and put him to death in his house.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14033025"/>
    <verse num="25">But the people of the land struck down all those who had conspired against King Amon. And the people of the land made Josiah his son king in his place.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034001"/>
  <chapter num="34">
    <heading>Josiah Reigns in Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="m" cid="c14034001.1"/>Josiah was eight years old when he began to reign, and he reigned thirty-one years in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034002"/>
    <verse num="2">And he did what was right in the eyes of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and walked in the ways of David his father; and he did not turn aside to the right hand or to the left.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034003"/>
    <verse num="3">For in the eighth year of his reign, while he was yet a boy, he began to seek the God of David his father, and in the twelfth year he began to purge Judah and Jerusalem of the high places, the <crossref let="n" cid="c14034003.1"/>Asherim, and the carved and the metal images.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034004"/>
    <verse num="4">And they chopped down the altars of the Baals in his presence, and he cut down the <crossref let="o" cid="c14034004.1"/>incense altars that stood above them. And he broke in pieces the <crossref let="n" cid="c14034004.2"/>Asherim and the carved and the metal images, and he made dust of them and <crossref let="o" cid="c14034004.3"/>scattered it over the graves of those who had sacrificed to them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034005"/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="p" cid="c14034005.1"/>He also burned the bones of the priests on their altars and cleansed Judah and Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034006"/>
    <verse num="6">And in the <crossref let="q" cid="c14034006.1"/>cities of Manasseh, Ephraim, and Simeon, and as far as Naphtali, in their ruins<note nid="n14034006.1"/> all around,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034007"/>
    <verse num="7">he broke down the altars and beat the <crossref let="n" cid="c14034007.1"/>Asherim and the images <crossref let="r" cid="c14034007.2"/>into powder and cut down all the incense altars throughout all the land of Israel. Then he returned to Jerusalem.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034008"/>
    <heading>The Book of the Law Found</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="s" cid="c14034008.1"/>Now in the eighteenth year of his reign, when he had cleansed the land and the house, he sent Shaphan the son of Azaliah, and Maaseiah the <crossref let="t" cid="c14034008.2"/>governor of the city, and Joah the son of Joahaz, <crossref let="u" cid="c14034008.3"/>the recorder, to repair the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034009"/>
    <verse num="9">They came to <crossref let="v" cid="c14034009.1"/>Hilkiah the high priest and gave him the money that had been brought into the house of God, which the Levites, the keepers of the threshold, had collected from <crossref let="q" cid="c14034009.2"/>Manasseh and Ephraim and from all the remnant of Israel and from all Judah and Benjamin and from the inhabitants of Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034010"/>
    <verse num="10">And they gave it to the workmen who were working in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. And the workmen who were working in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave it for repairing and restoring the house.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034011"/>
    <verse num="11">They gave it to the carpenters and the builders to buy quarried stone, and timber for binders and <crossref let="w" cid="c14034011.1"/>beams for the buildings that the kings of Judah had let go to ruin.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034012"/>
    <verse num="12">And the men did the work faithfully. Over them were set Jahath and Obadiah the Levites, of the sons of Merari, and Zechariah and Meshullam, of the sons of the Kohathites, to have oversight. <crossref let="x" cid="c14034012.1"/>The Levites, all who were skillful with instruments of music,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034013"/>
    <verse num="13">were over <crossref let="y" cid="c14034013.1"/>the burden-bearers and directed all who did work in every kind of service, and some of the Levites were scribes and officials and gatekeepers.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14">While they were bringing out the money that had been brought into the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="v" cid="c14034014.1"/>Hilkiah the priest found the Book of the Law of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> given through<note nid="n14034014.1"/> Moses.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034015"/>
    <verse num="15">Then Hilkiah answered and said to Shaphan the secretary, <q class="begin-double" qid="14034015.1" from="14034015.1" to="14034015.2"/>I have found the Book of the Law in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="14034015.2" from="14034015.1" to="14034015.2"/> And Hilkiah gave the book to Shaphan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034016"/>
    <verse num="16">Shaphan brought the book to the king, and further reported to the king, <q class="begin-double" qid="14034016.1" from="14034016.1" to="14034017.1"/>All that was committed to your servants they are doing.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034017"/>
    <verse num="17">They have emptied out the money that was found in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and have given it into the hand of the overseers and the workmen.<q class="end-double" qid="14034017.1" from="14034016.1" to="14034017.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034018"/>
    <verse num="18">Then Shaphan the secretary told the king, <q class="begin-double" qid="14034018.1" from="14034018.1" to="14034018.2"/>Hilkiah the priest has given me a book.<q class="end-double" qid="14034018.2" from="14034018.1" to="14034018.2"/> And Shaphan read from it before the king.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19">And when the king heard the words of the Law, <crossref let="z" cid="c14034019.1"/>he tore his clothes.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034020"/>
    <verse num="20">And the king commanded Hilkiah, Ahikam the son of Shaphan, Abdon the son of Micah, Shaphan the secretary, and Asaiah the king&apos;s servant, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034021"/>
    <verse num="21"><q class="begin-double" qid="14034021.1" from="14034021.1" to="14034021.2"/>Go, inquire of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for me and for those who are left in Israel and in Judah, concerning the words of the book that has been found. For great is <crossref let="a" cid="c14034021.1"/>the wrath of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> that is poured out on us, because our fathers have not kept the word of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, to do according to all that is written in this book.<q class="end-double" qid="14034021.2" from="14034021.1" to="14034021.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034022"/>
    <heading>Huldah Prophesies Disaster</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">So Hilkiah and those whom the king had sent<note nid="n14034022.1"/> went to Huldah the prophetess, the wife of Shallum the son of Tokhath, son of Hasrah, keeper of the wardrobe (now she lived in Jerusalem in the Second Quarter) and spoke to her to that effect.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034023"/>
    <verse num="23">And she said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="14034023.1" from="14034023.1" to="14034028.2"/>Thus says the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel: <q class="begin-single" qid="14034023.2" from="14034023.2" to="14034028.1"/>Tell the man who sent you to me,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034024"/>
    <verse num="24">Thus says the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, Behold, I will bring disaster upon this place and upon its inhabitants, all the curses that are written in the book that was read before the king of Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034025"/>
    <verse num="25">Because they have forsaken me and <crossref let="b" cid="c14034025.1"/>have made offerings to other gods, that they might provoke me to anger with all the works of their hands, therefore <crossref let="a" cid="c14034025.2"/>my wrath will be poured out on this place and will not be quenched.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034026"/>
    <verse num="26">But to the king of Judah, who sent you to inquire of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, thus shall you say to him, Thus says the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel: Regarding the words that you have heard,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034027"/>
    <verse num="27">because your heart was tender and you humbled yourself before God when you heard his words against this place and its inhabitants, and you have humbled yourself before me and have torn your clothes and wept before me, I also have heard you, declares the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034028"/>
    <verse num="28">Behold, I will gather you to your fathers, and you shall be gathered to your grave in peace, and your eyes shall not see all the disaster that I will bring upon this place and its inhabitants.<q class="end-single" qid="14034028.1" from="14034023.2" to="14034028.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="14034028.2" from="14034023.1" to="14034028.2"/> And they brought back word to the king.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034029"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="c" cid="c14034029.1"/>Then the king sent and gathered together all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034030"/>
    <verse num="30">And the king went up to the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, with all the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem and the priests and the Levites, all the people both great and small. And he read in their hearing all the words of the Book of the Covenant that had been found in the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034031"/>
    <verse num="31">And the king <crossref let="d" cid="c14034031.1"/>stood in his place <crossref let="e" cid="c14034031.2"/>and made a covenant before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, to walk after the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and to keep his commandments and his testimonies and his statutes, with all his heart and all his soul, to perform the words of the covenant that were written in this book.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034032"/>
    <verse num="32">Then he made all who were present in Jerusalem and in Benjamin join in it. And the inhabitants of Jerusalem did according to the covenant of God, the God of their fathers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14034033"/>
    <verse num="33">And Josiah took away <crossref let="f" cid="c14034033.1"/>all the abominations from all the territory that belonged to the people of Israel and made all who were present in Israel serve the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> their God. All his days they did not turn away from following the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035001"/>
  <chapter num="35">
    <heading>Josiah Keeps the Passover</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="g" cid="c14035001.1"/>Josiah kept a Passover to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in Jerusalem. And they slaughtered the Passover lamb <crossref let="h" cid="c14035001.2"/>on the fourteenth day of the first month.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035002"/>
    <verse num="2">He appointed the priests to their offices <crossref let="i" cid="c14035002.1"/>and encouraged them in the service of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035003"/>
    <verse num="3">And he said to the Levites <crossref let="j" cid="c14035003.1"/>who taught all Israel and who were holy to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <q class="begin-double" qid="14035003.1" from="14035003.1" to="14035006.1"/>Put the holy ark in the house that Solomon the son of David, king of Israel, built. You need not carry it on your shoulders. Now serve the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God and his people Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035004"/>
    <verse num="4">Prepare yourselves <crossref let="k" cid="c14035004.1"/>according to your fathers&apos; houses by your divisions, <crossref let="l" cid="c14035004.2"/>as prescribed in the writing of David king of Israel <crossref let="m" cid="c14035004.3"/>and the document of Solomon his son.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035005"/>
    <verse num="5">And <crossref let="n" cid="c14035005.1"/>stand in the Holy Place <crossref let="o" cid="c14035005.2"/>according to the groupings of the fathers&apos; houses of your brothers the lay people, and according to the division of the Levites by fathers&apos; household.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035006"/>
    <verse num="6">And slaughter the Passover lamb, and <crossref let="p" cid="c14035006.1"/>consecrate yourselves, and prepare for your brothers, to do according to the word of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> by<note nid="n14035006.1"/> Moses.<q class="end-double" qid="14035006.1" from="14035003.1" to="14035006.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">Then Josiah contributed to the lay people, as Passover offerings for all who were present, lambs and young goats from the flock to the number of 30,000, and 3,000 bulls; <crossref let="q" cid="c14035007.1"/>these were from the king&apos;s possessions.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035008"/>
    <verse num="8">And his officials contributed willingly to the people, to the priests, and to the Levites. <crossref let="r" cid="c14035008.1"/>Hilkiah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, the chief officers of the house of God, gave to the priests for the Passover offerings 2,600 Passover lambs and 300 bulls.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035009"/>
    <verse num="9">Conaniah also, and Shemaiah and Nethanel his brothers, and Hashabiah and Jeiel and Jozabad, the chiefs of the Levites, gave to the Levites for the Passover offerings 5,000 lambs and young goats and 500 bulls.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">When the service had been prepared for, the priests <crossref let="s" cid="c14035010.1"/>stood in their place, <crossref let="t" cid="c14035010.2"/>and the Levites in their divisions according to the king&apos;s command.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="u" cid="c14035011.1"/>And they slaughtered the Passover lamb, and the priests <crossref let="v" cid="c14035011.2"/>threw the blood that they received from them <crossref let="w" cid="c14035011.3"/>while the Levites flayed the sacrifices.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035012"/>
    <verse num="12">And they set aside the burnt offerings that they might distribute them according to the groupings of the fathers&apos; houses of the lay people, to offer to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, as it is written in the Book of Moses. And so they did with the bulls.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="x" cid="c14035013.1"/>And they roasted the Passover lamb with fire according to the rule; and they <crossref let="y" cid="c14035013.2"/>boiled the holy offerings in pots, in cauldrons, and in pans, and carried them quickly to all the lay people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035014"/>
    <verse num="14">And afterward they prepared for themselves and for the priests, because the priests, the sons of Aaron, were offering the burnt offerings and the fat parts until night; so the Levites prepared for themselves and for the priests, the sons of Aaron.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035015"/>
    <verse num="15">The singers, the sons of Asaph, were in their place <crossref let="z" cid="c14035015.1"/>according to the command of David, and Asaph, and Heman, and Jeduthun the king&apos;s <crossref let="a" cid="c14035015.2"/>seer; <crossref let="b" cid="c14035015.3"/>and the gatekeepers were at each gate. They did not need to depart from their service, for their brothers the Levites prepared for them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">So all the service of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was prepared that day, to keep the Passover and to offer burnt offerings on the altar of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, according to the command of King Josiah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035017"/>
    <verse num="17">And the people of Israel who were present kept the Passover at that time, <crossref let="c" cid="c14035017.1"/>and the Feast of Unleavened Bread seven days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035018"/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="d" cid="c14035018.1"/>No Passover like it had been kept in Israel since the days of Samuel the prophet. None of the kings of Israel had kept such a Passover as was kept by Josiah, and the priests and the Levites, and all Judah and Israel who were present, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035019"/>
    <verse num="19">In the eighteenth year of the reign of Josiah this Passover was kept.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035020"/>
    <heading>Josiah Killed in Battle</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="e" cid="c14035020.1"/>After all this, when Josiah had prepared the temple, Neco king of Egypt went up to fight at <crossref let="f" cid="c14035020.2"/>Carchemish on the Euphrates, and Josiah went out to meet him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035021"/>
    <verse num="21">But he sent envoys to him, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="14035021.1" from="14035021.1" to="14035021.2"/>What have we to do with each other, king of Judah? I am not coming against you this day, but against the house with which I am at war. And God has commanded me to hurry. Cease opposing God, who is with me, lest he destroy you.<q class="end-double" qid="14035021.2" from="14035021.1" to="14035021.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035022"/>
    <verse num="22">Nevertheless, Josiah did not turn away from him, but <crossref let="g" cid="c14035022.1"/>disguised himself in order to fight with him. He did not listen to the words of Neco from the mouth of God, but came to fight in the plain of <crossref let="h" cid="c14035022.2"/>Megiddo.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035023"/>
    <verse num="23">And the archers shot King Josiah. And the king said to his servants, <crossref let="i" cid="c14035023.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="14035023.1" from="14035023.1" to="14035023.2"/>Take me away, for I am badly wounded.<q class="end-double" qid="14035023.2" from="14035023.1" to="14035023.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035024"/>
    <verse num="24">So his servants took him out of the chariot and carried him in his second chariot and brought him to Jerusalem. And he died and was buried in the tombs of his fathers. <crossref let="j" cid="c14035024.1"/>All Judah and Jerusalem mourned for Josiah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035025"/>
    <verse num="25"><crossref let="k" cid="c14035025.1"/>Jeremiah also uttered a lament for Josiah; and all <crossref let="l" cid="c14035025.2"/>the singing men and singing women have spoken of Josiah in their laments to this day. They made these a rule in Israel; behold, they are written in the Laments.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035026"/>
    <verse num="26">Now the rest of the acts of Josiah, and his good deeds according to what is written in the Law of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14035027"/>
    <verse num="27">and his acts, first and last, behold, they are written in the Book of the Kings of Israel and Judah.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036001"/>
  <chapter num="36">
    <heading>Judah&apos;s Decline</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="m" cid="c14036001.1"/>The people of the land took Jehoahaz the son of Josiah and made him king in his father&apos;s place in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036002"/>
    <verse num="2">Jehoahaz was twenty-three years old when he began to reign, and he reigned three months in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036003"/>
    <verse num="3">Then the king of Egypt deposed him in Jerusalem and <crossref let="n" cid="c14036003.1"/>laid on the land a tribute of a hundred talents of silver and a talent<note nid="n14036003.1"/> of gold.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036004"/>
    <verse num="4">And the king of Egypt made Eliakim his brother king over Judah and Jerusalem, and changed his name to Jehoiakim. But Neco took Jehoahaz his brother and carried him to Egypt.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036005"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="o" cid="c14036005.1"/>Jehoiakim was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. He did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="p" cid="c14036006.1"/>Against him came up Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon <crossref let="q" cid="c14036006.2"/>and bound him in chains <crossref let="r" cid="c14036006.3"/>to take him to Babylon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="s" cid="c14036007.1"/>Nebuchadnezzar also carried part of the vessels of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to Babylon and put them in his palace in Babylon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="t" cid="c14036008.1"/>Now the rest of the acts of Jehoiakim, and the abominations that he did, and what was found against him, behold, they are written in the Book of the Kings of Israel and Judah. And Jehoiachin his son reigned in his place.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036009"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="u" cid="c14036009.1"/>Jehoiachin was eighteen<note nid="n14036009.1"/> years old when he became king, and he reigned three months and ten days in Jerusalem. He did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036010"/>
    <verse num="10">In <crossref let="v" cid="c14036010.1"/>the spring of the year King Nebuchadnezzar sent and brought him to Babylon, <crossref let="w" cid="c14036010.2"/>with the precious vessels of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and made his brother <crossref let="x" cid="c14036010.3"/>Zedekiah king over Judah and Jerusalem.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="y" cid="c14036011.1"/>Zedekiah was twenty-one years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036012"/>
    <verse num="12">He did what was evil in the sight of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God. He did not humble himself before <crossref let="z" cid="c14036012.1"/>Jeremiah the prophet, who spoke from the mouth of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="a" cid="c14036013.1"/>He also rebelled against King Nebuchadnezzar, who had made him swear by God. <crossref let="b" cid="c14036013.2"/>He stiffened his neck and hardened his heart against turning to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036014"/>
    <verse num="14">All the officers of the priests and the people likewise were exceedingly unfaithful, following all the abominations of the nations. And they polluted the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> that he had made holy in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of their fathers, <crossref let="c" cid="c14036015.1"/>sent persistently to them by his messengers, because he had compassion on his people and on his dwelling place.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036016"/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="d" cid="c14036016.1"/>But they kept mocking the messengers of God, <crossref let="e" cid="c14036016.2"/>despising his words and scoffing at his prophets, <crossref let="f" cid="c14036016.3"/>until the wrath of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> rose against his people, until there was no remedy.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036017"/>
    <heading>Jerusalem Captured and Burned</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="g" cid="c14036017.1"/>Therefore he brought up against them the king of the Chaldeans, who killed their young men with the sword in the house of their sanctuary and had no compassion on young man or virgin, old man or aged. He gave them all into his hand.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036018"/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="h" cid="c14036018.1"/>And all the vessels of the house of God, great and small, and the treasures of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and the treasures of the king and of his princes, all these he brought to Babylon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036019"/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="i" cid="c14036019.1"/>And they burned the house of God and broke down the wall of Jerusalem and burned all its palaces with fire and destroyed all its precious vessels.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036020"/>
    <verse num="20">He <crossref let="j" cid="c14036020.1"/>took into exile in Babylon those who had escaped from the sword, <crossref let="k" cid="c14036020.2"/>and they became servants to him and to his sons until the establishment of the kingdom of Persia,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036021"/>
    <verse num="21">to fulfill the word of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> by the mouth of Jeremiah, until the land had <crossref let="l" cid="c14036021.1"/>enjoyed its Sabbaths. All the days that it lay desolate <crossref let="m" cid="c14036021.2"/>it kept Sabbath, to fulfill seventy years.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036022"/>
    <heading>The Proclamation of Cyrus</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22"><crossref let="n" cid="c14036022.1"/>Now in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, <crossref let="o" cid="c14036022.2"/>that the word of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> by the mouth of Jeremiah might be fulfilled, <crossref let="p" cid="c14036022.3"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, so that he made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom and also put it in writing:</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v14036023"/>
    <verse num="23"><q class="begin-double" qid="14036023.1" from="14036023.1" to="14036023.4"/>Thus says Cyrus king of Persia, <q class="begin-single" qid="14036023.2" from="14036023.2" to="14036023.3"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of heaven, has given me all the kingdoms of the earth, and he has charged me to build him a house at Jerusalem, which is in Judah. Whoever is among you of all his people, may the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God be with him. Let him go up.<q class="end-single" qid="14036023.3" from="14036023.2" to="14036023.3"/><q class="end-double" qid="14036023.4" from="14036023.1" to="14036023.4"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
</book>
</crossway-bible>
