<?xml version='1.0' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" translation="English Standard Version" revision="2018-3-26" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
  <book title="Tobit" num="70">
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001001"/>
    <chapter num="1">
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">The book of the words of Tobit son of Tobiel, son of Ananiel, son of Aduel, son of Gabael, son of Raphael, son of Raguel, of the descendants of Asiel from the tribe of Naphtali,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001002"/>
      <verse num="2">who in the days of Shalmaneser<note nid="n70001002.1"/>, the king of the Assyrians, was taken into captivity from Thisbe, which is to the south<note nid="n70001002.2"/> of Kedesh of Naphtali in Upper Galilee above Asher to the west, north<note nid="n70001002.3"/> of Phogor.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001003"/>
      <heading>Tobit&apos;s Youth and Virtuous Life</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="3">I, Tobit, walked in the ways of truth and in righteous deeds all the days of my life, and I performed many acts of mercy for my brothers and my compatriots who went with me into captivity in the land of the Assyrians, to Nineveh.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001004"/>
      <verse num="4">Now when I was in my own country, in the land of Israel, when I was young, the whole tribe of Naphtali my ancestor<note nid="n70001004.1"/> broke away from the house of my ancestor David and from the city of Jerusalem, the place chosen from among all the tribes of Israel, where all the tribes should sacrifice. In it the temple of God&apos;s dwelling was consecrated and established for all generations forever.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">All my brothers and the house of Naphtali my ancestor&emdash;those people used to sacrifice on all the high places of Galilee to the calf that Jeroboam, king of Israel, made in Dan.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001006"/>
      <verse num="6">But I alone went often to Jerusalem at the time for the feasts, just as it is written for all Israel by an everlasting decree. I would hurry off to Jerusalem, taking the first fruits&emdash;the first fruits of my fields and the tithes of my livestock and the first shearings of the sheep&emdash;and I would give these to the priests, the sons of Aaron, at the altar.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001007"/>
      <verse num="7">I would give a tenth of the grain, wine, olive oil, pomegranates, figs, and the produce from the other fruit trees to the sons of Levi who ministered in Jerusalem. I tithed a second tenth in silver for the six years, and I would go and spend this in Jerusalem each year.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001008"/>
      <verse num="8">I would give these things to the orphans and widows and sojourners who had attached themselves to the sons of Israel: I would carry and give it to them in the third year and we would eat them according to the stipulation that had been stipulated concerning them in the Law of Moses and according to the commands which Deborah, the mother of Ananiel our father, had commanded me (for my father had died and left me an orphan).</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001009"/>
      <verse num="9">When I became a man I took a wife from the descendants of our family, and I fathered a son by her, and I called his name Tobias.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001010"/>
      <heading>Taken Captive to Nineveh</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">After I was carried away captive to Assyria, and while I was in captivity, I went to Nineveh. And all my brothers and my relatives ate the food<note nid="n70001010.1"/> of the Gentiles;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001011"/>
      <verse num="11">but I preserved my soul from eating the Gentiles&apos; food.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001012"/>
      <verse num="12">And because<note nid="n70001012.1"/> I had been mindful of my God with my whole soul,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001013"/>
      <verse num="13">the Most High gave me favor and good standing in the sight of Shalmaneser, and I used to purchase for him whatever he needed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001014"/>
      <verse num="14">I used to go into Media and buy for him there until he died. And I entrusted sacks of money to Gabael, the brother of Gabri, in the land of Media&emdash;ten talents of silver.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001015"/>
      <verse num="15">And when Shalmaneser died and his son Sennacherib reigned in his place, the roads to Media were unfit and I could no longer travel into Media.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001016"/>
      <heading>Courage in Burying the Dead</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">In the days of Shalmaneser I performed many acts of mercy for my brothers, for those of my kindred.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001017"/>
      <verse num="17">I would give my bread to the hungry and garments to the naked; and if ever I saw anyone from my people dead and thrown out behind the wall of Nineveh, I would bury him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001018"/>
      <verse num="18">And if King Sennacherib put anyone to death at the time he came fleeing from Judea (in the days of the judgment that the King of Heaven visited upon him for the blasphemies he uttered), I buried him. For in his anger he put to death many of the sons of Israel, and I stole away their bodies and buried them. Sennacherib sought them out, but did not find them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001019"/>
      <verse num="19">Then a certain one of the Ninevites went and informed the king about me, that I was burying them, so I hid myself. When I learned that the king knew about me and that I was being sought out to be put to death, I was terrified and ran away.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001020"/>
      <verse num="20">Then everything that belonged to me was confiscated and nothing was left to me, that had not been taken for the royal treasury, except my wife Anna and my son Tobias.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001021"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="21">But not forty<note nid="n70001021.1"/> days passed before two of Sennacherib&apos;s<note nid="n70001021.2"/> sons killed him. They fled into the mountains of Ararat, and Esar-haddon,<note nid="n70001021.3"/> his son, reigned after him. He appointed Ahikar son of my brother Anael over all the accounts of his kingdom and he himself had authority over the entire administration.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70001022"/>
      <verse num="22">Then Ahikar interceded for me, and I returned to Nineveh. Now Ahikar was cupbearer, keeper of the signet ring, administrator and accountant under Sennacherib king of the Assyrians, and Esar-haddon had appointed him second to himself.<note nid="n70001022.1"/> He was my nephew and a member of my family.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002001"/>
    <chapter num="2">
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">And during the time of King Esar-haddon<note nid="n70002001.1"/> I came back to my house, and my wife Anna and my son Tobias were restored to me. And at our Feast of Pentecost, which is a sacred festival of seven days, a good meal was prepared for me and I reclined to eat.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002002"/>
      <verse num="2">A table was set before me, and an abundance of cooked food was set before me, and I said to my son Tobias, <q class="begin-double" qid="70002002.1" from="70002002.1" to="70002002.2"/>Child, go about and, bring back any poor person whom you might find among our kindred,<note nid="n70002002.1"/> from among the captives of Nineveh, who is mindful with all his heart, so that he might eat together with us. Behold, child, I will wait until you return.<q class="end-double" qid="70002002.2" from="70002002.1" to="70002002.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002003"/>
      <verse num="3">So Tobias went to seek out any poor person from among our kindred. When he returned he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70002003.1" from="70002003.1" to="70002003.2"/>Father!<q class="end-double" qid="70002003.2" from="70002003.1" to="70002003.2"/> And I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70002003.3" from="70002003.3" to="70002003.4"/>Here I am, child!<q class="end-double" qid="70002003.4" from="70002003.3" to="70002003.4"/> And he, replying, said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70002003.5" from="70002003.5" to="70002003.6"/>Behold, father! One from our nation has been murdered and thrown into the marketplace, and now he lies there strangled.<q class="end-double" qid="70002003.6" from="70002003.5" to="70002003.6"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002004"/>
      <verse num="4">So leaping up, I left my meal before I had tasted it and took the body<note nid="n70002004.1"/> out of the street and set it in one of my rooms until the sun set and I could bury it.<note nid="n70002004.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002005"/>
      <verse num="5">And when I returned, I washed myself and began to eat my food in sorrow.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002006"/>
      <verse num="6">And I remembered the word of the prophet, what things Amos spoke against Bethel, saying:<end-paragraph/><begin-block-indent/><begin-paragraph class="line-group"/><begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="70002006.1" from="70002006.1" to="70002006.2"/>Your feasts shall be turned into mourning,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and all your songs into lamentation.<q class="end-double" qid="70002006.2" from="70002006.1" to="70002006.2"/><end-line/><end-paragraph/><end-block-indent/><begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/>And I wept.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002007"/>
      <heading>Tobit Becomes Blind</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">When the sun had set I went out, dug a grave, and buried him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002008"/>
      <verse num="8">And my neighbors were mocking me, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="70002008.1" from="70002008.1" to="70002008.2"/>Is he no longer afraid? For he was already sought out to be put to death for doing this deed, and he ran away. Now behold! He is back to burying the dead!<q class="end-double" qid="70002008.2" from="70002008.1" to="70002008.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002009"/>
      <verse num="9">On the same night I washed myself and I went out into my courtyard and fell asleep beside the courtyard wall, and my face was uncovered because of the heat.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002010"/>
      <verse num="10">I did not know that there were sparrows on the wall above me, and their warm droppings fell into my eyes and brought on white films. I went to the physicians to be healed, but the more they anointed me with their potions, the more my eyes were blinded by the white films until I was completely blind. For four years I had no use of my eyes. All my relatives<note nid="n70002010.1"/> grieved over me and Ahikar took care of me for two years, before he went to Elymais.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002011"/>
      <heading>Tobit&apos;s Wife Earns Their Livelihood</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="11">At that time my wife Anna earned money at women&apos;s work.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002012"/>
      <verse num="12">She used to send the products to their employers and they would pay her wages. On the seventh of Dystros, she cut off a woven piece and sent it to the employers and they paid her the whole price and gave her a kid from the herd to take home.<note nid="n70002012.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002013"/>
      <verse num="13">When she returned to me the kid began to bleat. So I called her and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70002013.1" from="70002013.1" to="70002013.2"/>Where did you get this goat? It is not stolen, is it? Return it to its owners, for we do not have the right to eat anything stolen.<q class="end-double" qid="70002013.2" from="70002013.1" to="70002013.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70002014"/>
      <verse num="14">And she said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="70002014.1" from="70002014.1" to="70002014.2"/>It was given to me as a gift in addition to my wage.<q class="end-double" qid="70002014.2" from="70002014.1" to="70002014.2"/> But I did not believe her and kept telling her to return it to the owners, and I became flushed over this on her account. Then she replied to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="70002014.3" from="70002014.3" to="70002014.4"/>And where are your deeds of mercy? Where are your righteous deeds? Behold! these things are known about you!<q class="end-double" qid="70002014.4" from="70002014.3" to="70002014.4"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003001"/>
    <chapter num="3">
      <heading>Tobit&apos;s Prayer</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Then I became greatly depressed in my soul. Groaning out loud, I wept and I began to pray as I groaned:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003002"/>
      <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="70003002.1" from="70003002.1" to="70003006.1"/>Righteous are you, O Lord; all your deeds are just and all your ways are merciful and true. You judge the world.<note nid="n70003002.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003003"/>
      <verse num="3">And now, Lord, remember me and look favorably upon me<note nid="n70003003.1"/>; do not punish me for my sins and for my unwitting offenses and those of my fathers. They sinned before you</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003004"/>
      <verse num="4">and they disobeyed your commandments, and you gave us over to plunder and captivity and death; you made us an example and a byword and a reproach among all the nations among which you scattered us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003005"/>
      <verse num="5">And now your many judgments are true, to deal with me for my sins, because we did not do what you commanded and we did not walk before you with sincerity.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003006"/>
      <verse num="6">And now deal with me according to your pleasure; command my spirit to withdraw from me, that I may be set free from the face of the earth and become earth myself. For it is better for me to die than to live, because I have heard false reproaches, and great sorrow is upon me. Lord, command that I be set free from this distress. Set me free to go to the eternal place and do not turn your face, Lord, away from me. It is better for me to die and not to hear reproaches than to continue to see so much distress in my life.<q class="end-double" qid="70003006.1" from="70003002.1" to="70003006.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003007"/>
      <heading>Sarah Falsely Accused</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">On that day, it befell Sarah, daughter of Raguel in Ecbatana of Media, that she heard reproaches from one of her father&apos;s maidservants,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003008"/>
      <verse num="8">because she had been given to seven husbands, and the evil demon Asmodeus killed them before they had been with her as it is prescribed for wives. So the maidservant said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="70003008.1" from="70003008.1" to="70003009.1"/>You are the one who kills your husbands! Behold! You have already been married to seven husbands and have not borne the name of any one of them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003009"/>
      <verse num="9">Why do you beat us over your dead husbands? Go along with them, and may we never see a son or daughter of yours!<q class="end-double" qid="70003009.1" from="70003008.1" to="70003009.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003010"/>
      <heading>Sarah&apos;s Prayer for Death</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">On that day she was grieved in her soul and began to weep. Ascending to the upper room in her father&apos;s house, she wanted to hang herself. But she reconsidered and said: <q class="begin-double" qid="70003010.1" from="70003010.1" to="70003010.4"/>Let it not happen that they reproach my father and say to him, <q class="begin-single" qid="70003010.2" from="70003010.2" to="70003010.3"/>You had one beloved daughter and she hanged herself to escape her troubles.<q class="end-single" qid="70003010.3" from="70003010.2" to="70003010.3"/> I would bring the old age of my father down to Hades in grief. It is better for me not to hang myself, but to beg the Lord that I might die and no longer hear reproaches during my life.<q class="end-double" qid="70003010.4" from="70003010.1" to="70003010.4"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003011"/>
      <verse num="11">At that very time, spreading out her hands toward the window, she prayed and said: <q class="begin-double" qid="70003011.1" from="70003011.1" to="70003015.1"/>Blessed are you, merciful God, and blessed is your name forever. May all your works bless you forever.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003012"/>
      <verse num="12">And now, O Lord, my face looks to you and I lift my eyes.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003013"/>
      <verse num="13">Speak, that I might be set free from the earth and that I might no longer hear reproaches.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003014"/>
      <verse num="14">You know, Master, that I am clean from any uncleanness with a man</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003015"/>
      <verse num="15">and that I did not stain my name or the name of my father in the land of my captivity. I am my father&apos;s only child, and he has no other child to be his heir, no near kinsman<note nid="n70003015.1"/> or relative for whom I should keep myself to be a wife. Already seven have been lost to me. Why should I yet live? And if it does not seem right to you to kill me, Lord, hear now how I am reproached!<q class="end-double" qid="70003015.1" from="70003011.1" to="70003015.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003016"/>
      <heading>Answer to Prayer</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">At that very moment, the prayer of both was heard in the presence of the glory of God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70003017"/>
      <verse num="17">And Raphael was sent to heal the two of them: with regard to Tobit, to remove the white films from his eyes, in order that he might see the light of God with his eyes; with regard to Sarah, daughter of Raguel, to give her as wife to Tobias son of Tobit and to send Asmodeus the evil demon away from her, because Tobias was entitled to inherit her before all those wishing to have her. At that very moment, Tobit returned from the courtyard into his house and Sarah, the daughter of Raguel, came down from the upper room.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004001"/>
    <chapter num="4">
      <heading>Tobit Gives Instructions to His Son</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">On that day Tobit remembered the silver that he had left in trust with Gabael at Rages in Media,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004002"/>
      <verse num="2">and he said in his heart: <q class="begin-double" qid="70004002.1" from="70004002.1" to="70004002.2"/>Behold! I have asked for death. Why do I not call my son Tobias and tell him about this silver before I die?<q class="end-double" qid="70004002.2" from="70004002.1" to="70004002.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004003"/>
      <verse num="3">So he called his son Tobias, and he came to him, and Tobit<note nid="n70004003.1"/> said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70004003.1" from="70004003.1" to="70004021.1"/>Bury me honorably and respect your mother and do not abandon her all the days of her life. Do what is pleasing to her and do not grieve her spirit in any matter.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004004"/>
      <verse num="4">Remember her, child, because she faced many dangers for you while you were in her womb. And when she dies, bury her beside me in one grave.<note nid="n70004004.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5"><q class="continue-double" qid="70004005.1" from="70004003.1" to="70004021.1"/>Remember the Lord all your days, child, and refuse to sin or to transgress his commandments. Do righteous deeds all the days of your life and do not walk in the paths of wrongdoing.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004006"/>
      <verse num="6">For those who practice what is true will prosper in their deeds.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004007"/>
      <verse num="7">Do deeds of mercy from your possessions to all who practice righteousness and do not let your eye begrudge the gift when you make it. Do not turn your face away from any poor man, and the face of God will not be turned away from you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004008"/>
      <verse num="8">If you have many possessions, make your gift from them in proportion; if few, do not be afraid to give according to the little you have.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004009"/>
      <verse num="9">So you will be laying up a good treasure for yourself against the day of necessity.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004010"/>
      <verse num="10">For practicing mercy delivers from death and keeps you from entering the darkness;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004011"/>
      <verse num="11">for practicing mercy is an excellent offering in the sight of the Most High for all who do it.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004012"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="12"><q class="continue-double" qid="70004012.1" from="70004003.1" to="70004021.1"/>Beware, child, of all fornication. First of all take a wife from among the descendants of your fathers and do not marry a foreign woman, who is not of your father&apos;s tribe; for we are the sons of the prophets. Noah, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, our fathers of old&emdash;remember, child, that these all took wives from among their kinsmen. They were blessed in their children, and their offspring will inherit the land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004013"/>
      <verse num="13">So now, child, love your kinfolk and do not disdain in your heart to take for yourself a wife from among your kinfolk and from the sons and daughters of your people. For in arrogant disdain there is ruin and great confusion; and in idleness there is loss and great want, because idleness is the mother of famine.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004014"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="14"><q class="continue-double" qid="70004014.1" from="70004003.1" to="70004021.1"/>Do not hold over till the next day the wages of any man who works for you, but pay him at once; and if you serve God you will receive payment. Watch yourself, my son, in everything you do and be disciplined in all your conduct.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004015"/>
      <verse num="15">And what you hate, do not do to anyone. Do not drink wine to excess or let drunkenness go with you on your way.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004016"/>
      <verse num="16">Give some of your bread to the hungry and some of your clothing to the naked. Give all your surplus to charity and do not let your eye begrudge the gift while you are making it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004017"/>
      <verse num="17">Place your loaves on the grave of the righteous, but give none to sinners.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004018"/>
      <verse num="18">Seek advice from every wise man and do not despise any useful counsel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004019"/>
      <verse num="19">Bless the Lord God on every occasion; ask him that your ways may be made straight and that all your paths and plans may prosper. For none of the nations has understanding; but the Lord will give them good counsel, and whomever he wishes he brings down as far as the lowest parts of Hades.<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/><q class="continue-double" qid="70004019.1" from="70004003.1" to="70004021.1"/>And now, child, remember these commands and let them not be blotted out of your mind.<note nid="n70004019.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004020"/>
      <verse num="20">And now, child, I tell you that I entrusted ten talents of silver to Gabael, the brother<note nid="n70004020.1"/> of Gabri, at Rages in Media.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70004021"/>
      <verse num="21">Do not be afraid, child, that we have become poor: Many good things are yours if you fear God and flee from every sin and do what is good in the sight of the Lord your God.<q class="end-double" qid="70004021.1" from="70004003.1" to="70004021.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005001"/>
    <chapter num="5">
      <heading>The Angel Raphael</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Then Tobias answered his father Tobit, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005001.1" from="70005001.1" to="70005002.1"/>Father, everything that you have commanded me I will do;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005002"/>
      <verse num="2">but how will I be able to obtain the silver<note nid="n70005002.1"/> from him when he does not know me and I do not know him? What sign am I to give him so that he will recognize me and believe me and give me the silver? And I do not know the roads leading into Media, that I might travel there.<q class="end-double" qid="70005002.1" from="70005001.1" to="70005002.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005003"/>
      <verse num="3">Then Tobit answered his son Tobias, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005003.1" from="70005003.1" to="70005003.2"/>He gave me his handwritten receipt, and I gave a receipt to him. I divided one in two pieces and we each took one piece, and I put one with the silver. And now, behold! It is twenty years since I entrusted this silver. And now, child, seek out a reliable man for yourself, who will travel with you, and we will pay him wages until you return. Now obtain this silver from him.<q class="end-double" qid="70005003.2" from="70005003.1" to="70005003.2"/> </verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005004"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="4">So Tobias went to look for a man who might go with him into Media, who knew the road. He went out and found the angel Raphael standing before him, though Tobias<note nid="n70005004.1"/> did not know that he was an angel of God.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005005"/>
      <verse num="5">Tobias<note nid="n70005005.1"/> said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005005.1" from="70005005.1" to="70005005.2"/>Where are you from, young man?<q class="end-double" qid="70005005.2" from="70005005.1" to="70005005.2"/> And he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005005.3" from="70005005.3" to="70005005.4"/>From the sons of Israel, your brothers, and I have come here to find employment.<q class="end-double" qid="70005005.4" from="70005005.3" to="70005005.4"/> Tobias<note nid="n70005005.2"/> said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005005.5" from="70005005.5" to="70005005.6"/>Do you know the road to go into Media?<q class="end-double" qid="70005005.6" from="70005005.5" to="70005005.6"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005006"/>
      <verse num="6">He said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005006.1" from="70005006.1" to="70005006.2"/>Yes, I was there often, and I know and have experience with all the roads. I have traveled many times into Media and lodged with Gabael, our brother, who lives at Rages in Media. It is a two-day journey from Ecbatana to Rages, for Rages lies on a mountain, but Ecbatana in the midst of a plain.<q class="end-double" qid="70005006.2" from="70005006.1" to="70005006.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005007"/>
      <verse num="7">Then Tobias<note nid="n70005007.1"/> said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005007.1" from="70005007.1" to="70005007.2"/>Wait for me, young man, until I go and tell my father, for I need you to go with me, and I will pay you your wages.<q class="end-double" qid="70005007.2" from="70005007.1" to="70005007.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005008"/>
      <verse num="8">And he said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005008.1" from="70005008.1" to="70005008.2"/>I will linger; only do not delay.<q class="end-double" qid="70005008.2" from="70005008.1" to="70005008.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005009"/>
      <verse num="9">So Tobias went and informed his father Tobit and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005009.1" from="70005009.1" to="70005009.2"/>Behold! I have found a man from among our brothers, the sons of Israel.<q class="end-double" qid="70005009.2" from="70005009.1" to="70005009.2"/> He said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005009.3" from="70005009.3" to="70005009.4"/>Call the man for me, so that I may learn what his ancestry is, from which tribe he comes, and whether he is a reliable man, that he should go with you, child.<q class="end-double" qid="70005009.4" from="70005009.3" to="70005009.4"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005010"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">So Tobias went out, called him, and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005010.1" from="70005010.1" to="70005010.2"/>Young man, my father is calling for you.<q class="end-double" qid="70005010.2" from="70005010.1" to="70005010.2"/> And he entered the house and Tobit greeted him first. And the angel<note nid="n70005010.1"/> said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005010.3" from="70005010.3" to="70005010.4"/>May many things come to be that will give you joy.<q class="end-double" qid="70005010.4" from="70005010.3" to="70005010.4"/> Replying, Tobit said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005010.5" from="70005010.5" to="70005010.6"/>What is left to give me joy? I am a person with no power in his eyes. I do not see the light of heaven, but I lie in darkness like the dead, who no longer see the light. I am living among the dead: I hear people&apos;s voices, but I do not see them.<q class="end-double" qid="70005010.6" from="70005010.5" to="70005010.6"/> And he said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005010.7" from="70005010.7" to="70005010.8"/>Take heart! Your healing from God is near. Take heart!<q class="end-double" qid="70005010.8" from="70005010.7" to="70005010.8"/> Then Tobit said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005010.9" from="70005010.9" to="70005010.10"/>My son Tobias wishes to journey into Media. If you are able to accompany him and guide him, I will give you your wages, brother.<q class="end-double" qid="70005010.10" from="70005010.9" to="70005010.10"/> He replied, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005010.11" from="70005010.11" to="70005010.12"/>I am able to go with him, and I know all the roads. I have gone often into Media and crossed all its plains, and I know the mountains and all its paths.<q class="end-double" qid="70005010.12" from="70005010.11" to="70005010.12"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005011"/>
      <verse num="11">Then Tobit<note nid="n70005011.1"/> said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005011.1" from="70005011.1" to="70005011.2"/>Brother, what is your lineage, and from what tribe do you come? Tell me, brother.<q class="end-double" qid="70005011.2" from="70005011.1" to="70005011.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005012"/>
      <verse num="12">But he answered, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005012.1" from="70005012.1" to="70005012.2"/>What need do you have of a tribe?<q class="end-double" qid="70005012.2" from="70005012.1" to="70005012.2"/> And Tobit<note nid="n70005012.1"/> said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005012.3" from="70005012.3" to="70005012.4"/>I would like to know the truth about whose you are, brother, and what your name is.<q class="end-double" qid="70005012.4" from="70005012.3" to="70005012.4"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005013"/>
      <verse num="13">He said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005013.1" from="70005013.1" to="70005013.2"/>I am Azarias son of the great Ananias, from among your brothers.<q class="end-double" qid="70005013.2" from="70005013.1" to="70005013.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005014"/>
      <verse num="14">Then Tobit<note nid="n70005014.1"/> said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005014.1" from="70005014.1" to="70005014.2"/>May you go in good health and be kept safe, brother. Do not be angry with me, brother, because I wanted to learn the truth about your lineage. You do turn out to be a brother, of a good and noble stock. I used to know Ananias and Nathan, the two sons of the great Shemeliah: they used to travel with me to Jerusalem and worship with me there, and they were not led astray. Your relatives<note nid="n70005014.2"/> are good people; you are from good stock, and may you go rejoicing.<q class="end-double" qid="70005014.2" from="70005014.1" to="70005014.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005015"/>
      <verse num="15">And he said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005015.1" from="70005015.1" to="70005016.1"/>I am giving you a daily wage of a drachma and any necessary expenses for you and likewise for my son.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005016"/>
      <verse num="16">Now go with my son, and I will add a bonus to your wages.<q class="end-double" qid="70005016.1" from="70005015.1" to="70005016.1"/> And he replied to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005016.2" from="70005016.2" to="70005016.3"/>I will go with him. Do not be afraid: we will be safe as we go, and we will return to you in safety, because the way is secure.<q class="end-double" qid="70005016.3" from="70005016.2" to="70005016.3"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005017"/>
      <verse num="17">And Tobit<note nid="n70005017.1"/> said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005017.1" from="70005017.1" to="70005017.2"/>Blessing be upon you, brother.<q class="end-double" qid="70005017.2" from="70005017.1" to="70005017.2"/><end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>Then he called his son and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005017.3" from="70005017.3" to="70005017.4"/>Child, get your things ready for the journey and go with your brother, and may God in heaven bring you both safely there and bring you both back to me safe and sound, and may his angel travel with you both in safety, child.<q class="end-double" qid="70005017.4" from="70005017.3" to="70005017.4"/> So he went out to make his journey, and he kissed his father and mother, and Tobit said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005017.5" from="70005017.5" to="70005017.6"/>Go safely!<q class="end-double" qid="70005017.6" from="70005017.5" to="70005017.6"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005018"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">His mother wept and said to Tobit, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005018.1" from="70005018.1" to="70005020.1"/>Why have you sent my child away? Is he not the staff in our hand as he goes in and out before us?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005019"/>
      <verse num="19">Do not pile silver upon silver, but let it be a ransom for our child.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005020"/>
      <verse num="20">For the life that is given to us by the Lord is enough for us.<q class="end-double" qid="70005020.1" from="70005018.1" to="70005020.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005021"/>
      <verse num="21">And he said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="70005021.1" from="70005021.1" to="70005022.1"/>Do not make an issue of this; our child will go safely and come back to us safe and sound. You will see with your own eyes on that day that he returns to you safely. So do not make an issue of this, and do not be afraid for them, sister,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70005022"/>
      <verse num="22">for a good angel will go with him. His journey will be successful, and he will come back safe and sound.<q class="end-double" qid="70005022.1" from="70005021.1" to="70005022.1"/> </verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006001"/>
    <chapter num="6">
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">So she stopped weeping.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006002"/>
      <heading>Journey to Rages</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="2">So the child went out, and the angel with him, and the dog came out and went along with them. The two journeyed along, and the first night came upon them, and they camped beside the Tigris river.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006003"/>
      <verse num="3">Then the child went down to wash his feet in the Tigris river. A large fish, leaping up from the river, tried to swallow the child&apos;s foot, and he cried out.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006004"/>
      <verse num="4">The angel said to the boy, <q class="begin-double" qid="70006004.1" from="70006004.1" to="70006004.2"/>Grab hold of the fish and master it!<q class="end-double" qid="70006004.2" from="70006004.1" to="70006004.2"/> So the young man took hold of the fish and dragged it up on the land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006005"/>
      <verse num="5">Then the angel said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70006005.1" from="70006005.1" to="70006005.2"/>Split the fish open and take out its gall and heart and liver and keep them with you, but throw away the entrails, for its gall and heart and liver are useful for medicine.<q class="end-double" qid="70006005.2" from="70006005.1" to="70006005.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006006"/>
      <verse num="6">So the boy split open the fish and gathered the gall, heart, and liver. And they broiled the fish and ate it, and left some to be salted.<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>And the two journeyed on together until they came near to Media.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006007"/>
      <verse num="7">Then the boy questioned the angel and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70006007.1" from="70006007.1" to="70006007.2"/>Brother Azarias, what kind of medicine is in the fish&apos;s heart and liver and in its gall?<q class="end-double" qid="70006007.2" from="70006007.1" to="70006007.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006008"/>
      <verse num="8">He said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70006008.1" from="70006008.1" to="70006009.1"/>As for the fish&apos;s heart and the liver, burn these in the presence of a man or woman who meets misfortune from a demon or evil spirit, and every such misfortune will flee from that person and not abide with him ever after.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006009"/>
      <verse num="9">And as for the gall, anoint the eyes of a person, upon which white films have formed, and breathe upon them (upon the white films), and they will be cured.<q class="end-double" qid="70006009.1" from="70006008.1" to="70006009.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006010"/>
      <heading>Raphael&apos;s Instructions</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">When he entered Media and was already drawing near to Ecbatana,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006011"/>
      <verse num="11">Raphael said to the youth, <q class="begin-double" qid="70006011.1" from="70006011.1" to="70006011.2"/>Brother Tobias?<q class="end-double" qid="70006011.2" from="70006011.1" to="70006011.2"/> And he said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70006011.3" from="70006011.3" to="70006011.4"/>Here I am.<q class="end-double" qid="70006011.4" from="70006011.3" to="70006011.4"/> And he said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70006011.5" from="70006011.5" to="70006012.1"/>We must lodge tonight with the family of Raguel. The man is a relative of yours, and he has a daughter named Sarah.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006012"/>
      <verse num="12">He has no male child nor daughter, but only Sarah, and you are nearest kin to her, more entitled than all other men to inherit her, and it is right for you to inherit all that belongs to her father. The girl is sensible, courageous, and very beautiful, and her father is honorable.<q class="end-double" qid="70006012.1" from="70006011.5" to="70006012.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006013"/>
      <verse num="13">And he continued,<note nid="n70006013.1"/> <q class="begin-double" qid="70006013.1" from="70006013.1" to="70006013.2"/>It has been shown to be right for you to take her. So listen to me, brother, and I will speak to her father about the girl this very night, that you might take her as your bride, and when we return from Rages we will celebrate her wedding feast. And I know that Raguel will certainly not be able to keep her from you nor to give her to another. He would be liable to the death penalty according to the judgment of the book of Moses, because he knows that the inheritance is proper for you to have, to take his daughter before any man. So now listen to me, brother, and we will speak about the girl this very night and we will get her betrothed to you. And when we return from Rages, we will take her and conduct her along with us to your house.<q class="end-double" qid="70006013.2" from="70006013.1" to="70006013.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006014"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="14">Then Tobias answered Raphael, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="70006014.1" from="70006014.1" to="70006015.1"/>Brother Azarias, I heard that she has already been given to seven husbands and they died in the bridal chamber on the wedding night: when they were approaching her, they died. I also heard people saying that a demon kills them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006015"/>
      <verse num="15">So now I am afraid, because it does not harm her, but if anyone wants to get close to her, it kills him. I am my father&apos;s only son, and I am afraid<note nid="n70006015.1"/> lest I die and bring the lives of my father and mother down to their graves in sorrow on my account. And they have no other son to bury them.<q class="end-double" qid="70006015.1" from="70006014.1" to="70006015.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006016"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">But the angel<note nid="n70006016.1"/> said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70006016.1" from="70006016.1" to="70006018.1"/>Do you not remember your father&apos;s commands, that he commanded you to take a wife from your father&apos;s household? So listen to me now, brother, and do not make an issue of this demon, and take her, for I know indeed that a wife will be given to you this very night.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006017"/>
      <verse num="17">Now, when you enter the bridal chamber, take some of the liver of the fish, and the heart, and place these upon the ashes of the incense burner, and the smell will go forth,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70006018"/>
      <verse num="18">and the demon will sense it, and he will flee and never appear around her again for all time. And when you are about to be with her, rise up first, both of you, and pray and implore the Lord of heaven, that mercy and deliverance might come upon you both. And do not be afraid, for she was made your portion from before eternity. You will deliver her, and she will go with you, and I assume that you will have children by her, and they will be like brothers to you. So do not make an issue of this.<q class="end-double" qid="70006018.1" from="70006016.1" to="70006018.1"/> When Tobias heard Raphael&apos;s words, and that she was a sister to him from his father&apos;s household, he loved her greatly and his heart fixed itself on her.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007001"/>
    <chapter num="7">
      <heading>Arrival at Raguel&apos;s Home</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">When they entered Ecbatana, he said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007001.1" from="70007001.1" to="70007001.2"/>Brother Azarias, lead me directly to Raguel our brother.<q class="end-double" qid="70007001.2" from="70007001.1" to="70007001.2"/> And he led him to the house of Raguel, and they found him seated beside the door of the courtyard. They greeted him first, and he said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007001.3" from="70007001.3" to="70007001.4"/>Many greetings, brothers; welcome, and good health to you.<q class="end-double" qid="70007001.4" from="70007001.3" to="70007001.4"/> And he led them into his house.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007002"/>
      <verse num="2">Then he said to Edna his wife, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007002.1" from="70007002.1" to="70007002.2"/>How much this young man resembles Tobit, my kinsman!<q class="end-double" qid="70007002.2" from="70007002.1" to="70007002.2"/><note nid="n70007002.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007003"/>
      <verse num="3">And Edna inquired of them, saying to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007003.1" from="70007003.1" to="70007003.2"/>Where are you from, brothers?<q class="end-double" qid="70007003.2" from="70007003.1" to="70007003.2"/> They answered her, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007003.3" from="70007003.3" to="70007003.4"/>We are from the sons of Naphtali, from among those taken captive in Nineveh.<q class="end-double" qid="70007003.4" from="70007003.3" to="70007003.4"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007004"/>
      <verse num="4">So she said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007004.1" from="70007004.1" to="70007004.2"/>Do you know our brother Tobit?<q class="end-double" qid="70007004.2" from="70007004.1" to="70007004.2"/> And they said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007004.3" from="70007004.3" to="70007004.4"/>We indeed know him.<q class="end-double" qid="70007004.4" from="70007004.3" to="70007004.4"/> And she asked them, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007004.5" from="70007004.5" to="70007004.6"/>Is he in good health?<q class="end-double" qid="70007004.6" from="70007004.5" to="70007004.6"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007005"/>
      <verse num="5">They said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007005.1" from="70007005.1" to="70007005.2"/>He is alive and in good health.<q class="end-double" qid="70007005.2" from="70007005.1" to="70007005.2"/> And Tobias said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007005.3" from="70007005.3" to="70007005.4"/>He is my father.<q class="end-double" qid="70007005.4" from="70007005.3" to="70007005.4"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007006"/>
      <verse num="6">Then Raguel sprang up and kissed him and wept,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007007"/>
      <verse num="7">and he spoke and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007007.1" from="70007007.1" to="70007007.2"/>Blessing be upon you, child, son of that good and noble father! O most wretched of evils, that a just man, one who practiced deeds of mercy, was rendered blind.<q class="end-double" qid="70007007.2" from="70007007.1" to="70007007.2"/> Then he fell upon the neck of his kinsman Tobias and wept.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007008"/>
      <verse num="8">And his wife Edna wept over him, and their daughter Sarah likewise wept.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007009"/>
      <verse num="9">Then he killed a ram from the flock and welcomed them earnestly.
        <end-paragraph/>
        <heading>Marriage of Tobias and Sarah</heading>
        <begin-paragraph/>When they had bathed and washed themselves and reclined at table to eat, Tobias said to Raphael, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007009.1" from="70007009.1" to="70007009.2"/>Brother Azarias, speak to Raguel, that he might give Sarah my sister to me.<q class="end-double" qid="70007009.2" from="70007009.1" to="70007009.2"/>
      </verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007010"/>
      <verse num="10">Raguel heard this and said to the youth, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007010.1" from="70007010.1" to="70007011.1"/>Eat, drink, and be merry this night, for there is no person for whom it is proper to take Sarah my daughter besides you, brother. Likewise I myself do not have authority to give her to another man besides you, for you are nearest kin<note nid="n70007010.1"/> to me. But I will nevertheless explain the truth to you, child.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007011"/>
      <verse num="11">I gave her to seven husbands from among our brothers, and they all died the night on which they were going in to be with her. But now, child, eat and drink, and the Lord will act among you.<q class="end-double" qid="70007011.1" from="70007010.1" to="70007011.1"/> And Tobias said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007011.2" from="70007011.2" to="70007011.3"/>I will surely eat nothing here nor will I drink until you settle the matters that concern me.<q class="end-double" qid="70007011.3" from="70007011.2" to="70007011.3"/> So Raguel said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007011.4" from="70007011.4" to="70007011.5"/>I hereby do it, and she is given to you according to the judgment of the book of Moses. It has been decided from heaven that she be given to you. Receive your sister. From now on you are her brother and she your sister. She is given to you from today and forever, and may the Lord of heaven lead you both on a good path this night, child, and may he bring mercy and peace upon you both.<q class="end-double" qid="70007011.5" from="70007011.4" to="70007011.5"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007012"/>
      <verse num="12">Then Raguel called his daughter Sarah, and she came to him, and taking her by the hand he gave her to Tobias<note nid="n70007012.1"/> and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007012.1" from="70007012.1" to="70007012.2"/>Receive your wife, given to you according to the law and according to the judgment written in the book of Moses. Take her and go to your father safe and sound. And may the God of heaven prosper your way in peace.<q class="end-double" qid="70007012.2" from="70007012.1" to="70007012.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007013"/>
      <verse num="13">And he called her mother, and he told her to bring a scroll and he wrote a marriage contract in the scroll, to the effect that he gave her to him as a wife according to the judgment of the law of Moses.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007014"/>
      <verse num="14">With that, they began to eat and drink.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007015"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="15">And Raguel called Edna his wife and said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="70007015.1" from="70007015.1" to="70007015.2"/>Sister, prepare the other room and lead Sarah<note nid="n70007015.1"/> there.<q class="end-double" qid="70007015.2" from="70007015.1" to="70007015.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007016"/>
      <verse num="16">So she proceeded to furnish the room as he said to her and led her there. Then she wept over her and wiped away her tears and said to her,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70007017"/>
      <verse num="17"><q class="begin-double" qid="70007017.1" from="70007017.1" to="70007017.2"/>Take heart, daughter; may the Lord of heaven grant you joy in place of your grief. Take heart, daughter.<q class="end-double" qid="70007017.2" from="70007017.1" to="70007017.2"/> And she went out.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008001"/>
    <chapter num="8">
      <heading>Tobias Routs the Demon</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">When they had finished eating and drinking, they wanted to go to sleep, so they escorted the youth and led him to the other room.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008002"/>
      <verse num="2">Tobias remembered Raphael&apos;s words, and he took the fish&apos;s liver and the heart out of the sack where he had been keeping them and put them upon the live ashes in the incense burner.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008003"/>
      <verse num="3">And the odor of the fish exercised a restraining force and the demon fled upward to the districts of Egypt, and Raphael went and ensnared him there and bound him at once. </verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008004"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="4">And they came and shut the door of the private room. Tobias arose from the bed and said to Sarah,<note nid="n70008004.1"/> <q class="begin-double" qid="70008004.1" from="70008004.1" to="70008004.2"/>Sister, get up. Let us pray and plead with our Lord that he might bring us mercy and deliverance.<q class="end-double" qid="70008004.2" from="70008004.1" to="70008004.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008005"/>
      <verse num="5">So she arose and they began to pray and plead that deliverance might come to them, and he began to say:<end-paragraph/><begin-block-indent/><begin-paragraph class="line-group"/><begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="70008005.1" from="70008005.1" to="70008007.1"/>Blessed are you, O God of our fathers,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and blessed is your name through all the ages and generations.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>Let the heavens and every creature bless you through the ages.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008006"/>
      <verse num="6"><begin-line/>You made Adam, and you made his wife Eve for him<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>as a helper and support.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>From them both the offspring of mankind came into being.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>You said, <q class="begin-single" qid="70008006.1" from="70008006.1" to="70008006.2"/>It is not good for the man to be alone;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>let us make a helper for him like himself.<q class="end-single" qid="70008006.2" from="70008006.1" to="70008006.2"/><end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008007"/>
      <begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/>
      <verse num="7">And now, it is not because of lust that I am taking this sister of mine, but with sincerity. Grant that she and I may find mercy and that we may grow old together.<q class="end-double" qid="70008007.1" from="70008005.1" to="70008007.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008008"/>
      <verse num="8">And they said together, <q class="begin-double" qid="70008008.1" from="70008008.1" to="70008008.2"/>Amen, Amen.<q class="end-double" qid="70008008.2" from="70008008.1" to="70008008.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008009"/>
      <verse num="9">Then they both went to sleep for the night.<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>But Raguel arose, called his household servants to him, and went off and dug a grave,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008010"/>
      <verse num="10">for he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70008010.1" from="70008010.1" to="70008010.2"/>Perhaps he will die and we will become a laughingstock and reproach.<q class="end-double" qid="70008010.2" from="70008010.1" to="70008010.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008011"/>
      <verse num="11">When he had finished digging the grave, Raguel went into the house and called his wife</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008012"/>
      <verse num="12">and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70008012.1" from="70008012.1" to="70008012.2"/>Send one of the maidservants to go and see whether he is alive or if he has died, that we might bury him so that no one might know.<q class="end-double" qid="70008012.2" from="70008012.1" to="70008012.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008013"/>
      <verse num="13">So they sent the maid. They lit a lamp and opened the door, and she went in and found them lying down and sleeping together.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008014"/>
      <verse num="14">And the maidservant came out and told them that he was alive and that there was no harm.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008015"/>
      <verse num="15">Then they blessed the God of heaven and said:<end-paragraph/><begin-block-indent/><begin-paragraph class="line-group"/><begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="70008015.1" from="70008015.1" to="70008017.1"/>Blessed are you, O God, with every pure blessing.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>Let them bless you throughout the ages.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008016"/>
      <verse num="16"><begin-line/>Blessed are you, because you have made me glad,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>And because it has not turned out as I was expecting;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>but you have treated us according to your great mercy.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008017"/>
      <verse num="17"><begin-line/>Blessed are you, because you have had mercy on two only children.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>Bring them mercy and deliverance, Master;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and bring their lives to fulfillment with gladness and mercy.<q class="end-double" qid="70008017.1" from="70008015.1" to="70008017.1"/><end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008018"/>
      <begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/>
      <verse num="18">Then he ordered his servants to fill in the grave before morning came.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008019"/>
      <heading>Wedding Feast</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">He told his wife to bake many loaves of bread and he went out to the herd and selected two cows and four rams and gave orders to make them ready, and they began to make preparations.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008020"/>
      <verse num="20">And he called Tobias and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70008020.1" from="70008020.1" to="70008021.1"/>For fourteen days you shall surely not depart hence, but you will stay here eating and drinking with me, and you will bring gladness to my daughter&apos;s afflicted soul.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70008021"/>
      <verse num="21">And of all that belongs to me, take half and depart hence to your father safe and sound. As for the other half, when my wife and I die, it is yours. Take heart, child: I am your father and Edna your mother, and we will be by your side and that of your sister from now on and forever. Take heart, child!<q class="end-double" qid="70008021.1" from="70008020.1" to="70008021.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70009001"/>
    <chapter num="9">
      <heading>The Money Recovered</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Then Tobias called Raphael and said to him,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70009002"/>
      <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="70009002.1" from="70009002.1" to="70009004.1"/>Brother Azarias, take four servants and two camels with you and go to Media. Present yourself to Gabael, give him the receipt, take possession of the silver, and bring him back with you to the wedding feast.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70009004"/>
      <verse num="3" altnum="4">For you know that my father is counting the days, and if I delay even one day I will cause him much grief. And you see what Raguel has sworn, and I cannot transgress his oath.<q class="end-double" qid="70009004.1" from="70009002.1" to="70009004.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70009005"/>
      <verse num="5">So Raphael made the journey to Rages in Media along with the four servants and the two camels, and they stayed overnight with Gabael. He gave him his receipt, and told him about Tobit&apos;s son Tobias, that he had taken a wife and that he was inviting Gabael<note nid="n70009005.1"/> to the wedding feast. Gabael<note nid="n70009005.2"/> arose and counted out the money bags with their seals intact and they agreed that all was in order.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70009006"/>
      <verse num="6">They both rose early in the morning and went to the wedding feast. They entered Raguel&apos;s home and found Tobias reclining at table. He got up and greeted him, and Gabael<note nid="n70009006.1"/> wept and blessed him and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70009006.1" from="70009006.1" to="70009006.2"/>Noble and good seed of a noble and good man, a just and mercy-working man! May the Lord give you and your wife and your father and your wife&apos;s mother blessing from heaven! Blessed is God, for I see in Tobias the very likeness of my cousin Tobit!<q class="end-double" qid="70009006.2" from="70009006.1" to="70009006.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010001"/>
    <chapter num="10">
      <heading>Anxiety of Tobias&apos; Parents</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Now day by day, Tobit was counting out how many days Tobias<note nid="n70010001.1"/> had been traveling and how many days he would need to return. And when the days had been completed and his son did not yet arrive,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010002"/>
      <verse num="2">he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70010002.1" from="70010002.1" to="70010002.2"/>Perhaps he has been held up there, or perhaps Gabael died and no one is there to give him the silver?<q class="end-double" qid="70010002.2" from="70010002.1" to="70010002.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010003"/>
      <verse num="3">And he began to grieve.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010004"/>
      <verse num="4">And Anna his wife said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70010004.1" from="70010004.1" to="70010004.2"/>My child has perished and is no longer among the living!<q class="end-double" qid="70010004.2" from="70010004.1" to="70010004.2"/> Then she began to mourn and to lament over her son and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010005"/>
      <verse num="5"><q class="begin-double" qid="70010005.1" from="70010005.1" to="70010005.2"/>Woe to me, child, that I allowed you, the light of my eyes, to leave!<q class="end-double" qid="70010005.2" from="70010005.1" to="70010005.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010006"/>
      <verse num="6">Tobit began to say to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="70010006.1" from="70010006.1" to="70010006.2"/>Be still and stop making an issue, sister; he is safe and sound. Something has probably distracted them there. The man traveling with him is reliable and one of our brothers. Do not grieve over him, sister; he is just about here.<q class="end-double" qid="70010006.2" from="70010006.1" to="70010006.2"/><note nid="n70010006.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010007"/>
      <verse num="7">And she said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70010007.1" from="70010007.1" to="70010007.2"/>You be quiet and stop deceiving me; my child has perished.<q class="end-double" qid="70010007.2" from="70010007.1" to="70010007.2"/> And she rushed out every day to look down the road by which her son had left and would not listen to anyone. And whenever the sun had set, she would go back in and wail and weep the whole night long and would take no sleep.
        <end-paragraph/>
        <heading>Tobias and Sarah Head for Home</heading>
        <begin-paragraph/>Now when the fourteen days of the wedding feast that Raguel had sworn to make for his daughter were completed, Tobias went to him and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70010007.3" from="70010007.3" to="70010007.4"/>Send me back, for I know that my father and mother do not believe that they will ever see me again. So now I ask you, father, that you dismiss me, so I may go to my father. I have already told you in what condition I left him.<q class="end-double" qid="70010007.4" from="70010007.3" to="70010007.4"/>
      </verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010008"/>
      <verse num="8">And Raguel said to Tobias, <q class="begin-double" qid="70010008.1" from="70010008.1" to="70010008.2"/>Stay, child; stay with me, and I will send messengers to your father Tobit, and they will inform him how things are with you.<q class="end-double" qid="70010008.2" from="70010008.1" to="70010008.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010009"/>
      <verse num="9">And he replied, <q class="begin-double" qid="70010009.1" from="70010009.1" to="70010009.2"/>By no means! I ask you to send me back from here to my father.<q class="end-double" qid="70010009.2" from="70010009.1" to="70010009.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010010"/>
      <verse num="10">So Raguel arose and gave Tobias his wife Sarah and half of all his belongings&emdash;male and female servants, cattle and sheep, donkeys and camels, garments, silver, and vessels.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010011"/>
      <verse num="11">And he sent them off safe and sound, and bade him farewell and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70010011.1" from="70010011.1" to="70010011.2"/>Be well, child, and go your way safe and sound. May the Lord of heaven prosper you and your wife Sarah, and may I see your children before I die.<q class="end-double" qid="70010011.2" from="70010011.1" to="70010011.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010012"/>
      <verse num="12">He said also to his daughter Sarah, <q class="begin-double" qid="70010012.1" from="70010012.1" to="70010012.2"/>Go to your father-in-law and your mother-in-law,<note nid="n70010012.1"/> because from now on they are your parents, as are the ones who gave you birth. Go in peace, daughter, and may I hear a good report about you as long as I live.<q class="end-double" qid="70010012.2" from="70010012.1" to="70010012.2"/> And saying farewell, he allowed them to go. And Edna said to Tobias, <q class="begin-double" qid="70010012.3" from="70010012.3" to="70010012.4"/>Child and beloved brother, may the Lord bring you back and may I live to see your children, yours and Sarah&apos;s,<note nid="n70010012.2"/> before I die. Before the Lord I am entrusting my daughter to you for safe keeping. Do nothing to grieve her all the days of your life. Go in peace, child. From now on I am your mother and Sarah is your sister. May we all prosper together all the days of our lives.<q class="end-double" qid="70010012.4" from="70010012.3" to="70010012.4"/> And she kissed them both and sent them off safe and sound.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70010013"/>
      <verse num="13">So Tobias left Raguel safe and sound, rejoicing and blessing the Lord of heaven and earth, the King of all, because he had made his journey a success. And he said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70010013.1" from="70010013.1" to="70010013.2"/>May it please<note nid="n70010013.1"/> you to honor them all the days of their lives.<q class="end-double" qid="70010013.2" from="70010013.1" to="70010013.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011001"/>
    <chapter num="11">
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">As they were approaching Kaserein, which is across from Nineveh,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011002"/>
      <verse num="2">Raphael said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70011002.1" from="70011002.1" to="70011003.1"/>You know in what condition we left your father.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011003"/>
      <verse num="3">Let us run ahead of your wife and prepare the house while they are coming.<q class="end-double" qid="70011003.1" from="70011002.1" to="70011003.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011004"/>
      <verse num="4">So they both went together, and he said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70011004.1" from="70011004.1" to="70011004.2"/>Take the gall in your hands.<q class="end-double" qid="70011004.2" from="70011004.1" to="70011004.2"/> And the dog went along behind them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">Now Anna sat looking intently down the road her son had taken.<note nid="n70011005.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011006"/>
      <verse num="6">And she caught sight of him coming and said to his father, <q class="begin-double" qid="70011006.1" from="70011006.1" to="70011006.2"/>Behold! your son is coming, and so is the man who went with him!<q class="end-double" qid="70011006.2" from="70011006.1" to="70011006.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011007"/>
      <heading>Tobit&apos;s Sight Restored</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">And Raphael said to Tobias before he drew near to his father, <q class="begin-double" qid="70011007.1" from="70011007.1" to="70011008.1"/>I know that his eyes will be opened.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011008"/>
      <verse num="8">Smear the fish&apos;s gall into his eyes, and the medicine will cause the white films to contract and peel away from his eyes, and your father will look up and see the light.<q class="end-double" qid="70011008.1" from="70011007.1" to="70011008.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011009"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="9">Then Anna ran up and fell upon her son&apos;s neck and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70011009.1" from="70011009.1" to="70011009.2"/>I have seen you, child; from now on I am ready to die.<q class="end-double" qid="70011009.2" from="70011009.1" to="70011009.2"/><note nid="n70011009.1"/> And she wept.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011010"/>
      <verse num="10">And Tobit got up, stumbling over his feet, and emerged from the door of the courtyard. And Tobias went up to him</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011011"/>
      <verse num="11">with the fish&apos;s gall in his hand, and he blew into his eyes and took hold of him and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70011011.1" from="70011011.1" to="70011011.2"/>Take heart, father,<q class="end-double" qid="70011011.2" from="70011011.1" to="70011011.2"/> and he put the medicine on him, and Tobit allowed him.<note nid="n70011011.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011013"/>
      <verse num="12" altnum="13">And he peeled away the white films<note nid="n70011013.1"/> from the corners of his eyes with his two hands. Then he fell on his neck</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011014"/>
      <verse num="14">and he wept and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70011014.1" from="70011014.1" to="70011014.2"/>I see you, child, the light of my eyes!<q class="end-double" qid="70011014.2" from="70011014.1" to="70011014.2"/> And he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70011014.3" from="70011014.3" to="70011015.1"/>Blessed is God, and blessed is his great name, and blessed are all his holy angels. May your great name be over us, and may all your angels be blessed through all the ages.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011015"/>
      <verse num="15">For he chastised me, and behold! I see my son Tobias!<q class="end-double" qid="70011015.1" from="70011014.3" to="70011015.1"/> And Tobias went in rejoicing and blessing God with his full voice,<note nid="n70011015.1"/> and Tobias reported to his father that his journey had prospered, and that he recovered the silver, and how he took Sarah the daughter of Raguel as his wife; and he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70011015.2" from="70011015.2" to="70011015.3"/>Behold! She has arrived and is at the very gate of Nineveh!<q class="end-double" qid="70011015.3" from="70011015.2" to="70011015.3"/> </verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011016"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">Then Tobit went out to the gate of Nineveh to meet his daughter-in-law, rejoicing and blessing God. When the Ninevites saw him as he was making his way and crossing through in his full strength with no one guiding him by the hand, they were amazed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011017"/>
      <verse num="17">And Tobit acknowledged before them that God had shown him mercy and opened his eyes. And Tobit came near to Sarah the wife of his son Tobias and blessed her and said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="70011017.1" from="70011017.1" to="70011017.2"/>May you enter safe and sound, daughter! Blessed is your God who has led you to us, daughter, and blessed is your father and your mother,<note nid="n70011017.1"/> and blessed is Tobias my son, and blessed are you, daughter. Come into your home safe and sound, with blessing and joy. Come in, daughter!<q class="end-double" qid="70011017.2" from="70011017.1" to="70011017.2"/> There was joy that day among all the Judeans who were in Nineveh.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011018"/>
      <verse num="18">And his nephews Ahikar and Nadab<note nid="n70011018.1"/> came to Tobit, rejoicing.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70011019"/>
      <verse num="19">The wedding was celebrated with joy for seven days, and many gifts were bestowed on them.<note nid="n70011019.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012001"/>
    <chapter num="12">
      <heading>Raphael&apos;s Wages</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">When the wedding feast was completed, Tobit called his son Tobias and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70012001.1" from="70012001.1" to="70012001.2"/>Child, see that you give his wages to the man who went with you, and that you add something over and above.<q class="end-double" qid="70012001.2" from="70012001.1" to="70012001.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012002"/>
      <verse num="2">He said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70012002.1" from="70012002.1" to="70012003.1"/>Father, how much am I to give him as his wages? It would not hurt me to give him half of the goods that he carried back with me.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012003"/>
      <verse num="3">For he has led me on my way safe and sound, and he cured my wife, and he fetched the silver with me, and he healed you. How much more shall I give him as wages?<q class="end-double" qid="70012003.1" from="70012002.1" to="70012003.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012004"/>
      <verse num="4">Tobit said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="70012004.1" from="70012004.1" to="70012004.2"/>It is right, child, for him to take half of all that he has come back carrying.<q class="end-double" qid="70012004.2" from="70012004.1" to="70012004.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012005"/>
      <verse num="5">So he called him and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="70012005.1" from="70012005.1" to="70012005.2"/>Take for your wages half of all that you came back carrying, and depart safe and sound.<q class="end-double" qid="70012005.2" from="70012005.1" to="70012005.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012006"/>
      <heading>Raphael&apos;s Exhortation</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="6">Then the angel<note nid="n70012006.1"/> called the two of them privately and said to them: <q class="begin-double" qid="70012006.1" from="70012006.1" to="70012015.1"/>Bless God and acknowledge him before all the living with respect to the good things he has done for you. Bless and sing hymns to his name. Report the words of God to all people honorably, and do not hesitate to acknowledge him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012007"/>
      <verse num="7">It is an honorable thing to keep a king&apos;s secret hidden and gloriously to reveal and acknowledge the works of God. Keep doing what is good, and evil will not come upon you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012008"/>
      <verse num="8">Prayer with sincerity, practicing mercy, and righteousness is better than wealth with injustice. It is a more honorable thing to do a work of mercy than to store up gold.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012009"/>
      <verse num="9">Practicing mercy delivers from death, and it purges away every sin. Those who do deeds of mercy will have full satisfaction from life;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012010"/>
      <verse num="10">but those who practice sin and injustice are enemies of their own souls.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012011"/>
      <heading>Raphael Discloses His Identity</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="11"><q class="continue-double" qid="70012011.1" from="70012006.1" to="70012015.1"/>I will tell you the whole truth and not conceal anything from you. I informed you already and said, <q class="begin-single" qid="70012011.2" from="70012011.2" to="70012011.3"/>It is an honorable thing to keep a king&apos;s secret hidden and gloriously to reveal the works of God.<q class="end-single" qid="70012011.3" from="70012011.2" to="70012011.3"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012012"/>
      <verse num="12">So now, when you prayed, and Sarah too, I brought the remembrance of your prayers before the glory of the Lord, and likewise when you buried the dead.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012013"/>
      <verse num="13">When you did not hesitate to rise and leave your meal and go and care for the dead,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012014"/>
      <verse num="14">then I was sent to you, to test you, and at the same time God sent me to heal you and your daughter-in-law<note nid="n70012014.1"/> Sarah.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012015"/>
      <verse num="15">I am Raphael, one of the seven angels who stand and enter before the glory of the Lord.<q class="end-double" qid="70012015.1" from="70012006.1" to="70012015.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012016"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">The two of them were troubled; they fell on their faces and they were greatly alarmed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012017"/>
      <verse num="17">And he said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="70012017.1" from="70012017.1" to="70012020.1"/>Do not be afraid; peace to you both. Bless God through all the ages.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012018"/>
      <verse num="18">When I was with you, it was not by my favor that I was with you, but by God&apos;s will. Bless him all your days; sing hymns to him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012019"/>
      <verse num="19">And you were looking at me, but<note nid="n70012019.1"/> I was not eating anything, but it appeared this way to you in a vision.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012020"/>
      <verse num="20">And now bless God and acknowledge him on earth. Behold! I am ascending to him who sent me. Write down all these things that have happened to you.<q class="end-double" qid="70012020.1" from="70012017.1" to="70012020.1"/> And he ascended.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012021"/>
      <verse num="21">Then they stood up, and they were no longer able to see him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70012022"/>
      <verse num="22">So they began to bless and to sing praise to God and to acknowledge him concerning these great works of his, how an angel of God appeared to them.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013001"/>
    <chapter num="13">
      <heading>Tobit&apos;s Thanksgiving to God</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Then Tobit<note nid="n70013001.1"/> said:<end-paragraph/><begin-block-indent/><begin-paragraph class="line-group"/><begin-line/><q class="begin-double" qid="70013001.1" from="70013001.1" to="70013018.3"/>Blessed is God who lives forever, and blessed is his kingdom,<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013002"/>
      <verse num="2"><begin-line class="indent"/>because he chastises, and he shows mercy; <end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>he leads down to Hades below the earth, <end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and he himself raises up again from great devastation, <end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and there is nothing that can escape his hand. <end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013003"/>
      <verse num="3"><begin-line/>Acknowledge him, O sons of Israel, before the nations;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>for he himself has scattered you among them,<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013004"/>
      <verse num="4"><begin-line class="indent"/>and he has shown you his greatness even there.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>So exalt him in the presence of every living thing,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>because he himself is our Lord;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>he is our God, and he is our Father, <end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and he is God through all the ages.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013005"/>
      <verse num="5"><begin-line/>He will chastise you for your unrighteous deeds,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and he will have mercy upon you all,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>from all the nations wherever you have been scattered.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013006"/>
      <verse num="6"><begin-line/>When you turn to him with all your heart and with all your soul,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>to do what is true before him,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>then he will turn to you<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and will surely not hide his face from you any longer.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>And now see what he has done with you;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>acknowledge him with your full voice,<note nid="n70013006.1"/> <end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>and bless the Lord of righteousness<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and exalt the King of the ages.<note nid="n70013006.2"/><end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>I acknowledge him in the land of my captivity,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and I show his power and majesty to a nation of sinners.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>Turn back, you sinners, and do what is right before him;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>who knows if he will accept you and have mercy on you?<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013007"/>
      <verse num="7"><begin-line/>I exalt my God<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and my soul exalts the King of heaven,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and will rejoice in his majesty.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013008"/>
      <verse num="8"><begin-line/>Let all people speak<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and acknowledge him in Jerusalem.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013009"/>
      <verse num="9"><begin-line/>O Jerusalem, the holy city,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>he will chastise you for the deeds of your sons,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and will again show mercy to the sons of the righteous.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013010"/>
      <verse num="10"><begin-line/>Acknowledge the Lord in good times<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and bless the King of the ages.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>Your tabernacle will once again be built for you with joy.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>May he cheer all those within you who are captives<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and love all those within you who are distressed,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>to all generations forever.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013011"/>
      <verse num="11"><begin-line/>A bright light will shine into all the ends of the earth:<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>many nations will come to you from far off,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and sojourners from all the farthest places of the earth will come<note nid="n70013011.1"/> to your holy name,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>bearing in their hands their gifts for the King of heaven.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>Generations of generations will render joyful worship within you,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and the name of the chosen one will last for generations forever.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013012"/>
      <verse num="12"><begin-line/>Cursed are all who speak a harsh word against you;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>cursed will be all those who overthrow and pull down your walls,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and all who topple your towers and burn your dwellings.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>But blessed will be all who revere you forever.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013013"/>
      <verse num="13"><begin-line/>Go, then, and rejoice over the sons of the righteous,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>because they will all be gathered together<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and will bless the Lord of the age.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013014"/>
      <verse num="14"><begin-line/>Happy are those who love you,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and happy are those who will rejoice over the peace you enjoy.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>Happy are all the people who will grieve over all your chastisements,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>because they will rejoice over you, <end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and they will see all your joy forever.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013015"/>
      <verse num="15"><begin-line/>Bless the Lord, the great King, O my soul,<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013016"/>
      <verse num="16"><begin-line class="indent"/>because Jerusalem will be built up for a city,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>God&apos;s<note nid="n70013016.1"/> house unto all ages.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>Happy would I be, if the remnant of my line might be present<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>to see your glory and to acknowledge the King of heaven.<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>The gates of Jerusalem will be built with sapphire and emerald,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and all her walls with precious stone;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>the towers of Jerusalem will be built with gold <end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and her outer fortifications with pure gold.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013017"/>
      <verse num="17"><begin-line/>The streets of Jerusalem will be paved with<note nid="n70013017.1"/> garnet and stone of Ophir;<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70013018"/>
      <verse num="18"><begin-line class="indent"/>and the gates of Jerusalem will speak songs of joyful worship, <end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and all her houses will say <q class="begin-single" qid="70013018.1" from="70013018.1" to="70013018.2"/>Hallelujah! Blessed is the God of Israel,<q class="end-single" qid="70013018.2" from="70013018.1" to="70013018.2"/><end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and the blessed will bless the holy name forever and beyond.<q class="end-double" qid="70013018.3" from="70013001.1" to="70013018.3"/><end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014001"/>
    <chapter num="14">
      <heading>Tobit&apos;s Final Counsel</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">And the words of Tobit&apos;s confession came to an end. And he died in peace at one hundred and twelve years of age and was buried honorably in Nineveh.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014002"/>
      <verse num="2">He was sixty-two years old when he was injured in his eyes, and after he regained sight he lived in prosperity<note nid="n70014002.1"/> and practiced deeds of mercy, and he continued to bless God and to acknowledge God&apos;s majesty.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014003"/>
      <verse num="3">When he was dying, he called his son Tobias and commanded him, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="70014003.1" from="70014003.1" to="70014011.1"/>Child, take your children</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014004"/>
      <verse num="4">and run away to Media, because I trust God&apos;s word concerning Nineveh, which Nahum spoke, that all these things will come to pass and befall Assyria<note nid="n70014004.1"/> and Nineveh. All things whatsoever that were spoken by the prophets of Israel, whom God sent, will come about, and nothing shall be lacking from all their words, but all things will come to pass in their appointed times. In Media there will be deliverance,<note nid="n70014004.2"/> more so than in Assyria and in Babylon. Therefore, I know and believe that all things that God said will be fulfilled and come to be, and not a single word of his speech will prove wrong. Our brothers living in the land of Israel will be scattered<note nid="n70014004.3"/> and taken from the good land into captivity, and all the land of Israel will be desolate, and Samaria and Jerusalem will be desolate, and the house of God will be in grief and will be burned down for a time.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014005"/>
      <verse num="5">But God will again have mercy on them, and God will bring them back into the land of Israel, and they will rebuild the house, though for a time not as the first one, until the span of the times is fulfilled. After this they will all return from their captivity and will rebuild Jerusalem gloriously, and the house of God will be built therein, just as the prophets of Israel spoke concerning it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014006"/>
      <verse num="6">And all the nations throughout the whole earth, all will turn and fear God sincerely, and they will all abandon their lying idols, which<note nid="n70014006.1"/> led them astray.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014007"/>
      <verse num="7">And they will bless the God of the ages in righteousness. All the sons of Israel who are delivered in those days, being mindful of God with sincerity, will be gathered and will come into Jerusalem and will dwell forever in the land of Abraham with security, and it will be given to them. And those who love God sincerely will rejoice, and those practicing sin and injustice will depart from all the land.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014009"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="8" altnum="9"><q class="continue-double" qid="70014009.1" from="70014003.1" to="70014011.1"/>So now, children, I am commanding you: serve God in sincerity and do what is pleasing before him. Your children also are to be instructed to practice righteousness and mercy and to remain mindful of God and to bless his name in every time with sincerity and with all their strength. And now you, child: leave Nineveh and do not remain here.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014010"/>
      <verse num="10">In the day that you bury your mother with me, that very day do not lodge overnight within its boundaries. For I see that much injustice is within it, and much guile is perpetrated within it, and they have no shame. See, child, what Nadab did to Ahikar who had reared him: was he not brought down alive into the earth? And God repaid him to his face with dishonor, and Ahikar came out into the light and Nadab went into everlasting darkness, because he sought to kill Ahikar. By practicing mercy, he stepped out of the fatal trap that Nadab set for him, and Nadab fell into the fatal trap and it destroyed him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014011"/>
      <verse num="11">So now, children, see what practicing mercy brings about, and what injustice brings about&emdash;that it kills. And now my soul is departing.<q class="end-double" qid="70014011.1" from="70014003.1" to="70014011.1"/>
        <end-paragraph/>
        <heading>Death of Tobit and Anna</heading>
        <begin-paragraph/>And they set him upon his bed, and he died and was buried honorably.
      </verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014012"/>
      <verse num="12">And when his mother died, Tobias buried her with his father. Then he and his wife departed for Media, and they dwelt in Ecbatana with Raguel his father-in-law.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014013"/>
      <verse num="13">He looked after them honorably in their old age and he buried them in Ecbatana of Media and he inherited the property of Raguel and of Tobit his father.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014014"/>
      <verse num="14">He died honorably at the age of one hundred and seventeen years.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v70014015"/>
      <verse num="15">And before he died, he saw and heard about the destruction of Nineveh, and he saw her captives being led into Media, which Cyaxares<note nid="n70014015.1"/> the king of Media had taken captive, and he blessed God for all the things that he brought upon the sons of Nineveh and Assyria.<note nid="n70014015.2"/> He rejoiced over Nineveh before he died, and blessed the Lord God for ages of ages.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
  </book>
</crossway-bible>
