<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible translation="English Standard Version" revision="2018-3-26" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
<book title="Bel and the Dragon" num="79">
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001001"/>
  <chapter num="1">
    <heading>Daniel and the Priests of Bel</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">When King Astyages was laid with his ancestors, Cyrus the Persian received his kingdom.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001002"/>
    <verse num="2">And Daniel was a companion of the king and was the most honored of his friends.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001003"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3">Now the Babylonians had an idol called Bel, and every day they spent on it twelve bushels of fine flour and forty sheep and fifty gallons of wine.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001004"/>
    <verse num="4">The king revered it and went every day to worship it. But Daniel kept worshiping his own God.<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>And the king said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001004.1" from="79001004.1" to="79001004.2"/>Why do you not worship Bel?<q class="end-double" qid="79001004.2" from="79001004.1" to="79001004.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001005"/>
    <verse num="5">He answered, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001005.1" from="79001005.1" to="79001005.2"/>Because I do not revere man-made idols, but the living God, who created heaven and earth and has dominion over all flesh.<q class="end-double" qid="79001005.2" from="79001005.1" to="79001005.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6">The king said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001006.1" from="79001006.1" to="79001006.2"/>Do you not think that Bel is a living God? Do you not see how much he eats and drinks every day?<q class="end-double" qid="79001006.2" from="79001006.1" to="79001006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001007"/>
    <verse num="7">Then Daniel laughed and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001007.1" from="79001007.1" to="79001007.2"/>Do not be deceived, O king, for this is but clay inside and brass outside, and it never ate or drank anything.<q class="end-double" qid="79001007.2" from="79001007.1" to="79001007.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">Then the king was angry, and he called his priests and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001008.1" from="79001008.1" to="79001009.1"/>If you do not tell me who is eating these provisions, you shall die.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001009"/>
    <verse num="9">But if you prove that Bel is eating them, Daniel shall die, because he blasphemed against Bel.<q class="end-double" qid="79001009.1" from="79001008.1" to="79001009.1"/> And Daniel said to the king, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001009.2" from="79001009.2" to="79001009.3"/>Let it be done as you have said.<q class="end-double" qid="79001009.3" from="79001009.2" to="79001009.3"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">Now there were seventy priests of Bel, besides their wives and children. And the king went with Daniel into the temple of Bel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001011"/>
    <verse num="11">And the priests of Bel said, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001011.1" from="79001011.1" to="79001012.1"/>Behold, we are going outside; you yourself, O king, shall set forth the food and mix and place the wine and shut the door and seal it with your signet.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001012"/>
    <verse num="12">And when you return in the morning, if you do not find that Bel has eaten it all, we will die; or else Daniel will, who is telling lies about us.<q class="end-double" qid="79001012.1" from="79001011.1" to="79001012.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001013"/>
    <verse num="13">They were unconcerned, for beneath the table they had made a hidden entrance, through which they used to go in regularly and consume the provisions.<note nid="n79001013.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14">When they had gone out, the king set forth the food for Bel. Then Daniel ordered his servants to bring ashes, and they sifted them throughout the whole temple in the presence of the king alone. Then they went out, shut the door, and sealed it with the king&apos;s signet and departed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001015"/>
    <verse num="15">In the night the priests came with their wives and children, as they were accustomed to do, and ate and drank everything.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">Early in the morning the king rose and came, and Daniel with him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001017"/>
    <verse num="17">And the king<note nid="n79001017.1"/> said, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001017.1" from="79001017.1" to="79001017.2"/>Are the seals unbroken, Daniel?<q class="end-double" qid="79001017.2" from="79001017.1" to="79001017.2"/> He answered, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001017.3" from="79001017.3" to="79001017.4"/>They are unbroken, O king.<q class="end-double" qid="79001017.4" from="79001017.3" to="79001017.4"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18">As soon as the doors were opened, the king looked at the table and shouted in a loud voice, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001018.1" from="79001018.1" to="79001018.2"/>You are great, O Bel; and with you there is no deceit, none at all.<q class="end-double" qid="79001018.2" from="79001018.1" to="79001018.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19">Then Daniel laughed and restrained the king from going in and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001019.1" from="79001019.1" to="79001019.2"/>Look at the floor and notice whose footsteps these are.<q class="end-double" qid="79001019.2" from="79001019.1" to="79001019.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001020"/>
    <verse num="20">The king said, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001020.1" from="79001020.1" to="79001020.2"/>I see the footsteps of men and women and children.<q class="end-double" qid="79001020.2" from="79001020.1" to="79001020.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001021"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="21">Then the king was enraged, and he seized the priests and their wives and children; and they showed him the secret doors through which they were accustomed to enter and devour what was on the table.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001022"/>
    <verse num="22">Therefore the king put them to death and gave Bel over to Daniel, who destroyed it and its temple.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001023"/>
    <heading>Daniel Kills the Dragon</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="23">There was also a great dragon, which the Babylonians revered.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001024"/>
    <verse num="24">And the king said to Daniel, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001024.1" from="79001024.1" to="79001024.2"/>You cannot deny that this is a living god; so worship him.<q class="end-double" qid="79001024.2" from="79001024.1" to="79001024.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001025"/>
    <verse num="25">Daniel said, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001025.1" from="79001025.1" to="79001026.1"/>I will worship the Lord my God, for he is the living God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001026"/>
    <verse num="26">But if you, O king, will give me permission, I will slay the dragon without sword or club.<q class="end-double" qid="79001026.1" from="79001025.1" to="79001026.1"/> The king said, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001026.2" from="79001026.2" to="79001026.3"/>I give you permission.<q class="end-double" qid="79001026.3" from="79001026.2" to="79001026.3"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001027"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="27">Then Daniel took pitch, fat, and hair and boiled them together and made cakes, which he fed to the dragon. The dragon ate them and burst open. And Daniel said, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001027.1" from="79001027.1" to="79001027.2"/>See what you have been worshiping!<q class="end-double" qid="79001027.2" from="79001027.1" to="79001027.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001028"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="28">When the Babylonians heard it, they were very indignant and conspired against the king, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001028.1" from="79001028.1" to="79001028.2"/>The king has become a Jew; he has destroyed Bel and slain the dragon and slaughtered the priests.<q class="end-double" qid="79001028.2" from="79001028.1" to="79001028.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001029"/>
    <verse num="29">Going to the king, they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001029.1" from="79001029.1" to="79001029.2"/>Hand Daniel over to us or else we will kill you and your household.<q class="end-double" qid="79001029.2" from="79001029.1" to="79001029.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001030"/>
    <verse num="30">The king saw that they were pressing him hard, and under compulsion he handed Daniel over to them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001031"/>
    <heading>Daniel in the Lions&apos; Den</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="31">They threw Daniel into the lions&apos; den, and he was there for six days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001032"/>
    <verse num="32">There were seven lions in the den, and every day they had been given two human bodies and two sheep; but these were not given to them now, so that they might devour Daniel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001033"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="33">Now the prophet Habakkuk was in Judea. He had boiled pottage and had broken bread into a bowl and was going into the field to take it to the reapers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001034"/>
    <verse num="34">But the angel of the Lord said to Habakkuk, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001034.1" from="79001034.1" to="79001034.2"/>Take the dinner that you have to Babylon, to Daniel, in the lions&apos; den.<q class="end-double" qid="79001034.2" from="79001034.1" to="79001034.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001035"/>
    <verse num="35">Habakkuk said, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001035.1" from="79001035.1" to="79001035.2"/>Sir, I have never seen Babylon, and I know nothing about the den.<q class="end-double" qid="79001035.2" from="79001035.1" to="79001035.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001036"/>
    <verse num="36">Then the angel of the Lord took him by the crown of his head and lifted him by his hair and set him down in Babylon, right over the den, with the rushing sound of the wind itself.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001037"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="37">Then Habakkuk shouted, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001037.1" from="79001037.1" to="79001037.2"/>Daniel, Daniel! Take the dinner that God has sent you.<q class="end-double" qid="79001037.2" from="79001037.1" to="79001037.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001038"/>
    <verse num="38">And Daniel said, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001038.1" from="79001038.1" to="79001038.2"/>You have remembered me, O God, and have not forsaken those who love you.<q class="end-double" qid="79001038.2" from="79001038.1" to="79001038.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001039"/>
    <verse num="39">So Daniel arose and ate. And the angel of God immediately returned Habakkuk to his own place.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001040"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="40">On the seventh day the king came to mourn for Daniel. When he came to the den he looked in, and there sat Daniel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001041"/>
    <verse num="41">And the king shouted with a loud voice, <q class="begin-double" qid="79001041.1" from="79001041.1" to="79001041.2"/>You are great, O Lord God of Daniel, and there is no other besides you.<q class="end-double" qid="79001041.2" from="79001041.1" to="79001041.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v79001042"/>
    <verse num="42">And he pulled Daniel<note nid="n79001042.1"/> out and threw into the den those who had attempted his destruction, and they were devoured immediately before his eyes.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
</book>
</crossway-bible>
