<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='yes'?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" translation="English Standard Version" revision="2018-3-26" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
  <book title="2 Esdras" num="86">
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001001"/>
    <chapter num="1">
      <heading>Genealogy of Ezra</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">The second book of the prophet Ezra son of Seraiah, son of Azariah, son of Hilkiah, son of Shallum, son of Zadok, son of Ahitub,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001002"/>
      <verse num="2">son of Ahijah, son of Phinehas, son of Eli, son of Amariah, son of Azariah, son of Meraioth, son of Arna, son of Uzzi, son of Borith, son of Abishua, son of Phinehas, son of Eleazar,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001003"/>
      <verse num="3">son of Aaron, of the tribe of Levi, who was a captive in the country of the Medes in the reign of King Artaxerxes of the Persians.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001004"/>
      <heading>Ezra’s Prophetic Call</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="4">The word of the Lord came to me, saying,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001005"/>
      <verse num="5"><q class="begin-double" qid="86001005.1" from="86001005.1" to="86002009.1"/>Go, declare to my people their evil deeds and to their children the iniquities that they have committed against me, so that they may tell their children<q class="end-single" qid="86001005.2"/>s children</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001006"/>
      <verse num="6">that the sins of their parents have increased in them, for they have forgotten me and have offered sacrifices to strange gods.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001007"/>
      <verse num="7">Was it not I who brought them out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of bondage? But they have angered me and despised my counsels.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001008"/>
      <verse num="8">Pull out the hair of your head and hurl all evils upon them, for they have not obeyed my law—they are a rebellious people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001009"/>
      <verse num="9">How long shall I endure them, on whom I have bestowed such great benefits?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001010"/>
      <verse num="10">For their sake I have overthrown many kings: I struck down Pharaoh with his servants and all his army.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001011"/>
      <verse num="11">I have destroyed all nations before them and scattered in the east the people of two provinces, Tyre and Sidon; I have slain all their enemies.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001012"/>
      <heading>God’s Mercies to Israel</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="12"><q class="continue-double" qid="86001012.1" from="86001005.1" to="86002009.1"/>But speak to them and say, Thus says the Lord:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001013"/>
      <verse num="13">Surely it was I who brought you through the sea and made safe highways for you where there was no road; I gave you Moses as leader and Aaron as priest;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001014"/>
      <verse num="14">I provided light for you from a pillar of fire and did great wonders among you. Yet you have forgotten me, says the Lord.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001015"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="15"><q class="continue-double" qid="86001015.1" from="86001005.1" to="86002009.1"/>Thus says the Lord Almighty: The quails were a sign to you; I gave you camps for your protection, and in them you complained.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001016"/>
      <verse num="16">You have not rejoiced in my name at the destruction of your enemies, but to this day you still complain.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001017"/>
      <verse num="17">Where are the benefits that I bestowed on you? When you were hungry and thirsty in the wilderness, did you not cry out to me,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001018"/>
      <verse num="18">saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="86001018.1" from="86001018.1" to="86001018.2"/>Why have you led us into this wilderness to kill us? It would have been better for us to serve the Egyptians than to die in this wilderness.<q class="end-single" qid="86001018.2" from="86001018.1" to="86001018.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001019"/>
      <verse num="19">I pitied your groanings and gave you manna for food; you ate the bread of angels.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001020"/>
      <verse num="20">When you were thirsty, did I not split open the rock so that waters flowed in abundance? Because of the heat I covered you with the leaves of trees.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001021"/>
      <verse num="21">I divided fertile lands among you; I drove out the Canaanites, the Perizzites, and the Philistines before you. What more can I do for you? says the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001022"/>
      <verse num="22">Thus says the Lord Almighty: When you were in the wilderness, at the bitter stream, thirsty and blaspheming my name,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001023"/>
      <verse num="23">I did not send fire upon you for your blasphemies, but threw a tree into the water and made the stream sweet.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001024"/>
      <heading>Israel’s Disobedience and Rejection</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="24"><q class="continue-double" qid="86001024.1" from="86001005.1" to="86002009.1"/>What shall I do to you, O Jacob? You would not obey me, O Judah. I will turn to other nations and will give them my name, that they may keep my statutes.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001025"/>
      <verse num="25">Because you have forsaken me, I also will forsake you. When you beg mercy of me, I will show you no mercy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001026"/>
      <verse num="26">When you call upon me, I will not listen to you; for you have defiled your hands with blood, and your feet are swift to commit murder.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001027"/>
      <verse num="27">It is not as though you had forsaken me; you have forsaken yourselves, says the Lord.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001028"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="28"><q class="continue-double" qid="86001028.1" from="86001005.1" to="86002009.1"/>Thus says the Lord Almighty: Have I not entreated you as a father entreats his sons or a mother her daughters or a nurse her children,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001029"/>
      <verse num="29">that you should be my people and I should be your God and that you should be my children and I should be your father?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001030"/>
      <verse num="30">I gathered you as a hen gathers her hatchlings under her wings. But now, what shall I do to you? I will cast you out from my presence.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001031"/>
      <verse num="31">When you offer oblations to me, I will turn my face from you; for I have rejected your holy days and new moons and circumcisions of the flesh.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001032"/>
      <verse num="32">I sent to you my servants the prophets, but you have taken and slain them and torn their bodies in pieces; their blood I will require of you, says the Lord.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001033"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="33"><q class="continue-double" qid="86001033.1" from="86001005.1" to="86002009.1"/>Thus says the Lord Almighty: Your house is desolate; I will drive you out as the wind drives straw;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001034"/>
      <verse num="34">and your sons will have no children, because with you they have neglected my commandment and have done what is evil in my sight.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001035"/>
      <verse num="35">I will give your houses to a people that will come, that without having heard me will believe. Those to whom I have shown no signs will do what I have commanded.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001036"/>
      <verse num="36">They have seen no prophets, yet will recall their former state.<note nid="n86001036.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001037"/>
      <verse num="37">I call to witness the gratitude of the people that is to come, whose children rejoice with gladness; though they do not see me with bodily eyes, yet with the spirit they will believe the things I have said.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001038"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="38"><q class="continue-double" qid="86001038.1" from="86001005.1" to="86002009.1"/>And now, father, look with pride and see the people coming from the east;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001039"/>
      <verse num="39">to them I will give as leaders Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob and Hosea and Amos and Micah and Joel and Obadiah and Jonah</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86001040"/>
      <verse num="40">and Nahum and Habakkuk, Zephaniah, Haggai, Zechariah and Malachi, who is also called the messenger of the Lord.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002001"/>
    <chapter num="2">
      <heading>God’s Judgment on Israel</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1"><q class="continue-double" qid="86002001.1" from="86001005.1" to="86002009.1"/>Thus says the Lord: I brought this people out of bondage, and I gave them commandments through my servants the prophets; but they would not listen to them and made my counsels void.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002002"/>
      <verse num="2">The mother who bore them says to them, <q class="begin-single" qid="86002002.1" from="86002002.1" to="86002004.1"/>Go, my children, because I am a widow and forsaken.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002003"/>
      <verse num="3">I brought you up with gladness; but with mourning and sorrow I have lost you, because you have sinned before the Lord God and have done what is evil in my sight.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002004"/>
      <verse num="4">But now what can I do for you? For I am a widow and forsaken. Go, my children, and ask for mercy from the Lord.<q class="end-single" qid="86002004.1" from="86002002.1" to="86002004.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002005"/>
      <verse num="5">I call upon you, father, as a witness in addition to the mother of the children, because they would not keep my covenant,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002006"/>
      <verse num="6">that you may bring confusion upon them and bring their mother to ruin, so that they may have no offspring.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002007"/>
      <verse num="7">Let them be scattered among the nations, let their names be blotted out from the earth, because they have despised my covenant.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002008"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="8"><q class="continue-double" qid="86002008.1" from="86001005.1" to="86002009.1"/>Woe to you, Assyria, who conceal the unrighteous in your midst! O wicked nation, remember what I did to Sodom and Gomorrah,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002009"/>
      <verse num="9">whose land lies in lumps of pitch and heaps of ashes. Thus will I do to those who have not listened to me, says the Lord Almighty.<q class="end-double" qid="86002009.1" from="86001005.1" to="86002009.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002010"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">Thus says the Lord to Ezra: <q class="begin-double" qid="86002010.1" from="86002010.1" to="86002032.1"/>Tell my people that I will give them the kingdom of Jerusalem, which I was going to give to Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002011"/>
      <verse num="11">Moreover, I will take back to myself their glory and will give to these others the everlasting habitations, which I had prepared for Israel.<note nid="n86002011.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002012"/>
      <verse num="12">The tree of life shall give them fragrant perfume, and they shall neither toil nor become weary.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002013"/>
      <verse num="13">Ask<note nid="n86002013.1"/> and you will receive; pray that your days may be few, that they may be shortened. The kingdom is already prepared for you; watch!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002014"/>
      <verse num="14">Call, O call heaven and earth to witness, for I left out evil and created good, because I live, says the Lord.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002015"/>
      <heading>Exhortation to Good Works</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="15"><q class="continue-double" qid="86002015.1" from="86002010.1" to="86002032.1"/>Mother, embrace your sons; bring them up with gladness, as does the dove; make their footing firm, because I have chosen you, says the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002016"/>
      <verse num="16">And I will raise up the dead from their places and will bring them out from their tombs, because I recognize my name in them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002017"/>
      <verse num="17">Do not fear, mother of children, for I have chosen you, says the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002018"/>
      <verse num="18">I will send you help, my servants Isaiah and Jeremiah.<note nid="n86002018.1"/> According to their counsel I have consecrated and prepared for you twelve trees loaded with various fruits</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002019"/>
      <verse num="19">and the same number of springs flowing with milk and honey and seven mighty mountains on which roses and lilies grow; by these I will fill your children with joy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002020"/>
      <verse num="20">Guard the rights of the widow, secure justice for the fatherless, give to the needy, defend the orphan, clothe the naked,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002021"/>
      <verse num="21">care for the injured and the weak, do not ridicule a lame person, protect the maimed, and let the blind one have a vision of my splendor.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002022"/>
      <verse num="22">Protect the old and the young within your walls.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002023"/>
      <verse num="23">When you find any who are dead, commit them to the grave and mark<note nid="n86002023.1"/> it,<note nid="n86002023.2"/> and I will give you the first place in my resurrection.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002024"/>
      <verse num="24">Pause and be quiet, my people, because your rest will come.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002025"/>
      <verse num="25">Good nurse, nourish your children and strengthen their feet.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002026"/>
      <verse num="26">Not one of the servants whom I have given you will perish, for I will require them from among your number.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002027"/>
      <verse num="27">Do not be anxious, for when the day of tribulation and anguish comes, others shall weep and be sorrowful, but you shall rejoice and have abundance.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002028"/>
      <verse num="28">The nations shall envy you, but they shall not be able to do anything against you, says the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002029"/>
      <verse num="29">My hands will cover you, that your children may not see Gehenna.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002030"/>
      <verse num="30">Rejoice, O mother, with your children, because I will deliver you, says the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002031"/>
      <verse num="31">Remember your children that sleep, because I will bring them out of the hiding places of the earth and will show mercy to them; for I am merciful, says the Lord Almighty.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002032"/>
      <verse num="32">Embrace your offspring until I come and proclaim mercy to them; because my springs run over, and my grace will not fail.<q class="end-double" qid="86002032.1" from="86002010.1" to="86002032.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002033"/>
      <heading>Ezra on Mount Horeb</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="33">I, Ezra, received a command from the Lord on Mount Horeb to go to Israel. When I came to them they rejected me and refused the Lord<q class="end-single" qid="86002033.1"/>s commandment.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002034"/>
      <verse num="34">Therefore I say to you, O nations that hear and understand, <q class="begin-double" qid="86002034.1" from="86002034.1" to="86002041.2"/>Await your shepherd; he will give you everlasting rest, because he who will come at the end of the age is close at hand.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002035"/>
      <verse num="35">Be ready for the rewards of the kingdom, because endless light will shine upon you for evermore.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002036"/>
      <verse num="36">Flee from the shadow of this age, receive the joy of your glory; I publicly call on my Savior to witness.<note nid="n86002036.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002037"/>
      <verse num="37">Receive what the Lord has entrusted to you and be joyful, giving thanks to him who has called you to heavenly kingdoms.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002038"/>
      <verse num="38">Arise, stand upright, and see at the feast of the Lord the number of those who have been sealed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002039"/>
      <verse num="39">Those who have departed from the shadow of this age have received glorious garments from the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002040"/>
      <verse num="40">Take again your full number, O Zion, and enfold your people who are clothed in white, who have fulfilled the law of the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002041"/>
      <verse num="41">The number of your children, whom you desired, is full; ask the Lord<q class="end-single" qid="86002041.1"/>s power that your people, who have been called from the beginning, may be made holy.<q class="end-double" qid="86002041.2" from="86002034.1" to="86002041.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002042"/>
      <heading>Ezra Sees the Son of God</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="42">I, Ezra, saw on Mount Zion a great multitude, which I could not number, and they all were praising the Lord with songs.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002043"/>
      <verse num="43">In their midst was a young man of great stature, taller than any of the others, and on the head of each of them he placed a crown, but he was more exalted than they. And I was held spellbound.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002044"/>
      <verse num="44">Then I asked an angel, <q class="begin-double" qid="86002044.1" from="86002044.1" to="86002044.2"/>Who are these, my lord?<q class="end-double" qid="86002044.2" from="86002044.1" to="86002044.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002045"/>
      <verse num="45">He answered and said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86002045.1" from="86002045.1" to="86002045.2"/>These are they who have put off mortal clothing and have put on the immortal, and they have confessed the name of God; now they are being crowned and receive palms.<q class="end-double" qid="86002045.2" from="86002045.1" to="86002045.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002046"/>
      <verse num="46">Then I said to the angel, <q class="begin-double" qid="86002046.1" from="86002046.1" to="86002046.2"/>Who is that young man who places crowns on them and puts palms in their hands?<q class="end-double" qid="86002046.2" from="86002046.1" to="86002046.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002047"/>
      <verse num="47">He answered and said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86002047.1" from="86002047.1" to="86002047.2"/>He is the Son of God, whom they confessed in the world.<q class="end-double" qid="86002047.2" from="86002047.1" to="86002047.2"/> So I began to praise those who had stood valiantly for the name of the Lord.<note nid="n86002047.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86002048"/>
      <verse num="48">Then the angel said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86002048.1" from="86002048.1" to="86002048.2"/>Go, tell my people how great and many are the wonders of the Lord God that you have seen.<q class="end-double" qid="86002048.2" from="86002048.1" to="86002048.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003001"/>
    <chapter num="3">
      <heading>First Vision: Ezra’s Prayer of Complaint</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">In the thirtieth year after the destruction of our city, I, Salathiel, who am also called Ezra, was in Babylon. I was troubled as I lay on my bed, and my thoughts welled up in my heart,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003002"/>
      <verse num="2">because I saw the desolation of Zion and the wealth of those who lived in Babylon.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003003"/>
      <verse num="3">My spirit was greatly agitated, and I began to speak anxious words to the Most High and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003004"/>
      <verse num="4"><q class="begin-double" qid="86003004.1" from="86003004.1" to="86003036.1"/>O sovereign Lord, did you not speak at the beginning when you formed the earth—and that without help—and commanded the dust<note nid="n86003004.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003005"/>
      <verse num="5">and it gave<note nid="n86003005.1"/> you Adam, a lifeless body? Yet he was the workmanship of your hands, and you breathed into him the breath of life, and he was made alive in your presence.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003006"/>
      <verse num="6">And you led him into the garden that your right hand had planted before the earth appeared.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003007"/>
      <verse num="7">And you laid upon him one commandment of yours; but he transgressed it, and immediately you appointed death for him and for his descendants. From him there sprang nations and tribes, peoples and clans, without number.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003008"/>
      <verse num="8">And every nation walked after its own will and did ungodly things before you and scorned you, and you did not hinder them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003009"/>
      <verse num="9">But again, in its time you brought the flood upon the inhabitants of the world and destroyed them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003010"/>
      <verse num="10">And the same fate befell them: as death came upon Adam, so the flood upon them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003011"/>
      <verse num="11">But you left one of them, Noah with his household, and all the righteous who have descended from him.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003012"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="12"><q class="continue-double" qid="86003012.1" from="86003004.1" to="86003036.1"/>When those who dwelt on earth began to multiply, they produced children and peoples and many nations, and again they began to be more ungodly than were their ancestors.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003013"/>
      <verse num="13">And when they were committing iniquity before you, you chose for yourself one of them, whose name was Abraham;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003014"/>
      <verse num="14">and you loved him, and to him only you revealed the end of the times, secretly by night.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003015"/>
      <verse num="15">You made with him an everlasting covenant and promised him that you would never forsake his descendants; and you gave to him Isaac, and to Isaac you gave Jacob and Esau.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003016"/>
      <verse num="16">And you set apart Jacob for yourself, but Esau you rejected; and Jacob became a great multitude.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003017"/>
      <verse num="17">And when you led his descendants out of Egypt, you brought them to Mount Sinai.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003018"/>
      <verse num="18">You bent down the heavens and shook<note nid="n86003018.1"/> the earth and moved the world and made the depths to tremble and troubled the times.<note nid="n86003018.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003019"/>
      <verse num="19">And your glory passed through the four gates of fire and earthquake and wind and ice, to give the law to the descendants of Jacob and your commandment to the posterity of Israel.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003020"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="20"><q class="continue-double" qid="86003020.1" from="86003004.1" to="86003036.1"/>Yet you did not take away from them their evil heart, so that your law might bring forth fruit in them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003021"/>
      <verse num="21">For the first Adam, burdened with an evil heart, transgressed and was overcome, as were also all who were descended from him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003022"/>
      <verse num="22">Thus the disease became permanent; the law was in the people<q class="end-single" qid="86003022.1"/>s heart along with the evil root, but what was good departed, and the evil remained.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003023"/>
      <verse num="23">So the times passed and the years were completed, and you raised up for yourself a servant, named David.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003024"/>
      <verse num="24">And you commanded him to build a city for your name and in it to offer you oblations from what is yours.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003025"/>
      <verse num="25">This was done for many years; but the inhabitants of the city transgressed,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003026"/>
      <verse num="26">in everything doing as Adam and all his descendants had done, for they also bore the evil heart.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003027"/>
      <verse num="27">So you delivered the city into the hands of your enemies.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003028"/>
      <heading>Babylon Compared with Zion</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="28"><q class="continue-double" qid="86003028.1" from="86003004.1" to="86003036.1"/>Then I said in my heart, Are the deeds of those who inhabit Babylon any better? Is that why she has gained dominion over Zion?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003029"/>
      <verse num="29">For when I came here I saw ungodly deeds without number, and my soul has seen many sinners during these thirty years.<note nid="n86003029.1"/> And my heart failed me,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003030"/>
      <verse num="30">for I have seen how you endure those who sin and have spared those who act wickedly and have destroyed your people and have preserved your enemies</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003031"/>
      <verse num="31">and have not shown to anyone how your way may be comprehended.<note nid="n86003031.1"/> Are the deeds of Babylon better than those of Zion?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003032"/>
      <verse num="32">Or has another nation known you besides Israel? Or what tribes have so believed your covenants as these tribes of Jacob?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003033"/>
      <verse num="33">Yet their reward has not appeared, and their labor has borne no fruit. For I have traveled widely among the nations and have seen that they abound in wealth, though they are unmindful of your commandments.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003034"/>
      <verse num="34">Now therefore weigh in a balance our iniquities and those of the inhabitants of the world; and so it will be found which way the turn of the scale will incline.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003035"/>
      <verse num="35">When have the inhabitants of the earth not sinned in your sight? Or what nation has kept your commandments so well?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86003036"/>
      <verse num="36">You may indeed find individual people who have kept your commandments, but nations you will not find.<q class="end-double" qid="86003036.1" from="86003004.1" to="86003036.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004001"/>
    <chapter num="4">
      <heading>Limitations of the Human Mind</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Then the angel that had been sent to me, whose name was Uriel, answered</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004002"/>
      <verse num="2">and said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004002.1" from="86004002.1" to="86004002.2"/>Your understanding has utterly failed regarding this world, and do you wish<note nid="n86004002.1"/> to comprehend the way of the Most High?<q class="end-double" qid="86004002.2" from="86004002.1" to="86004002.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004003"/>
      <verse num="3">Then I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004003.1" from="86004003.1" to="86004003.2"/>Yes, my lord.<q class="end-double" qid="86004003.2" from="86004003.1" to="86004003.2"/> And he replied to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004003.3" from="86004003.3" to="86004004.1"/>I have been sent to show you three ways and to put before you three problems.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004004"/>
      <verse num="4">If you can solve one of them for me, I also will show you the way you desire to see and will teach you why the heart is evil.<q class="end-double" qid="86004004.1" from="86004003.3" to="86004004.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004005.1" from="86004005.1" to="86004005.2"/>Speak on, my lord.<q class="end-double" qid="86004005.2" from="86004005.1" to="86004005.2"/><end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004005.3" from="86004005.3" to="86004005.4"/>Go, weigh for me the weight of fire or measure for me a measure<note nid="n86004005.1"/> of wind or call back for me the day that is past.<q class="end-double" qid="86004005.4" from="86004005.3" to="86004005.4"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004006"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="6">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004006.1" from="86004006.1" to="86004006.2"/>Who of those that have been born can do this, that you ask me concerning these things?<q class="end-double" qid="86004006.2" from="86004006.1" to="86004006.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004007"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004007.1" from="86004007.1" to="86004009.1"/>If I had asked you, <q class="begin-single" qid="86004007.2" from="86004007.2" to="86004007.3"/>How many dwellings are in the heart of the sea, or how many springs are at the source of the deep, or how many ways<note nid="n86004007.1"/> are above the firmament, or which are the exits of hell, or which are the entrances<note nid="n86004007.2"/> of paradise?<q class="end-single" qid="86004007.3" from="86004007.2" to="86004007.3"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004008"/>
      <verse num="8">perhaps you would have said to me, <q class="begin-single" qid="86004008.1" from="86004008.1" to="86004008.2"/>I never went down into the deep, nor as yet did I descend<note nid="n86004008.1"/> into hell, neither did I ever ascend into heaven.<q class="end-single" qid="86004008.2" from="86004008.1" to="86004008.2"/><note nid="n86004008.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004009"/>
      <verse num="9">But now I have asked you only about fire and wind and the day, things through which you have passed and without which you cannot exist,<note nid="n86004009.1"/> and you have given me no answer about them!<q class="end-double" qid="86004009.1" from="86004007.1" to="86004009.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004010"/>
      <verse num="10">And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004010.1" from="86004010.1" to="86004011.1"/>You cannot understand the things with which you have grown up;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004011"/>
      <verse num="11">how then can your mind comprehend the way of the Most High? For the way of the Most High is without measure. And how can one who is already corrupt<note nid="n86004011.1"/> by the corrupt world understand the way of the incorruptible?<q class="end-double" qid="86004011.1" from="86004010.1" to="86004011.1"/><note nid="n86004011.2"/> When I heard this, I fell on my face<note nid="n86004011.3"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004012"/>
      <verse num="12">and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004012.1" from="86004012.1" to="86004012.2"/>It would be better for us not to be here than to come here and live in ungodliness and to suffer and not understand why.<q class="end-double" qid="86004012.2" from="86004012.1" to="86004012.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004013"/>
      <heading>Parable of Forest and Sea</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="13">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004013.1" from="86004013.1" to="86004018.1"/>It happened one day that the forests of the trees of the plain went out,<note nid="n86004013.1"/> and they made a plan</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004014"/>
      <verse num="14">and said, <q class="begin-single" qid="86004014.1" from="86004014.1" to="86004014.2"/>Come, let us go and make war against the sea, that it may recede before us and that we may make for ourselves more forests.<q class="end-single" qid="86004014.2" from="86004014.1" to="86004014.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004015"/>
      <verse num="15">And in like manner the waves of the sea also made a plan and said, <q class="begin-single" qid="86004015.1" from="86004015.1" to="86004015.2"/>Come, let us go up and make war on<note nid="n86004015.1"/> the forest of the plain so that there also we may gain more territory for ourselves.<q class="end-single" qid="86004015.2" from="86004015.1" to="86004015.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004016"/>
      <verse num="16">But the plan of the forest was in vain, for the fire came and consumed it;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004017"/>
      <verse num="17">likewise also the plan of the waves of the sea, for the sand stood firm and stopped them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004018"/>
      <verse num="18">If now you were a judge between them, which would you undertake to justify and which to condemn?<q class="end-double" qid="86004018.1" from="86004013.1" to="86004018.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004019"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004019.1" from="86004019.1" to="86004019.2"/>Each has made a foolish plan, for the land is assigned to the forest, and to the sea is assigned a place to carry its waves.<q class="end-double" qid="86004019.2" from="86004019.1" to="86004019.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004020"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="20">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004020.1" from="86004020.1" to="86004021.1"/>You have judged rightly, but why have you not judged so in your own case?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004021"/>
      <verse num="21">For as the land is assigned to the forest and the sea to its waves, so also those who dwell upon earth can understand only what is on the earth, and he who is above the heavens can understand what is above the height of the heavens.<q class="end-double" qid="86004021.1" from="86004020.1" to="86004021.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004022"/>
      <heading>New Age to Make All Things Clear</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="22">Then I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004022.1" from="86004022.1" to="86004025.1"/>I beg you, my lord, why<note nid="n86004022.1"/> have I been endowed with the power of understanding?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004023"/>
      <verse num="23">For I did not wish to inquire about the ways above, but about those things that we daily experience: why Israel has been given over to the Gentiles as a reproach; why the people whom you loved has been given over to godless tribes, and the law of our fathers has been made of no effect and the written covenants no longer exist;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004024"/>
      <verse num="24">and why we pass from the world like locusts, and our life is like a mist,<note nid="n86004024.1"/> and we are not worthy to obtain mercy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004025"/>
      <verse num="25">But what will he do for his name, by which we are called? It is about these things that I have asked.<q class="end-double" qid="86004025.1" from="86004022.1" to="86004025.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004026"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="26">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004026.1" from="86004026.1" to="86004032.1"/>If you are alive, you will see, and if you live long,<note nid="n86004026.1"/> you will often marvel, because the age is hastening swiftly to its end.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004027"/>
      <verse num="27">For it will not be able to bring the things that have been promised to the righteous in their appointed times, because this age is full of sadness and infirmities.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004028"/>
      <verse num="28">For the evil about which<note nid="n86004028.1"/> you ask me has been sown, but the harvest of it has not yet come.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004029"/>
      <verse num="29">If therefore that which has been sown is not reaped and if the place where the evil has been sown does not pass away, the field where the good has been sown will not come.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004030"/>
      <verse num="30">For a grain of evil seed was sown in Adam<q class="end-single" qid="86004030.1"/>s heart from the beginning, and how much ungodliness it has produced until now and will produce until the time of threshing comes!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004031"/>
      <verse num="31">Consider now for yourself how much fruit of ungodliness a grain of evil seed has produced.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004032"/>
      <verse num="32">When heads of grain without number are sown, how great a threshing floor they will fill!<q class="end-double" qid="86004032.1" from="86004026.1" to="86004032.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004033"/>
      <heading>When Will the New Age Come?</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="33">Then I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004033.1" from="86004033.1" to="86004033.2"/>How long<note nid="n86004033.1"/> and when will these things be? For our years are few and evil.<q class="end-double" qid="86004033.2" from="86004033.1" to="86004033.2"/><note nid="n86004033.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004034"/>
      <verse num="34">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004034.1" from="86004034.1" to="86004037.2"/>You do not hasten faster than the Most High, for your haste is for yourself,<note nid="n86004034.1"/> but the Highest hastens on behalf of many.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004035"/>
      <verse num="35">Did not the souls of the righteous in their storerooms ask about these matters, saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="86004035.1" from="86004035.1" to="86004035.2"/>How long are we to remain here?<note nid="n86004035.1"/> And when will come the harvest of our reward?<q class="end-single" qid="86004035.2" from="86004035.1" to="86004035.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004036"/>
      <verse num="36">And Jeremiel the archangel answered them and said, <q class="begin-single" qid="86004036.1" from="86004036.1" to="86004037.1"/>When the number of those like yourselves is completed;<note nid="n86004036.1"/> for he has weighed the age in the balance</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004037"/>
      <verse num="37">and measured the times by measure and numbered the times by number; and he will not move or arouse them until that measure is fulfilled.<q class="end-single" qid="86004037.1" from="86004036.1" to="86004037.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="86004037.2" from="86004034.1" to="86004037.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004038"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="38">Then I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004038.1" from="86004038.1" to="86004039.1"/>O sovereign Lord, but all of us also are full of ungodliness.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004039"/>
      <verse num="39">And it is perhaps on account of us that the time of threshing is delayed for the righteous—on account of the sins of those who dwell on earth.<q class="end-double" qid="86004039.1" from="86004038.1" to="86004039.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004040"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="40">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004040.1" from="86004040.1" to="86004040.2"/>Go and ask a woman who is with child if, when her nine months have been completed, her womb can keep the child within her any longer.<q class="end-double" qid="86004040.2" from="86004040.1" to="86004040.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004041"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="41">And I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004041.1" from="86004041.1" to="86004041.2"/>No, lord, it cannot.<q class="end-double" qid="86004041.2" from="86004041.1" to="86004041.2"/><end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004041.3" from="86004041.3" to="86004043.1"/>In Hades the storerooms of the souls are like the womb.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004042"/>
      <verse num="42">For just as a woman who is in travail makes haste to escape the pains of birth, so also do these places hasten to give back those things that were committed to them from the beginning.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004043"/>
      <verse num="43">Then the things that you desire to see will be disclosed to you.<q class="end-double" qid="86004043.1" from="86004041.3" to="86004043.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004044"/>
      <heading>How Much Time Remains?</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="44">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004044.1" from="86004044.1" to="86004046.1"/>If I have found favor in your sight and if it is possible and if I am worthy,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004045"/>
      <verse num="45">show me this also: whether more time is to come than has passed or whether for us the greater part has gone by.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004046"/>
      <verse num="46">For I know what has gone by, but I do not know what is to come.<q class="end-double" qid="86004046.1" from="86004044.1" to="86004046.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004047"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="47">And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004047.1" from="86004047.1" to="86004047.2"/>Stand at my right side, and I will show you the interpretation of a parable.<q class="end-double" qid="86004047.2" from="86004047.1" to="86004047.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004048"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="48">So I stood and looked, and behold, a flaming furnace passed by before me, and when the flame had gone by I looked, and behold, the smoke remained.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004049"/>
      <verse num="49">And after this a cloud full of water passed before me and poured down a heavy and violent rain, and when the rainstorm had passed, drops remained in the cloud.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004050"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="50">And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004050.1" from="86004050.1" to="86004050.2"/>Consider it for yourself; for as the rain is more than the drops, and the fire is greater than the smoke, so the quantity that passed was far greater; but drops and smoke remained.<q class="end-double" qid="86004050.2" from="86004050.1" to="86004050.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004051"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="51">Then I prayed and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004051.1" from="86004051.1" to="86004051.2"/>Do you think that I shall live until those days? And what will take place<note nid="n86004051.1"/> in those days?<q class="end-double" qid="86004051.2" from="86004051.1" to="86004051.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86004052"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="52">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86004052.1" from="86004052.1" to="86005013.1"/>Concerning the signs about which you ask me, I can tell you in part; but I was not sent to tell you concerning your life, for I do not know.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005001"/>
    <chapter num="5">
      <heading>Signs of the End</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1"><q class="continue-double" qid="86005001.1" from="86004052.1" to="86005013.1"/>Now concerning the signs: behold, the days are coming when those who dwell on earth shall be seized with great terror,<note nid="n86005001.1"/> and the lot<note nid="n86005001.2"/> of truth shall be hidden, and the land shall be barren of faith.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005002"/>
      <verse num="2">And unrighteousness shall be increased beyond what you yourself see and beyond what you heard of formerly.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005003"/>
      <verse num="3">And the land that you now see ruling shall be waste and untrodden,<note nid="n86005003.1"/> and men shall see it desolate.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005004"/>
      <verse num="4">But if the Most High grants that you live, you shall see it thrown into confusion after the third period;<note nid="n86005004.1"/><end-paragraph/><begin-block-indent/><begin-paragraph class="line-group"/><begin-line/>and the sun shall suddenly shine forth at night,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and the moon during the day.<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005005"/>
      <verse num="5"><begin-line/>Blood shall drip from wood,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and the stone shall utter its voice;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>the peoples shall be troubled,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and the atmosphere shall be changed.<note nid="n86005005.1"/><end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005006"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="6">And one shall reign whom those who dwell on earth do not expect, and the birds shall fly away;<note nid="n86005006.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005007"/>
      <verse num="7">and the sea of Sodom shall cast up fish; and one whom the many do not know shall make his voice heard by night, and all shall hear his voice.<note nid="n86005007.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005008"/>
      <verse num="8">There shall be chasms also in many places, and fire shall often break out, and the wild beasts shall roam beyond their haunts, and menstrual women shall bring forth monsters.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005009"/>
      <verse num="9">And salt waters shall be found in the sweet, and all friends shall fight against one another; then shall reason hide itself, and wisdom shall withdraw into its storeroom,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005010"/>
      <verse num="10">and it shall be sought by many but shall not be found, and unrighteousness and unrestraint shall increase on earth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005011"/>
      <verse num="11">And one country shall ask its neighbor, <q class="begin-single" qid="86005011.1" from="86005011.1" to="86005011.2"/>Has righteousness or anyone who does right passed through you?<q class="end-single" qid="86005011.2" from="86005011.1" to="86005011.2"/> And it will answer, <q class="begin-single" qid="86005011.3" from="86005011.3" to="86005011.4"/>No.<q class="end-single" qid="86005011.4" from="86005011.3" to="86005011.4"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005012"/>
      <verse num="12">And at that time men shall hope but not obtain; they shall labor but their ways shall not prosper.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005013"/>
      <verse num="13">These are the signs that I am permitted to tell you, and if you pray again and weep as you do now and fast for seven days, you shall hear yet greater things than these.<q class="end-double" qid="86005013.1" from="86004052.1" to="86005013.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005014"/>
      <heading>Conclusion of First Vision</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="14">Then I awoke, and my body shuddered violently, and my soul was so troubled that it fainted.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005015"/>
      <verse num="15">But the angel who had come and talked with me held me and strengthened me and set me on my feet.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005016"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="16">Now on the second night Phaltiel, a chief of the people, came to me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005016.1" from="86005016.1" to="86005018.1"/>Where have you been? And why is your face sad?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005017"/>
      <verse num="17">Or do you not know that Israel has been entrusted to you in the land of their exile?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005018"/>
      <verse num="18">Rise therefore and eat some bread, so that you may not forsake us, like a shepherd who leaves his flock in the power of cruel wolves.<q class="end-double" qid="86005018.1" from="86005016.1" to="86005018.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005019"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">Then I said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005019.1" from="86005019.1" to="86005019.2"/>Depart from me and do not come near me for seven days, and then you may come to me and I will tell you the matter.<q class="end-double" qid="86005019.2" from="86005019.1" to="86005019.2"/><note nid="n86005019.1"/><end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>He heard what I said and left me.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005020"/>
      <verse num="20">So I fasted seven days, mourning and weeping, as Uriel the angel had commanded me.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005021"/>
      <heading>Second Vision: Ezra’s Second Prayer of Complaint</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="21">And after seven days the thoughts of my heart were very grievous to me again.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005022"/>
      <verse num="22">Then my soul recovered the spirit of understanding, and I began once more to speak words in the presence of the Most High.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005023"/>
      <verse num="23">And I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005023.1" from="86005023.1" to="86005030.1"/>O sovereign Lord, from every forest of the earth and from all its trees you have chosen for yourself one vine,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005024"/>
      <verse num="24">and from all the lands of the world you have chosen for yourself one region,<note nid="n86005024.1"/> and from all the flowers of the world you have chosen for yourself one lily,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005025"/>
      <verse num="25">and from all the depths of the sea you have filled for yourself one river, and from all the cities that have been built you have consecrated Zion for yourself,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005026"/>
      <verse num="26">and from all the birds that have been created you have named for yourself one dove, and from all the flocks that have been made you have accepted<note nid="n86005026.1"/> for yourself one sheep,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005027"/>
      <verse num="27">and from all the multitude of peoples you have gotten for yourself one people; and to this people, whom you have loved, you have given the law that is approved by all.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005028"/>
      <verse num="28">And now, O Lord, why have you given over the one to the many and dishonored<note nid="n86005028.1"/> the one root beyond the others and scattered your only one among the many?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005029"/>
      <verse num="29">And those who opposed your law<note nid="n86005029.1"/> have trodden down those who believed your covenant.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005030"/>
      <verse num="30">If you do really hate your people, they should be punished at your own hands.<q class="end-double" qid="86005030.1" from="86005023.1" to="86005030.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005031"/>
      <heading>Response to Ezra’s Complaints</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="31">When I had spoken these words, the angel who had come to me on a previous night was sent to me,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005032"/>
      <verse num="32">and he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005032.1" from="86005032.1" to="86005032.2"/>Listen to me, and I will instruct you; pay attention to me, and I will tell you more.<q class="end-double" qid="86005032.2" from="86005032.1" to="86005032.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005033"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="33">And I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005033.1" from="86005033.1" to="86005033.2"/>Speak, my lord.<q class="end-double" qid="86005033.2" from="86005033.1" to="86005033.2"/> And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005033.3" from="86005033.3" to="86005033.4"/>Are you greatly disturbed over Israel?<note nid="n86005033.1"/> Or do you love him more than his Maker does?<q class="end-double" qid="86005033.4" from="86005033.3" to="86005033.4"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005034"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="34">And I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005034.1" from="86005034.1" to="86005034.2"/>No, my lord, but because of my grief I have spoken; for every hour I suffer agonies of heart, while I struggle to understand the way of the Most High and to search out part of his judgment.<q class="end-double" qid="86005034.2" from="86005034.1" to="86005034.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005035"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="35">And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005035.1" from="86005035.1" to="86005035.2"/>You cannot.<q class="end-double" qid="86005035.2" from="86005035.1" to="86005035.2"/> And I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005035.3" from="86005035.3" to="86005035.5"/>Why not, my lord? Why then was I born? Or why did not my mother<q class="end-single" qid="86005035.4"/>s womb become my grave, that I might not see the travail of Jacob and the exhaustion of the people of Israel?<q class="end-double" qid="86005035.5" from="86005035.3" to="86005035.5"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005036"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="36">He said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005036.1" from="86005036.1" to="86005037.1"/>Count up for me those who have not yet come and gather for me the scattered raindrops and make the withered flowers bloom again for me;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005037"/>
      <verse num="37">open for me the closed storerooms and bring forth for me the winds shut up in them or show me the appearance of one whom you have never seen<note nid="n86005037.1"/> or show me the picture of a voice; and then I will explain to you the travail that you ask to understand.<q class="end-double" qid="86005037.1" from="86005036.1" to="86005037.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005038"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="38">And I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005038.1" from="86005038.1" to="86005039.1"/>O sovereign Lord, who is able to know these things except he whose dwelling is not with men?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005039"/>
      <verse num="39">As for me, I am without wisdom and miserable,<note nid="n86005039.1"/> and how can I speak concerning the things that you have asked me?<q class="end-double" qid="86005039.1" from="86005038.1" to="86005039.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005040"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="40">He said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005040.1" from="86005040.1" to="86005040.2"/>Just as you cannot do one of the things that were mentioned, so you cannot discover my judgment or the goal of the love that I have promised my people.<q class="end-double" qid="86005040.2" from="86005040.1" to="86005040.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005041"/>
      <heading>Why Successive Generations Have Been Created</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="41">And I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005041.1" from="86005041.1" to="86005041.2"/>Yet behold, O Lord, you make promises to those who are alive at the end, but what will those do who were before us, or we, or those who come after us?<q class="end-double" qid="86005041.2" from="86005041.1" to="86005041.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005042"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="42">He said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005042.1" from="86005042.1" to="86005042.2"/>I shall liken my judgment to a circle;<note nid="n86005042.1"/> just as for those who are last there is no slowness, so for those who are first there is no haste.<q class="end-double" qid="86005042.2" from="86005042.1" to="86005042.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005043"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="43">Then I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005043.1" from="86005043.1" to="86005043.2"/>Could you not have created at one time those who have been and those who are and those who will be, that you might show your judgment the sooner?<q class="end-double" qid="86005043.2" from="86005043.1" to="86005043.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005044"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="44">He replied to me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005044.1" from="86005044.1" to="86005044.2"/>The creation cannot make more haste than the Creator, neither can the world hold at one time those who have been created in it.<q class="end-double" qid="86005044.2" from="86005044.1" to="86005044.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005045"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="45">And I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005045.1" from="86005045.1" to="86005045.2"/>How have you said to your servant that you<note nid="n86005045.1"/> will certainly give life at one time to your creation? If therefore all creatures will live at one time<note nid="n86005045.2"/> and the creation will sustain them, it might even now be able to support all of them present at one time.<q class="end-double" qid="86005045.2" from="86005045.1" to="86005045.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005046"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="46">He said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005046.1" from="86005046.1" to="86005046.5"/>Ask a woman<q class="end-single" qid="86005046.2"/>s womb and say to it, <q class="begin-single" qid="86005046.3" from="86005046.3" to="86005046.4"/>If you bear ten<note nid="n86005046.1"/> children, why one after another?<q class="end-single" qid="86005046.4" from="86005046.3" to="86005046.4"/> Request it therefore to produce ten at one time.<q class="end-double" qid="86005046.5" from="86005046.1" to="86005046.5"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005047"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="47">I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005047.1" from="86005047.1" to="86005047.2"/>Of course it cannot, but only each in its own time.<q class="end-double" qid="86005047.2" from="86005047.1" to="86005047.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005048"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="48">He said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005048.1" from="86005048.1" to="86005049.1"/>Even so have I given the womb of the earth to those who from time to time are sown in it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005049"/>
      <verse num="49">For as an infant does not bring forth and a woman who has become old does not bring forth any longer, so have I organized the world that I created.<q class="end-double" qid="86005049.1" from="86005048.1" to="86005049.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005050"/>
      <heading>When and How Will the End Come?</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="50">Then I inquired and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005050.1" from="86005050.1" to="86005050.2"/>Since you have now given me the opportunity, let me speak before you. Is our mother, of whom you have told me, still young? Or is she now approaching old age?<q class="end-double" qid="86005050.2" from="86005050.1" to="86005050.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005051"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="51">He replied to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005051.1" from="86005051.1" to="86005055.1"/>Ask a woman who bears children, and she will tell you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005052"/>
      <verse num="52">Say to her, <q class="begin-single" qid="86005052.1" from="86005052.1" to="86005052.2"/>Why are those whom you have borne recently not like those whom you bore before, but smaller in stature?<q class="end-single" qid="86005052.2" from="86005052.1" to="86005052.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005053"/>
      <verse num="53">And she herself will answer you, <q class="begin-single" qid="86005053.1" from="86005053.1" to="86005053.2"/>Those born in the strength of youth are different from those born during the time of old age, when the womb is failing.<q class="end-single" qid="86005053.2" from="86005053.1" to="86005053.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005054"/>
      <verse num="54">Therefore you also should consider that you and your contemporaries are smaller in stature than those who were before you</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005055"/>
      <verse num="55">and those who come after you will be smaller than you, as born of a creation that already is aging and passing the strength of youth.<q class="end-double" qid="86005055.1" from="86005051.1" to="86005055.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86005056"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="56">And I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86005056.1" from="86005056.1" to="86005056.2"/>O Lord, I beg you, if I have found favor in your sight, show your servant through whom you visit your creation.<q class="end-double" qid="86005056.2" from="86005056.1" to="86005056.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006001"/>
    <chapter num="6">
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86006001.1" from="86006001.1" to="86006006.1"/>The beginning is by the hand of man,<note nid="n86006001.1"/> but the end by my own hands. For before the circuit of the world existed and before<note nid="n86006001.2"/> the portals of the world were in place and before the assembled winds blew</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006002"/>
      <verse num="2">and before the rumblings of thunder sounded and before the flashes of lightning shone and before the foundations of paradise were laid</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006003"/>
      <verse num="3">and before the beautiful flowers were seen and before the powers of movement<note nid="n86006003.1"/> were established and before the innumerable hosts of angels were gathered together</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006004"/>
      <verse num="4">and before the heights of the air were lifted up and before the measures of the firmaments were named and before the footstool of Zion was established</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006005"/>
      <verse num="5">and before the present years were reckoned and before the imaginations of those who now sin were estranged and before those who stored up treasures of faith were sealed—</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006006"/>
      <verse num="6">then I planned these things, and they were made through me and not through another.<q class="end-double" qid="86006006.1" from="86006001.1" to="86006006.1"/><note nid="n86006006.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006007"/>
      <heading>Dividing the Times</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">And I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86006007.1" from="86006007.1" to="86006007.2"/>What will be the dividing of the times? Or when will be the end of the first age and the beginning of the age that follows?<q class="end-double" qid="86006007.2" from="86006007.1" to="86006007.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006008"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="8">He said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86006008.1" from="86006008.1" to="86006010.1"/>From Abraham to Isaac,<note nid="n86006008.1"/> because from him were born Jacob and Esau, for Jacob<q class="end-single" qid="86006008.2"/>s hand held Esau<q class="end-single" qid="86006008.3"/>s heel from the beginning.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006009"/>
      <verse num="9">For Esau is the end of this age, and Jacob is the beginning of the age that follows.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006010"/>
      <verse num="10">For the beginning of a man is his hand, and the end of a man is his heel;<note nid="n86006010.1"/> between the heel and the hand seek for nothing else, Ezra!<q class="end-double" qid="86006010.1" from="86006008.1" to="86006010.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006011"/>
      <heading>More Signs of the End</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="11">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86006011.1" from="86006011.1" to="86006012.1"/>O sovereign Lord, if I have found favor in your sight,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006012"/>
      <verse num="12">show your servant the end of your signs that you showed me in part on a previous night.<q class="end-double" qid="86006012.1" from="86006011.1" to="86006012.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006013"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="13">He answered and said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86006013.1" from="86006013.1" to="86006016.1"/>Rise to your feet and you will hear a full, resounding voice.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006014"/>
      <verse num="14">And if the place where you are standing is greatly shaken</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006015"/>
      <verse num="15">while the voice is speaking, do not be terrified; because the word concerns the end, and the foundations of the earth will understand</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006016"/>
      <verse num="16">that the speech concerns them. They will tremble and be shaken, for they know that their end must be changed.<q class="end-double" qid="86006016.1" from="86006013.1" to="86006016.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006017"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="17">When I heard this, I rose to my feet and listened, and behold, a voice was speaking, and its sound was like the sound of many waters.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006018"/>
      <verse num="18">And it said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86006018.1" from="86006018.1" to="86006028.1"/>Behold, the days are coming, and it shall be that when I draw near to visit the inhabitants of the earth,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006019"/>
      <verse num="19">and when I require from the doers of iniquity the penalty of their iniquity, and when the humiliation of Zion is complete,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006020"/>
      <verse num="20">and when the seal is placed upon the age that is about to pass away, then I will show these signs: the books shall be opened before the firmament, and all shall see it together.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006021"/>
      <verse num="21">Infants a year old shall speak with their voices, and women with child shall give birth to premature children at three or four months, and these shall live and dance.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006022"/>
      <verse num="22">Sown places shall suddenly appear unsown,<note nid="n86006022.1"/> and full storehouses shall suddenly be found to be empty;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006023"/>
      <verse num="23">and the trumpet shall sound aloud, and when all hear it, they shall suddenly be terrified.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006024"/>
      <verse num="24">At that time friends shall make war on friends like enemies, and the earth and those who inhabit it shall be terrified, and the springs of the fountains shall stand still, so that for three hours they shall not flow.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006025"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="25"><q class="continue-double" qid="86006025.1" from="86006018.1" to="86006028.1"/>And it shall be that whoever remains after all that I have foretold to you shall himself be saved and shall see my salvation and the end of my world.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006026"/>
      <verse num="26">And they shall see the men who were taken up, who from their birth have not tasted death; and the heart of the earth<q class="end-single" qid="86006026.1"/>s<note nid="n86006026.1"/> inhabitants shall be changed and converted to a different spirit.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006027"/>
      <verse num="27">For evil shall be blotted out, and deceit shall be quenched;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006028"/>
      <verse num="28">faithfulness shall flourish, and corruption shall be overcome; and the truth, which has been so long without fruit, shall be revealed.<q class="end-double" qid="86006028.1" from="86006018.1" to="86006028.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006029"/>
      <heading>Conclusion of Second Vision</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="29">While he spoke to me, behold, little by little the place where I was standing began to rock to and fro.<note nid="n86006029.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006030"/>
      <verse num="30">And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86006030.1" from="86006030.1" to="86006034.2"/>I have come to show you these things this night.<note nid="n86006030.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006031"/>
      <verse num="31">If therefore you will pray again and fast again for seven days, I will again declare to you greater things than these,<note nid="n86006031.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006032"/>
      <verse num="32">because your voice has surely been heard before the Most High; for the Mighty One has seen your uprightness and has also observed the purity that you have maintained from your youth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006033"/>
      <verse num="33">Therefore he sent me to show you all these things and to say to you:<note nid="n86006033.1"/> <q class="begin-single" qid="86006033.1" from="86006033.1" to="86006034.1"/>Believe and do not be afraid!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006034"/>
      <verse num="34">Do not be quick to think vain thoughts concerning the former times, lest you be hasty concerning the last times.<q class="end-single" qid="86006034.1" from="86006033.1" to="86006034.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="86006034.2" from="86006030.1" to="86006034.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006035"/>
      <heading>Third Vision: Creation of the World</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="35">Now after this I wept again and fasted seven days as before, in order to complete the three weeks as I had been told.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006036"/>
      <verse num="36">And on the eighth night my heart was troubled within me again, and I began to speak in the presence of the Most High.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006037"/>
      <verse num="37">For my spirit was greatly aroused, and my soul was in distress.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006038"/>
      <heading>God’s Work in Creation</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="38">I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86006038.1" from="86006038.1" to="86006059.1"/>O Lord, you spoke at the beginning of creation and said on the first day, <q class="begin-single" qid="86006038.2" from="86006038.2" to="86006038.3"/>Let heaven and earth be made,<q class="end-single" qid="86006038.3" from="86006038.2" to="86006038.3"/> and your word accomplished the work.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006039"/>
      <verse num="39">And then the Spirit was hovering, and darkness and silence embraced everything; the sound of man<q class="end-single" qid="86006039.1"/>s voice was not yet there.<note nid="n86006039.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006040"/>
      <verse num="40">Then you commanded that a ray of light be brought forth from your treasuries, so that your works might then appear.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006041"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="41"><q class="continue-double" qid="86006041.1" from="86006038.1" to="86006059.1"/>Again, on the second day, you created the spirit of the firmament and commanded him to divide and separate the waters, that one part might move upward and the other part remain beneath.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006042"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="42"><q class="continue-double" qid="86006042.1" from="86006038.1" to="86006059.1"/>On the third day you commanded the waters to be gathered together in the seventh part of the earth; six parts you dried up and kept so that some of them might be planted and cultivated and be of service before you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006043"/>
      <verse num="43">For your word went forth, and at once the work was done.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006044"/>
      <verse num="44">For immediately fruit came forth in endless abundance and of varied appeal to the taste and flowers of inimitable color and innumerable beautiful trees<note nid="n86006044.1"/> and odors of inexpressible fragrance. These were made on the third day.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006045"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="45"><q class="continue-double" qid="86006045.1" from="86006038.1" to="86006059.1"/>On the fourth day you commanded the brightness of the sun, the light of the moon, and the arrangement of the stars to come into being;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006046"/>
      <verse num="46">and you commanded them to serve man, who was about to be formed.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006047"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="47"><q class="continue-double" qid="86006047.1" from="86006038.1" to="86006059.1"/>On the fifth day you commanded the seventh part, where the water had been gathered together, to bring forth living creatures, birds, and fishes; and so it was done.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006048"/>
      <verse num="48">The mute and lifeless water produced living creatures, as it was commanded,<note nid="n86006048.1"/> that therefore the nations might declare your wondrous works.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006049"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="49"><q class="continue-double" qid="86006049.1" from="86006038.1" to="86006059.1"/>Then you kept in existence two living creatures that you created;<note nid="n86006049.1"/> the name of one you called Behemoth and the name of the other Leviathan.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006050"/>
      <verse num="50">And you separated one from the other, for the seventh part where the water had been gathered together could not hold them both.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006051"/>
      <verse num="51">And you gave Behemoth one of the parts that had been dried up on the third day, to live in it, where there are 1,000 mountains;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006052"/>
      <verse num="52">but to Leviathan you gave the seventh part of the watery part;<note nid="n86006052.1"/> and you have kept them to be eaten by whom you will and when you will.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006053"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="53"><q class="continue-double" qid="86006053.1" from="86006038.1" to="86006059.1"/>On the sixth day you commanded the earth to bring forth before you cattle, beasts, and creeping things;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006054"/>
      <verse num="54">and over these you placed Adam, as ruler over all the works that you had made; and from him we have all come, the people whom you have chosen.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006055"/>
      <heading>Why Do God’s People Suffer?</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="55"><q class="continue-double" qid="86006055.1" from="86006038.1" to="86006059.1"/>All this I have spoken before you, O Lord, because you have said that it was for us that you created this world.<note nid="n86006055.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006056"/>
      <verse num="56">As for the other nations that have descended from Adam, you have said that they are nothing and that they are like spittle, and you have compared their abundance to a drop from a bucket.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006057"/>
      <verse num="57">And now, O Lord, behold, these nations, which are reputed as nothing, domineer over us and trample<note nid="n86006057.1"/> us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006058"/>
      <verse num="58">But we your people, whom you have called your firstborn, only begotten, zealous for you,<note nid="n86006058.1"/> and dearest, have been given into their hands.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86006059"/>
      <verse num="59">If the world has indeed been created for us, why do we not possess our world as an inheritance? How long will this be so?<q class="end-double" qid="86006059.1" from="86006038.1" to="86006059.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007001"/>
    <chapter num="7">
      <heading>Response to Ezra’s Questions</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">When I had finished speaking these words, the angel who had been sent to me on the former nights was sent to me again,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007002"/>
      <verse num="2">and he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007002.1" from="86007002.1" to="86007002.2"/>Rise, Ezra, and listen to the words that I have come to speak to you.<q class="end-double" qid="86007002.2" from="86007002.1" to="86007002.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007003"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="3">I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007003.1" from="86007003.1" to="86007003.2"/>Speak, my lord.<q class="end-double" qid="86007003.2" from="86007003.1" to="86007003.2"/> And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007003.3" from="86007003.3" to="86007009.1"/>There is a sea set in a wide expanse so that it is broad<note nid="n86007003.1"/> and vast,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007004"/>
      <verse num="4">but it has an entrance set in a narrow place, so that it is like a river.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007005"/>
      <verse num="5">If anyone, then, wishes to reach the sea, to look at it, or to navigate it,<note nid="n86007005.1"/> how can he come to the broad part unless he passes through the narrow part?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007006"/>
      <verse num="6">Another example: there is a city built and set on a plain, and it is full of all good things;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007007"/>
      <verse num="7">but the entrance to it is narrow and set in a precipitous place, so that there is fire on the right hand and deep water on the left;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007008"/>
      <verse num="8">and there is only one path lying between them, that is, between the fire and the water, so that only one man can walk upon that path.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007009"/>
      <verse num="9">If now that city is given to a man for an inheritance, how will the heir receive his inheritance unless he passes through the danger set before him?<q class="end-double" qid="86007009.1" from="86007003.3" to="86007009.1"/><note nid="n86007009.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007010"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007010.1" from="86007010.1" to="86007010.2"/>He cannot, lord.<q class="end-double" qid="86007010.2" from="86007010.1" to="86007010.2"/> And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007010.3" from="86007010.3" to="86007016.1"/>So also is Israel<q class="end-single" qid="86007010.4"/>s portion.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007011"/>
      <verse num="11">For I made the world for their sake, and when Adam transgressed my statutes, what had been made was judged.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007012"/>
      <verse num="12">And so the entrances of this world were made narrow and sorrowful and toilsome; they are few and evil, full of dangers and involved in great hardships.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007013"/>
      <verse num="13">But the entrances of the greater<note nid="n86007013.1"/> world are broad and safe and really yield the fruit of immortality.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007014"/>
      <verse num="14">Therefore unless the living pass through the difficult and vain experiences, they can never receive those things that have been reserved for them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007015"/>
      <verse num="15">But now why are you disturbed, seeing that you are to perish? And why are you moved, seeing that you are mortal?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007016"/>
      <verse num="16">And why have you not considered in your mind what is to come, rather than what is now present?<q class="end-double" qid="86007016.1" from="86007010.3" to="86007016.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007017"/>
      <heading>Fate of the Ungodly</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="17">Then I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007017.1" from="86007017.1" to="86007018.1"/>O sovereign Lord, behold, you have ordained in your law that the righteous shall inherit these things, but that the ungodly shall perish.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007018"/>
      <verse num="18">The righteous therefore can endure difficult circumstances while hoping for easier ones; but those who have done wickedly have suffered the difficult circumstances and will not see the easier ones.<q class="end-double" qid="86007018.1" from="86007017.1" to="86007018.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007019"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007019.1" from="86007019.1" to="86007044.1"/>You are not a better judge than God or wiser than the Most High!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007020"/>
      <verse num="20">Let many perish who are now living, rather than that the law of God that is set before them be disregarded!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007021"/>
      <verse num="21">For God strictly commanded those who came into the world, when they came, what they should do to live, and what they should observe to avoid punishment.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007022"/>
      <verse num="22">Nevertheless they were not obedient and spoke against him:<end-paragraph/><begin-block-indent/><begin-paragraph class="line-group"/><begin-line/>They devised for themselves vain thoughts<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007023"/>
      <verse num="23"><begin-line class="indent"/>and proposed to themselves wicked frauds;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>they even declared that the Most High does not exist,<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and they ignored his ways!<end-line class="br"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007024"/>
      <verse num="24"><begin-line/>They scorned his law<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and denied his covenants;<end-line class="br"/><begin-line/>they have been unfaithful to his statutes<end-line class="br"/><begin-line class="indent"/>and have not performed his works.<end-line/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007025"/>
      <heading>Temporary Messianic Kingdom</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="25"><q class="continue-double" qid="86007025.1" from="86007019.1" to="86007044.1"/>Therefore, Ezra, empty things are for the empty, and full things are for the full.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007026"/>
      <verse num="26">For behold, the time will come, when the signs that I have foretold to you will come to pass, that the city that now is not seen shall appear,<note nid="n86007026.1"/> and the land that now is hidden shall be disclosed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007027"/>
      <verse num="27">And everyone who has been delivered from the evils that I have foretold shall see my wonders.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007028"/>
      <verse num="28">For my son the Messiah<note nid="n86007028.1"/> shall be revealed with those who are with him, and those who remain shall rejoice 400 years.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007029"/>
      <verse num="29">And after these years my son the Messiah shall die, and all who draw human breath.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007030"/>
      <verse num="30">And the world shall be turned back to primeval silence for seven days, as it was at the first beginnings; so that no one shall be left.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007031"/>
      <verse num="31">And after seven days the world, which is not yet awake, shall be roused, and that which is corruptible shall perish.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007032"/>
      <verse num="32">And the earth shall give up those who are asleep in it, and the dust those who dwell silently in it; and the storerooms shall give up the souls that have been committed to them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007033"/>
      <verse num="33">And the Most High shall be revealed upon the seat of judgment, and compassion shall pass away, mercy shall grow distant,<note nid="n86007033.1"/> and patience shall be withdrawn;<note nid="n86007033.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007034"/>
      <verse num="34">but only judgment shall remain, truth shall stand, and faithfulness shall grow strong.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007035"/>
      <verse num="35">And recompense shall follow, and the reward shall be manifested; righteous deeds shall awake, and unrighteous deeds shall not sleep.<note nid="n86007035.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007036"/>
      <verse num="36">Then the pit<note nid="n86007036.1"/> of torment shall appear, and opposite it shall be the place of rest; and the furnace of hell<note nid="n86007036.2"/> shall be disclosed, and opposite it the paradise of delight.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007037"/>
      <verse num="37">Then the Most High will say to the nations that have been raised from the dead, <q class="begin-single" qid="86007037.1" from="86007037.1" to="86007038.1"/>Look now and understand whom you have denied, whom you have not served, whose commandments you have despised!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007038"/>
      <verse num="38">Look on this side and on that; here are delight and rest, and there are fire and torments!<q class="end-single" qid="86007038.1" from="86007037.1" to="86007038.1"/> Thus he will<note nid="n86007038.1"/> speak to them on the day of judgment—</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007039"/>
      <verse num="39">a day that has no sun or moon or stars</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007040"/>
      <verse num="40">or cloud or thunder or lightning or wind or water or air or darkness or evening or morning</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007041"/>
      <verse num="41">or summer or spring or harvest or heat<note nid="n86007041.1"/> or frost or cold or hail or rain or dew</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007042"/>
      <verse num="42">or noon or night or dawn or shining or brightness or light, but only the splendor of the glory of the Most High, by which all shall see what has been determined for them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007043"/>
      <verse num="43">For it will last for about a week of years.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007044"/>
      <verse num="44">This is my judgment and its prescribed order; and to you alone have I shown these things.<q class="end-double" qid="86007044.1" from="86007019.1" to="86007044.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007045"/>
      <heading>Only a Few Will Be Saved</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="45">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007045.1" from="86007045.1" to="86007048.1"/>O Lord, I said then and I say now:<note nid="n86007045.1"/> Blessed are those who are alive and keep your commandments!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007046"/>
      <verse num="46">But what of those for whom I prayed?<note nid="n86007046.1"/> For who among the living is there that has not sinned, or who among those who have been born has not transgressed your covenant?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007047"/>
      <verse num="47">And now I see that the world to come will bring delight to few, but torments to many.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007048"/>
      <verse num="48">For an evil heart has grown up in us, which has alienated us from God<note nid="n86007048.1"/> and has brought us into corruption and the ways of death and has shown us the paths of perdition and removed us far from life—and that not just a few of us but almost all who have been created!<q class="end-double" qid="86007048.1" from="86007045.1" to="86007048.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007049"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="49">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007049.1" from="86007049.1" to="86007052.2"/>Listen to me, Ezra,<note nid="n86007049.1"/> and I will instruct you and will admonish you yet again.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007050"/>
      <verse num="50">For this reason the Most High has made not one world but two.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007051"/>
      <verse num="51">For whereas you have said that the righteous are not many but few, while the ungodly abound, hear the explanation for this.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007052"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="52"><q class="continue-double" qid="86007052.1" from="86007049.1" to="86007052.2"/>If you have just a few precious stones, will you add to them lead and clay?<q class="end-double" qid="86007052.2" from="86007049.1" to="86007052.2"/><note nid="n86007052.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007053"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="53">I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007053.1" from="86007053.1" to="86007053.2"/>Lord, how could that be?<q class="end-double" qid="86007053.2" from="86007053.1" to="86007053.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007054"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="54">And he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007054.1" from="86007054.1" to="86007057.1"/>Not only that, but ask the earth and she will tell you; defer to her, and she will declare it to you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007055"/>
      <verse num="55">Say to her, <q class="begin-single" qid="86007055.1" from="86007055.1" to="86007056.1"/>You produce gold and silver and brass and also iron and lead and clay;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007056"/>
      <verse num="56">but silver is more abundant than gold, and brass than silver, and iron than brass, and lead than iron, and clay than lead.<q class="end-single" qid="86007056.1" from="86007055.1" to="86007056.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007057"/>
      <verse num="57">Judge therefore which things are precious and desirable, those that are abundant or those that are rare?<q class="end-double" qid="86007057.1" from="86007054.1" to="86007057.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007058"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="58">I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007058.1" from="86007058.1" to="86007058.2"/>O sovereign Lord, what is plentiful is of less worth, for what is rarer is more precious.<q class="end-double" qid="86007058.2" from="86007058.1" to="86007058.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007059"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="59">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007059.1" from="86007059.1" to="86007061.1"/>Weigh within yourself<note nid="n86007059.1"/> what you have thought, for he who has what is hard to get rejoices more than he who has what is plentiful.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007060"/>
      <verse num="60">So also will be the judgment<note nid="n86007060.1"/> that I have promised; for I will rejoice over the few who shall be saved, because it is they who have made my glory to prevail now, and through them my name has now been honored.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007061"/>
      <verse num="61">And I will not grieve over the multitude of those who perish; for it is they who are now like a mist and are similar to a flame and smoke—they are set on fire and burn hotly and are extinguished.<q class="end-double" qid="86007061.1" from="86007059.1" to="86007061.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007062"/>
      <heading>Lamentation of Ezra, with Response</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="62">I replied and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007062.1" from="86007062.1" to="86007069.1"/>O earth, what have you brought forth, if the mind is made out of the dust like the other created things!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007063"/>
      <verse num="63">For it would have been better if the dust itself had not been born, so that the mind might not have been made from it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007064"/>
      <verse num="64">But now the mind grows with us, and therefore we are tormented, because we perish and know it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007065"/>
      <verse num="65">Let the human race lament, but let the beasts of the field be glad; let all who have been born lament, but let the four-footed beasts and the flocks rejoice!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007066"/>
      <verse num="66">For it is much better with them than with us; for they do not look for a judgment, nor do they know of any torment or life<note nid="n86007066.1"/> promised to them after death.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007067"/>
      <verse num="67">For what does it profit us that we shall be preserved alive but cruelly tormented?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007068"/>
      <verse num="68">For all who have been born are involved in iniquities and are full of sins and burdened with transgressions.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007069"/>
      <verse num="69">And if we were not to come into judgment after death, perhaps it would have been better for us.<q class="end-double" qid="86007069.1" from="86007062.1" to="86007069.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007070"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="70">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007070.1" from="86007070.1" to="86007074.1"/>When the Most High made the world and Adam and all who have come from him, he first prepared the judgment and the things that pertain to the judgment.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007071"/>
      <verse num="71">And now understand from your own words, for you have said that the mind grows with us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007072"/>
      <verse num="72">For this reason, therefore, those who dwell on earth shall be tormented, because though they had understanding they committed iniquity, and though they received the commandments they did not keep them, and though they obtained the law they dealt unfaithfully with what they received.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007073"/>
      <verse num="73">What, then, will they have to say in the judgment, or how will they answer in the last times?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007074"/>
      <verse num="74">For how long the time is that the Most High has been patient with those who inhabit the world, and not for their sake, but because of the times that he has foreordained!<q class="end-double" qid="86007074.1" from="86007070.1" to="86007074.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007075"/>
      <heading>State of the Dead before Judgment</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="75">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007075.1" from="86007075.1" to="86007075.2"/>If I have found favor in your sight, O Lord, show this also to your servant: whether after death, as soon as every one of us yields up his soul, we shall be kept in rest until those times come when you will renew the creation, or whether we shall be tormented at once?<q class="end-double" qid="86007075.2" from="86007075.1" to="86007075.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007076"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="76">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007076.1" from="86007076.1" to="86007099.1"/>I will show you that also, but do not be associated with those who have shown scorn or number yourself among those who are tormented.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007077"/>
      <verse num="77">For you have a treasure of works laid up with the Most High; but it will not be shown to you until the last times.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007078"/>
      <verse num="78">Now, concerning death, the teaching is: When the decisive decree has gone forth from the Most High that a person shall die, as the spirit leaves the body to return again to him who gave it, first of all it adores the glory of the Most High.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007079"/>
      <verse num="79">And if it is one of those who have shown scorn and have not kept the ways of the Most High and who have despised his law and who have hated those who fear God—</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007080"/>
      <verse num="80">such spirits shall not enter into habitations, but shall immediately wander about in torments, ever grieving and sad, in seven ways.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007081"/>
      <verse num="81">The first way: because they have scorned the law of the Most High.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007082"/>
      <verse num="82">The second way: because they cannot now repent and do good<note nid="n86007082.1"/> that they may live.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007083"/>
      <verse num="83">The third way: they shall see the reward laid up for those who have trusted the covenants of the Most High.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007084"/>
      <verse num="84">The fourth way: they shall consider the torment laid up for themselves in the last days.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007085"/>
      <verse num="85">The fifth way: they shall see how the habitations of the other souls<note nid="n86007085.1"/> are guarded by angels in profound quiet.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007086"/>
      <verse num="86">The sixth way: they shall see how some of them will pass over into torments.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007087"/>
      <verse num="87">The seventh way, which is worse<note nid="n86007087.1"/> than all the ways that have been mentioned: because they shall utterly waste away in confusion and be consumed with shame<note nid="n86007087.2"/> and shall wither with fear at seeing the glory of the Most High before whom they sinned while they were alive and before whom they are to be judged in the last times.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007088"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="88"><q class="continue-double" qid="86007088.1" from="86007076.1" to="86007099.1"/>Now this is the order of those who have kept the ways of the Most High, when they shall be separated from their mortal body.<note nid="n86007088.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007089"/>
      <verse num="89">During the time that they lived in it,<note nid="n86007089.1"/> they laboriously served the Most High and withstood danger every hour, that they might keep the law of the Lawgiver perfectly.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007090"/>
      <verse num="90">Therefore this is the teaching concerning them:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007091"/>
      <verse num="91">First of all, they shall see with great joy the glory of him who receives them, for they shall have rest in seven orders.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007092"/>
      <verse num="92">The first order: because they have struggled with great effort to overcome the evil thought that was formed with them, that it might not lead them astray from life into death.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007093"/>
      <verse num="93">The second order: because they see the perplexity in which the souls of the ungodly wander and the punishment that awaits them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007094"/>
      <verse num="94">The third order: they see the witness that he who formed them bears concerning them, that while they were alive they kept the law that was given them in trust.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007095"/>
      <verse num="95">The fourth order: they understand the rest that they now enjoy, being gathered into their chambers and guarded by angels in profound quiet and the glory that awaits them in the last days.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007096"/>
      <verse num="96">The fifth order: they rejoice that they have now escaped what is corruptible and shall inherit what is to come; and besides they see the straits and toil<note nid="n86007096.1"/> from which they have been delivered and the spacious liberty that they are to receive and enjoy in immortality.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007097"/>
      <verse num="97">The sixth order: when it is shown to them how their face is to shine like the sun and how they are to be made like the light of the stars, being incorruptible from then on.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007098"/>
      <verse num="98">The seventh order, which is greater than all that have been mentioned: because they shall rejoice with boldness and shall be confident without confusion and shall be glad without fear, for they hasten to see the face of him whom they served in life and from whom they are to receive their reward when glorified.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007099"/>
      <verse num="99">This is the order of the souls of the righteous, as henceforth is announced;<note nid="n86007099.1"/> and the aforesaid are the ways of torment that those who would not give heed shall suffer hereafter.<q class="end-double" qid="86007099.1" from="86007076.1" to="86007099.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007100"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="100">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007100.1" from="86007100.1" to="86007100.2"/>Will time therefore be given to the souls, after they have been separated from the bodies, to see what you have described to me?<q class="end-double" qid="86007100.2" from="86007100.1" to="86007100.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007101"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="101">He said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007101.1" from="86007101.1" to="86007101.2"/>They shall have freedom for seven days, so that during these seven days they may see the things that have been predicted, and afterward they shall be gathered in their habitations.<q class="end-double" qid="86007101.2" from="86007101.1" to="86007101.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007102"/>
      <heading>No Intercession for the Ungodly</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="102">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007102.1" from="86007102.1" to="86007103.1"/>If I have found favor in your sight, show further to me, your servant, whether on the day of judgment the righteous will be able to intercede for the ungodly or to entreat the Most High for them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007103"/>
      <verse num="103">fathers for sons or sons for parents, brothers for brothers, relatives for their kinsmen, or friends for friends.<q class="end-double" qid="86007103.1" from="86007102.1" to="86007103.1"/><note nid="n86007103.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007104"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="104">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007104.1" from="86007104.1" to="86007105.1"/>Since you have found favor in my sight, I will show you this also. The day of judgment is decisive<note nid="n86007104.1"/> and displays to all the seal of truth. Just as now a father does not send his son or a son his father or a master his servant or a friend his dearest friend to be ill<note nid="n86007104.2"/> or sleep or eat or be healed in his stead,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007105"/>
      <verse num="105">so no one shall ever pray for another on that day, neither shall anyone lay a burden on another;<note nid="n86007105.1"/> for then everyone shall bear his own righteousness and unrighteousness.<q class="end-double" qid="86007105.1" from="86007104.1" to="86007105.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007106"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="36" altnum="106">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007106.1" from="86007106.1" to="86007111.1"/>How then do we find that first Abraham prayed for the people of Sodom, and Moses for our fathers who sinned in the desert,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007107"/>
      <verse num="37" altnum="107">and Joshua after him for Israel in the days of Achan,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007108"/>
      <verse num="38" altnum="108">and Samuel in the days of Saul,<note nid="n86007108.1"/> and David for the plague, and Solomon for those in the sanctuary,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007109"/>
      <verse num="39" altnum="109">and Elijah for those who received the rain and for the one who was dead, that he might live,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007110"/>
      <verse num="40" altnum="110">and Hezekiah for the people in the days of Sennacherib, and many others prayed for many?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007111"/>
      <verse num="41" altnum="111">If therefore the righteous have prayed for the ungodly now, when corruption has increased and unrighteousness has multiplied, why will it not be so then as well?<q class="end-double" qid="86007111.1" from="86007106.1" to="86007111.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007112"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="42" altnum="112">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007112.1" from="86007112.1" to="86007115.1"/>This present world is not the end;<note nid="n86007112.1"/> the glory of God does not abide in it;<note nid="n86007112.2"/> therefore those who were strong prayed for the weak.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007113"/>
      <verse num="43" altnum="113">But the day of judgment will be the end of this age and the beginning<note nid="n86007113.1"/> of the immortal age to come, in which corruption has passed away,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007114"/>
      <verse num="44" altnum="114">sinful indulgence has come to an end, unbelief has been cut off, and righteousness has increased and truth has appeared.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007115"/>
      <verse num="45" altnum="115">Therefore no one will then be able to have mercy on him who has been condemned in the judgment or to harm<note nid="n86007115.1"/> him who is victorious.<q class="end-double" qid="86007115.1" from="86007112.1" to="86007115.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007116"/>
      <heading>Lamentation over the Fate of Most People</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="46" altnum="116">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007116.1" from="86007116.1" to="86007126.1"/>This is my first and last word, that it would have been better if the earth had not produced Adam or else, when it had produced him, had restrained him from sinning.<note nid="n86007116.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007117"/>
      <verse num="47" altnum="117">For what good is it to all that they live in sorrow now and expect punishment after death?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007118"/>
      <verse num="48" altnum="118">O Adam, what have you done? For though it was you who sinned, the fall was not yours alone, but ours also who are your descendants.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007119"/>
      <verse num="49" altnum="119">For what good is it to us, if an eternal age has been promised to us, but we have done deeds that bring death?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007120"/>
      <verse num="50" altnum="120">And what good is it that an everlasting hope has been promised us, but we have miserably failed?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007121"/>
      <verse num="51" altnum="121">Or that safe and healthful habitations have been reserved for us, but we have lived<note nid="n86007121.1"/> wickedly?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007122"/>
      <verse num="52" altnum="122">Or that the glory of the Most High will defend those who have led a pure life, but we have walked in the most wicked ways?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007123"/>
      <verse num="53" altnum="123">Or that a paradise shall be revealed, whose fruit remains unspoiled and in which are abundance and healing, but we shall not enter it,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007124"/>
      <verse num="54" altnum="124">because we have lived in unseemly places?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007125"/>
      <verse num="55" altnum="125">Or that the faces of those who practiced self-control shall shine more than the stars, but our faces shall be blacker than darkness?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007126"/>
      <verse num="56" altnum="126">For while we lived and committed iniquity we did not consider what we should suffer after death.<q class="end-double" qid="86007126.1" from="86007116.1" to="86007126.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007127"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="57" altnum="127">He answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007127.1" from="86007127.1" to="86007131.1"/>This is the meaning of the contest that the person who is born on earth shall wage,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007128"/>
      <verse num="58" altnum="128">that if he is defeated he shall suffer what you have said, but if he is victorious he shall receive what I have said.<note nid="n86007128.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007129"/>
      <verse num="59" altnum="129">For this is the way of which Moses, while he was alive, spoke to the people, saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="86007129.1" from="86007129.1" to="86007129.2"/>Choose for yourself life, that you may live!<q class="end-single" qid="86007129.2" from="86007129.1" to="86007129.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007130"/>
      <verse num="60" altnum="130">But they did not believe him or the prophets after him or even myself who have spoken to them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007131"/>
      <verse num="61" altnum="131">Therefore there shall not be<note nid="n86007131.1"/> grief at their destruction, so much as joy over the life of those who believed.<q class="end-double" qid="86007131.1" from="86007127.1" to="86007131.1"/><note nid="n86007131.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007132"/>
      <heading>Ezra Appeals to God’s Mercy</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="62" altnum="132">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86007132.1" from="86007132.1" to="86007140.1"/>I know, O Lord, that the Most High is now called merciful, because he has mercy on those who have not yet come into the world;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007133"/>
      <verse num="63" altnum="133">and gracious, because he is gracious to those who turn in repentance to his law;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007134"/>
      <verse num="64" altnum="134">and patient, because he shows patience toward those who have sinned, since they are his own works;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007135"/>
      <verse num="65" altnum="135">and bountiful, because he would rather give than take away;<note nid="n86007135.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007136"/>
      <verse num="66" altnum="136">and abundant in compassion, because he makes his compassions abound more and more to those now living and to those who are gone and to those yet to come,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007137"/>
      <verse num="67" altnum="137">for if he did not make them abound, the world with those who inhabit it would not have life;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007138"/>
      <verse num="68" altnum="138">and he is called giver, because if he did not give out of his goodness so that those who have committed iniquities might be relieved of them, not one ten-thousandth of mankind could have life;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007139"/>
      <verse num="69" altnum="139">and judge, because if he did not pardon those who were created by his word and blot out the multitude of their sins,<note nid="n86007139.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86007140"/>
      <verse num="70" altnum="140">there would<note nid="n86007140.1"/> be left only very few of the innumerable multitude.<q class="end-double" qid="86007140.1" from="86007132.1" to="86007140.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008001"/>
    <chapter num="8">
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86008001.1" from="86008001.1" to="86008003.1"/>The Most High made this world for the sake of many, but the world to come for the sake of few.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008002"/>
      <verse num="2">But I tell you a parable, Ezra. Just as, when you ask the earth, it will tell you that it provides very much clay from which earthenware is made, but only a little dust from which gold comes; so is the course of the present world.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008003"/>
      <verse num="3">Many have been created, but few shall be saved.<q class="end-double" qid="86008003.1" from="86008001.1" to="86008003.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008004"/>
      <heading>Ezra Again Appeals to God’s Mercy</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="4">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86008004.1" from="86008004.1" to="86008019.1"/>Then take delight in<note nid="n86008004.1"/> of understanding, O my soul, and drink wisdom, O my heart!<note nid="n86008004.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008005"/>
      <verse num="5">For not of your own will did you come into the world,<note nid="n86008005.1"/> and against your will you depart, for you have been given only a short time to live.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008006"/>
      <verse num="6">O Lord,<note nid="n86008006.1"/> grant to your servant that we may pray before you and give us seed for our heart and cultivation of our understanding so that fruit may be produced, by which every mortal who bears the likeness<note nid="n86008006.2"/> of a human being may be able to live.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008007"/>
      <verse num="7">For you alone exist, and we are a work of your hands, as you have declared.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008008"/>
      <verse num="8">And because you give life to the body that is now fashioned in the womb and furnish it with members, what you have created is preserved in fire and water, and for nine months the womb that you have formed<note nid="n86008008.1"/> endures your creation that has been created in it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008009"/>
      <verse num="9">But that which keeps and that which is kept shall both be kept by your keeping.<note nid="n86008009.1"/> And when the womb gives up again what has been created in it,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008010"/>
      <verse num="10">you have commanded that from the members themselves<note nid="n86008010.1"/> milk should be supplied that is the fruit of the breasts,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008011"/>
      <verse num="11">so that what has been fashioned may be nourished for a time; and afterward you will guide him in your mercy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008012"/>
      <verse num="12">You have brought him up in your righteousness and instructed him in your law and taught<note nid="n86008012.1"/> him in your wisdom.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008013"/>
      <verse num="13">You will take away his life, for he is your creation; and you will make him live, for he is your work.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008014"/>
      <verse num="14">If then you will suddenly and quickly<note nid="n86008014.1"/> destroy him who with so great labor was fashioned by your command, to what purpose was he made?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008015"/>
      <verse num="15">And now I will speak out: About all mankind you know best; but I will speak about your people, for whom I am grieved;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008016"/>
      <verse num="16">and about your inheritance, for whom I lament; and about Israel, for whom I am sad; and about the seed of Jacob, for whom I am troubled.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008017"/>
      <verse num="17">Therefore I will pray before you for myself and for them, for I see the failings of us who dwell in the land</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008018"/>
      <verse num="18">and I have heard of the judgment<note nid="n86008018.1"/> that is to come.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008019"/>
      <verse num="19">Therefore hear my voice and understand my words, and I will speak before you.<q class="end-double" qid="86008019.1" from="86008004.1" to="86008019.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008020"/>
      <heading>Ezra’s Prayer<begin-paragraph/>The beginning of the words of Ezra<q class="end-single" qid="86008019.2"/>s prayer, before he was taken up. He said:</heading>
      <verse num="20"><q class="begin-double" qid="86008020.1" from="86008020.1" to="86008036.1"/>O Lord who inhabits eternity,<note nid="n86008020.1"/> whose eyes are exalted<note nid="n86008020.2"/> and whose upper chambers are in the air,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008021"/>
      <verse num="21">whose throne is beyond measure and whose glory is beyond comprehension, before whom the hosts of angels stand trembling</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008022"/>
      <verse num="22">and at whose command they are changed to wind and fire,<note nid="n86008022.1"/> whose word is sure and whose utterances are certain, whose ordinance is strong and whose command is terrible,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008023"/>
      <verse num="23">whose look dries up the depths and whose indignation makes the mountains melt away and whose truth is established forever<note nid="n86008023.1"/>—</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008024"/>
      <verse num="24">hear, O Lord, the voice<note nid="n86008024.1"/> of your servant and give ear to the petition of your creature; attend to my words.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008025"/>
      <verse num="25">For as long as I live I will speak, and as long as I have understanding I will answer.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008026"/>
      <verse num="26">O look not upon the sins of your people, but at those who have served you in truth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008027"/>
      <verse num="27">Regard not<note nid="n86008027.1"/> those who act wickedly, but those who have kept your covenants amid afflictions.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008028"/>
      <verse num="28">Think not on those who have lived wickedly in your sight; but remember those who have willingly acknowledged that you are to be feared.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008029"/>
      <verse num="29">Let it not be your will to destroy those who have had the ways of cattle; but regard those who have gloriously taught<note nid="n86008029.1"/> your law.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008030"/>
      <verse num="30">Be not angry with those who are deemed worse than beasts; but love those who have always put their trust in your glory.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008031"/>
      <verse num="31">For we and our forebears have passed our lives in ways that bring death;<note nid="n86008031.1"/> but you, because of us sinners, are called merciful.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008032"/>
      <verse num="32">For if you have desired to have pity on us, who have no works of righteousness,<note nid="n86008032.1"/> then you will be called merciful.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008033"/>
      <verse num="33">For the righteous, who have many works laid up with you, shall receive their reward in consequence of their own deeds.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008034"/>
      <verse num="34">But what is man, that you are angry with him; or what is a corruptible race, that you are so bitter against it?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008035"/>
      <verse num="35">For in truth there is no one among those who have been born who has not acted wickedly, and among those who have existed<note nid="n86008035.1"/> there is no one who has not transgressed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008036"/>
      <verse num="36">For in this, O Lord, your goodness<note nid="n86008036.1"/> will be declared, when you are merciful to those who have no store of good works.<q class="end-double" qid="86008036.1" from="86008020.1" to="86008036.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008037"/>
      <heading>Response to Ezra’s Prayer</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="37">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86008037.1" from="86008037.1" to="86008041.2"/>Some things you have spoken rightly, and it will come to pass according to your words.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008038"/>
      <verse num="38">For indeed I will not concern myself about the fashioning of those who have sinned or about their death, their judgment, or their destruction;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008039"/>
      <verse num="39">but I will rejoice over the creation of the righteous, over their pilgrimage also and their life<note nid="n86008039.1"/> and their receiving their reward.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008040"/>
      <verse num="40">As I have spoken, therefore, so it shall be.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008041"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="41"><q class="continue-double" qid="86008041.1" from="86008037.1" to="86008041.2"/>For just as the farmer sows many seeds upon the ground and plants a multitude of seedlings and yet not all that have been sown will come up<note nid="n86008041.1"/> in due season and not all that were planted will take root, so also those who have been sown in the world will not all live.<q class="end-double" qid="86008041.2" from="86008037.1" to="86008041.2"/><note nid="n86008041.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008042"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="42">I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86008042.1" from="86008042.1" to="86008045.1"/>If I have found favor before you, let me speak.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008043"/>
      <verse num="43">For if the farmer<q class="end-single" qid="86008043.1"/>s seed does not come up, because it has not received your rain in due season or if it has been ruined by too much rain, it perishes.<note nid="n86008043.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008044"/>
      <verse num="44">But man, who has been formed by your hands and is called your own image because he is made like you and for whose sake you have formed all things—have you also made him like the farmer<q class="end-single" qid="86008044.1"/>s seed?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008045"/>
      <verse num="45">No, O Lord<note nid="n86008045.1"/> who is over us! But spare your people and have mercy on your inheritance, for you have mercy on your own creation.<q class="end-double" qid="86008045.1" from="86008042.1" to="86008045.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008046"/>
      <heading>Ezra’s Final Appeal for Mercy</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="46">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86008046.1" from="86008046.1" to="86008062.1"/>Things that are present are for those who live now, and things that are future are for those who will live hereafter.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008047"/>
      <verse num="47">For you come far short of being able to love my creation more than I love it. But you have often compared yourself<note nid="n86008047.1"/> to the unrighteous. Never do so!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008048"/>
      <verse num="48">But even in this respect you will be praiseworthy before the Most High,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008049"/>
      <verse num="49">because you have humbled yourself, as is becoming for you, and have not deemed yourself to be among the righteous in order to receive<note nid="n86008049.1"/> the greatest glory.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008050"/>
      <verse num="50">For many miseries will affect those who inhabit the world in the last times, because they have walked in great pride.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008051"/>
      <verse num="51">But think of your own case and inquire concerning the glory of those who are like yourself,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008052"/>
      <verse num="52">because it is for you that paradise is opened, the tree of life is planted, the age to come is prepared, delight<note nid="n86008052.1"/> is provided, a city is built, rest is appointed,<note nid="n86008052.2"/> goodness is established, and wisdom perfected beforehand.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008053"/>
      <verse num="53">The root of evil is sealed up from you, illness is banished from you, and death is hidden; hell has fled and corruption has been forgotten;<note nid="n86008053.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008054"/>
      <verse num="54">sorrows have passed away, and in the end the treasure of immortality is made manifest.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008055"/>
      <verse num="55">Therefore do not ask any more questions about the multitude of those who perish.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008056"/>
      <verse num="56">For they also received freedom, but they despised the Most High and were contemptuous of his law and forsook his ways.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008057"/>
      <verse num="57">Moreover they have even trampled upon his righteous ones</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008058"/>
      <verse num="58">and said in their hearts that there is no God—though knowing full well that they must die.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008059"/>
      <verse num="59">For just as the things that have been predicted await<note nid="n86008059.1"/> you, so the thirst and torment that are prepared await them. For the Most High did not intend that human beings should be destroyed;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008060"/>
      <verse num="60">but they themselves who were created have defiled the name of him who made them and have been ungrateful to him who prepared life for them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008061"/>
      <verse num="61">Therefore my judgment is now drawing near;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008062"/>
      <verse num="62">I have not shown this to all, but only to you and a few like you.<q class="end-double" qid="86008062.1" from="86008046.1" to="86008062.1"/><end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>Then I answered and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86008063"/>
      <verse num="63"><q class="begin-double" qid="86008063.1" from="86008063.1" to="86008063.2"/>Behold, O Lord, you have now shown me a multitude of the signs that you will do in the last times, but you have not shown me when you will do them.<q class="end-double" qid="86008063.2" from="86008063.1" to="86008063.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009001"/>
    <chapter num="9">
      <heading>More Signs of the End</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86009001.1" from="86009001.1" to="86009013.1"/>Measure carefully in your mind, and when you see that a certain part of the predicted signs are past,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009002"/>
      <verse num="2">then you will know that it is the very time when the Most High is about to visit the world that he has made.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009003"/>
      <verse num="3">So when there shall appear in the world earthquakes, tumult of peoples, intrigues of nations, wavering of leaders, confusion of princes,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009004"/>
      <verse num="4">then you will know that it was of these that the Most High spoke from the days that were of old.<note nid="n86009004.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009005"/>
      <verse num="5">For just as with everything that has occurred in the world, the beginning is evident<note nid="n86009005.1"/> and the end manifest;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009006"/>
      <verse num="6">so also are the times of the Most High: the beginnings are manifest in wonders and mighty works, and the end in deeds and in signs.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009007"/>
      <verse num="7">And it shall be that everyone who will be saved and will be able to escape on account of his works or on account of the faith by which he has believed</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009008"/>
      <verse num="8">will survive the dangers that have been predicted and will see my salvation in my land and within my borders, which I have sanctified for myself from the beginning.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009009"/>
      <verse num="9">Then those who have now abandoned<note nid="n86009009.1"/> my ways shall be amazed, and those who have rejected them with contempt shall dwell in torments.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009010"/>
      <verse num="10">For as many as did not acknowledge me in their lifetime, although they received my benefits,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009011"/>
      <verse num="11">and as many as scorned my law while they still had freedom and did not understand but despised it<note nid="n86009011.1"/> while an opportunity of repentance was still open to them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009012"/>
      <verse num="12">these must in torment acknowledge it after death.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009013"/>
      <verse num="13">Therefore, do not continue to be curious as to how the ungodly will be punished; but inquire how the righteous will live,<note nid="n86009013.1"/> those to whom the age belongs and for whose sake the age was made.<q class="end-double" qid="86009013.1" from="86009001.1" to="86009013.1"/><note nid="n86009013.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009014"/>
      <heading>Argument Recapitulated</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="14">I answered and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009015"/>
      <verse num="15"><q class="begin-double" qid="86009015.1" from="86009015.1" to="86009016.1"/>I said before and I say now and will say it again: there are more who perish than those who will live,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009016"/>
      <verse num="16">as a wave is greater than a drop of water.<q class="end-double" qid="86009016.1" from="86009015.1" to="86009016.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009017"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="17">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86009017.1" from="86009017.1" to="86009025.1"/>As is the field, so is the seed; and as are the flowers, so are the colors; and as is the work, so is the judgment; and as is the farmer, so is the threshing floor.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009018"/>
      <verse num="18">For there was a time in this age when I was preparing for those who now exist, before the world was made for them to dwell in, and no one opposed me then, for no one existed;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009019"/>
      <verse num="19">but now those who have been created in this world that is supplied both with an unfailing table and an inexhaustible pasture<note nid="n86009019.1"/> have become corrupt in their ways.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009020"/>
      <verse num="20">So I considered my world, and behold, it was lost, and my earth, and behold, it was in peril because of the devices of those who<note nid="n86009020.1"/> had come into it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009021"/>
      <verse num="21">And I saw and spared some<note nid="n86009021.1"/> with great difficulty and saved for myself one grape out of a cluster and one plant out of a great forest.<note nid="n86009021.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009022"/>
      <verse num="22">So let the multitude perish that has been born in vain, but let my grape and my plant be saved, because with much labor I have perfected them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009023"/>
      <verse num="23">But if you will let seven days more pass—do not fast during them, however;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009024"/>
      <verse num="24">but go into a field of flowers where no house has been built and eat only of the flowers of the field and taste no meat and drink no wine, but eat only flowers,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009025"/>
      <verse num="25">and pray to the Most High continually—then I will come and talk with you.<q class="end-double" qid="86009025.1" from="86009017.1" to="86009025.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009026"/>
      <heading>Fourth Vision: Abiding Glory of the Mosaic Law</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="26">So I went, as he directed me, into the field that is called Ardat;<note nid="n86009026.1"/> and there I sat among the flowers and ate of the plants of the field, and the nourishment they afforded satisfied me.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009027"/>
      <verse num="27">And after seven days, as I lay on the grass, my heart was troubled again as it was before.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009028"/>
      <verse num="28">And my mouth was opened, and I began to speak before the Most High and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009029"/>
      <verse num="29"><q class="begin-double" qid="86009029.1" from="86009029.1" to="86009037.1"/>O Lord, you showed yourself<note nid="n86009029.1"/> to our fathers in the wilderness when they came out from Egypt and when they came into the untrodden and unfruitful wilderness;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009030"/>
      <verse num="30">and you said, <q class="begin-single" qid="86009030.1" from="86009030.1" to="86009031.1"/>Hear me, O Israel, and give heed to my words, O descendants of Jacob.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009031"/>
      <verse num="31">For behold, I sow my law in you, and it shall bring forth fruit in you and you shall be glorified through it forever.<q class="end-single" qid="86009031.1" from="86009030.1" to="86009031.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009032"/>
      <verse num="32">But though our fathers received the law, they did not keep it and did not observe the statutes; yet the fruit of the law did not perish—for it could not perish, because it was yours.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009033"/>
      <verse num="33">Yet those who received it perished, because they did not keep what had been sown in them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009034"/>
      <verse num="34">And behold, it is the rule that, when the ground has received seed or the sea a ship or any dish food or drink, and when it happens that what was sown or what was launched or what was put in is destroyed,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009035"/>
      <verse num="35">they are destroyed, but the things that held them remain; yet with us it has not been so.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009036"/>
      <verse num="36">For we who have received the law and sinned will perish, as well as our heart that received it;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009037"/>
      <verse num="37">the law, however, does not perish but remains in its glory.<q class="end-double" qid="86009037.1" from="86009029.1" to="86009037.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009038"/>
      <heading>A Weeping Woman</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="38">When I said these things in my heart, I lifted up<note nid="n86009038.1"/> my eyes and saw a woman on my right, and<note nid="n86009038.2"/> she was mourning and weeping with a loud voice and was deeply grieved at heart, and her clothes were rent, and there were ashes on her head.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009039"/>
      <verse num="39">Then I dismissed the thoughts with which I had been engaged and turned to her</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009040"/>
      <verse num="40">and said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="86009040.1" from="86009040.1" to="86009040.2"/>Why are you weeping, and why are you grieved at heart?<q class="end-double" qid="86009040.2" from="86009040.1" to="86009040.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009041"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="41">And she said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86009041.1" from="86009041.1" to="86009041.2"/>Let me alone, my lord, that I may weep for myself and continue to mourn, for I am greatly embittered in spirit and deeply afflicted.<q class="end-double" qid="86009041.2" from="86009041.1" to="86009041.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009042"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="42">And I said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="86009042.1" from="86009042.1" to="86009042.2"/>What has happened to you? Tell me.<q class="end-double" qid="86009042.2" from="86009042.1" to="86009042.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009043"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="43">And she said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86009043.1" from="86009043.1" to="86010004.1"/>Your servant was barren and had no child, though I lived with my husband thirty years.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009044"/>
      <verse num="44">And every hour and every day during those thirty years I implored the Most High, night and day.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009045"/>
      <verse num="45">And after thirty years God heard your handmaid and looked upon my affliction<note nid="n86009045.1"/> and considered my distress and gave me a son. And I rejoiced greatly over him, I and my husband and all my neighbors;<note nid="n86009045.2"/> and we gave great glory to the Mighty One.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009046"/>
      <verse num="46">And I brought him up with much care.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86009047"/>
      <verse num="47">So when he grew up and I came to take a wife for him, I set a day for the marriage feast.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010001"/>
    <chapter num="10">
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1"><q class="continue-double" qid="86010001.1" from="86009043.1" to="86010004.1"/>But it happened that when my son entered his wedding chamber, he fell down and died.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010002"/>
      <verse num="2">Then we<note nid="n86010002.1"/> put out the lamps, and all my neighbors<note nid="n86010002.2"/> attempted to console me; and I remained quiet until evening of the second day.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010003"/>
      <verse num="3">But when they all had stopped consoling me, that I might be quiet, I got up in the night and fled and came to this field, as you see.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010004"/>
      <verse num="4">And now I intend not to return to the city, but to stay here, and I will neither eat nor drink, but without ceasing mourn and fast until I die.<q class="end-double" qid="86010004.1" from="86009043.1" to="86010004.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">Then I broke off the reflections with which I was still engaged and answered her in anger and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010006"/>
      <verse num="6"><q class="begin-double" qid="86010006.1" from="86010006.1" to="86010017.1"/>You most foolish of women, do you not see our mourning, and what has happened to us?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010007"/>
      <verse num="7">For Zion, the mother of us all, is in deep grief and great affliction.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010008"/>
      <verse num="8">It is most appropriate to mourn now, because we are all mourning, and to be sorrowful, because we are all sorrowing; you, however, are sorrowing for one son.<note nid="n86010008.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010009"/>
      <verse num="9">Now ask the earth, and she will tell you that it is she who ought to mourn over so many who have come into being upon her.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010010"/>
      <verse num="10">And from the beginning all have been born of her, and others will come; and behold, almost all go to perdition, and a multitude of them are destined for destruction.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010011"/>
      <verse num="11">Who then ought to mourn the more, she<note nid="n86010011.1"/> who lost so great a multitude or you who are grieving for one?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010012"/>
      <verse num="12">But if you say to me, <q class="begin-single" qid="86010012.1" from="86010012.1" to="86010012.2"/>My lamentation is not like the earth<q class="end-single" qid="86010012.2" from="86010012.1" to="86010012.2"/>s, for I have lost the fruit of my womb, which I brought forth in pain and bore in sorrow;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010013"/>
      <verse num="13">but it is with the earth according to the way of the earth—the multitude that is now in it goes as it came<q class="end-single" qid="86010013.1"/>;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010014"/>
      <verse num="14">then I say to you, <q class="begin-single" qid="86010014.1" from="86010014.1" to="86010014.2"/>As you brought forth in sorrow, so the earth also has from the beginning given her fruit, that is, man, to him who made her.<q class="end-single" qid="86010014.2" from="86010014.1" to="86010014.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010015"/>
      <verse num="15">Now, therefore, keep your sorrow to yourself and bear bravely the troubles that have come upon you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010016"/>
      <verse num="16">For if you acknowledge the decree of God to be just, you will receive your son back in due time and will be praised among women.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010017"/>
      <verse num="17">Therefore go into the city to your husband.<q class="end-double" qid="86010017.1" from="86010006.1" to="86010017.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010018"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">She said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86010018.1" from="86010018.1" to="86010018.2"/>I will not do so; I will not go into the city, but I will die here.<q class="end-double" qid="86010018.2" from="86010018.1" to="86010018.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010019"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">So I spoke again to her and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010020"/>
      <verse num="20"><q class="begin-double" qid="86010020.1" from="86010020.1" to="86010024.1"/>Do not do that thing, but let yourself be persuaded because of the troubles of Zion and be consoled because of the sorrow of Jerusalem.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010021"/>
      <verse num="21">For you see that our sanctuary has been laid waste, our altar thrown down, our temple destroyed;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010022"/>
      <verse num="22">our harp has been laid low, our song has been silenced, and our rejoicing has been ended; the light of our lampstand has been put out, the ark of our covenant has been plundered, our holy things have been polluted, and the name by which we are called has been profaned; our free men<note nid="n86010022.1"/> have suffered abuse, our priests have been burned to death, our Levites have gone into captivity, our virgins have been defiled, and our wives have been ravished; our righteous men have been carried off, our little ones have been cast out, our young men have been enslaved and our strong men made powerless.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010023"/>
      <verse num="23">And, what is more than all, the seal of Zion—for she has now lost the seal of her glory and has been given over into the hands of those that hate us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010024"/>
      <verse num="24">Therefore shake off your great sadness and lay aside your many sorrows, so that the Mighty One may be merciful to you,<note nid="n86010024.1"/> and the Most High may give you rest, a relief from your troubles.<q class="end-double" qid="86010024.1" from="86010020.1" to="86010024.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010025"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="25">While I was talking to her, behold, her face suddenly shone exceedingly, and her face flashed like lightning, so that I was too frightened to approach her, and my heart was terrified. While<note nid="n86010025.1"/> I was wondering what this meant,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010026"/>
      <verse num="26">behold, she suddenly uttered a loud and fearful cry, so that the earth shook at the sound.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010027"/>
      <verse num="27">And I looked, and behold, the woman was no longer visible to me, but there was an established city,<note nid="n86010027.1"/> and a place of huge foundations showed itself. Then I was afraid and cried with a loud voice and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010028"/>
      <verse num="28"><q class="begin-double" qid="86010028.1" from="86010028.1" to="86010028.2"/>Where is the angel Uriel, who came to me at first? For it was he who brought me into this overpowering bewilderment; my end has become corruption, and my prayer a reproach.<q class="end-double" qid="86010028.2" from="86010028.1" to="86010028.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010029"/>
      <heading>Uriel’s Interpretation of Fourth Vision</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="29">As I was speaking these words, behold, the angel who had come to me at first came to me, and he looked upon me;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010030"/>
      <verse num="30">and behold, I lay there like a corpse and I was deprived of my understanding. Then he grasped my right hand and strengthened me and set me on my feet and said to me,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010031"/>
      <verse num="31"><q class="begin-double" qid="86010031.1" from="86010031.1" to="86010031.2"/>What is the matter with you? And why are you troubled? And why are your understanding and the thoughts of your mind troubled?<q class="end-double" qid="86010031.2" from="86010031.1" to="86010031.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010032"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="32">I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86010032.1" from="86010032.1" to="86010032.2"/>Because you have forsaken me! I did as you directed,<note nid="n86010032.1"/> and behold, I saw and still see what I am unable to explain.<q class="end-double" qid="86010032.2" from="86010032.1" to="86010032.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010033"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="33">He said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86010033.1" from="86010033.1" to="86010033.2"/>Stand up like a man, and I will instruct you.<q class="end-double" qid="86010033.2" from="86010033.1" to="86010033.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010034"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="34">I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86010034.1" from="86010034.1" to="86010037.1"/>Speak, my lord; only do not forsake me, lest I die before my time.<note nid="n86010034.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010035"/>
      <verse num="35">For I have seen what I did not know, and I have heard what I do not understand.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010036"/>
      <verse num="36">Or is my mind deceived, and my soul dreaming?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010037"/>
      <verse num="37">Now therefore I entreat you to give your servant an explanation of this.<q class="end-double" qid="86010037.1" from="86010034.1" to="86010037.1"/><note nid="n86010037.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010038"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="38">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86010038.1" from="86010038.1" to="86010059.1"/>Listen to me and I will inform you and tell you about the things that you fear, for the Most High has revealed many secrets to you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010039"/>
      <verse num="39">For he has seen your righteous conduct, that you have sorrowed continually for your people and mourned greatly over Zion.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010040"/>
      <verse num="40">This therefore is the explanation.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010041"/>
      <verse num="41">The woman who appeared to you a little while ago, whom you saw mourning and began to console—</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010042"/>
      <verse num="42">but you do not now see the form of a woman, but an established city<note nid="n86010042.1"/> has appeared to you—</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010043"/>
      <verse num="43">and as for her telling you about the misfortune of her son, this is the interpretation:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010044"/>
      <verse num="44">This woman whom you saw, whom you now see as an established city, is Zion.<note nid="n86010044.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010045"/>
      <verse num="45">And as for her telling you that she was barren for thirty years, it is because there were 3,000<note nid="n86010045.1"/> years in the world before any offering was offered in it.<note nid="n86010045.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010046"/>
      <verse num="46">And after 3,000<note nid="n86010046.1"/> years Solomon built the city and offered offerings; then it was that the barren woman bore a son.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010047"/>
      <verse num="47">And as for her telling you that she brought him up with much care, that was the period of residence in Jerusalem.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010048"/>
      <verse num="48">And as for her saying to you, <q class="begin-single" qid="86010048.1" from="86010048.1" to="86010048.2"/>When my son entered his wedding chamber he died,<q class="end-single" qid="86010048.2" from="86010048.1" to="86010048.2"/> and that misfortune had overtaken her,<note nid="n86010048.1"/> that was the destruction that befell Jerusalem.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010049"/>
      <verse num="49">And behold, you saw her likeness, how she mourned for her son, and you began to console her for what had happened.<note nid="n86010049.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010050"/>
      <verse num="50">For now the Most High, seeing that you are sincerely grieved and profoundly distressed for her, has shown you the brilliance of her glory and the loveliness of her beauty.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010051"/>
      <verse num="51">Therefore I told you to remain in the field where no house had been built,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010052"/>
      <verse num="52">for I knew that the Most High would reveal these things to you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010053"/>
      <verse num="53">Therefore I told you to go into the field where there was no foundation of any building,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010054"/>
      <verse num="54">for no work of human construction could endure in a place where the city of the Most High was to be revealed.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010055"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="55"><q class="continue-double" qid="86010055.1" from="86010038.1" to="86010059.1"/>Therefore do not be afraid and do not let your heart be terrified; but go in and see the splendor and vastness of the building, as far as it is possible for your eyes to see it,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010056"/>
      <verse num="56">and afterward you will hear as much as your ears can hear.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010057"/>
      <verse num="57">For you are more blessed than many, and you have been called before the Most High, as but few have been.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010058"/>
      <verse num="58">But tomorrow night you shall remain here,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86010059"/>
      <verse num="59">and the Most High will show you in those dream visions what the Most High will do to those who dwell on earth in the last days.<q class="end-double" qid="86010059.1" from="86010038.1" to="86010059.1"/><end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>So I slept that night and the following one, as he had commanded me.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011001"/>
    <chapter num="11">
      <heading>Fifth Vision: The Eagle</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">On the second night I had a dream, and behold, there came up from the sea an eagle that had twelve<note nid="n86011001.1"/> wings and three heads.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011002"/>
      <verse num="2">And I looked, and behold, he spread his wings over all the earth, and all the winds of heaven blew upon him, and the clouds were gathered about him.<note nid="n86011002.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011003"/>
      <verse num="3">And I looked, and out of his wings there grew opposing wings; and they became little, puny wings.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011004"/>
      <verse num="4">But his heads were at rest; the middle head was larger than the other heads, but it also was at rest with them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011005"/>
      <verse num="5">And I looked, and behold, the eagle flew with his wings, to reign over the earth and over those who dwell in it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011006"/>
      <verse num="6">And I saw how all things under heaven were subjected to him, and no one spoke against him, not even one of the creatures that was on the earth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011007"/>
      <verse num="7">And I looked, and behold, the eagle rose upon his talons and uttered a cry to his wings, saying,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011008"/>
      <verse num="8"><q class="begin-double" qid="86011008.1" from="86011008.1" to="86011009.1"/>Do not all watch at the same time; let each sleep in his own place and watch in his turn;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011009"/>
      <verse num="9">but let the heads be reserved for the last.<q class="end-double" qid="86011009.1" from="86011008.1" to="86011009.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011010"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">And I looked, and behold, the voice did not come from his heads, but from the midst of his body.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011011"/>
      <verse num="11">And I counted his opposing wings, and behold, there were eight of them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011012"/>
      <verse num="12">And I looked, and behold, on the right side one wing arose, and it reigned over all the earth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011013"/>
      <verse num="13">And while it was reigning it came to its end and disappeared, so that its place was not seen. Then the next wing arose and reigned, and it continued to reign a long time.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011014"/>
      <verse num="14">And while it was reigning its end came also, so that it disappeared like the first.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011015"/>
      <verse num="15">And behold, a voice sounded, saying to it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011016"/>
      <verse num="16"><q class="begin-double" qid="86011016.1" from="86011016.1" to="86011017.1"/>Hear me, you who have ruled the earth all this time; I announce this to you before you disappear.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011017"/>
      <verse num="17">After you no one shall rule as long as you or even half as long.<q class="end-double" qid="86011017.1" from="86011016.1" to="86011017.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011018"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">Then the third wing raised itself up and held the rule like the former ones, and it also disappeared.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011019"/>
      <verse num="19">And so it went with all the wings; they wielded power one after another and then were never seen again.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011020"/>
      <verse num="20">And I looked, and behold, in due course the wings that followed<note nid="n86011020.1"/> also rose up on the right<note nid="n86011020.2"/> side, in order to rule. There were some of them that ruled, yet disappeared suddenly;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011021"/>
      <verse num="21">and others of them rose up, but did not hold the rule.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011022"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="22">And after this I looked, and behold, the twelve wings and the two little wings disappeared;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011023"/>
      <verse num="23">and nothing remained on the eagle<q class="end-single" qid="86011023.1"/>s body except the three heads that were at rest and six little wings.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011024"/>
      <verse num="24">And I looked, and behold, two little wings separated from the six and remained under the head that was on the right side; but four remained in their place.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011025"/>
      <verse num="25">And I looked, and behold, these four little wings<note nid="n86011025.1"/> planned to set themselves up and hold the rule.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011026"/>
      <verse num="26">And I looked, and behold, one was set up, but suddenly disappeared;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011027"/>
      <verse num="27">a second also, and this disappeared more quickly than the first.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011028"/>
      <verse num="28">And I looked, and behold, the two that remained were planning between themselves to reign;<note nid="n86011028.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011029"/>
      <verse num="29">and while they were planning, behold, one of the heads that were at rest (the one that was in the middle) awoke; for it was greater than the other two heads.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011030"/>
      <verse num="30">And I saw how it allied the two heads with itself,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011031"/>
      <verse num="31">and behold, the head turned with those that were with it, and it devoured the two little wings<note nid="n86011031.1"/> that were planning to reign.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011032"/>
      <verse num="32">Moreover this head gained control of the whole earth and with much oppression dominated its inhabitants; and it had greater power over the world than all the wings that had gone before.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011033"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="33">And after this I looked, and behold, the middle head also suddenly disappeared, just as the wings had done.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011034"/>
      <verse num="34">But the two heads remained, which also ruled over the earth and its inhabitants.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011035"/>
      <verse num="35">And I looked, and behold, the head on the right side devoured the one on the left.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011036"/>
      <heading>A Lion Roused from the Forest</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="36">Then I heard a voice saying to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86011036.1" from="86011036.1" to="86011036.2"/>Look before you and consider what you see.<q class="end-double" qid="86011036.2" from="86011036.1" to="86011036.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011037"/>
      <verse num="37">And I looked, and behold, a creature like a lion was aroused out of the forest, roaring; and I heard how he uttered a man<q class="end-single" qid="86011037.1"/>s voice to the eagle and spoke, saying,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011038"/>
      <verse num="38"><q class="begin-double" qid="86011038.1" from="86011038.1" to="86011046.2"/>Listen and I will speak to you. The Most High says to you,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011039"/>
      <verse num="39"><q class="begin-single" qid="86011039.1" from="86011039.1" to="86011046.1"/>Are you not the one that remains of the four beasts that I had made to reign in my world, so that the end of my times might come through them?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011040"/>
      <verse num="40">You, the fourth that has come, have conquered all the beasts that have gone before; and you have held sway over the world with much terror and over all the earth with grievous oppression; and for so long you have dwelt<note nid="n86011040.1"/> on the earth with deceit.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011041"/>
      <verse num="41">And you have judged the earth, but not with truth;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011042"/>
      <verse num="42">for you have afflicted the meek and injured the peaceable; you have hated those who tell the truth and have loved liars; you have destroyed the fortifications<note nid="n86011042.1"/> of those who brought forth fruit and have laid low the walls of those who did you no harm.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011043"/>
      <verse num="43">And so your insolence has come up before the Most High, and your pride to the Mighty One.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011044"/>
      <verse num="44">And the Most High has looked upon his times, and behold, they are ended, and his ages are completed!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011045"/>
      <verse num="45">Therefore you will surely disappear, you eagle, and your terrifying wings and your evilest little wings and your malicious heads and your evilest talons and your whole worthless body,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86011046"/>
      <verse num="46">so that the whole earth, freed from your violence, may be refreshed and relieved and may hope for the judgment and mercy of him who made it.<q class="end-single" qid="86011046.1" from="86011039.1" to="86011046.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="86011046.2" from="86011038.1" to="86011046.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012001"/>
    <chapter num="12">
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">While the lion was saying these words to the eagle, I looked,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012002"/>
      <verse num="2">and behold, the remaining head disappeared. And the two wings that had gone over to it arose<note nid="n86012002.1"/> and set themselves up to reign, and their reign was brief and full of tumult.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012003"/>
      <verse num="3">And I looked, and behold, they also disappeared, and the whole body of the eagle was burned, and the earth was exceedingly terrified.<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>Then I awoke in great perplexity of mind and great fear, and I said to my spirit,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012004"/>
      <verse num="4"><q class="begin-double" qid="86012004.1" from="86012004.1" to="86012006.1"/>Behold, you have brought this upon me, because you search out the ways of the Most High.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012005"/>
      <verse num="5">Behold, I am still weary in mind and very weak in my spirit, and not even a little strength is left in me, because of the great fear with which I have been terrified this night.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012006"/>
      <verse num="6">Therefore I will now plead with the Most High that he may strengthen me to the end.<q class="end-double" qid="86012006.1" from="86012004.1" to="86012006.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012007"/>
      <heading>Interpretation of Fifth Vision</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="7">And I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86012007.1" from="86012007.1" to="86012009.1"/>O sovereign Lord, if I have found favor in your sight and if I have been privileged<note nid="n86012007.1"/> before you beyond many others and if my prayer has indeed come up before your face,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012008"/>
      <verse num="8">strengthen me and show me, your servant, the interpretation and meaning of this terrifying vision, that you may fully comfort my soul.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012009"/>
      <verse num="9">For you have judged me worthy to be shown the end of the times and the last events of the times.<q class="end-double" qid="86012009.1" from="86012007.1" to="86012009.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012010"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="10">He said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86012010.1" from="86012010.1" to="86012039.1"/>This is the interpretation of this vision that you have seen:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012011"/>
      <verse num="11">The eagle that you saw coming up from the sea is the fourth kingdom that appeared in a vision to your brother Daniel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012012"/>
      <verse num="12">But it was not explained to him as I now explain or have explained it to you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012013"/>
      <verse num="13">Behold, the days are coming when a kingdom shall arise on earth, and it shall be more terrifying than all the kingdoms that have been before it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012014"/>
      <verse num="14">And twelve kings shall reign in it, one after another.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012015"/>
      <verse num="15">But the second that is to reign shall hold sway for a longer time than any other of the twelve.<note nid="n86012015.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012016"/>
      <verse num="16">This is the interpretation of the twelve wings that you saw.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012017"/>
      <verse num="17">As for your seeing<note nid="n86012017.1"/> a voice that spoke, coming not from the eagle<q class="end-single" qid="86012017.1"/>s<note nid="n86012017.2"/> heads but from the midst of his body, this is the interpretation:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012018"/>
      <verse num="18">In the midst of<note nid="n86012018.1"/> the time of that kingdom great struggles shall arise, and it shall be in danger of falling; nevertheless it shall not fall then, but shall regain its former power.<note nid="n86012018.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012019"/>
      <verse num="19">As for your seeing eight little wings arising from<note nid="n86012019.1"/> his wings, this is the interpretation:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012020"/>
      <verse num="20">Eight kings shall arise in it, whose times shall be short and their years swift;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012021"/>
      <verse num="21">and two of them shall perish when the middle of its time draws near; and four shall be kept for the time when its end approaches; but two shall be kept until the end.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012022"/>
      <verse num="22">As for your seeing three heads at rest, this is the interpretation:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012023"/>
      <verse num="23">In its last days the Most High will raise up three kings,<note nid="n86012023.1"/> and they<note nid="n86012023.2"/> shall renew many things in it and shall rule the earth</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012024"/>
      <verse num="24">and its inhabitants more oppressively than all who were before them; therefore they are called the heads of the eagle.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012025"/>
      <verse num="25">For it is they who shall sum up his wickedness and perform his last actions.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012026"/>
      <verse num="26">As for your seeing that the large head disappeared, one of the kings<note nid="n86012026.1"/> shall die in his bed, but in agonies.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012027"/>
      <verse num="27">But as for the two who remained, the sword shall devour them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012028"/>
      <verse num="28">For the sword of one shall devour him who was with him; but he also shall fall by the sword in the last days.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012029"/>
      <verse num="29">As for your seeing two little wings<note nid="n86012029.1"/> passing over to<note nid="n86012029.2"/> the head that was on the right side,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012030"/>
      <verse num="30">this is the interpretation: It is these whom the Most High has kept for the eagle<q class="end-single" qid="86012030.1"/>s<note nid="n86012030.1"/> end; this was the reign that was brief and full of tumult, as you have seen.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012031"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="31"><q class="continue-double" qid="86012031.1" from="86012010.1" to="86012039.1"/>And as for the lion whom you saw rousing up out of the forest and roaring and speaking to the eagle and reproving him for his unrighteousness and as for all his words that you have heard,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012032"/>
      <verse num="32">this is the Messiah<note nid="n86012032.1"/> whom the Most High has kept until the end of days, who will arise from the posterity of David and will come and speak to them;<note nid="n86012032.2"/> he will denounce them for their ungodliness and for their wickedness and will cast up before them their contemptuous dealings.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012033"/>
      <verse num="33">For first he will set them living in judgment, and when he has reproved them, then he will destroy them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012034"/>
      <verse num="34">But he will deliver in mercy the remnant of my people, those who have been saved throughout my borders, and he will make them joyful until the end comes, the day of judgment, of which I spoke to you at the beginning.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012035"/>
      <verse num="35">This is the dream that you saw, and this is its interpretation.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012036"/>
      <verse num="36">And you alone were worthy to learn this secret of the Most High.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012037"/>
      <verse num="37">Therefore write all these things that you have seen in a book and put it in a hidden place;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012038"/>
      <verse num="38">and you shall teach them to the wise among your people, whose hearts you know are able to comprehend and keep these secrets.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012039"/>
      <verse num="39">But wait here seven days more, so that you may be shown whatever it pleases the Most High to show you.<q class="end-double" qid="86012039.1" from="86012010.1" to="86012039.1"/> Then he left me.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012040"/>
      <heading>The People Come to Ezra</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="40">When all the people heard that the seven days were past and I had not returned to the city, they all gathered together, from the least to the greatest, and came to me and spoke to me, saying,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012041"/>
      <verse num="41"><q class="begin-double" qid="86012041.1" from="86012041.1" to="86012045.1"/>How have we offended you, and what harm have we done you, that you have forsaken us and sit in this place?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012042"/>
      <verse num="42">For of all the prophets you alone are left to us, like a cluster of grapes from the vintage and like a lamp in a dark place and like a haven for a ship saved from a storm.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012043"/>
      <verse num="43">Are not the evils that have befallen us sufficient?<note nid="n86012043.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012044"/>
      <verse num="44">Therefore if you forsake us, how much better it would have been for us if we also had been consumed in the burning of Zion!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012045"/>
      <verse num="45">For we are no better than those who died there.<q class="end-double" qid="86012045.1" from="86012041.1" to="86012045.1"/> And they wept with a loud voice.<end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>Then I answered them and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012046"/>
      <verse num="46"><q class="begin-double" qid="86012046.1" from="86012046.1" to="86012049.1"/>Take courage, O Israel; and do not be sorrowful, O house of Jacob;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012047"/>
      <verse num="47">for the Most High has you in remembrance, and the Mighty One has not forgotten you forever.<note nid="n86012047.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012048"/>
      <verse num="48">As for me, I have neither forsaken you nor withdrawn from you; but I have come to this place to pray on account of the desolation of Zion and to seek mercy on account of the humiliation of our<note nid="n86012048.1"/> sanctuary.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012049"/>
      <verse num="49">Now go, every one of you to his house, and after these days I will come to you.<q class="end-double" qid="86012049.1" from="86012046.1" to="86012049.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012050"/>
      <verse num="50">So the people went into the city, as I told them to do.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86012051"/>
      <verse num="51">But I sat in the field seven days, as the angel<note nid="n86012051.1"/> had commanded me; and I ate only of the flowers of the field, and my food was of plants during those days.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013001"/>
    <chapter num="13">
      <heading>Sixth Vision: The Man from the Sea</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">After seven days I dreamed a dream in the night;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013002"/>
      <verse num="2">and behold, a great<note nid="n86013002.1"/> wind arose from the sea and stirred up all its waves.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013003"/>
      <verse num="3">And I looked, and behold, this wind made something like the figure of a man come up out of the heart of the sea. And I looked, and behold,<note nid="n86013003.1"/> that man flew<note nid="n86013003.2"/> with the clouds of heaven; and wherever he turned his face to look, everything under his gaze trembled,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013004"/>
      <verse num="4">and whenever his voice issued from his mouth, all who heard his voice melted as wax melts<note nid="n86013004.1"/> when it feels the fire.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">After this I looked, and behold, an innumerable multitude of people were gathered together from the four winds of heaven to make war against the man who came up out of the sea.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013006"/>
      <verse num="6">And I looked, and behold, he carved out for himself a great mountain and flew up upon it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013007"/>
      <verse num="7">And I tried to see the region or place from which the mountain was carved, but I could not.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013008"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="8">After this I looked, and behold, all who had gathered together against him, to wage war with him, were much afraid, yet dared to fight.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013009"/>
      <verse num="9">And behold, when he saw the onrush of the approaching multitude, he neither lifted his hand nor held a spear or any weapon of war;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013010"/>
      <verse num="10">but I saw only how he sent forth from his mouth as it were a stream of fire and from his lips a flaming breath, and from his tongue he shot forth a storm of fiery coals.<note nid="n86013010.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013011"/>
      <verse num="11">All these were mingled together, the stream of fire and the flaming breath and the great storm and fell on the onrushing multitude that was prepared to fight and burned them all up, so that suddenly nothing was seen of the innumerable multitude but only the dust of ashes and the smell of smoke. When I saw it, I was amazed.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013012"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="12">After this I saw the same man come down from the mountain and call to him another multitude that was peaceable.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013013"/>
      <verse num="13">Then many people<note nid="n86013013.1"/> came to him, some of whom were joyful and some sorrowful; some of them were bound, and some were bringing others as offerings.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013014"/>
      <heading>Interpretation of Sixth Vision<begin-paragraph/>Then in great fear I awoke; and I implored the Most High and said,</heading>
      <verse num="14"><q class="begin-double" qid="86013014.1" from="86013014.1" to="86013020.1"/>From the beginning you have shown your servant these wonders and have deemed me worthy to have my prayer heard by you;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013015"/>
      <verse num="15">now show me also the interpretation of this dream.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013016"/>
      <verse num="16">For as I consider it in my mind, alas for those who will be left in those days! And still more, alas for those who are not left!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013017"/>
      <verse num="17">For those who are not left will be sad,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013018"/>
      <verse num="18">because they understand what is reserved for the last days, but cannot attain it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013019"/>
      <verse num="19">But alas for those also who are left and for that very reason! For they shall see great dangers and much distress, as these dreams show.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013020"/>
      <verse num="20">Yet it is better<note nid="n86013020.1"/> to come into these things,<note nid="n86013020.2"/> though incurring peril than to pass from the world like a cloud and not to see what shall happen in the last days.<q class="end-double" qid="86013020.1" from="86013014.1" to="86013020.1"/><end-paragraph/><begin-paragraph/>He answered me and said,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013021"/>
      <verse num="21"><q class="begin-double" qid="86013021.1" from="86013021.1" to="86013050.1"/>I will tell you the interpretation of the vision, and I will also explain to you the things that you have mentioned.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013022"/>
      <verse num="22">As for what you said about those who are left, this is the interpretation:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013023"/>
      <verse num="23">He who brings the peril at that time will himself protect those who fall into peril, who have works and have faith in the Almighty.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013024"/>
      <verse num="24">Understand therefore that those who are left are more blessed than those who have died.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013025"/>
      <verse num="25">This is the interpretation of the vision: As for your seeing a man come up from the heart of the sea,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013026"/>
      <verse num="26">this is he whom the Most High has been keeping for many ages, through whom he will deliver<note nid="n86013026.1"/> his creation; and he will direct those who are left.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013027"/>
      <verse num="27">And as for your seeing fiery breath<note nid="n86013027.1"/> and a storm coming out of his mouth</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013028"/>
      <verse num="28">and as for his not holding a spear or weapon of war, yet destroying the onrushing multitude that came to conquer him, this is the interpretation:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013029"/>
      <verse num="29">Behold, the days are coming when the Most High will deliver those who are on the earth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013030"/>
      <verse num="30">And bewilderment of mind shall come over those who dwell on the earth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013031"/>
      <verse num="31">And they shall plan to make war against one another, city against city, place against place, people against people, and kingdom against kingdom.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013032"/>
      <verse num="32">And when these things come to pass and the signs occur that I showed you before, then my Son<note nid="n86013032.1"/> will be revealed, whom you saw as a man coming up from the sea.<note nid="n86013032.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013033"/>
      <verse num="33">And when all the nations hear his voice, every man shall leave his own land and the warfare that they have against one another;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013034"/>
      <verse num="34">and an innumerable multitude shall be gathered together, as you saw, desiring to come and conquer him.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013035"/>
      <verse num="35">But he will stand on the top of Mount Zion.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013036"/>
      <verse num="36">And Zion will come and be made manifest to all people, prepared and built, as you saw the mountain carved out without hands.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013037"/>
      <verse num="37">And he, my Son, will reprove the assembled nations for their ungodliness (this was symbolized by the storm)</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013038"/>
      <verse num="38">and will reproach them to their face with their evil deeds<note nid="n86013038.1"/> and the torments with which they are to be tortured (which were symbolized by the flames) and will destroy them without effort by<note nid="n86013038.2"/> the law (which was symbolized by the fire).</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013039"/>
      <verse num="39">And as for your seeing him gather to himself another multitude that was peaceable,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013040"/>
      <verse num="40">these are the ten<note nid="n86013040.1"/> tribes that were led away from their own land into captivity in the days of King Hoshea, whom King Shalmaneser of the Assyrians led captive; he took them across the river, and they were taken into another land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013041"/>
      <verse num="41">But they formed this plan for themselves, that they would leave the multitude of the nations and go to a more distant region, where mankind had never lived,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013042"/>
      <verse num="42">that there at least they might keep their statutes that they had not kept in their own land.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013043"/>
      <verse num="43">And they went in by the narrow passages of the Euphrates river.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013044"/>
      <verse num="44">For at that time the Most High performed signs for them and stopped the channels of the river until they had passed over.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013045"/>
      <verse num="45">Through that region<note nid="n86013045.1"/> there was a long way to go, a journey of a year and a half; and that country is called Arzareth.<note nid="n86013045.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013046"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="46"><q class="continue-double" qid="86013046.1" from="86013021.1" to="86013050.1"/>Then they dwelt there until the last times; and now, when they are about to come again,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013047"/>
      <verse num="47">the Most High will stop<note nid="n86013047.1"/> the channels of the river again, so that they may be able to pass over. Therefore you saw the multitude gathered together in peace.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013048"/>
      <verse num="48">But those who are left of your people, who are found within my holy borders, shall be saved.<note nid="n86013048.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013049"/>
      <verse num="49">Therefore when he destroys the multitude of the nations that are gathered together, he will defend the people who remain.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013050"/>
      <verse num="50">And then he will show them very many wonders.<q class="end-double" qid="86013050.1" from="86013021.1" to="86013050.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013051"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="51">I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86013051.1" from="86013051.1" to="86013051.2"/>O sovereign Lord, explain this to me: Why did I see the man coming up from the heart of the sea?<q class="end-double" qid="86013051.2" from="86013051.1" to="86013051.2"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013052"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="52">He said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86013052.1" from="86013052.1" to="86013056.1"/>Just as no one can explore or know what is in the depths of the sea, so no one on earth can see my Son or those who are with him, except in the time of his day.<note nid="n86013052.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013053"/>
      <verse num="53">This is the interpretation of the dream that you saw. And you alone have been enlightened about this,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013054"/>
      <verse num="54">because you have forsaken your own ways and have applied yourself to mine and have searched out my law;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013055"/>
      <verse num="55">for you have devoted your life to wisdom and called understanding your mother.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013056"/>
      <verse num="56">Therefore I have shown you this, for there is a reward laid up with the Most High. And after three more days I will tell you other things and explain weighty and wondrous matters to you.<q class="end-double" qid="86013056.1" from="86013052.1" to="86013056.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013057"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="57">Then I arose and walked in the field, giving great glory and praise to the Most High because of his wonders, which he did from time to time,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86013058"/>
      <verse num="58">and because he governs the times and whatever things come to pass in their seasons. And I stayed there three days.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014001"/>
    <chapter num="14">
      <heading>Seventh Vision: The Lord Commissions Ezra</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">On the third day, while I was sitting under an oak, behold, a voice came out of a bush opposite me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86014001.1" from="86014001.1" to="86014001.2"/>Ezra, Ezra.<q class="end-double" qid="86014001.2" from="86014001.1" to="86014001.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014002"/>
      <verse num="2">And I said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86014002.1" from="86014002.1" to="86014002.2"/>Here I am, Lord,<q class="end-double" qid="86014002.2" from="86014002.1" to="86014002.2"/> and I rose to my feet.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014003"/>
      <verse num="3">Then he said to me, <q class="begin-double" qid="86014003.1" from="86014003.1" to="86014018.1"/>I revealed myself in a bush and spoke to Moses, when my people were in bondage in Egypt;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014004"/>
      <verse num="4">and I sent him and led<note nid="n86014004.1"/> my people out of Egypt; and I led him up on Mount Sinai, where I kept him with me many days;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014005"/>
      <verse num="5">and I told him many wondrous things and showed him the secrets of the times and declared to him<note nid="n86014005.1"/> the end of the times. Then I commanded him, saying,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014006"/>
      <verse num="6"><q class="begin-single" qid="86014006.1" from="86014006.1" to="86014006.2"/>These words you shall publish openly, and these you shall keep secret.<q class="end-single" qid="86014006.2" from="86014006.1" to="86014006.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014007"/>
      <verse num="7">And now I say to you:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014008"/>
      <verse num="8">Lay up in your heart the signs that I have shown you, the dreams that you have seen, and the interpretations that you have heard;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014009"/>
      <verse num="9">for you shall be taken up from among human beings, and henceforth you shall live with my Son and with those who are like you, until the times are ended.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014010"/>
      <verse num="10">For the age has lost its youth, and the times begin to grow old.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014011"/>
      <verse num="11">For the age is divided into twelve parts, and nine<note nid="n86014011.1"/> of its parts have already passed,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014012"/>
      <verse num="12">as well as half of the tenth part; so two of its parts remain, besides half of the tenth part.<note nid="n86014012.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014013"/>
      <verse num="13">Now therefore, set your house in order and reprove your people; comfort the lowly among them and instruct those that are wise.<note nid="n86014013.1"/> And now renounce the life that is corruptible</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014014"/>
      <verse num="14">and put away from you mortal thoughts; cast away from you the burdens of man and divest yourself now of your weak nature</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014015"/>
      <verse num="15">and lay to one side the thoughts that are most grievous to you and hasten to escape from these times.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014016"/>
      <verse num="16">For evils worse than those that you have now seen happen shall be done hereafter.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014017"/>
      <verse num="17">For the weaker the world becomes through old age, the more shall evils be multiplied among<note nid="n86014017.1"/> its inhabitants.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014018"/>
      <verse num="18">For truth shall go farther away, and falsehood shall come near. For the eagle<note nid="n86014018.1"/> that you saw in the vision is already hastening to come.<q class="end-double" qid="86014018.1" from="86014003.1" to="86014018.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014019"/>
      <heading>Ezra’s Concern to Restore the Scriptures</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="19">Then I answered and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86014019.1" from="86014019.1" to="86014022.1"/>Let me speak<note nid="n86014019.1"/> in your presence, Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014020"/>
      <verse num="20">For behold, I will go, as you have commanded me, and I will reprove the people who are now living; but who will warn those who will be born hereafter? For the world lies in darkness, and its inhabitants are without light.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014021"/>
      <verse num="21">For your law has been burned, and so no one knows the things that have been done or will be done by you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014022"/>
      <verse num="22">If then I have found favor before you, send the Holy Spirit into me, and I will write everything that has happened in the world from the beginning, the things that were written in your law, that people may be able to find the path, and that those who wish to live in the last days may live.<q class="end-double" qid="86014022.1" from="86014019.1" to="86014022.1"/><note nid="n86014022.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014023"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="23">He answered me and said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86014023.1" from="86014023.1" to="86014026.1"/>Go and gather the people and tell them not to seek you for forty days.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014024"/>
      <verse num="24">But prepare for yourself many writing tablets and take with you Sarea, Dabria, Selemia, Elkana,<note nid="n86014024.1"/> and Asiel—these five, because they are trained to write rapidly;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014025"/>
      <verse num="25">and you shall come here, and I will light in your heart the lamp of understanding, which shall not be put out until what you are about to write is finished.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014026"/>
      <verse num="26">And when you have finished, some things you shall make public, and some you shall deliver in secret to the wise; tomorrow at this hour you shall begin to write.<q class="end-double" qid="86014026.1" from="86014023.1" to="86014026.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014027"/>
      <heading>Ezra’s Last Words to the People</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="27">Then I went as he commanded me, and I gathered all the people together and said to them,<note nid="n86014027.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014028"/>
      <verse num="28"><q class="begin-double" qid="86014028.1" from="86014028.1" to="86014036.1"/>Hear these words, O Israel.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014029"/>
      <verse num="29">At first our fathers dwelt as aliens in Egypt, and they were delivered from there</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014030"/>
      <verse num="30">and received the law of life, which they did not keep, which you also have transgressed after them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014031"/>
      <verse num="31">Then land was given to you for a possession in the land of Zion; but you and your fathers committed iniquity and did not keep the ways that the Most High commanded you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014032"/>
      <verse num="32">And because he is a righteous judge, in due time he took from you what he had given.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014033"/>
      <verse num="33">And now you are here, and your kindred are farther in the interior.<note nid="n86014033.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014034"/>
      <verse num="34">If you, then, will rule over your minds and discipline your hearts, you shall be kept alive, and after death you shall obtain mercy.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014035"/>
      <verse num="35">For after death the judgment will come, when we shall live again; and then the names of the righteous will become manifest, and the deeds of the ungodly will be disclosed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014036"/>
      <verse num="36">But let no one come to me now, and let no one seek me for forty days.<q class="end-double" qid="86014036.1" from="86014028.1" to="86014036.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014037"/>
      <heading>Restoration of the Scriptures</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="37">So I took the five men, as he commanded me, and we proceeded to the field and remained there.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014038"/>
      <verse num="38">And on the next day, behold, a voice called me, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="86014038.1" from="86014038.1" to="86014038.2"/>Ezra, open your mouth and drink what I give you to drink.<q class="end-double" qid="86014038.2" from="86014038.1" to="86014038.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014039"/>
      <verse num="39">Then I opened my mouth, and behold, a full cup was offered to me; it was full of something like water, but its color was like fire.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014040"/>
      <verse num="40">And I took it and drank; and when I had drunk it, my heart poured forth understanding, and wisdom increased in my breast, and<note nid="n86014040.1"/> my spirit retained its memory;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014041"/>
      <verse num="41">and my mouth was opened and was no longer closed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014042"/>
      <verse num="42">And the Most High gave understanding to the five men, and by turns they wrote what was dictated, in characters that they did not know.<note nid="n86014042.1"/> They sat forty days and wrote during the daytime and ate their bread at night.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014043"/>
      <verse num="43">As for me, I spoke in the daytime and was not silent at night.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014044"/>
      <verse num="44">So during the forty days ninety-four<note nid="n86014044.1"/> books were written.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014045"/>
      <verse num="45">And when the forty days were ended, the Most High spoke to me, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="86014045.1" from="86014045.1" to="86014047.1"/>Make public the twenty-four<note nid="n86014045.1"/> books that you wrote first, and let the worthy and the unworthy read them;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014046"/>
      <verse num="46">but keep the seventy that were written last, in order to give them to the wise among your people.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014047"/>
      <verse num="47">For in them is the spring of understanding, the fountain of wisdom, and the river of knowledge.<q class="end-double" qid="86014047.1" from="86014045.1" to="86014047.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86014048"/>
      <verse num="48">And I did so.<note nid="n86014048.1"/></verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015001"/>
    <chapter num="15">
      <heading>Vengeance on the Wicked</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1"><note nid="n86015001.1"/>The Lord says, Behold, speak in the ears of my people the words of the prophecy that I will put in your mouth</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015002"/>
      <verse num="2">and cause them to be written on paper; for they are trustworthy and true.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015003"/>
      <verse num="3">Do not fear the plots against you and do not be troubled by the unbelief of those who oppose you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015004"/>
      <verse num="4">For every unbeliever shall die in his unbelief.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015005"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="5">Behold, says the Lord, I bring evils upon the world, the sword and famine and death and destruction.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015006"/>
      <verse num="6">For iniquity has spread throughout every land, and their harmful deeds have reached their limit.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015007"/>
      <verse num="7">Therefore, says the Lord,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015008"/>
      <verse num="8">I will be silent no longer concerning their ungodly deeds that they impiously commit, neither will I tolerate their wicked practices. Behold, innocent and righteous blood cries out to me, and the souls of the righteous cry out continually.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015009"/>
      <verse num="9">I will surely avenge them, says the Lord, and will receive to myself all the innocent blood from among them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015010"/>
      <verse num="10">Behold, my people are led like a flock to the slaughter; I will not allow them to live any longer in the land of Egypt,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015011"/>
      <verse num="11">but I will bring them out with a mighty hand and with an uplifted arm and will strike Egypt with a plague, as before, and will destroy all its land.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015012"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="12">Let Egypt and its foundations mourn on account of the plague of chastisement and punishment that the Lord will bring upon it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015013"/>
      <verse num="13">Let the farmers that till the ground mourn, because their seed shall fail and their trees shall be ruined by blight and hail and by a terrible tempest.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015014"/>
      <verse num="14">Alas for the world and for those who live in it!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015015"/>
      <verse num="15">For the sword and misery draw near them, and nation shall rise up to fight against nation, with swords in their hands.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015016"/>
      <verse num="16">For there shall be unrest among people; growing strong against one another, they shall in their might have no respect for their king or the chief of their leaders.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015017"/>
      <verse num="17">For a man will desire to go into a city and shall not be able.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015018"/>
      <verse num="18">For because of their pride the cities shall be in confusion, the houses shall be destroyed, and people shall be afraid.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015019"/>
      <verse num="19">A man shall have no pity upon his neighbors, but shall make an assault upon their houses with the sword and plunder their goods, because of hunger for bread and because of great tribulation.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015020"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="20">Behold, says God, I call together all the kings of the earth to fear me, from the rising sun and from the south, from the east and from Lebanon; to turn and repay what they have given them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015021"/>
      <verse num="21">Just as they have done to my elect until this day, so I will do and will repay into their bosom. Thus says the Lord God:</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015022"/>
      <verse num="22">My right hand will not spare the sinners, and my sword will not cease from those who shed innocent blood on earth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015023"/>
      <verse num="23">And a fire will go forth from his wrath and will consume the foundations of the earth and the sinners, like straw that is kindled.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015024"/>
      <verse num="24">Woe to those who sin and do not observe my commandments, says the Lord;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015025"/>
      <verse num="25">I will not spare them. Depart, you faithless children! Do not pollute my sanctuary.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015026"/>
      <verse num="26">For the Lord<note nid="n86015026.1"/> knows all who transgress against him; therefore he will hand them over to death and slaughter.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015027"/>
      <verse num="27">For now calamities have come upon the whole earth, and you shall remain in them; for God will not deliver you, because you have sinned against him.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015028"/>
      <heading>Terrifying Vision of Warfare</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="28">Behold, a terrifying sight, appearing from the east!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015029"/>
      <verse num="29">The nations of the dragons of Arabia shall come out with many chariots, and from the day that they set out, their hissing shall spread over the earth, so that all who hear them fear and tremble.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015030"/>
      <verse num="30">Also the Carmonians, raging in wrath, shall go forth like wild boars<note nid="n86015030.1"/> of the forest, and with great power they shall come and engage them in battle and shall devastate a portion of the land of the Assyrians with their teeth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015031"/>
      <verse num="31">And then the dragons, remembering their origin, shall become still stronger; and if they combine in great power and turn to pursue them,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015032"/>
      <verse num="32">then these shall be disorganized and silenced by their power and shall turn and flee.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015033"/>
      <verse num="33">And from the land of the Assyrians an enemy in ambush shall beset them and destroy one of them, and fear and trembling shall come upon their army, and indecision upon their kings.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015034"/>
      <heading>Judgment on Babylon</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="34">Behold, clouds from the east and from the north to the south; and their appearance is very threatening, full of wrath and storm.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015035"/>
      <verse num="35">They shall throw themselves against one another and shall pour out a heavy tempest upon the earth, and their own tempest; and there shall be blood from the sword as high as a horse<q class="end-single" qid="86015035.1"/>s belly</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015036"/>
      <verse num="36">and a man<q class="end-single" qid="86015036.1"/>s thigh and a camel<q class="end-single" qid="86015036.2"/>s hock.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015037"/>
      <verse num="37">And there shall be fear and great trembling upon the earth; and those who see that wrath shall be horror-stricken, and they shall be seized with trembling.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015038"/>
      <verse num="38">And, after that, heavy storm clouds shall be stirred up from the south and from the north, and another part from the west.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015039"/>
      <verse num="39">And the winds from the east shall prevail over the cloud that was<note nid="n86015039.1"/> raised in wrath and shall dispel it; and the tempest that was to cause destruction by the east wind shall be driven violently toward the south and west.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015040"/>
      <verse num="40">And great and mighty clouds, full of wrath and tempest, shall rise, to destroy all the earth and its inhabitants, and shall pour out upon every high and lofty place<note nid="n86015040.1"/> a terrible tempest,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015041"/>
      <verse num="41">fire and hail and flying swords and floods of water, in order that all the fields and all the streams may be filled with the abundance of those waters.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015042"/>
      <verse num="42">And they shall destroy cities and walls, mountains and hills, trees of the forests, and grass of the meadows and their grain.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015043"/>
      <verse num="43">And they shall go on steadily to Babylon and shall destroy her.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015044"/>
      <verse num="44">They shall come to her and surround her; they shall pour out the tempest and all its wrath upon her; then the dust and smoke shall go up to heaven, and all who are about her shall wail over her.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015045"/>
      <verse num="45">And those who survive shall serve those who have destroyed her.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015046"/>
      <heading>Judgment on Asia</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="46">And you, Asia, who share in the glamour of Babylon and the glory of her person—</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015047"/>
      <verse num="47">woe to you, miserable wretch! For you have made yourself like her; you have decked out your daughters for sexual immorality to please and take pride in your lovers, who have always lusted after you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015048"/>
      <verse num="48">You have imitated that hateful prostitute<note nid="n86015048.1"/> in all her deeds and devices; therefore God says,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015049"/>
      <verse num="49">I will send evils upon you, widowhood, poverty, famine, sword, and pestilence, to devastate your houses and bring you to destruction and death.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015050"/>
      <verse num="50">And the glory of your power shall wither like a flower, when the heat rises that is sent upon you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015051"/>
      <verse num="51">You shall be weakened like a wretched woman who is beaten and wounded, so that you cannot receive your mighty lovers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015052"/>
      <verse num="52">Would I have dealt with you so violently, says the Lord,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015053"/>
      <verse num="53">If you had not killed my chosen people at every opportunity, exulting and clapping your hands and talking about their death when you were drunk?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015054"/>
      <verse num="54">Beautify the appearance of your face!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015055"/>
      <verse num="55">The reward of a prostitute is in your bosom, therefore you shall receive your recompense.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015056"/>
      <verse num="56">As you will do to my chosen people, says the Lord, so God will do to you and will hand you over to adversities.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015057"/>
      <verse num="57">Your children shall die of hunger, and you shall fall by the sword, and your cities shall be wiped out, and all your people who are in the open country shall fall by the sword.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015058"/>
      <verse num="58">And those who are in the mountains and highlands<note nid="n86015058.1"/> shall perish of hunger, and they shall eat their own flesh in hunger for bread and drink their own blood in thirst for water.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015059"/>
      <verse num="59">Unhappy above all others, you shall come and suffer fresh afflictions.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015060"/>
      <verse num="60">And as they pass they shall wreck the hateful<note nid="n86015060.1"/> city and shall destroy a part of your land and abolish a portion of your glory, as they return from devastated Babylon.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015061"/>
      <verse num="61">And you shall be broken down by them like stubble, and they shall be like fire to you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015062"/>
      <verse num="62">And they shall devour you and your cities, your land and your mountains; they shall burn with fire all your forests and your fruitful trees.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86015063"/>
      <verse num="63">They shall carry your children away captive and shall plunder your wealth and abolish the splendor of your face.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016001"/>
    <chapter num="16">
      <heading>Further Denunciations</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="1">Woe to you, Babylon and Asia! Woe to you, Egypt and Syria!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016002"/>
      <verse num="2">Tie sackcloth and haircloth<note nid="n86016002.1"/> around your waist and wail for your children and lament for them; for your destruction is at hand.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016003"/>
      <verse num="3">The sword has been sent upon you, and who is there to turn it back?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016004"/>
      <verse num="4">A fire has been sent upon you, and who is there to quench it?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016005"/>
      <verse num="5">Calamities have been sent upon you, and who is there to drive them away?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016006"/>
      <verse num="6">Can one drive off a hungry lion in the forest or quench a fire in the stubble once it has begun to burn?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016007"/>
      <verse num="7">Can one turn back an arrow shot by a strong archer?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016008"/>
      <verse num="8">The Lord God sends calamities, and who will drive them away?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016009"/>
      <verse num="9">Fire will go forth from his wrath, and who is there to quench it?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016010"/>
      <verse num="10">He will flash lightning, and who will not be afraid? He will thunder, and who will not be terrified?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016011"/>
      <verse num="11">The Lord will threaten, and who will not be utterly shattered at his presence?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016012"/>
      <verse num="12">The earth and its foundations quake, the sea is churned up from the depths, and its waves and the fish also shall be troubled at the presence of the Lord and before the glory of his power.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016013"/>
      <verse num="13">For his right hand that bends the bow is strong, and his arrows that he shoots are sharp and will not miss when they begin to be shot to the ends of the world.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016014"/>
      <verse num="14">Behold, calamities are sent forth and shall not return until they come over the earth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016015"/>
      <verse num="15">The fire is kindled and shall not be put out until it consumes the foundations of the earth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016016"/>
      <verse num="16">Just as an arrow shot by a mighty archer does not return, so the calamities that are sent upon the earth shall not return.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016017"/>
      <verse num="17">Alas for me! Alas for me! Who will deliver me in those days?</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016018"/>
      <heading>Horror of the Last Days</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="18">The beginning of sorrows, when there shall be much lamentation; the beginning of famine, when many shall perish; the beginning of wars, when the powers shall be terrified; the beginning of calamities, when all shall tremble. What shall they do in these circumstances, when the calamities come?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016019"/>
      <verse num="19">Behold, famine and plague, tribulation and anguish are sent as scourges for the correction of humanity.<note nid="n86016019.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016020"/>
      <verse num="20">Yet for all this they will not turn from their iniquities, nor will they ever be mindful of the scourges.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016021"/>
      <verse num="21">Behold, provision will be so cheap upon earth that they will imagine that peace is assured for them, and then the calamities shall spring up on the earth—the sword, famine, and great confusion.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016022"/>
      <verse num="22">For many of those who live on the earth shall perish by famine; and those who survive the famine shall die by the sword.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016023"/>
      <verse num="23">And the dead shall be cast out like dung, and there shall be no one to console them; for the earth shall be left desolate, and its cities shall be demolished.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016024"/>
      <verse num="24">No one shall be left to cultivate the earth or to sow it.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016025"/>
      <verse num="25">The trees shall bear fruit, and who will gather it?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016026"/>
      <verse num="26">The grapes shall ripen, and who will tread them? For in all places there shall be great solitude;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016027"/>
      <verse num="27">one person will long to see another or even to hear his voice.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016028"/>
      <verse num="28">For out of a city, ten shall be left; and out of the field, two who have hidden themselves in thick groves and clefts in the rocks.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016029"/>
      <verse num="29">As in an olive orchard three or four olives may be left on every tree</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016030"/>
      <verse num="30">or as when a vineyard is gathered some clusters may be left by those who search carefully through the vineyard,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016031"/>
      <verse num="31">so in those days three or four shall be left by those who search their houses with the sword.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016032"/>
      <verse num="32">And the earth shall be left desolate, and its fields shall be for thornbushes,<note nid="n86016032.1"/> and its roads and all its paths shall bring forth thorns, because no sheep will go along them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016033"/>
      <verse num="33">Virgins shall mourn because they have no bridegrooms; women shall mourn because they have no husbands; their daughters shall mourn, because they have no helpers.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016034"/>
      <verse num="34">Their bridegrooms shall be killed in war, and their husbands shall perish of famine.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016035"/>
      <heading>God’s People Must Prepare for the End</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="35">Listen now to these things and understand them, O servants of the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016036"/>
      <verse num="36">See the word of the Lord; receive it, do not disbelieve what the Lord says.<note nid="n86016036.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016037"/>
      <verse num="37">Behold, the calamities draw near and are not delayed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016038"/>
      <verse num="38">Just as a woman with child, in the ninth month, when the time of her delivery draws near, has great pains about her womb for two or three hours beforehand, and when the child comes forth from the womb, there will not be a moment<q class="end-single" qid="86016038.1"/>s delay,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016039"/>
      <verse num="39">so the calamities will not delay in coming forth upon the earth, and the world will groan, and pains will seize it on every side.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016040"/>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="40">Hear my words, O my people; prepare for battle, and in the midst of the calamities be like strangers on the earth.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016041"/>
      <verse num="41">Let him that sells be like one who will flee; let him that buys be like one who will lose;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016042"/>
      <verse num="42">let him that does business be like one who will not make a profit; and let him that builds a house be like one who will not live in it;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016043"/>
      <verse num="43">let him that sows be like one who will not reap; so also him that prunes the vines, like one who will not gather the grapes;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016044"/>
      <verse num="44">them that marry, like those who will have no children; and them that do not marry, like those who are widowed.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016045"/>
      <verse num="45">Because those who labor, labor in vain;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016046"/>
      <verse num="46">for strangers shall gather their fruits and plunder their goods and overthrow their houses and take their children captive; for in captivity and famine they will beget their children.<note nid="n86016046.1"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016047"/>
      <verse num="47">Those who conduct business, do it only to be plundered; the more they adorn their cities, their houses and possessions, and their persons,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016048"/>
      <verse num="48">the angrier I will be with them for their sins, says the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016049"/>
      <verse num="49">Just as a respectable and virtuous woman abhors a prostitute,</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016050"/>
      <verse num="50">so righteousness shall abhor iniquity, when she decks herself out, and shall accuse her to her face, when he comes who will defend him who searches out every sin on earth.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016051"/>
      <heading>Power and Wisdom of God</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="51">Therefore do not be like her or her works.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016052"/>
      <verse num="52">For behold, just a little while, and iniquity will be removed from the earth, and righteousness will reign over us.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016053"/>
      <verse num="53">Let no sinner say that he has not sinned; for God<note nid="n86016053.1"/> will burn coals of fire on the head of him who says, <q class="begin-double" qid="86016053.1" from="86016053.1" to="86016053.2"/>I have not sinned before God and his glory.<q class="end-double" qid="86016053.2" from="86016053.1" to="86016053.2"/><note nid="n86016053.2"/></verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016054"/>
      <verse num="54">Behold, the Lord knows all the works of men, their imaginations and their thoughts and their hearts.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016055"/>
      <verse num="55">He said, <q class="begin-double" qid="86016055.1" from="86016055.1" to="86016055.2"/>Let the earth be made,<q class="end-double" qid="86016055.2" from="86016055.1" to="86016055.2"/> and it was made; <q class="begin-double" qid="86016055.3" from="86016055.3" to="86016055.4"/>Let the heaven be made,<q class="end-double" qid="86016055.4" from="86016055.3" to="86016055.4"/> and it was made.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016056"/>
      <verse num="56">At his word the stars were fixed, and he knows the number of the stars.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016057"/>
      <verse num="57">It is he who searches the deep and its treasures; who has measured the sea and its contents;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016058"/>
      <verse num="58">who has enclosed the sea in the midst of the waters and by his word has suspended the earth over the water;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016059"/>
      <verse num="59">who has spread out the heaven like an arch and founded it upon the waters;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016060"/>
      <verse num="60">who has put springs of water in the desert and pools on the tops of the mountains, to send rivers from the heights to water the earth;</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016061"/>
      <verse num="61">who formed man and put a heart in the midst of his body and gave him breath and life and understanding</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016062"/>
      <verse num="62">and the spirit of almighty God; who made all things and searches out hidden things in hidden places.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016063"/>
      <verse num="63">Surely he knows your imaginations and what you think in your hearts! Woe to those who sin and want to hide their sins!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016064"/>
      <verse num="64">Because the Lord will strictly examine all their works and will make a public spectacle of all of you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016065"/>
      <verse num="65">And when your sins come out before men, you shall be put to shame; and your own iniquities shall stand as your accusers in that day.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016066"/>
      <verse num="66">What will you do? Or how will you hide your sins before God and his angels?</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016067"/>
      <verse num="67">Behold, God is the judge, fear him! Cease from your sins and forget your iniquities, never to commit them again; so God will lead you forth and deliver you from all tribulation.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016068"/>
      <heading>Impending Persecution of God’s People</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="68">For behold, the burning wrath of a great multitude is kindled over you, and they shall carry off some of you and shall feed you what was sacrificed to idols.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016069"/>
      <verse num="69">And those who consent to eat shall be held in<note nid="n86016069.1"/> derision and contempt and be trodden under foot.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016070"/>
      <verse num="70">For in many places<note nid="n86016070.1"/> and in neighboring cities there shall be a great insurrection against those who fear the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016071"/>
      <verse num="71">They shall be like mad men, sparing no one, but plundering and destroying those who continue to fear the Lord.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016072"/>
      <verse num="72">For they shall destroy and plunder their goods and drive them out of their houses.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016073"/>
      <verse num="73">Then the tested quality of my elect shall be manifest, as gold that is tested by fire.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016074"/>
      <heading>Promise of Divine Deliverance</heading>
      <begin-paragraph/>
      <verse num="74">Hear, my elect, says the Lord. Behold, the days of tribulation are at hand, and I will deliver you from them.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016075"/>
      <verse num="75">Do not fear or doubt, for God is your guide.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016076"/>
      <verse num="76">You who keep my commandments and precepts, says the Lord God, do not let your sins pull you down or your iniquities prevail over you.</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016077"/>
      <verse num="77">Woe to those who are choked by their sins and overwhelmed by their iniquities, as a field is choked with underbrush and its path<note nid="n86016077.1"/> overwhelmed with thorns, so that no one can pass through!</verse>
      <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v86016078"/>
      <verse num="78">It is shut off and given up to be consumed by fire.</verse>
      <end-paragraph/>
    </chapter>
  </book>
</crossway-bible>
