<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible translation="English Standard Version" revision="2025-02-02" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
<book title="Joshua" num="6">
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001001"/>
  <chapter num="1">
    <heading>God Commissions Joshua</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">After the death of Moses the <crossref let="a" cid="c06001001.1"/>servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua the son of Nun, Moses&apos; <crossref let="b" cid="c06001001.2"/>assistant,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="06001002.1" from="06001002.1" to="06001009.1"/>Moses my servant is dead. Now therefore arise, go over this Jordan, you and all this people, into the land that I am giving to them, to the people of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001003"/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="c" cid="c06001003.1"/>Every place that the sole of your foot will tread upon I have given to you, just as I promised to Moses.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="d" cid="c06001004.1"/>From the wilderness and this Lebanon as far as the great river, the river Euphrates, all the land of the Hittites to the Great Sea toward the going down of the sun shall be your territory.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001005"/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="e" cid="c06001005.1"/>No man shall be able to stand before you all the days of your life. Just <crossref let="f" cid="c06001005.2"/>as I was with Moses, so <crossref let="g" cid="c06001005.3"/>I will be with you. <crossref let="h" cid="c06001005.4"/>I will not leave you or forsake you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="i" cid="c06001006.1"/>Be strong and courageous, for you shall cause this people to inherit the land that I swore to their fathers to give them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001007"/>
    <verse num="7">Only be strong and <crossref let="j" cid="c06001007.1"/>very courageous, being careful to do according to all the law <crossref let="k" cid="c06001007.2"/>that Moses my servant commanded you. <crossref let="l" cid="c06001007.3"/>Do not turn from it to the right hand or to the left, that you may have good success<note nid="n06001007.1"/> wherever you go.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001008"/>
    <verse num="8">This Book of the Law shall not depart from your mouth, but <crossref let="m" cid="c06001008.1"/>you shall meditate on it day and night, so that you may be careful to do according to all that is written in it. For then you will make your way prosperous, and then you will have good success.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001009"/>
    <verse num="9">Have I not commanded you? <crossref let="n" cid="c06001009.1"/>Be strong and courageous. <crossref let="o" cid="c06001009.2"/>Do not be frightened, and do not be dismayed, for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God is with you wherever you go.<q class="end-double" qid="06001009.1" from="06001002.1" to="06001009.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001010"/>
    <heading>Joshua Assumes Command</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">And Joshua commanded the <crossref let="p" cid="c06001010.1"/>officers of the people,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001011"/>
    <verse num="11"><q class="begin-double" qid="06001011.1" from="06001011.1" to="06001011.4"/>Pass through the midst of the camp and command the people, <q class="begin-single" qid="06001011.2" from="06001011.2" to="06001011.3"/>Prepare your provisions, for <crossref let="q" cid="c06001011.1"/>within three days <crossref let="r" cid="c06001011.2"/>you are to pass over this Jordan to go in to take possession of the land that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God is giving you to possess.<q class="end-single" qid="06001011.3" from="06001011.2" to="06001011.3"/><q class="end-double" qid="06001011.4" from="06001011.1" to="06001011.4"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">And to the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh Joshua said,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001013"/>
    <verse num="13"><q class="begin-double" qid="06001013.1" from="06001013.1" to="06001015.1"/>Remember the word that <crossref let="s" cid="c06001013.1"/>Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded you, saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="06001013.2" from="06001013.2" to="06001013.3"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God is providing you a place of rest and will give you this land.<q class="end-single" qid="06001013.3" from="06001013.2" to="06001013.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001014"/>
    <verse num="14">Your wives, your little ones, and your livestock shall remain in the land that Moses gave you beyond the Jordan, but all the men of valor among you shall pass over armed before your brothers and shall help them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="t" cid="c06001015.1"/>until the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gives rest to your brothers as he has to you, and they also take possession of the land that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God is giving them. <crossref let="u" cid="c06001015.2"/>Then you shall return to the land of your possession and shall possess it, the land that Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave you beyond the Jordan toward the sunrise.<q class="end-double" qid="06001015.1" from="06001013.1" to="06001015.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">And they answered Joshua, <q class="begin-double" qid="06001016.1" from="06001016.1" to="06001018.1"/>All that you have commanded us we will do, and wherever you send us we will go.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001017"/>
    <verse num="17">Just as we obeyed Moses in all things, so we will obey you. Only may the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God <crossref let="v" cid="c06001017.1"/>be with you, as he was with Moses!</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06001018"/>
    <verse num="18">Whoever rebels against your commandment and disobeys your words, whatever you command him, shall be put to death. <crossref let="w" cid="c06001018.1"/>Only be strong and courageous.<q class="end-double" qid="06001018.1" from="06001016.1" to="06001018.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002001"/>
  <chapter num="2">
    <heading>Rahab Hides the Spies</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">And Joshua the son of Nun <crossref let="x" cid="c06002001.1"/>sent<note nid="n06002001.1"/> two men secretly from Shittim as spies, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="06002001.1" from="06002001.1" to="06002001.2"/>Go, view the land, especially Jericho.<q class="end-double" qid="06002001.2" from="06002001.1" to="06002001.2"/> And they went and came into the house of <crossref let="y" cid="c06002001.2"/>a prostitute whose name was <crossref let="z" cid="c06002001.3"/>Rahab and lodged there.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002002"/>
    <verse num="2">And it was told to the king of Jericho, <q class="begin-double" qid="06002002.1" from="06002002.1" to="06002002.2"/>Behold, men of Israel have come here tonight to search out the land.<q class="end-double" qid="06002002.2" from="06002002.1" to="06002002.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002003"/>
    <verse num="3">Then the king of Jericho sent to Rahab, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="06002003.1" from="06002003.1" to="06002003.2"/>Bring out the men who have come to you, who entered your house, for they have come to search out all the land.<q class="end-double" qid="06002003.2" from="06002003.1" to="06002003.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002004"/>
    <verse num="4">But the woman had taken the two men and hidden them. And she said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06002004.1" from="06002004.1" to="06002005.1"/>True, the men came to me, but I did not know where they were from.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002005"/>
    <verse num="5">And when the gate was about to be closed at dark, the men went out. I do not know where the men went. Pursue them quickly, for you will overtake them.<q class="end-double" qid="06002005.1" from="06002004.1" to="06002005.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002006"/>
    <verse num="6">But she had brought them up to the roof and hid them with the stalks of flax that she had laid in order on the roof.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002007"/>
    <verse num="7">So the men pursued after them on the way to the Jordan <crossref let="a" cid="c06002007.1"/>as far as the fords. And the gate was shut as soon as the pursuers had gone out.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">Before the men<note nid="n06002008.1"/> lay down, she came up to them on the roof</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002009"/>
    <verse num="9">and said to the men, <q class="begin-double" qid="06002009.1" from="06002009.1" to="06002013.1"/>I know that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has given you the land, <crossref let="b" cid="c06002009.1"/>and that the fear of you has fallen upon us, and that all the inhabitants of the land <crossref let="c" cid="c06002009.2"/>melt away before you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002010"/>
    <verse num="10">For we have heard how the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="d" cid="c06002010.1"/>dried up the water of the Red Sea before you when you came out of Egypt, and <crossref let="e" cid="c06002010.2"/>what you did to the two kings of the Amorites who were beyond the Jordan, to <crossref let="f" cid="c06002010.3"/>Sihon and Og, whom you devoted to destruction.<note nid="n06002010.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002011"/>
    <verse num="11">And <crossref let="g" cid="c06002011.1"/>as soon as we heard it, <crossref let="h" cid="c06002011.2"/>our hearts melted, and there was no spirit left in any man because of you, for <crossref let="i" cid="c06002011.3"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God, he is God in the heavens above and on the earth beneath.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002012"/>
    <verse num="12">Now then, please swear to me by the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> that, as I have dealt kindly with you, you also will deal kindly with my father&apos;s house, and <crossref let="j" cid="c06002012.1"/>give me a sure sign</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002013"/>
    <verse num="13">that you will save alive my father and mother, my brothers and sisters, and all who belong to them, and deliver our lives from death.<q class="end-double" qid="06002013.1" from="06002009.1" to="06002013.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002014"/>
    <verse num="14">And the men said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="06002014.1" from="06002014.1" to="06002014.2"/>Our life for yours even to death! If you do not tell this business of ours, then when the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gives us the land <crossref let="k" cid="c06002014.1"/>we will deal kindly and faithfully with you.<q class="end-double" qid="06002014.2" from="06002014.1" to="06002014.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">Then she <crossref let="l" cid="c06002015.1"/>let them down by a rope through the window, for her house was built into the city wall, so that she lived in the wall.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002016"/>
    <verse num="16">And she said<note nid="n06002016.1"/> to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="06002016.1" from="06002016.1" to="06002016.2"/>Go into the hills, or the pursuers will encounter you, and hide there three days until the pursuers have returned. Then afterward you may go your way.<q class="end-double" qid="06002016.2" from="06002016.1" to="06002016.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002017"/>
    <verse num="17">The men said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="06002017.1" from="06002017.1" to="06002020.1"/>We will be guiltless with respect to this oath of yours that you have made us swear.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002018"/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="m" cid="c06002018.1"/>Behold, when we come into the land, you shall tie this scarlet cord in the window through which you let us down, <crossref let="n" cid="c06002018.2"/>and you shall gather into your house your father and mother, your brothers, and all your father&apos;s household.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002019"/>
    <verse num="19">Then if anyone goes out of the doors of your house into the street, <crossref let="o" cid="c06002019.1"/>his blood shall be on his own head, and we shall be guiltless. But if a hand is laid on anyone who is with you in the house, his blood shall be on our head.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002020"/>
    <verse num="20">But if you <crossref let="p" cid="c06002020.1"/>tell this business of ours, then we shall be guiltless with respect to your oath that you have made us swear.<q class="end-double" qid="06002020.1" from="06002017.1" to="06002020.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002021"/>
    <verse num="21">And she said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06002021.1" from="06002021.1" to="06002021.2"/>According to your words, so be it.<q class="end-double" qid="06002021.2" from="06002021.1" to="06002021.2"/> Then she sent them away, and they departed. And she tied the scarlet cord in the window.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">They departed and went into the hills and remained there three days until the pursuers returned, and the pursuers searched all along the way and found nothing.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002023"/>
    <verse num="23">Then the two men returned. They came down from the hills and <crossref let="q" cid="c06002023.1"/>passed over and came to Joshua the son of Nun, and they told him all that had happened to them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06002024"/>
    <verse num="24">And they said to Joshua, <q class="begin-double" qid="06002024.1" from="06002024.1" to="06002024.2"/>Truly <crossref let="r" cid="c06002024.1"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has given all the land into our hands. And also, all the inhabitants of the land <crossref let="s" cid="c06002024.2"/>melt away because of us.<q class="end-double" qid="06002024.2" from="06002024.1" to="06002024.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003001"/>
  <chapter num="3">
    <heading>Israel Crosses the Jordan</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Then Joshua rose early in the morning and they set out <crossref let="t" cid="c06003001.1"/>from Shittim. And they came to the Jordan, he and all the people of Israel, and lodged there before they passed over.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="u" cid="c06003002.1"/>At the end of three days the officers went through the camp</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003003"/>
    <verse num="3">and commanded the people, <q class="begin-double" qid="06003003.1" from="06003003.1" to="06003004.1"/>As soon as you see the ark of the covenant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God being carried by <crossref let="v" cid="c06003003.1"/>the Levitical priests, then you shall set out from your place and follow it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="w" cid="c06003004.1"/>Yet there shall be a distance between you and it, about 2,000 cubits<note nid="n06003004.1"/> in length. Do not come near it, in order that you may know the way you shall go, for you have not passed this way before.<q class="end-double" qid="06003004.1" from="06003003.1" to="06003004.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003005"/>
    <verse num="5">Then Joshua said to the people, <crossref let="x" cid="c06003005.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06003005.1" from="06003005.1" to="06003005.2"/>Consecrate yourselves, for tomorrow the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will do wonders among you.<q class="end-double" qid="06003005.2" from="06003005.1" to="06003005.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003006"/>
    <verse num="6">And Joshua said to the priests, <crossref let="y" cid="c06003006.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06003006.1" from="06003006.1" to="06003006.2"/>Take up the ark of the covenant and pass on before the people.<q class="end-double" qid="06003006.2" from="06003006.1" to="06003006.2"/> So they took up the ark of the covenant and went before the people.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua, <q class="begin-double" qid="06003007.1" from="06003007.1" to="06003008.3"/>Today I will begin to <crossref let="z" cid="c06003007.1"/>exalt you in the sight of all Israel, that they may know that, <crossref let="a" cid="c06003007.2"/>as I was with Moses, so I will be with you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003008"/>
    <verse num="8">And as for you, command <crossref let="b" cid="c06003008.1"/>the priests who bear the ark of the covenant, <q class="begin-single" qid="06003008.1" from="06003008.1" to="06003008.2"/>When you come to the brink of the waters of the Jordan, <crossref let="c" cid="c06003008.2"/>you shall stand still in the Jordan.<q class="end-single" qid="06003008.2" from="06003008.1" to="06003008.2"/><q class="end-double" qid="06003008.3" from="06003007.1" to="06003008.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003009"/>
    <verse num="9">And Joshua said to the people of Israel, <q class="begin-double" qid="06003009.1" from="06003009.1" to="06003009.2"/>Come here and listen to the words of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.<q class="end-double" qid="06003009.2" from="06003009.1" to="06003009.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003010"/>
    <verse num="10">And Joshua said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06003010.1" from="06003010.1" to="06003013.1"/>Here is how you shall know that <crossref let="d" cid="c06003010.1"/>the living God is among you and that he will without fail <crossref let="e" cid="c06003010.2"/>drive out from before you the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Hivites, the Perizzites, the Girgashites, the Amorites, and the Jebusites.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003011"/>
    <verse num="11">Behold, the ark of the covenant of <crossref let="f" cid="c06003011.1"/>the Lord of all the earth<note nid="n06003011.1"/> <crossref let="g" cid="c06003011.2"/>is passing over before you into the Jordan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003012"/>
    <verse num="12">Now therefore <crossref let="h" cid="c06003012.1"/>take twelve men from the tribes of Israel, <crossref let="i" cid="c06003012.2"/>from each tribe a man.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003013"/>
    <verse num="13">And <crossref let="j" cid="c06003013.1"/>when the soles of the feet of the priests bearing the ark of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="f" cid="c06003013.2"/>the Lord of all the earth, shall rest in the waters of the Jordan, the waters of the Jordan shall be cut off from flowing, and the waters coming down from above shall <crossref let="k" cid="c06003013.3"/>stand in one heap.<q class="end-double" qid="06003013.1" from="06003010.1" to="06003013.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14">So when the people set out from their tents to pass over the Jordan with the priests bearing <crossref let="l" cid="c06003014.1"/>the ark of the covenant before the people,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003015"/>
    <verse num="15">and as soon as those bearing the ark had come as far as the Jordan, and <crossref let="m" cid="c06003015.1"/>the feet of the priests bearing the ark were dipped in the brink of the water (now <crossref let="n" cid="c06003015.2"/>the Jordan overflows all its banks <crossref let="o" cid="c06003015.3"/>throughout the time of harvest),</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003016"/>
    <verse num="16">the waters coming down from above stood and rose up in a heap very far away, at Adam, the city that is beside <crossref let="p" cid="c06003016.1"/>Zarethan, and those flowing down toward the Sea of <crossref let="q" cid="c06003016.2"/>the Arabah, <crossref let="r" cid="c06003016.3"/>the Salt Sea, were completely cut off. And the people passed over opposite Jericho.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06003017"/>
    <verse num="17">Now the priests bearing the ark of the covenant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> stood firmly on dry ground in the midst of the Jordan, <crossref let="s" cid="c06003017.1"/>and all Israel was passing over on dry ground until all the nation finished passing over the Jordan.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004001"/>
  <chapter num="4">
    <heading>Twelve Memorial Stones from the Jordan</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">When all the nation had finished passing <crossref let="t" cid="c06004001.1"/>over the Jordan, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="u" cid="c06004002.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06004002.1" from="06004002.1" to="06004003.3"/>Take twelve men from the people, from each tribe a man,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004003"/>
    <verse num="3">and command them, saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="06004003.1" from="06004003.1" to="06004003.2"/>Take <crossref let="v" cid="c06004003.1"/>twelve stones from here out of the midst of the Jordan, from the very place <crossref let="w" cid="c06004003.2"/>where the priests&apos; feet stood firmly, and bring them over with you and lay them down in <crossref let="x" cid="c06004003.3"/>the place where you lodge tonight.<q class="end-single" qid="06004003.2" from="06004003.1" to="06004003.2"/><q class="end-double" qid="06004003.3" from="06004002.1" to="06004003.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004004"/>
    <verse num="4">Then Joshua called the twelve men from the people of Israel, whom he had appointed, a man from each tribe.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004005"/>
    <verse num="5">And Joshua said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="06004005.1" from="06004005.1" to="06004007.1"/>Pass on before the ark of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God into the midst of the Jordan, and take up each of you a stone upon his shoulder, according to the number of the tribes of the people of Israel,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004006"/>
    <verse num="6">that this may be a sign among you. <crossref let="y" cid="c06004006.1"/>When your children ask in time to come, <q class="begin-single" qid="06004006.1" from="06004006.1" to="06004006.2"/>What do those stones mean to you?<q class="end-single" qid="06004006.2" from="06004006.1" to="06004006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004007"/>
    <verse num="7">then you shall tell them that <crossref let="z" cid="c06004007.1"/>the waters of the Jordan were cut off before the ark of the covenant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. When it passed over the Jordan, the waters of the Jordan were cut off. So these stones shall be to the people of Israel <crossref let="a" cid="c06004007.2"/>a memorial forever.<q class="end-double" qid="06004007.1" from="06004005.1" to="06004007.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">And the people of Israel did just as Joshua commanded and took up twelve stones out of the midst of the Jordan, according to the number of the tribes of the people of Israel, just as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> told Joshua. And they carried them over with them to the place where they lodged and laid them down<note nid="n06004008.1"/> there.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004009"/>
    <verse num="9">And Joshua set up<note nid="n06004009.1"/> twelve stones in the midst of the Jordan, <crossref let="b" cid="c06004009.1"/>in the place where the feet of the priests bearing the ark of the covenant had stood; and they are there to this day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004010"/>
    <verse num="10">For the priests bearing the ark stood in the midst of the Jordan until everything was finished that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Joshua to tell the people, according to all that Moses had commanded Joshua.
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-paragraph/>The people passed over in haste.
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004011"/>
    <verse num="11">And when all the people had finished passing over, the ark of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and the priests passed over before the people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004012"/>
    <verse num="12">The sons of Reuben and the sons of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh <crossref let="c" cid="c06004012.1"/>passed over armed before the people of Israel, as Moses had told them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004013"/>
    <verse num="13">About 40,000 ready for war passed over before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for battle, to the plains of Jericho.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004014"/>
    <verse num="14">On that day the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="d" cid="c06004014.1"/>exalted Joshua in the sight of all Israel, and they stood in awe of him just as they had stood in awe of Moses, all the days of his life.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004016"/>
    <verse num="16"><q class="begin-double" qid="06004016.1" from="06004016.1" to="06004016.2"/>Command the priests bearing <crossref let="e" cid="c06004016.1"/>the ark of the testimony to come up out of the Jordan.<q class="end-double" qid="06004016.2" from="06004016.1" to="06004016.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004017"/>
    <verse num="17">So Joshua commanded the priests, <q class="begin-double" qid="06004017.1" from="06004017.1" to="06004017.2"/>Come up out of the Jordan.<q class="end-double" qid="06004017.2" from="06004017.1" to="06004017.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004018"/>
    <verse num="18">And when the priests bearing the ark of the covenant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> came up from the midst of the Jordan, and the soles of the priests&apos; feet were lifted up on dry ground, the waters of the Jordan returned to their place and overflowed all its banks, <crossref let="f" cid="c06004018.1"/>as before.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19">The people came up out of the Jordan on the tenth day of the first month, and they encamped at <crossref let="g" cid="c06004019.1"/>Gilgal on the east border of Jericho.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004020"/>
    <verse num="20">And <crossref let="h" cid="c06004020.1"/>those twelve stones, which they took out of the Jordan, Joshua set up at Gilgal.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004021"/>
    <verse num="21">And he said to the people of Israel, <crossref let="i" cid="c06004021.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06004021.1" from="06004021.1" to="06004024.1"/>When your children ask their fathers in times to come, <q class="begin-single" qid="06004021.2" from="06004021.2" to="06004021.3"/>What do these stones mean?<q class="end-single" qid="06004021.3" from="06004021.2" to="06004021.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004022"/>
    <verse num="22">then you shall let your children know, <crossref let="j" cid="c06004022.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="06004022.1" from="06004022.1" to="06004022.2"/>Israel passed over this Jordan on dry ground.<q class="end-single" qid="06004022.2" from="06004022.1" to="06004022.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004023"/>
    <verse num="23">For the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God dried up the waters of the Jordan for you until you passed over, as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God did to the Red Sea, <crossref let="k" cid="c06004023.1"/>which he dried up for us until we passed over,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06004024"/>
    <verse num="24"><crossref let="l" cid="c06004024.1"/>so that all the peoples of the earth may know that the hand of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is <crossref let="m" cid="c06004024.2"/>mighty, that you may <crossref let="n" cid="c06004024.3"/>fear the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God forever.<q class="end-double" qid="06004024.1" from="06004021.1" to="06004024.1"/><note nid="n06004024.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005001"/>
  <chapter num="5">
    <heading>The New Generation Circumcised</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">As soon as all the kings of the Amorites who were beyond the Jordan to the west, and all the kings of the Canaanites <crossref let="o" cid="c06005001.1"/>who were by the sea, <crossref let="p" cid="c06005001.2"/>heard that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had dried up the waters of the Jordan for the people of Israel until they had crossed over, their hearts <crossref let="q" cid="c06005001.3"/>melted and <crossref let="r" cid="c06005001.4"/>there was no longer any spirit in them because of the people of Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005002"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="2">At that time the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua, <q class="begin-double" qid="06005002.1" from="06005002.1" to="06005002.2"/>Make <crossref let="s" cid="c06005002.1"/>flint knives and circumcise the sons of Israel a second time.<q class="end-double" qid="06005002.2" from="06005002.1" to="06005002.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005003"/>
    <verse num="3">So Joshua made flint knives and circumcised the sons of Israel at Gibeath-haaraloth.<note nid="n06005003.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005004"/>
    <verse num="4">And this is the reason why Joshua circumcised them: <crossref let="t" cid="c06005004.1"/>all the males of the people who came out of Egypt, all the men of war, had died in the wilderness on the way after they had come out of Egypt.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005005"/>
    <verse num="5">Though all the people who came out had been circumcised, yet all the people who were born on the way in the wilderness after they had come out of Egypt had not been circumcised.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005006"/>
    <verse num="6">For the people of Israel walked <crossref let="u" cid="c06005006.1"/>forty years in the wilderness, until all the nation, the men of war who came out of Egypt, perished, because they did not obey the voice of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>; the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="v" cid="c06005006.2"/>swore to them that he would not let them see the land that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had sworn to their fathers to give to us, <crossref let="w" cid="c06005006.3"/>a land flowing with milk and honey.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005007"/>
    <verse num="7">So it was <crossref let="x" cid="c06005007.1"/>their children, whom he raised up in their place, that Joshua circumcised. For they were uncircumcised, because they had not been circumcised on the way.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">When the circumcising of the whole nation was finished, they remained in their places in the camp until they were healed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005009"/>
    <verse num="9">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua, <q class="begin-double" qid="06005009.1" from="06005009.1" to="06005009.2"/>Today I have rolled away the <crossref let="y" cid="c06005009.1"/>reproach of Egypt from you.<q class="end-double" qid="06005009.2" from="06005009.1" to="06005009.2"/> And so the name of that place is called <crossref let="z" cid="c06005009.2"/>Gilgal<note nid="n06005009.1"/> to this day.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005010"/>
    <heading>First Passover in Canaan</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">While the people of Israel were encamped at Gilgal, they kept the Passover <crossref let="a" cid="c06005010.1"/>on the fourteenth day of the month in the evening on the plains of Jericho.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005011"/>
    <verse num="11">And the day after the Passover, on that very day, they ate of the produce of the land, unleavened cakes and parched grain.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005012"/>
    <verse num="12">And <crossref let="b" cid="c06005012.1"/>the manna ceased the day after they ate of the produce of the land. And there was no longer manna for the people of Israel, but they ate of the fruit of the land of Canaan that year.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005013"/>
    <heading>The Commander of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s Army</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">When Joshua was by Jericho, he lifted up his eyes and looked, and behold, <crossref let="c" cid="c06005013.1"/>a man was standing before him <crossref let="d" cid="c06005013.2"/>with his drawn sword in his hand. And Joshua went to him and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="06005013.1" from="06005013.1" to="06005013.2"/>Are you for us, or for our adversaries?<q class="end-double" qid="06005013.2" from="06005013.1" to="06005013.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005014"/>
    <verse num="14">And he said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06005014.1" from="06005014.1" to="06005014.2"/>No; but I am the commander of the army of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. Now I have come.<q class="end-double" qid="06005014.2" from="06005014.1" to="06005014.2"/> And Joshua <crossref let="e" cid="c06005014.1"/>fell on his face to the earth and worshiped<note nid="n06005014.1"/> and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="06005014.3" from="06005014.3" to="06005014.4"/>What does my lord say to his servant?<q class="end-double" qid="06005014.4" from="06005014.3" to="06005014.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06005015"/>
    <verse num="15">And the commander of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s army said to Joshua, <crossref let="f" cid="c06005015.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06005015.1" from="06005015.1" to="06005015.2"/>Take off your sandals from your feet, for the place where you are standing is holy.<q class="end-double" qid="06005015.2" from="06005015.1" to="06005015.2"/> And Joshua did so.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006001"/>
  <chapter num="6">
    <heading>The Fall of Jericho</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Now Jericho was shut up inside and outside because of the people of Israel. None went out, and none came in.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006002"/>
    <verse num="2">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua, <q class="begin-double" qid="06006002.1" from="06006002.1" to="06006005.1"/>See, <crossref let="g" cid="c06006002.1"/>I have given Jericho into your hand, with its king and mighty men of valor.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006003"/>
    <verse num="3">You shall march around the city, all the men of war going around the city once. Thus shall you do for six days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006004"/>
    <verse num="4">Seven priests shall bear seven <crossref let="h" cid="c06006004.1"/>trumpets of <crossref let="i" cid="c06006004.2"/>rams&apos; horns before the ark. On the seventh day you shall march around the city seven times, and <crossref let="j" cid="c06006004.3"/>the priests shall blow the trumpets.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006005"/>
    <verse num="5">And when they make a long blast with the ram&apos;s horn, when you hear the sound of the trumpet, then all the people shall shout with a great shout, and the wall of the city will fall down flat,<note nid="n06006005.1"/> and the people shall go up, everyone straight before him.<q class="end-double" qid="06006005.1" from="06006002.1" to="06006005.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006006"/>
    <verse num="6">So Joshua the son of Nun called the priests and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="06006006.1" from="06006006.1" to="06006006.2"/>Take up the ark of the covenant and let seven priests bear seven trumpets of rams&apos; horns before the ark of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="06006006.2" from="06006006.1" to="06006006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006007"/>
    <verse num="7">And he said to the people, <q class="begin-double" qid="06006007.1" from="06006007.1" to="06006007.2"/>Go forward. March around the city and let <crossref let="k" cid="c06006007.1"/>the armed men pass on before the ark of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="06006007.2" from="06006007.1" to="06006007.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">And just as Joshua had commanded the people, the seven priests bearing the seven trumpets of rams&apos; horns before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> went forward, blowing the trumpets, with the ark of the covenant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> following them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006009"/>
    <verse num="9">The armed men were walking before the priests who were blowing the trumpets, and the <crossref let="l" cid="c06006009.1"/>rear guard was walking after the ark, while the trumpets blew continually.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006010"/>
    <verse num="10">But Joshua commanded the people, <q class="begin-double" qid="06006010.1" from="06006010.1" to="06006010.2"/>You shall not shout or make your voice heard, neither shall any word go out of your mouth, until the day I tell you to shout. Then you shall shout.<q class="end-double" qid="06006010.2" from="06006010.1" to="06006010.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006011"/>
    <verse num="11">So he caused the ark of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to circle the city, going about it once. And they came into the camp and spent the night in the camp.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">Then Joshua rose early in the morning, and <crossref let="m" cid="c06006012.1"/>the priests took up the ark of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006013"/>
    <verse num="13">And the seven priests bearing the seven trumpets of rams&apos; horns before the ark of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> walked on, and they blew the trumpets continually. And the armed men were walking before them, and the rear guard was walking after the ark of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, while the trumpets blew continually.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006014"/>
    <verse num="14">And the second day they marched around the city once, and returned into the camp. So they did for six days.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">On the seventh day they rose early, at the dawn of day, and marched around the city in the same manner seven times. It was only on that day that they marched around the city seven times.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006016"/>
    <verse num="16">And at the seventh time, when the priests had blown the trumpets, Joshua said to the people, <q class="begin-double" qid="06006016.1" from="06006016.1" to="06006019.1"/>Shout, for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has given you the city.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006017"/>
    <verse num="17">And the city and all that is within it shall be <crossref let="n" cid="c06006017.1"/>devoted to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for destruction.<note nid="n06006017.1"/> Only Rahab the prostitute and all who are with her in her house shall live, because she <crossref let="o" cid="c06006017.2"/>hid the messengers whom we sent.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006018"/>
    <verse num="18">But you, keep yourselves from the things devoted to destruction, lest when you have devoted them you take any of the devoted things and make the camp of Israel <crossref let="p" cid="c06006018.1"/>a thing for destruction and <crossref let="q" cid="c06006018.2"/>bring trouble upon it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006019"/>
    <verse num="19">But all silver and gold, and every vessel of bronze and iron, are holy to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>; they shall go into the treasury of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="06006019.1" from="06006016.1" to="06006019.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006020"/>
    <verse num="20">So the people shouted, and the trumpets were blown. As soon as the people heard the sound of the trumpet, the people shouted a great shout, and <crossref let="r" cid="c06006020.1"/>the wall fell down flat, so that the people went up into the city, every man straight before him, and they captured the city.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006021"/>
    <verse num="21">Then they <crossref let="s" cid="c06006021.1"/>devoted all in the city to destruction, both men and women, young and old, oxen, sheep, and donkeys, with the edge of the sword.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">But to the two men who had spied out the land, Joshua said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06006022.1" from="06006022.1" to="06006022.2"/>Go into the prostitute&apos;s house and bring out from there the woman and all who belong to her, <crossref let="t" cid="c06006022.1"/>as you swore to her.<q class="end-double" qid="06006022.2" from="06006022.1" to="06006022.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006023"/>
    <verse num="23">So the young men who had been spies went in and brought out Rahab and <crossref let="u" cid="c06006023.1"/>her father and mother and brothers and all who belonged to her. And they brought all her relatives and put them outside the camp of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006024"/>
    <verse num="24">And they burned the city with fire, and everything in it. <crossref let="v" cid="c06006024.1"/>Only the silver and gold, and the vessels of bronze and of iron, they put into the treasury of the house of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006025"/>
    <verse num="25">But Rahab the prostitute and her father&apos;s household and all who belonged to her, Joshua saved alive. And <crossref let="w" cid="c06006025.1"/>she has lived in Israel to this day, because she hid the messengers whom Joshua sent to spy out Jericho.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006026"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="26">Joshua laid an oath on them at that time, saying, <crossref let="x" cid="c06006026.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06006026.1" from="06006026.1" to="06006026.3"/>Cursed before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> be the man who rises up and rebuilds this city, Jericho.
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
        <begin-line/><q class="continue-double" qid="06006026.2" from="06006026.1" to="06006026.3"/>At the cost of his firstborn<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>shall he lay its foundation,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line/>and at the cost of his youngest son<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>shall he set up its gates.<q class="end-double" qid="06006026.3" from="06006026.1" to="06006026.3"/><end-line/>
    </verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <end-block-indent/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06006027"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="27"><crossref let="y" cid="c06006027.1"/>So the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> was with Joshua, and <crossref let="z" cid="c06006027.2"/>his fame was in all the land.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007001"/>
  <chapter num="7">
    <heading>Israel Defeated at Ai</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">But the people of Israel broke faith in regard to the devoted things, for <crossref let="a" cid="c06007001.1"/>Achan the son of Carmi, son of Zabdi, son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, took some of the devoted things. And the anger of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> burned against the people of Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007002"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="2">Joshua sent men from Jericho to Ai, which is near <crossref let="b" cid="c06007002.1"/>Beth-aven, east of Bethel, and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="06007002.1" from="06007002.1" to="06007002.2"/>Go up and spy out the land.<q class="end-double" qid="06007002.2" from="06007002.1" to="06007002.2"/> And the men went up and spied out Ai.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007003"/>
    <verse num="3">And they returned to Joshua and said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="06007003.1" from="06007003.1" to="06007003.2"/>Do not have all the people go up, but let about two or three thousand men go up and attack Ai. Do not make the whole people toil up there, for they are few.<q class="end-double" qid="06007003.2" from="06007003.1" to="06007003.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007004"/>
    <verse num="4">So about three thousand men went up there from the people. And <crossref let="c" cid="c06007004.1"/>they fled before the men of Ai,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007005"/>
    <verse num="5">and the men of Ai killed about thirty-six of their men and chased them before the gate as far as Shebarim and struck them at the descent. And the hearts of the people <crossref let="d" cid="c06007005.1"/>melted and became as water.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6">Then Joshua <crossref let="e" cid="c06007006.1"/>tore his clothes and <crossref let="f" cid="c06007006.2"/>fell to the earth on his face before the ark of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> until the evening, he and the elders of Israel. And they put <crossref let="g" cid="c06007006.3"/>dust on their heads.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007007"/>
    <verse num="7">And Joshua said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06007007.1" from="06007007.1" to="06007009.1"/>Alas, O Lord <span class="divine-name">God</span>, <crossref let="h" cid="c06007007.1"/>why have you brought this people over the Jordan at all, to give us into the hands of the Amorites, to destroy us? Would that we had been content to dwell beyond the Jordan!</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007008"/>
    <verse num="8">O Lord, what can I say, when Israel has turned their backs before their enemies!</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007009"/>
    <verse num="9">For the Canaanites and all the inhabitants of the land will hear of it and will surround us and <crossref let="i" cid="c06007009.1"/>cut off our name from the earth. And what will you do for your great name?<q class="end-double" qid="06007009.1" from="06007007.1" to="06007009.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007010"/>
    <heading>The Sin of Achan</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua, <q class="begin-double" qid="06007010.1" from="06007010.1" to="06007015.2"/>Get up! Why have you fallen on your face?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007011"/>
    <verse num="11">Israel has sinned; they have <crossref let="j" cid="c06007011.1"/>transgressed my covenant that I commanded them; they have taken some of the <crossref let="k" cid="c06007011.2"/>devoted things; they have stolen and lied and put them among their own belongings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="l" cid="c06007012.1"/>Therefore the people of Israel cannot stand before their enemies. They <crossref let="m" cid="c06007012.2"/>turn their backs before their enemies, because they have become <crossref let="n" cid="c06007012.3"/>devoted for destruction.<note nid="n06007012.1"/> I will be with you no more, unless you destroy <crossref let="o" cid="c06007012.4"/>the devoted things from among you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007013"/>
    <verse num="13">Get up! Consecrate the people and say, <crossref let="p" cid="c06007013.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="06007013.1" from="06007013.1" to="06007015.1"/>Consecrate yourselves for tomorrow; for thus says the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, God of Israel, <q class="begin-inner-double" qid="06007013.2" from="06007013.2" to="06007013.3"/>There are devoted things in your midst, O Israel. You cannot stand before your enemies until you take away the devoted things from among you.<q class="end-inner-double" qid="06007013.3" from="06007013.2" to="06007013.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007014"/>
    <verse num="14">In the morning therefore you shall be brought near <crossref let="q" cid="c06007014.1"/>by your tribes. And the tribe that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> takes by lot shall come near by clans. And the clan that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> takes shall come near by households. And the household that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> takes shall come near man by man.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="r" cid="c06007015.1"/>And he who is taken with the devoted things shall be burned with fire, he and all that he has, because he has <crossref let="s" cid="c06007015.2"/>transgressed the covenant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and because he has done <crossref let="t" cid="c06007015.3"/>an outrageous thing in Israel.<q class="end-single" qid="06007015.1" from="06007013.1" to="06007015.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="06007015.2" from="06007010.1" to="06007015.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">So Joshua rose early in the morning and brought Israel near tribe by tribe, and the tribe of Judah was taken.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007017"/>
    <verse num="17">And he brought near the clans of Judah, and the clan of the <crossref let="u" cid="c06007017.1"/>Zerahites was taken. And he brought near the clan of the Zerahites man by man, and Zabdi was taken.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007018"/>
    <verse num="18">And he brought near his household man by man, and Achan the son of Carmi, son of Zabdi, son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, was taken.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007019"/>
    <verse num="19">Then Joshua said to Achan, <q class="begin-double" qid="06007019.1" from="06007019.1" to="06007019.2"/>My son, <crossref let="v" cid="c06007019.1"/>give glory to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God of Israel and <crossref let="w" cid="c06007019.2"/>give praise<note nid="n06007019.1"/> to him. And <crossref let="x" cid="c06007019.3"/>tell me now what you have done; do not hide it from me.<q class="end-double" qid="06007019.2" from="06007019.1" to="06007019.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007020"/>
    <verse num="20">And Achan answered Joshua, <q class="begin-double" qid="06007020.1" from="06007020.1" to="06007021.1"/>Truly <crossref let="y" cid="c06007020.1"/>I have sinned against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God of Israel, and this is what I did:</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007021"/>
    <verse num="21">when I saw among the spoil a beautiful cloak from Shinar, and 200 shekels of silver, and a bar of gold weighing 50 shekels,<note nid="n06007021.1"/> then I coveted them and took them. And see, they are hidden in the earth inside my tent, with the silver underneath.<q class="end-double" qid="06007021.1" from="06007020.1" to="06007021.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">So Joshua sent messengers, and they ran to the tent; and behold, it was hidden in his tent with the silver underneath.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007023"/>
    <verse num="23">And they took them out of the tent and brought them to Joshua and to all the people of Israel. And they laid them down before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007024"/>
    <verse num="24">And Joshua and all Israel with him took Achan the son of Zerah, and the silver and the cloak and the bar of gold, and his sons and daughters and his oxen and donkeys and sheep and his tent and all that he had. And they brought them up to the <crossref let="z" cid="c06007024.1"/>Valley of Achor.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007025"/>
    <verse num="25">And Joshua said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06007025.1" from="06007025.1" to="06007025.2"/>Why did you <crossref let="a" cid="c06007025.1"/>bring trouble on us? The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> brings trouble on you today.<q class="end-double" qid="06007025.2" from="06007025.1" to="06007025.2"/> And all Israel <crossref let="b" cid="c06007025.2"/>stoned him with stones. <crossref let="c" cid="c06007025.3"/>They burned them with fire and stoned them with stones.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06007026"/>
    <verse num="26">And they raised over him <crossref let="d" cid="c06007026.1"/>a great heap of stones that remains to this day. Then <crossref let="e" cid="c06007026.2"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> turned from his burning anger. Therefore, to this day the name of that place is called the Valley of Achor.<note nid="n06007026.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008001"/>
  <chapter num="8">
    <heading>The Fall of Ai</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua, <crossref let="f" cid="c06008001.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06008001.1" from="06008001.1" to="06008002.1"/>Do not fear and do not be dismayed. Take all the fighting men with you, and arise, go up to Ai. See, <crossref let="g" cid="c06008001.2"/>I have given into your hand the king of Ai, and his people, his city, and his land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008002"/>
    <verse num="2">And you shall do to Ai and its king as you did <crossref let="h" cid="c06008002.1"/>to Jericho and its king. Only <crossref let="i" cid="c06008002.2"/>its spoil and its livestock you shall take as plunder for yourselves. Lay an ambush against the city, behind it.<q class="end-double" qid="06008002.1" from="06008001.1" to="06008002.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008003"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3">So Joshua and all the fighting men arose to go up to Ai. And Joshua chose 30,000 mighty men of valor and sent them out by night.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008004"/>
    <verse num="4">And he commanded them, <q class="begin-double" qid="06008004.1" from="06008004.1" to="06008008.1"/>Behold, <crossref let="j" cid="c06008004.1"/>you shall lie in ambush against the city, behind it. Do not go very far from the city, but all of you remain ready.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008005"/>
    <verse num="5">And I and all the people who are with me will approach the city. And when they come out against us <crossref let="k" cid="c06008005.1"/>just as before, we shall flee before them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008006"/>
    <verse num="6">And they will come out after us, until we have <crossref let="l" cid="c06008006.1"/>drawn them away from the city. For they will say, <q class="begin-single" qid="06008006.1" from="06008006.1" to="06008006.2"/>They are fleeing from us, just as before.<q class="end-single" qid="06008006.2" from="06008006.1" to="06008006.2"/> So we will flee before them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008007"/>
    <verse num="7">Then you shall rise up from the ambush and seize the city, for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God will give it into your hand.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008008"/>
    <verse num="8">And as soon as you have taken the city, you shall set the city on fire. You shall do according to the word of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. <crossref let="m" cid="c06008008.1"/>See, I have commanded you.<q class="end-double" qid="06008008.1" from="06008004.1" to="06008008.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008009"/>
    <verse num="9">So Joshua sent them out. And they went to the place of ambush and lay between Bethel and Ai, to the west of Ai, but Joshua spent that night among the people.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">Joshua arose early in the morning and mustered the people and went up, he and the elders of Israel, before the people to Ai.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008011"/>
    <verse num="11">And <crossref let="n" cid="c06008011.1"/>all the fighting men who were with him went up and drew near before the city and encamped on the north side of Ai, with a ravine between them and Ai.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008012"/>
    <verse num="12">He took about 5,000 men and set them in ambush between Bethel and Ai, to the west of the city.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008013"/>
    <verse num="13">So they stationed the forces, the main encampment that was north of the city and its rear guard west of the city. But Joshua spent that night in the valley.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008014"/>
    <verse num="14">And as soon as the king of Ai saw this, he and all his people, the men of the city, hurried and went out early to the appointed place<note nid="n06008014.1"/> toward <crossref let="o" cid="c06008014.1"/>the Arabah to meet Israel in battle. <crossref let="p" cid="c06008014.2"/>But he did not know that there was an ambush against him behind the city.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008015"/>
    <verse num="15">And Joshua and all Israel <crossref let="q" cid="c06008015.1"/>pretended to be beaten before them and fled in the direction of the wilderness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008016"/>
    <verse num="16">So all the people who were in the city were called together to pursue them, and as they pursued Joshua they <crossref let="r" cid="c06008016.1"/>were drawn away from the city.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008017"/>
    <verse num="17">Not a man was left in Ai or Bethel who did not go out after Israel. They left the city open and pursued Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18">Then the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua, <crossref let="s" cid="c06008018.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06008018.1" from="06008018.1" to="06008018.2"/>Stretch out the javelin that is in your hand toward Ai, for I will give it into your hand.<q class="end-double" qid="06008018.2" from="06008018.1" to="06008018.2"/> And Joshua stretched out the javelin that was in his hand toward the city.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008019"/>
    <verse num="19">And the men in the ambush rose quickly out of their place, and as soon as he had stretched out his hand, they ran and entered the city and captured it. And they hurried to set the city on fire.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008020"/>
    <verse num="20">So when the men of Ai looked back, behold, the smoke of the city went up to heaven, and they had no power to flee this way or that, for the people who fled to the wilderness turned back against the pursuers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008021"/>
    <verse num="21">And when Joshua and all Israel saw that the ambush had captured the city, and that the smoke of the city went up, then they turned back and struck down the men of Ai.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008022"/>
    <verse num="22">And the others came out from the city against them, so they were in the midst of Israel, some on this side, and some on that side. And Israel struck them down, until there was <crossref let="t" cid="c06008022.1"/>left none that survived or escaped.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008023"/>
    <verse num="23">But the king of Ai they took alive, and brought him near to Joshua.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008024"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24">When Israel had finished killing all the inhabitants of Ai in the open wilderness where they pursued them, and all of them to the very last had fallen by the edge of the sword, all Israel returned to Ai and struck it down with the edge of the sword.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008025"/>
    <verse num="25">And all who fell that day, both men and women, were 12,000, all the people of Ai.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008026"/>
    <verse num="26">But Joshua did not draw back his hand with which he <crossref let="u" cid="c06008026.1"/>stretched out the javelin until he had devoted all the inhabitants of Ai to destruction.<note nid="n06008026.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008027"/>
    <verse num="27">Only the livestock and the spoil of that city Israel took as their plunder, according to the word of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> that he <crossref let="v" cid="c06008027.1"/>commanded Joshua.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008028"/>
    <verse num="28">So Joshua burned Ai and made it forever a <crossref let="w" cid="c06008028.1"/>heap of ruins, as it is to this day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008029"/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="x" cid="c06008029.1"/>And he hanged the king of Ai on a tree until evening. <crossref let="y" cid="c06008029.2"/>And at sunset Joshua commanded, and they took his body down from the tree and threw it at the entrance of the gate of the city and <crossref let="z" cid="c06008029.3"/>raised over it a great heap of stones, which stands there to this day.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008030"/>
    <heading>Joshua Renews the Covenant</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="30">At that time Joshua built an altar to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, <crossref let="a" cid="c06008030.1"/>on Mount Ebal,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008031"/>
    <verse num="31">just as Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had commanded the people of Israel, as it is written in the Book of the Law of Moses, <q class="begin-double" qid="06008031.1" from="06008031.1" to="06008031.2"/>an altar of uncut stones, upon which no man has wielded an iron tool.<q class="end-double" qid="06008031.2" from="06008031.1" to="06008031.2"/> And they offered on it burnt offerings to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and sacrificed peace offerings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008032"/>
    <verse num="32">And there, in the presence of the people of Israel, he wrote on <crossref let="b" cid="c06008032.1"/>the stones a copy of the law of Moses, which he had written.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008033"/>
    <verse num="33">And all Israel, <crossref let="c" cid="c06008033.1"/>sojourner as well as native born, with their elders and officers and their judges, stood on opposite sides of the ark before the Levitical priests <crossref let="d" cid="c06008033.2"/>who carried the ark of the covenant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, half of them in front of Mount Gerizim and half of them in front of Mount Ebal, <crossref let="e" cid="c06008033.3"/>just as Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had commanded at the first, to bless the people of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008034"/>
    <verse num="34">And afterward <crossref let="f" cid="c06008034.1"/>he read all the words of the law, <crossref let="g" cid="c06008034.2"/>the blessing and the curse, according to all that is written in the Book of the Law.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06008035"/>
    <verse num="35">There was not a word of all that Moses commanded that Joshua did not read before all the assembly of Israel, <crossref let="h" cid="c06008035.1"/>and the women, and the little ones, and <crossref let="i" cid="c06008035.2"/>the sojourners who lived<note nid="n06008035.1"/> among them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009001"/>
  <chapter num="9">
    <heading>The Gibeonite Deception</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">As soon as all the kings who were beyond the Jordan <crossref let="j" cid="c06009001.1"/>in the hill country and in the lowland all along the coast <crossref let="k" cid="c06009001.2"/>of the Great Sea toward Lebanon, <crossref let="l" cid="c06009001.3"/>the Hittites, the Amorites, the Canaanites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites, heard of this,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009002"/>
    <verse num="2">they gathered together as one to fight against Joshua and Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009003"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3">But when the inhabitants of <crossref let="m" cid="c06009003.1"/>Gibeon heard what Joshua had done <crossref let="n" cid="c06009003.2"/>to Jericho and <crossref let="o" cid="c06009003.3"/>to Ai,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009004"/>
    <verse num="4">they on their part acted with cunning and went and made ready provisions and took worn-out sacks for their donkeys, and wineskins, worn-out and torn and mended,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009005"/>
    <verse num="5">with worn-out, patched sandals on their feet, and worn-out clothes. And all their provisions were dry and crumbly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009006"/>
    <verse num="6">And they went to Joshua in <crossref let="p" cid="c06009006.1"/>the camp at Gilgal and said to him and to the men of Israel, <q class="begin-double" qid="06009006.1" from="06009006.1" to="06009006.2"/>We have come from a distant country, so now make a covenant with us.<q class="end-double" qid="06009006.2" from="06009006.1" to="06009006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009007"/>
    <verse num="7">But the men of Israel said to <crossref let="q" cid="c06009007.1"/>the Hivites, <q class="begin-double" qid="06009007.1" from="06009007.1" to="06009007.2"/>Perhaps you live among us; then <crossref let="r" cid="c06009007.2"/>how can we make a covenant with you?<q class="end-double" qid="06009007.2" from="06009007.1" to="06009007.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009008"/>
    <verse num="8">They said to Joshua, <crossref let="s" cid="c06009008.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06009008.1" from="06009008.1" to="06009008.2"/>We are your servants.<q class="end-double" qid="06009008.2" from="06009008.1" to="06009008.2"/> And Joshua said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="06009008.3" from="06009008.3" to="06009008.4"/>Who are you? And where do you come from?<q class="end-double" qid="06009008.4" from="06009008.3" to="06009008.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009009"/>
    <verse num="9">They said to him, <crossref let="t" cid="c06009009.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06009009.1" from="06009009.1" to="06009013.1"/>From a very distant country your servants have come, because of the name of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God. <crossref let="u" cid="c06009009.2"/>For we have heard a report of him, and all that he did in Egypt,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="v" cid="c06009010.1"/>and all that he did to the two kings of the Amorites who were beyond the Jordan, to Sihon the king of Heshbon, and to Og king of Bashan, who lived in <crossref let="w" cid="c06009010.2"/>Ashtaroth.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009011"/>
    <verse num="11">So our elders and all the inhabitants of our country said to us, <q class="begin-single" qid="06009011.1" from="06009011.1" to="06009011.4"/>Take provisions in your hand for the journey and go to meet them and say to them, <q class="begin-inner-double" qid="06009011.2" from="06009011.2" to="06009011.3"/>We are your servants. Come now, make a covenant with us.<q class="end-inner-double" qid="06009011.3" from="06009011.2" to="06009011.3"/><q class="end-single" qid="06009011.4" from="06009011.1" to="06009011.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009012"/>
    <verse num="12">Here is our bread. It was still warm when we took it from our houses as our food for the journey on the day we set out to come to you, but now, behold, it is dry and crumbly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009013"/>
    <verse num="13">These wineskins were new when we filled them, and behold, they have burst. And these garments and sandals of ours are worn out from the very long journey.<q class="end-double" qid="06009013.1" from="06009009.1" to="06009013.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009014"/>
    <verse num="14">So the men took some of their provisions, but <crossref let="x" cid="c06009014.1"/>did not ask counsel from the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009015"/>
    <verse num="15">And Joshua <crossref let="y" cid="c06009015.1"/>made peace with them and made a covenant with them, to let them live, and the leaders of the congregation swore to them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">At the end of three days after they had made a covenant with them, they heard that they were their neighbors <crossref let="z" cid="c06009016.1"/>and that they lived among them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009017"/>
    <verse num="17">And the people of Israel set out and reached their cities on the third day. <crossref let="a" cid="c06009017.1"/>Now their cities were Gibeon, Chephirah, Beeroth, and Kiriath-jearim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009018"/>
    <verse num="18">But the people of Israel did not attack them, because the leaders of the congregation had sworn to them by the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel. Then all the congregation murmured against the leaders.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009019"/>
    <verse num="19">But all the leaders said to all the congregation, <q class="begin-double" qid="06009019.1" from="06009019.1" to="06009020.1"/>We have sworn to them by the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, and now we may not touch them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009020"/>
    <verse num="20">This we will do to them: let them live, lest <crossref let="b" cid="c06009020.1"/>wrath be upon us, <crossref let="c" cid="c06009020.2"/>because of the oath that we swore to them.<q class="end-double" qid="06009020.1" from="06009019.1" to="06009020.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009021"/>
    <verse num="21">And the leaders said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="06009021.1" from="06009021.1" to="06009021.2"/>Let them live.<q class="end-double" qid="06009021.2" from="06009021.1" to="06009021.2"/> So they became <crossref let="d" cid="c06009021.1"/>cutters of wood and drawers of water for all the congregation, just as the leaders <crossref let="e" cid="c06009021.2"/>had said of them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">Joshua summoned them, and he said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="06009022.1" from="06009022.1" to="06009023.1"/>Why did you deceive us, saying, <crossref let="f" cid="c06009022.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="06009022.2" from="06009022.2" to="06009022.3"/>We are very far from you,<q class="end-single" qid="06009022.3" from="06009022.2" to="06009022.3"/> when <crossref let="g" cid="c06009022.2"/>you dwell among us?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009023"/>
    <verse num="23">Now therefore you are cursed, and some of you shall never be anything but servants, <crossref let="h" cid="c06009023.1"/>cutters of wood and drawers of water for the house of my God.<q class="end-double" qid="06009023.1" from="06009022.1" to="06009023.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009024"/>
    <verse num="24">They answered Joshua, <q class="begin-double" qid="06009024.1" from="06009024.1" to="06009025.1"/>Because it was told to your servants for a certainty that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God had <crossref let="i" cid="c06009024.1"/>commanded his servant Moses to give you all the land and to destroy all the inhabitants of the land from before you&emdash;so <crossref let="j" cid="c06009024.2"/>we feared greatly for our lives because of you and did this thing.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009025"/>
    <verse num="25">And now, behold, we are in your hand. Whatever seems good and right in your sight to do to us, do it.<q class="end-double" qid="06009025.1" from="06009024.1" to="06009025.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009026"/>
    <verse num="26">So he did this to them and delivered them out of the hand of the people of Israel, and they did not kill them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06009027"/>
    <verse num="27">But Joshua made them that day <crossref let="k" cid="c06009027.1"/>cutters of wood and drawers of water for the congregation and for the altar of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, to this day, <crossref let="l" cid="c06009027.2"/>in the place that he should choose.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010001"/>
  <chapter num="10">
    <heading>The Sun Stands Still</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">As soon as Adoni-zedek, king of Jerusalem, heard how Joshua had captured Ai and had devoted it to destruction,<note nid="n06010001.1"/> <crossref let="m" cid="c06010001.1"/>doing to Ai and its king <crossref let="n" cid="c06010001.2"/>as he had done to Jericho and its king, and <crossref let="o" cid="c06010001.3"/>how the inhabitants of Gibeon had made peace with Israel and were among them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="p" cid="c06010002.1"/>he<note nid="n06010002.1"/> feared greatly, because Gibeon was a great city, like one of the royal cities, and because it was greater than Ai, and all its men were warriors.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010003"/>
    <verse num="3">So Adoni-zedek king of Jerusalem sent to Hoham king of Hebron, to Piram king of Jarmuth, to Japhia king of Lachish, and to Debir king of Eglon, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010004"/>
    <verse num="4"><q class="begin-double" qid="06010004.1" from="06010004.1" to="06010004.2"/>Come up to me and help me, and let us strike Gibeon. For <crossref let="q" cid="c06010004.1"/>it has made peace with Joshua and with the people of Israel.<q class="end-double" qid="06010004.2" from="06010004.1" to="06010004.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010005"/>
    <verse num="5">Then the five kings of the Amorites, the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, and the king of Eglon, <crossref let="r" cid="c06010005.1"/>gathered their forces and went up with all their armies and encamped against Gibeon and made war against it.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6">And the men of Gibeon sent to Joshua <crossref let="s" cid="c06010006.1"/>at the camp in Gilgal, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="06010006.1" from="06010006.1" to="06010006.2"/>Do not relax your hand from your servants. Come up to us quickly and save us and help us, for all the kings of the Amorites who dwell in the hill country are gathered against us.<q class="end-double" qid="06010006.2" from="06010006.1" to="06010006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010007"/>
    <verse num="7">So Joshua went up from Gilgal, he and <crossref let="t" cid="c06010007.1"/>all the people of war with him, and all the mighty men of valor.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010008"/>
    <verse num="8">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua, <crossref let="u" cid="c06010008.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06010008.1" from="06010008.1" to="06010008.2"/>Do not fear them, for I have given them into your hands. <crossref let="v" cid="c06010008.2"/>Not a man of them shall stand before you.<q class="end-double" qid="06010008.2" from="06010008.1" to="06010008.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010009"/>
    <verse num="9">So Joshua came upon them suddenly, having marched up all night from Gilgal.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="w" cid="c06010010.1"/>And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> threw them into a panic before Israel, who<note nid="n06010010.1"/> struck them with a great blow at Gibeon and chased them by the way of <crossref let="x" cid="c06010010.2"/>the ascent of Beth-horon and struck them as far as Azekah and Makkedah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010011"/>
    <verse num="11">And as they fled before Israel, while they were <crossref let="x" cid="c06010011.1"/>going down the ascent of Beth-horon, <crossref let="y" cid="c06010011.2"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> threw down large stones from heaven on them as far as Azekah, and they died. There were more who died because of the hailstones than the sons of Israel killed with the sword.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">At that time Joshua spoke to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in the day when the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave the Amorites over to the sons of Israel, and he said in the sight of Israel,
      <end-paragraph/>
      <begin-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="line-group"/>
        <begin-line/><crossref let="z" cid="c06010012.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06010012.1" from="06010012.1" to="06010012.2"/>Sun, stand still at Gibeon,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>and moon, in the Valley of Aijalon.<q class="end-double" qid="06010012.2" from="06010012.1" to="06010012.2"/><end-line class="br"/>
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010013"/>
    <verse num="13">
        <begin-line/>And the sun stood still, and the moon stopped,<end-line class="br"/>
        <begin-line class="indent"/>until the nation took vengeance on their enemies.<end-line/>
      <end-paragraph/>
      <end-block-indent/>
      <begin-paragraph class="same-paragraph"/>Is this not written in the Book of Jashar? The sun stopped in the midst of heaven and did not hurry to set for about a whole day.
    </verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010014"/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="a" cid="c06010014.1"/>There has been no day like it before or since, when the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> heeded the voice of a man, for <crossref let="b" cid="c06010014.2"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> fought for Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">So <crossref let="c" cid="c06010015.1"/>Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, to the camp at Gilgal.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010016"/>
    <heading>Five Amorite Kings Executed</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">These five kings fled and hid themselves in the cave at <crossref let="d" cid="c06010016.1"/>Makkedah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010017"/>
    <verse num="17">And it was told to Joshua, <q class="begin-double" qid="06010017.1" from="06010017.1" to="06010017.2"/>The five kings have been found, hidden in the cave at Makkedah.<q class="end-double" qid="06010017.2" from="06010017.1" to="06010017.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010018"/>
    <verse num="18">And Joshua said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06010018.1" from="06010018.1" to="06010019.1"/>Roll large stones against the mouth of the cave and set men by it to guard them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010019"/>
    <verse num="19">but do not stay there yourselves. Pursue your enemies; <crossref let="e" cid="c06010019.1"/>attack their rear guard. Do not let them enter their cities, for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God has given them into your hand.<q class="end-double" qid="06010019.1" from="06010018.1" to="06010019.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010020"/>
    <verse num="20">When Joshua and the sons of Israel had finished striking them with a great blow <crossref let="f" cid="c06010020.1"/>until they were wiped out, and when the remnant that remained of them had entered into the fortified cities,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010021"/>
    <verse num="21">then all the people returned safe to Joshua in the camp at Makkedah. <crossref let="g" cid="c06010021.1"/>Not a man moved his tongue against any of the people of Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">Then Joshua said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06010022.1" from="06010022.1" to="06010022.2"/>Open the mouth of the cave and bring those five kings out to me from the cave.<q class="end-double" qid="06010022.2" from="06010022.1" to="06010022.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010023"/>
    <verse num="23">And they did so, and brought those five kings out to him from the cave, the king of Jerusalem, the king of Hebron, the king of Jarmuth, the king of Lachish, and the king of Eglon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010024"/>
    <verse num="24">And when they brought those kings out to Joshua, Joshua summoned all the men of Israel and said to the chiefs of the men of war who had gone with him, <q class="begin-double" qid="06010024.1" from="06010024.1" to="06010024.2"/>Come near; put your feet on the necks of these kings.<q class="end-double" qid="06010024.2" from="06010024.1" to="06010024.2"/> Then they came near and put their feet on their necks.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010025"/>
    <verse num="25">And Joshua said to them, <crossref let="h" cid="c06010025.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06010025.1" from="06010025.1" to="06010025.2"/>Do not be afraid or dismayed; be strong and courageous. <crossref let="i" cid="c06010025.2"/>For thus the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will do to all your enemies against whom you fight.<q class="end-double" qid="06010025.2" from="06010025.1" to="06010025.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010026"/>
    <verse num="26">And afterward Joshua struck them and put them to death, and he hanged them on five trees. And <crossref let="j" cid="c06010026.1"/>they hung on the trees until evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010027"/>
    <verse num="27">But at the time of the going down of the sun, Joshua commanded, and <crossref let="k" cid="c06010027.1"/>they took them down from the trees and threw them into the cave where they had hidden themselves, and they set large stones against the mouth of the cave, which remain to this very day.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010028"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="28">As for <crossref let="l" cid="c06010028.1"/>Makkedah, Joshua captured it on that day and struck it, and its king, with the edge of the sword. He devoted to destruction every person in it; he left none remaining. And he did to the king of Makkedah <crossref let="m" cid="c06010028.2"/>just as he had done to the king of Jericho.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010029"/>
    <heading>Conquest of Southern Canaan</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29">Then Joshua and all Israel with him passed on from Makkedah to <crossref let="n" cid="c06010029.1"/>Libnah and fought against Libnah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010030"/>
    <verse num="30">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave it also and its king into the hand of Israel. And he struck it with the edge of the sword, and every person in it; he left none remaining in it. And he did to its king <crossref let="m" cid="c06010030.1"/>as he had done to the king of Jericho.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010031"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="31">Then Joshua and all Israel with him passed on from Libnah to <crossref let="o" cid="c06010031.1"/>Lachish and laid siege to it and fought against it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010032"/>
    <verse num="32">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave Lachish into the hand of Israel, and he captured it on the second day and struck it with the edge of the sword, and every person in it, as he had done to Libnah.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010033"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="33">Then Horam king of <crossref let="p" cid="c06010033.1"/>Gezer came up to help Lachish. And Joshua struck him and his people, until he left none remaining.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010034"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="34">Then Joshua and all Israel with him passed on from Lachish to <crossref let="q" cid="c06010034.1"/>Eglon. And they laid siege to it and fought against it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010035"/>
    <verse num="35">And they captured it on that day, and struck it with the edge of the sword. And he devoted every person in it to destruction that day, as he had done to Lachish.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010036"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="36">Then Joshua and all Israel with him went up from Eglon to <crossref let="r" cid="c06010036.1"/>Hebron. And they fought against it</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010037"/>
    <verse num="37">and captured it and struck it with the edge of the sword, and its king and its towns, and every person in it. He left none remaining, as he had done to Eglon, and devoted it to destruction and every person in it.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010038"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="38">Then Joshua and all Israel with him turned back to <crossref let="s" cid="c06010038.1"/>Debir and fought against it</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010039"/>
    <verse num="39">and he captured it with its king and all its towns. And they struck them with the edge of the sword and devoted to destruction every person in it; he left none remaining. Just as he had done to Hebron and to Libnah and its king, so he did to Debir and to its king.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010040"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="40">So Joshua struck the whole land, the hill country and the Negeb and the lowland <crossref let="t" cid="c06010040.1"/>and the slopes, and all their kings. He left none remaining, <crossref let="u" cid="c06010040.2"/>but devoted to destruction all that breathed, just as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God of Israel commanded.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010041"/>
    <verse num="41">And Joshua struck them from <crossref let="v" cid="c06010041.1"/>Kadesh-barnea as far as Gaza, and all the country of <crossref let="w" cid="c06010041.2"/>Goshen, as far as Gibeon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010042"/>
    <verse num="42">And Joshua captured all these kings and their land at one time, <crossref let="x" cid="c06010042.1"/>because the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God of Israel fought for Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06010043"/>
    <verse num="43"><crossref let="y" cid="c06010043.1"/>Then Joshua returned, and all Israel with him, to the camp at Gilgal.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011001"/>
  <chapter num="11">
    <heading>Conquests in Northern Canaan</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">When Jabin, king of Hazor, heard of this, he <crossref let="z" cid="c06011001.1"/>sent to Jobab king of Madon, and to the king of Shimron, and to the king of Achshaph,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011002"/>
    <verse num="2">and to the kings who were in the northern hill country, and in the <crossref let="a" cid="c06011002.1"/>Arabah south of <crossref let="b" cid="c06011002.2"/>Chinneroth, and in the lowland, and <crossref let="c" cid="c06011002.3"/>in Naphoth-dor on the <crossref let="d" cid="c06011002.4"/>west,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011003"/>
    <verse num="3">to the Canaanites in the east and the west, the Amorites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, and the <crossref let="e" cid="c06011003.1"/>Jebusites in the hill country, and the <crossref let="f" cid="c06011003.2"/>Hivites under <crossref let="g" cid="c06011003.3"/>Hermon in the land of <crossref let="h" cid="c06011003.4"/>Mizpah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011004"/>
    <verse num="4">And they came out with all their troops, a great horde, in number <crossref let="i" cid="c06011004.1"/>like the sand that is on the seashore, with very many horses and chariots.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011005"/>
    <verse num="5">And all these kings joined their forces and came and encamped together at the waters of Merom to fight against Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua, <crossref let="j" cid="c06011006.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06011006.1" from="06011006.1" to="06011006.2"/>Do not be afraid of them, for tomorrow at this time I will give over all of them, slain, to Israel. You shall <crossref let="k" cid="c06011006.2"/>hamstring their horses and burn their <crossref let="l" cid="c06011006.3"/>chariots with fire.<q class="end-double" qid="06011006.2" from="06011006.1" to="06011006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011007"/>
    <verse num="7">So Joshua and all his warriors came <crossref let="m" cid="c06011007.1"/>suddenly against them by the waters of Merom and fell upon them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011008"/>
    <verse num="8">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave them into the hand of Israel, who struck them and chased them as far as <crossref let="n" cid="c06011008.1"/>Great Sidon and <crossref let="o" cid="c06011008.2"/>Misrephoth-maim, and eastward as far as the Valley of <crossref let="p" cid="c06011008.3"/>Mizpeh. And they struck them until he left none remaining.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011009"/>
    <verse num="9">And Joshua did to them <crossref let="q" cid="c06011009.1"/>just as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to him: he hamstrung their horses and burned their chariots with fire.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">And Joshua turned back at that time and captured <crossref let="r" cid="c06011010.1"/>Hazor and struck its king with the sword, for Hazor formerly was the head of all those kingdoms.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011011"/>
    <verse num="11">And they struck with the sword all who were in it, devoting them to destruction;<note nid="n06011011.1"/> <crossref let="s" cid="c06011011.1"/>there was none left that breathed. And he burned Hazor with fire.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011012"/>
    <verse num="12">And all the cities of those kings, and all their kings, Joshua captured, and struck them with the edge of the sword, devoting them to destruction, <crossref let="t" cid="c06011012.1"/>just as Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had commanded.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011013"/>
    <verse num="13">But none of the cities that stood on mounds did Israel burn, except Hazor alone; that Joshua burned.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011014"/>
    <verse num="14">And all the spoil of these cities and the livestock, the people of Israel took for their plunder. But every person they struck with the edge of the sword until they had destroyed them, and they did not leave any who breathed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="u" cid="c06011015.1"/>Just as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had commanded Moses his servant, <crossref let="v" cid="c06011015.2"/>so Moses commanded Joshua, <crossref let="w" cid="c06011015.3"/>and so Joshua did. He left nothing undone of all that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had commanded Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">So Joshua took all that land, <crossref let="x" cid="c06011016.1"/>the hill country and all the Negeb and <crossref let="y" cid="c06011016.2"/>all the land of Goshen <crossref let="z" cid="c06011016.3"/>and the lowland <crossref let="z" cid="c06011016.4"/>and the Arabah <crossref let="a" cid="c06011016.5"/>and the hill country of Israel and its lowland</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="b" cid="c06011017.1"/>from Mount Halak, which rises toward Seir, as far as <crossref let="c" cid="c06011017.2"/>Baal-gad in the Valley of Lebanon below <crossref let="d" cid="c06011017.3"/>Mount Hermon. And he captured <crossref let="e" cid="c06011017.4"/>all their kings and struck them and put them to death.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011018"/>
    <verse num="18">Joshua made war <crossref let="f" cid="c06011018.1"/>a long time with all those kings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011019"/>
    <verse num="19">There was not a city that made peace with the people of Israel except <crossref let="g" cid="c06011019.1"/>the Hivites, the inhabitants of Gibeon. They took them all in battle.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011020"/>
    <verse num="20">For it was the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s doing <crossref let="h" cid="c06011020.1"/>to harden their hearts that they should come against Israel in battle, in order that they should be devoted to destruction and should receive no mercy but be destroyed, <crossref let="i" cid="c06011020.2"/>just as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011021"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="21">And Joshua came at that time and cut off <crossref let="j" cid="c06011021.1"/>the Anakim from the hill country, from Hebron, from Debir, from Anab, and from all the hill country of Judah, and from all the hill country of Israel. Joshua devoted them to destruction with their cities.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011022"/>
    <verse num="22">There was none of the Anakim left in the land of the people of Israel. Only in Gaza, <crossref let="k" cid="c06011022.1"/>in Gath, and in Ashdod did some remain.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06011023"/>
    <verse num="23">So Joshua took the whole land, <crossref let="l" cid="c06011023.1"/>according to all that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had spoken to Moses. <crossref let="m" cid="c06011023.2"/>And Joshua gave it for an inheritance to Israel <crossref let="n" cid="c06011023.3"/>according to their tribal allotments. And the land had rest from war.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012001"/>
  <chapter num="12">
    <heading>Kings Defeated by Moses</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Now these are the kings of the land whom the people of Israel defeated and took possession of their land beyond the Jordan toward the sunrise, from <crossref let="o" cid="c06012001.1"/>the Valley of the Arnon to Mount Hermon, with all <crossref let="p" cid="c06012001.2"/>the Arabah eastward:</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="q" cid="c06012002.1"/>Sihon king of the Amorites who lived at Heshbon and ruled from Aroer, which is on the edge of the Valley of the Arnon, and <crossref let="r" cid="c06012002.2"/>from the middle of the valley as far as the <crossref let="s" cid="c06012002.3"/>river Jabbok, the boundary of the Ammonites, that is, half of Gilead,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012003"/>
    <verse num="3">and <crossref let="p" cid="c06012003.1"/>the Arabah <crossref let="t" cid="c06012003.2"/>to the Sea of Chinneroth eastward, and in the direction of Beth-jeshimoth, to the Sea of the Arabah, the Salt Sea, southward to the foot of <crossref let="u" cid="c06012003.3"/>the slopes of Pisgah;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012004"/>
    <verse num="4">and <crossref let="v" cid="c06012004.1"/>Og<note nid="n06012004.1"/> king of Bashan, one of the remnant of <crossref let="w" cid="c06012004.2"/>the Rephaim, <crossref let="x" cid="c06012004.3"/>who lived at Ashtaroth and at Edrei</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012005"/>
    <verse num="5">and ruled over <crossref let="y" cid="c06012005.1"/>Mount Hermon and <crossref let="z" cid="c06012005.2"/>Salecah and all Bashan <crossref let="a" cid="c06012005.3"/>to the boundary of the Geshurites and the Maacathites, and over half of Gilead to the boundary of Sihon king of Heshbon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="b" cid="c06012006.1"/>Moses, the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and the people of Israel defeated them. And Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="c" cid="c06012006.2"/>gave their land for a possession to the Reubenites and the Gadites and the half-tribe of Manasseh.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012007"/>
    <heading>Kings Defeated by Joshua</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">And these are the kings of the land whom Joshua and the people of Israel defeated on the west side of the Jordan, from Baal-gad in the Valley of Lebanon to <crossref let="d" cid="c06012007.1"/>Mount Halak, that rises toward Seir (and Joshua gave their land to the tribes of Israel as a possession <crossref let="e" cid="c06012007.2"/>according to their allotments,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="f" cid="c06012008.1"/>in the hill country, in the lowland, in the Arabah, in the slopes, in the wilderness, and in the Negeb, the land of <crossref let="g" cid="c06012008.2"/>the Hittites, the Amorites, the Canaanites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites):</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="h" cid="c06012009.1"/>the king of Jericho, one; <crossref let="i" cid="c06012009.2"/>the king of Ai, which is beside Bethel, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="j" cid="c06012010.1"/>the king of Jerusalem, one; <crossref let="j" cid="c06012010.2"/>the king of Hebron, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="j" cid="c06012011.1"/>the king of Jarmuth, one; <crossref let="j" cid="c06012011.2"/>the king of Lachish, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="j" cid="c06012012.1"/>the king of Eglon, one; <crossref let="k" cid="c06012012.2"/>the king of Gezer, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="l" cid="c06012013.1"/>the king of Debir, one; the king of Geder, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012014"/>
    <verse num="14">the king of Hormah, one; the king of Arad, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="m" cid="c06012015.1"/>the king of Libnah, one; the king of Adullam, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012016"/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="n" cid="c06012016.1"/>the king of Makkedah, one; <crossref let="o" cid="c06012016.2"/>the king of Bethel, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012017"/>
    <verse num="17">the king of Tappuah, one; the king of Hepher, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012018"/>
    <verse num="18">the king of Aphek, one; the king of Lasharon, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012019"/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="p" cid="c06012019.1"/>the king of Madon, one; <crossref let="q" cid="c06012019.2"/>the king of Hazor, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="p" cid="c06012020.1"/>the king of Shimron-meron, one; <crossref let="p" cid="c06012020.2"/>the king of Achshaph, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012021"/>
    <verse num="21"><crossref let="r" cid="c06012021.1"/>the king of Taanach, one; <crossref let="r" cid="c06012021.2"/>the king of Megiddo, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012022"/>
    <verse num="22">the king of Kedesh, one; the king of Jokneam in Carmel, one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012023"/>
    <verse num="23"><crossref let="r" cid="c06012023.1"/>the king of Dor in <crossref let="s" cid="c06012023.2"/>Naphath-dor, one; the king of Goiim in Galilee,<note nid="n06012023.1"/> one;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06012024"/>
    <verse num="24">the king of Tirzah, one: in all, thirty-one kings.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013001"/>
  <chapter num="13">
    <heading>Land Still to Be Conquered</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Now Joshua <crossref let="t" cid="c06013001.1"/>was old and advanced in years, and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="06013001.1" from="06013001.1" to="06013007.1"/>You are old and advanced in years, and there remains yet very much land <crossref let="u" cid="c06013001.2"/>to possess.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="v" cid="c06013002.1"/>This is the land that yet remains: all the <crossref let="w" cid="c06013002.2"/>regions of the Philistines, and all those of the Geshurites</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013003"/>
    <verse num="3">(from the <crossref let="x" cid="c06013003.1"/>Shihor, which is east of Egypt, northward to the boundary of Ekron, it is counted as Canaanite; <crossref let="y" cid="c06013003.2"/>there are five rulers of the Philistines, those of Gaza, Ashdod, Ashkelon, Gath, and Ekron), and those of <crossref let="z" cid="c06013003.3"/>the Avvim,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013004"/>
    <verse num="4">in the south, all the land of the Canaanites, and Mearah that belongs to the Sidonians, to Aphek, to the boundary of <crossref let="a" cid="c06013004.1"/>the Amorites,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013005"/>
    <verse num="5">and the land of the <crossref let="b" cid="c06013005.1"/>Gebalites, and all Lebanon, toward the sunrise, from <crossref let="c" cid="c06013005.2"/>Baal-gad below Mount Hermon to <crossref let="d" cid="c06013005.3"/>Lebo-hamath,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013006"/>
    <verse num="6">all the inhabitants of the hill country from Lebanon to <crossref let="e" cid="c06013006.1"/>Misrephoth-maim, even all the Sidonians. I myself will drive <crossref let="f" cid="c06013006.2"/>them out from before the people of Israel. Only <crossref let="g" cid="c06013006.3"/>allot the land to Israel <crossref let="h" cid="c06013006.4"/>for an inheritance, as I have commanded you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013007"/>
    <verse num="7">Now therefore <crossref let="i" cid="c06013007.1"/>divide this land for an inheritance to the nine tribes and half the tribe of Manasseh.<q class="end-double" qid="06013007.1" from="06013001.1" to="06013007.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013008"/>
    <heading>The Inheritance East of the Jordan</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">With the other half of the tribe of Manasseh<note nid="n06013008.1"/> the Reubenites and the Gadites received their inheritance, <crossref let="j" cid="c06013008.1"/>which Moses gave them, beyond the Jordan eastward, as Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave them:</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="k" cid="c06013009.1"/>from Aroer, which is on the edge of the Valley of the Arnon, and the city that is in the middle of the valley, and <crossref let="l" cid="c06013009.2"/>all the tableland of Medeba as far as Dibon;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="m" cid="c06013010.1"/>and all the cities of Sihon king of the Amorites, who reigned in Heshbon, as far as the boundary of the Ammonites;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013011"/>
    <verse num="11">and Gilead, and the <crossref let="n" cid="c06013011.1"/>region of the Geshurites and Maacathites, and all Mount Hermon, and <crossref let="n" cid="c06013011.2"/>all Bashan to Salecah;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="n" cid="c06013012.1"/>all the kingdom of Og in Bashan, who reigned in Ashtaroth and in Edrei (he alone was left of <crossref let="n" cid="c06013012.2"/>the remnant of the Rephaim); <crossref let="o" cid="c06013012.3"/>these Moses had struck and driven out.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="p" cid="c06013013.1"/>Yet the people of Israel did not drive out the Geshurites or the Maacathites, but Geshur and Maacath dwell in the midst of Israel to this day.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="q" cid="c06013014.1"/>To the tribe of Levi alone Moses gave no inheritance. The offerings by fire to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God of Israel are their inheritance, as he said to him.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15">And Moses gave an inheritance to the tribe of the people of Reuben according to their clans.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013016"/>
    <verse num="16">So their territory was from Aroer, <crossref let="r" cid="c06013016.1"/>which is on the edge of the Valley of the Arnon, and the city that is in the middle of the valley, and all the tableland by <crossref let="s" cid="c06013016.2"/>Medeba;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013017"/>
    <verse num="17">with Heshbon, and all its cities that are in the tableland; <crossref let="s" cid="c06013017.1"/>Dibon, and Bamoth-baal, and Beth-baal-meon,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013018"/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="t" cid="c06013018.1"/>and Jahaz, and Kedemoth, and Mephaath,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013019"/>
    <verse num="19">and <crossref let="u" cid="c06013019.1"/>Kiriathaim, and <crossref let="u" cid="c06013019.2"/>Sibmah, and Zereth-shahar on the hill of the valley,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013020"/>
    <verse num="20">and <crossref let="v" cid="c06013020.1"/>Beth-peor, and <crossref let="w" cid="c06013020.2"/>the slopes of Pisgah, and <crossref let="w" cid="c06013020.3"/>Beth-jeshimoth,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013021"/>
    <verse num="21">that is, <crossref let="x" cid="c06013021.1"/>all the cities of the tableland, and all the kingdom of Sihon king of the Amorites, who reigned in Heshbon, <crossref let="y" cid="c06013021.2"/>whom Moses defeated with <crossref let="z" cid="c06013021.3"/>the leaders of Midian, Evi and Rekem and Zur and Hur and Reba, the princes of Sihon, who lived in the land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013022"/>
    <verse num="22"><crossref let="z" cid="c06013022.1"/>Balaam also, the son of Beor, the one who practiced divination, was killed with the sword by the people of Israel among the rest of their slain.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013023"/>
    <verse num="23">And the border of the people of Reuben was the Jordan as a boundary. This was the inheritance of the people of Reuben, according to their clans with their cities and villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013024"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24">Moses gave an inheritance also to the tribe of Gad, to the people of Gad, according to their clans.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013025"/>
    <verse num="25"><crossref let="a" cid="c06013025.1"/>Their territory was Jazer, and all the cities of Gilead, and half the land of the Ammonites, to Aroer, which is east of <crossref let="b" cid="c06013025.2"/>Rabbah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013026"/>
    <verse num="26">and from Heshbon to Ramath-mizpeh and Betonim, and from <crossref let="c" cid="c06013026.1"/>Mahanaim to the territory of Debir,<note nid="n06013026.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013027"/>
    <verse num="27">and in the valley Beth-haram, Beth-nimrah, <crossref let="d" cid="c06013027.1"/>Succoth, and Zaphon, the rest of the kingdom of Sihon king of Heshbon, having the Jordan as a boundary, to the lower end of the Sea of <crossref let="e" cid="c06013027.2"/>Chinnereth, eastward beyond the Jordan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013028"/>
    <verse num="28">This is the inheritance of the people of Gad according to their clans, with their cities and villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013029"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29">And Moses gave an inheritance to the half-tribe of Manasseh. It was allotted to the half-tribe of the people of Manasseh according to their clans.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013030"/>
    <verse num="30">Their region extended from <crossref let="f" cid="c06013030.1"/>Mahanaim, through all Bashan, the whole kingdom of Og king of Bashan, and all <crossref let="g" cid="c06013030.2"/>the towns of Jair, which are in Bashan, sixty cities,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013031"/>
    <verse num="31">and half Gilead, and <crossref let="h" cid="c06013031.1"/>Ashtaroth, and Edrei, the cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan. These were allotted to the people of <crossref let="i" cid="c06013031.2"/>Machir the son of Manasseh for the half of the people of Machir according to their clans.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013032"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="32">These are the inheritances that Moses distributed <crossref let="j" cid="c06013032.1"/>in the plains of Moab, beyond the Jordan east of Jericho.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06013033"/>
    <verse num="33"><crossref let="k" cid="c06013033.1"/>But to the tribe of Levi Moses gave no inheritance; the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> God of Israel is their inheritance, <crossref let="k" cid="c06013033.2"/>just as he said to them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014001"/>
  <chapter num="14">
    <heading>The Inheritance West of the Jordan</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">These are the inheritances that the people of Israel received in the land of Canaan, which <crossref let="l" cid="c06014001.1"/>Eleazar the priest and Joshua the son of Nun and the heads of the fathers&apos; houses of the tribes of the people of Israel gave them to inherit.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014002"/>
    <verse num="2">Their inheritance was <crossref let="m" cid="c06014002.1"/>by lot, just as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had commanded by the hand of Moses for the nine and one-half tribes.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014003"/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="n" cid="c06014003.1"/>For Moses had given an inheritance to the two and one-half tribes beyond the Jordan, <crossref let="o" cid="c06014003.2"/>but to the Levites he gave no inheritance among them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014004"/>
    <verse num="4">For <crossref let="p" cid="c06014004.1"/>the people of Joseph were two tribes, Manasseh and Ephraim. And no portion was given to the Levites in the land, but only cities to dwell in, with their pasturelands for their livestock and their substance.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014005"/>
    <verse num="5">The people of Israel did <crossref let="q" cid="c06014005.1"/>as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses; they allotted the land.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014006"/>
    <heading>Caleb&apos;s Request and Inheritance</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6">Then the people of Judah came to Joshua at Gilgal. And Caleb the son of Jephunneh the <crossref let="r" cid="c06014006.1"/>Kenizzite said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="06014006.1" from="06014006.1" to="06014012.1"/>You know <crossref let="s" cid="c06014006.2"/>what the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Moses the man of God in Kadesh-barnea concerning you and me.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014007"/>
    <verse num="7">I was forty years old when Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="t" cid="c06014007.1"/>sent me from Kadesh-barnea to spy out the land, and I brought him word again as it was in my heart.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014008"/>
    <verse num="8">But <crossref let="u" cid="c06014008.1"/>my brothers who went up with me made the heart of the people melt; yet I wholly followed the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> my God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014009"/>
    <verse num="9">And Moses swore on that day, saying, <crossref let="v" cid="c06014009.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="06014009.1" from="06014009.1" to="06014009.2"/>Surely the land <crossref let="w" cid="c06014009.2"/>on which your foot has trodden shall be an inheritance for you and your children forever, because you have wholly followed the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> my God.<q class="end-single" qid="06014009.2" from="06014009.1" to="06014009.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014010"/>
    <verse num="10">And now, behold, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has kept me alive, <crossref let="x" cid="c06014010.1"/>just as he said, these <crossref let="y" cid="c06014010.2"/>forty-five years since the time that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke this word to Moses, while Israel walked in the wilderness. And now, behold, I am this day <crossref let="y" cid="c06014010.3"/>eighty-five years old.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="z" cid="c06014011.1"/>I am still as strong today as I was in the day that Moses sent me; my strength now is as my strength was then, for war and <crossref let="a" cid="c06014011.2"/>for going and coming.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014012"/>
    <verse num="12">So now give me this hill country of which the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke on that day, for you heard on that day how the <crossref let="b" cid="c06014012.1"/>Anakim were there, with great fortified cities. It may be that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will be with me, and I shall drive them out just as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said.<q class="end-double" qid="06014012.1" from="06014006.1" to="06014012.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">Then Joshua <crossref let="c" cid="c06014013.1"/>blessed him, and he gave <crossref let="d" cid="c06014013.2"/>Hebron to Caleb the son of Jephunneh for an inheritance.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014014"/>
    <verse num="14">Therefore Hebron became the inheritance of Caleb the son of Jephunneh the Kenizzite to this day, <crossref let="e" cid="c06014014.1"/>because he wholly followed the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06014015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="f" cid="c06014015.1"/>Now the name of Hebron formerly was Kiriath-arba.<note nid="n06014015.1"/> (Arba<note nid="n06014015.2"/> was the greatest man among the Anakim.) <crossref let="g" cid="c06014015.2"/>And the land had rest from war.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015001"/>
  <chapter num="15">
    <heading>The Allotment for Judah</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">The allotment for the tribe of the people of Judah according to their clans reached southward <crossref let="h" cid="c06015001.1"/>to the boundary of Edom, to <crossref let="i" cid="c06015001.2"/>the wilderness of Zin at the farthest south.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015002"/>
    <verse num="2">And their south boundary ran from the end of the <crossref let="h" cid="c06015002.1"/>Salt Sea, from the bay that faces southward.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015003"/>
    <verse num="3">It goes out southward of <crossref let="j" cid="c06015003.1"/>the ascent of Akrabbim, passes along to Zin, and goes up south of Kadesh-barnea, along by Hezron, up to Addar, turns about to Karka,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015004"/>
    <verse num="4">passes along to Azmon, goes out by <crossref let="k" cid="c06015004.1"/>the Brook of Egypt, and comes to its end at the sea. This shall be your south boundary.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015005"/>
    <verse num="5">And the east boundary is the <crossref let="h" cid="c06015005.1"/>Salt Sea, to the mouth of the Jordan. And the boundary on the north side runs from the bay of the sea at the mouth of the Jordan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015006"/>
    <verse num="6">And the boundary goes up to <crossref let="l" cid="c06015006.1"/>Beth-hoglah and passes along north of <crossref let="m" cid="c06015006.2"/>Beth-arabah. And the boundary goes up to <crossref let="n" cid="c06015006.3"/>the stone of Bohan the son of Reuben.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015007"/>
    <verse num="7">And the boundary goes up to Debir from <crossref let="o" cid="c06015007.1"/>the Valley of Achor, and so northward, turning toward Gilgal, which is opposite <crossref let="p" cid="c06015007.2"/>the ascent of Adummim, which is on the south side of the valley. And the boundary passes along to the waters of <crossref let="p" cid="c06015007.3"/>En-shemesh and ends at <crossref let="q" cid="c06015007.4"/>En-rogel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015008"/>
    <verse num="8">Then the boundary goes up by <crossref let="r" cid="c06015008.1"/>the Valley of the Son of Hinnom at the southern shoulder of the Jebusite (<crossref let="s" cid="c06015008.2"/>that is, Jerusalem). And the boundary goes up to the top of the mountain that lies over against the Valley of Hinnom, on the west, at the northern end of the Valley <crossref let="t" cid="c06015008.3"/>of Rephaim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015009"/>
    <verse num="9">Then the boundary extends from the top of the mountain <crossref let="u" cid="c06015009.1"/>to the spring of the waters of Nephtoah, and from there to the cities of Mount Ephron. Then the boundary bends around to Baalah (<crossref let="v" cid="c06015009.2"/>that is, Kiriath-jearim).</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015010"/>
    <verse num="10">And the boundary circles west of Baalah to Mount Seir, passes along to the northern shoulder of Mount Jearim (that is, Chesalon), and goes down to <crossref let="w" cid="c06015010.1"/>Beth-shemesh and passes along by <crossref let="x" cid="c06015010.2"/>Timnah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015011"/>
    <verse num="11">The boundary goes out <crossref let="y" cid="c06015011.1"/>to the shoulder of the hill north of Ekron, then the boundary bends around to Shikkeron and passes along to Mount <crossref let="z" cid="c06015011.2"/>Baalah and goes out to Jabneel. Then the boundary comes to an end at the sea.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015012"/>
    <verse num="12">And the west boundary was <crossref let="a" cid="c06015012.1"/>the Great Sea with its coastline. This is the boundary around the people of Judah according to their clans.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">According to the commandment of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to Joshua, he gave to Caleb the son of Jephunneh a portion among the people of Judah, <crossref let="b" cid="c06015013.1"/>Kiriath-arba, that is, <crossref let="b" cid="c06015013.2"/>Hebron (Arba was the father of Anak).</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015014"/>
    <verse num="14">And Caleb drove out from there the three sons of Anak, <crossref let="c" cid="c06015014.1"/>Sheshai and Ahiman and Talmai, the descendants of Anak.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015015"/>
    <verse num="15">And he went up from there against the inhabitants of Debir. <crossref let="d" cid="c06015015.1"/>Now the name of Debir formerly was Kiriath-sepher.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015016"/>
    <verse num="16">And Caleb said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06015016.1" from="06015016.1" to="06015016.2"/>He who attacks Kiriath-sepher and captures it, I will give him Achsah my daughter as wife.<q class="end-double" qid="06015016.2" from="06015016.1" to="06015016.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="e" cid="c06015017.1"/>And Othniel the son of Kenaz, <crossref let="f" cid="c06015017.2"/>the brother of Caleb, captured it. And he gave him Achsah his daughter as wife.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015018"/>
    <verse num="18">When she came to him, she urged him to ask her father for a field. And she dismounted from her donkey, and Caleb said to her, <q class="begin-double" qid="06015018.1" from="06015018.1" to="06015018.2"/>What do you want?<q class="end-double" qid="06015018.2" from="06015018.1" to="06015018.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015019"/>
    <verse num="19">She said to him, <q class="begin-double" qid="06015019.1" from="06015019.1" to="06015019.2"/>Give me a blessing. Since you have given me the land of the Negeb, give me also springs of water.<q class="end-double" qid="06015019.2" from="06015019.1" to="06015019.2"/> And he gave her the upper springs and the lower springs.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015020"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20">This is the inheritance of the tribe of the people of Judah according to their clans.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015021"/>
    <verse num="21">The cities belonging to the tribe of the people of Judah in the extreme south, toward the boundary of Edom, were Kabzeel, <crossref let="g" cid="c06015021.1"/>Eder, Jagur,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015022"/>
    <verse num="22">Kinah, Dimonah, Adadah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015023"/>
    <verse num="23">Kedesh, Hazor, Ithnan,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015024"/>
    <verse num="24"><crossref let="h" cid="c06015024.1"/>Ziph, Telem, Bealoth,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015025"/>
    <verse num="25">Hazor-hadattah, Kerioth-hezron (that is, Hazor),</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015026"/>
    <verse num="26">Amam, Shema, Moladah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015027"/>
    <verse num="27">Hazar-gaddah, Heshmon, Beth-pelet,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015028"/>
    <verse num="28">Hazar-shual, <crossref let="i" cid="c06015028.1"/>Beersheba, Biziothiah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015029"/>
    <verse num="29">Baalah, Iim, Ezem,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015030"/>
    <verse num="30">Eltolad, Chesil, Hormah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015031"/>
    <verse num="31"><crossref let="j" cid="c06015031.1"/>Ziklag, Madmannah, Sansannah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015032"/>
    <verse num="32">Lebaoth, Shilhim, Ain, and Rimmon: in all, twenty-nine cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015033"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="33">And in the lowland, <crossref let="k" cid="c06015033.1"/>Eshtaol, Zorah, Ashnah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015034"/>
    <verse num="34">Zanoah, En-gannim, Tappuah, Enam,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015035"/>
    <verse num="35"><crossref let="l" cid="c06015035.1"/>Jarmuth, <crossref let="m" cid="c06015035.2"/>Adullam, <crossref let="n" cid="c06015035.3"/>Socoh, <crossref let="n" cid="c06015035.4"/>Azekah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015036"/>
    <verse num="36">Shaaraim, Adithaim, Gederah, Gederothaim: fourteen cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015037"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="37">Zenan, Hadashah, Migdal-gad,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015038"/>
    <verse num="38">Dilean, Mizpeh, Joktheel,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015039"/>
    <verse num="39"><crossref let="o" cid="c06015039.1"/>Lachish, Bozkath, <crossref let="p" cid="c06015039.2"/>Eglon,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015040"/>
    <verse num="40">Cabbon, Lahmam, Chitlish,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015041"/>
    <verse num="41">Gederoth, Beth-dagon, Naamah, and <crossref let="q" cid="c06015041.1"/>Makkedah: sixteen cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015042"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="42"><crossref let="r" cid="c06015042.1"/>Libnah, Ether, Ashan,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015043"/>
    <verse num="43">Iphtah, Ashnah, Nezib,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015044"/>
    <verse num="44"><crossref let="s" cid="c06015044.1"/>Keilah, Achzib, and Mareshah: nine cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015045"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="45"><crossref let="t" cid="c06015045.1"/>Ekron, with its towns and its villages;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015046"/>
    <verse num="46">from Ekron to the sea, all that were by the side of Ashdod, with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015047"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="47"><crossref let="t" cid="c06015047.1"/>Ashdod, its towns and its villages; <crossref let="t" cid="c06015047.2"/>Gaza, its towns and its villages; to <crossref let="u" cid="c06015047.3"/>the Brook of Egypt, and <crossref let="v" cid="c06015047.4"/>the Great Sea with its coastline.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015048"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="48">And in the hill country, Shamir, Jattir, Socoh,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015049"/>
    <verse num="49">Dannah, Kiriath-sannah (<crossref let="w" cid="c06015049.1"/>that is, Debir),</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015050"/>
    <verse num="50">Anab, Eshtemoh, Anim,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015051"/>
    <verse num="51"><crossref let="x" cid="c06015051.1"/>Goshen, Holon, and <crossref let="y" cid="c06015051.2"/>Giloh: eleven cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015052"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="52">Arab, Dumah, Eshan,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015053"/>
    <verse num="53">Janim, Beth-tappuah, Aphekah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015054"/>
    <verse num="54">Humtah, <crossref let="z" cid="c06015054.1"/>Kiriath-arba (that is, <crossref let="z" cid="c06015054.2"/>Hebron), and Zior: nine cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015055"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="55"><crossref let="a" cid="c06015055.1"/>Maon, <crossref let="a" cid="c06015055.2"/>Carmel, <crossref let="b" cid="c06015055.3"/>Ziph, Juttah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015056"/>
    <verse num="56">Jezreel, Jokdeam, Zanoah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015057"/>
    <verse num="57">Kain, Gibeah, and <crossref let="c" cid="c06015057.1"/>Timnah: ten cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015058"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="58">Halhul, Beth-zur, Gedor,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015059"/>
    <verse num="59">Maarath, Beth-anoth, and Eltekon: six cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015060"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="60"><crossref let="d" cid="c06015060.1"/>Kiriath-baal (that is, Kiriath-jearim), and Rabbah: two cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015061"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="61">In the wilderness, <crossref let="e" cid="c06015061.1"/>Beth-arabah, Middin, Secacah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015062"/>
    <verse num="62">Nibshan, the City of Salt, and <crossref let="f" cid="c06015062.1"/>Engedi: six cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06015063"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="63">But the <crossref let="g" cid="c06015063.1"/>Jebusites, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, <crossref let="h" cid="c06015063.2"/>the people of Judah could not drive out, <crossref let="h" cid="c06015063.3"/>so the Jebusites dwell with the people of Judah at Jerusalem to this day.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06016001"/>
  <chapter num="16">
    <heading>The Allotment for Ephraim and Manasseh</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">The allotment of the people of Joseph went from the Jordan by Jericho, east of the waters of Jericho, <crossref let="i" cid="c06016001.1"/>into the wilderness, going up from Jericho into the hill country to Bethel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06016002"/>
    <verse num="2">Then <crossref let="j" cid="c06016002.1"/>going from Bethel to Luz, it passes along to Ataroth, the territory of the Archites.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06016003"/>
    <verse num="3">Then it goes down westward to the territory of the Japhletites, as far as the territory of Lower <crossref let="k" cid="c06016003.1"/>Beth-horon, then to <crossref let="l" cid="c06016003.2"/>Gezer, and it ends at the sea.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06016004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="m" cid="c06016004.1"/>The people of Joseph, Manasseh and Ephraim, received their inheritance.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06016005"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5">The territory of the people of Ephraim by their clans was as follows: the boundary of their inheritance on the east was <crossref let="n" cid="c06016005.1"/>Ataroth-addar as far as Upper Beth-horon,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06016006"/>
    <verse num="6">and the boundary goes from there to the sea. On the north is <crossref let="o" cid="c06016006.1"/>Michmethath. Then on the east the boundary turns around toward Taanath-shiloh and passes along beyond it on the east to Janoah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06016007"/>
    <verse num="7">then it goes down from Janoah to Ataroth and <crossref let="p" cid="c06016007.1"/>to Naarah, and touches Jericho, ending at the Jordan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06016008"/>
    <verse num="8">From <crossref let="q" cid="c06016008.1"/>Tappuah the boundary goes westward to the brook Kanah and ends at the sea. Such is the inheritance of the tribe of the people of Ephraim by their clans,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06016009"/>
    <verse num="9">together with <crossref let="q" cid="c06016009.1"/>the towns that were set apart for the people of Ephraim within the inheritance of the Manassites, all those towns with their villages.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06016010"/>
    <verse num="10">However, <crossref let="r" cid="c06016010.1"/>they did not drive out the Canaanites who lived in Gezer, so the Canaanites have lived in the midst of Ephraim to this day but have been made <crossref let="s" cid="c06016010.2"/>to do forced labor.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017001"/>
  <chapter num="17">
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Then allotment was made to the people of Manasseh, for he was <crossref let="t" cid="c06017001.1"/>the firstborn of Joseph. To <crossref let="u" cid="c06017001.2"/>Machir the firstborn of Manasseh, the father of Gilead, <crossref let="v" cid="c06017001.3"/>were allotted Gilead and Bashan, because he was a man of war.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017002"/>
    <verse num="2">And allotments were made <crossref let="w" cid="c06017002.1"/>to the rest of the people of Manasseh by their clans, Abiezer, Helek, Asriel, Shechem, Hepher, and Shemida. These were the male descendants of Manasseh the son of Joseph, by their clans.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017003"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3">Now <crossref let="x" cid="c06017003.1"/>Zelophehad the son of Hepher, son of Gilead, son of Machir, son of Manasseh, had no sons, but only daughters, and these are the names of his daughters: <crossref let="x" cid="c06017003.2"/>Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017004"/>
    <verse num="4">They approached <crossref let="y" cid="c06017004.1"/>Eleazar the priest and Joshua the son of Nun and the leaders and said, <crossref let="z" cid="c06017004.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06017004.1" from="06017004.1" to="06017004.2"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses to give us an inheritance along with our brothers.<q class="end-double" qid="06017004.2" from="06017004.1" to="06017004.2"/> So according to the mouth of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> he gave them an inheritance among the brothers of their father.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017005"/>
    <verse num="5">Thus there fell to Manasseh ten portions, besides <crossref let="a" cid="c06017005.1"/>the land of Gilead and Bashan, which is on the other side of the Jordan,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017006"/>
    <verse num="6">because the daughters of Manasseh received an inheritance along with his sons. The land of Gilead was allotted to the rest of the people of Manasseh.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">The territory of Manasseh reached from Asher to <crossref let="b" cid="c06017007.1"/>Michmethath, which is east of Shechem. Then the boundary goes along southward to the inhabitants of En-tappuah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017008"/>
    <verse num="8">The land of <crossref let="c" cid="c06017008.1"/>Tappuah belonged to Manasseh, but the town of Tappuah on the boundary of Manasseh belonged to the people of Ephraim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="c" cid="c06017009.1"/>Then the boundary went down to the brook Kanah. These cities, to the south of the brook, among the cities of Manasseh, belong to Ephraim. Then the boundary of Manasseh goes on the north side of the brook and ends at the sea,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017010"/>
    <verse num="10">the land to the south being Ephraim&apos;s and that to the north being Manasseh&apos;s, with the sea forming its boundary. On the north Asher is reached, and on the east Issachar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017011"/>
    <verse num="11">Also in Issachar and in Asher <crossref let="d" cid="c06017011.1"/>Manasseh had Beth-shean and its villages, and Ibleam and its villages, and the inhabitants of <crossref let="d" cid="c06017011.2"/>Dor and its villages, and the inhabitants of En-dor and its villages, and the inhabitants of <crossref let="d" cid="c06017011.3"/>Taanach and its villages, and the inhabitants of <crossref let="d" cid="c06017011.4"/>Megiddo and its villages; <crossref let="e" cid="c06017011.5"/>the third is Naphath.<note nid="n06017011.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="f" cid="c06017012.1"/>Yet the people of Manasseh could not take possession of those cities, but the Canaanites persisted in dwelling in that land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017013"/>
    <verse num="13">Now when the people of Israel grew strong, they put the Canaanites <crossref let="g" cid="c06017013.1"/>to forced labor, but did not utterly drive them out.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14">Then <crossref let="h" cid="c06017014.1"/>the people of Joseph spoke to Joshua, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="06017014.1" from="06017014.1" to="06017014.2"/>Why have you given me but <crossref let="i" cid="c06017014.2"/>one lot and one portion as an inheritance, although I am <crossref let="j" cid="c06017014.3"/>a numerous people, since all along the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has blessed me?<q class="end-double" qid="06017014.2" from="06017014.1" to="06017014.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017015"/>
    <verse num="15">And Joshua said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="06017015.1" from="06017015.1" to="06017015.2"/>If you are a numerous people, go up by yourselves to the forest, and there clear ground for yourselves in the land of the Perizzites and <crossref let="k" cid="c06017015.1"/>the Rephaim, since <crossref let="l" cid="c06017015.2"/>the hill country of Ephraim is too narrow for you.<q class="end-double" qid="06017015.2" from="06017015.1" to="06017015.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017016"/>
    <verse num="16">The people of Joseph said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06017016.1" from="06017016.1" to="06017016.2"/>The hill country is not enough for us. Yet all the Canaanites who dwell in the plain have <crossref let="m" cid="c06017016.1"/>chariots of iron, both those in Beth-shean and its villages and those in <crossref let="n" cid="c06017016.2"/>the Valley of Jezreel.<q class="end-double" qid="06017016.2" from="06017016.1" to="06017016.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017017"/>
    <verse num="17">Then Joshua said to the house of Joseph, to Ephraim and Manasseh, <q class="begin-double" qid="06017017.1" from="06017017.1" to="06017018.1"/>You are a numerous people and have great power. You shall not have one allotment only,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06017018"/>
    <verse num="18">but the hill country shall be yours, for though it is a forest, you shall clear it and possess it to its farthest borders. For you shall drive out the Canaanites, <crossref let="o" cid="c06017018.1"/>though they have chariots of iron, and though they are strong.<q class="end-double" qid="06017018.1" from="06017017.1" to="06017018.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018001"/>
  <chapter num="18">
    <heading>Allotment of the Remaining Land</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Then the whole congregation of the people of Israel assembled at <crossref let="p" cid="c06018001.1"/>Shiloh and set up <crossref let="q" cid="c06018001.2"/>the tent of meeting there. The land lay subdued before them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018002"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="2">There remained among the people of Israel seven tribes whose inheritance had not yet been apportioned.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018003"/>
    <verse num="3">So Joshua said to the people of Israel, <crossref let="r" cid="c06018003.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06018003.1" from="06018003.1" to="06018007.1"/>How long will you put off going in to take possession of the land, which the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of your fathers, has given you?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018004"/>
    <verse num="4">Provide three men from each tribe, and I will send them out that they may set out and go up and down the land. They shall write a description of it with a view to their inheritances, and then come to me.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018005"/>
    <verse num="5">They shall divide it into seven portions. <crossref let="s" cid="c06018005.1"/>Judah shall continue in his territory on the south, <crossref let="t" cid="c06018005.2"/>and the house of Joseph shall continue in their territory on the north.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018006"/>
    <verse num="6">And you shall describe the land in seven divisions and bring the description here to me. <crossref let="u" cid="c06018006.1"/>And I will cast lots for you here before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="v" cid="c06018007.1"/>The Levites have no portion among you, for the priesthood of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is their heritage. <crossref let="w" cid="c06018007.2"/>And Gad and Reuben and half the tribe of Manasseh have received their inheritance beyond the Jordan eastward, which Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave them.<q class="end-double" qid="06018007.1" from="06018003.1" to="06018007.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">So the men arose and went, and Joshua charged those who went to write the description of the land, saying, <q class="begin-double" qid="06018008.1" from="06018008.1" to="06018008.2"/>Go up and down in the land and write a description and return to me. And I will cast lots for you here before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in Shiloh.<q class="end-double" qid="06018008.2" from="06018008.1" to="06018008.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018009"/>
    <verse num="9">So the men went and passed up and down in the land and wrote in a book a description of it by towns in seven divisions. Then they came to Joshua to the camp at Shiloh,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018010"/>
    <verse num="10">and Joshua <crossref let="x" cid="c06018010.1"/>cast lots for them in Shiloh before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. And there Joshua apportioned the land to the people of Israel, <crossref let="y" cid="c06018010.2"/>to each his portion.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018011"/>
    <heading>The Inheritance for Benjamin</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11">The lot of the tribe of the people of Benjamin according to its clans came up, and the territory allotted to it fell between the people of Judah and the people of Joseph.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="z" cid="c06018012.1"/>On the north side their boundary began at the Jordan. <crossref let="a" cid="c06018012.2"/>Then the boundary goes up to the shoulder north of Jericho, then up through the hill country westward, and it ends at the wilderness of <crossref let="b" cid="c06018012.3"/>Beth-aven.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018013"/>
    <verse num="13">From there the boundary passes along southward in the direction of Luz, to the shoulder of <crossref let="c" cid="c06018013.1"/>Luz (that is, Bethel), then the boundary goes down to <crossref let="d" cid="c06018013.2"/>Ataroth-addar, on the mountain that lies south of Lower <crossref let="e" cid="c06018013.3"/>Beth-horon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018014"/>
    <verse num="14">Then the boundary goes in another direction, turning on the <crossref let="f" cid="c06018014.1"/>western side southward from the mountain that lies to the south, opposite Beth-horon, and it ends at Kiriath-baal (<crossref let="g" cid="c06018014.2"/>that is, Kiriath-jearim), a city belonging to the people of Judah. This forms the western side.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018015"/>
    <verse num="15">And the southern side begins at the outskirts of Kiriath-jearim. And the boundary goes from there to Ephron,<note nid="n06018015.1"/> <crossref let="g" cid="c06018015.1"/>to the spring of the waters of Nephtoah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018016"/>
    <verse num="16">Then the boundary goes down to the border of the mountain that overlooks <crossref let="h" cid="c06018016.1"/>the Valley of the Son of Hinnom, which is at the north end of the Valley of <crossref let="i" cid="c06018016.2"/>Rephaim. And it then goes down the <crossref let="h" cid="c06018016.3"/>Valley of Hinnom, south of the shoulder of the Jebusites, and downward to <crossref let="j" cid="c06018016.4"/>En-rogel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018017"/>
    <verse num="17">Then it bends in a northerly direction going on to En-shemesh, and from there goes to Geliloth, which is opposite the ascent of Adummim. Then it goes down to <crossref let="k" cid="c06018017.1"/>the stone of Bohan the son of Reuben,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018018"/>
    <verse num="18">and passing on to the north of <crossref let="l" cid="c06018018.1"/>the shoulder of Beth-arabah<note nid="n06018018.1"/> it goes down to <crossref let="l" cid="c06018018.2"/>the Arabah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018019"/>
    <verse num="19">Then the boundary passes on to the north of the shoulder of <crossref let="k" cid="c06018019.1"/>Beth-hoglah. And the boundary ends at the northern bay of <crossref let="m" cid="c06018019.2"/>the Salt Sea, at the south end of the Jordan: this is the southern border.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018020"/>
    <verse num="20">The Jordan forms its boundary on the eastern side. This is the inheritance of the people of Benjamin, according to their clans, boundary by boundary all around.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018021"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="21">Now the cities of the tribe of the people of Benjamin according to their clans were <crossref let="n" cid="c06018021.1"/>Jericho, Beth-hoglah, Emek-keziz,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018022"/>
    <verse num="22">Beth-arabah, Zemaraim, Bethel,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018023"/>
    <verse num="23">Avvim, Parah, Ophrah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018024"/>
    <verse num="24">Chephar-ammoni, Ophni, Geba&emdash;twelve cities with their villages:</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018025"/>
    <verse num="25">Gibeon, Ramah, Beeroth,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018026"/>
    <verse num="26">Mizpeh, Chephirah, Mozah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018027"/>
    <verse num="27">Rekem, Irpeel, Taralah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06018028"/>
    <verse num="28">Zela, Haeleph, <crossref let="o" cid="c06018028.1"/>Jebus<note nid="n06018028.1"/> (that is, Jerusalem), Gibeah<note nid="n06018028.2"/> and Kiriath-jearim<note nid="n06018028.3"/>&emdash;fourteen cities with their villages. This is the inheritance of the people of Benjamin according to its clans.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019001"/>
  <chapter num="19">
    <heading>The Inheritance for Simeon</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">The second lot came out for Simeon, for the tribe of the people of Simeon, according to their clans, <crossref let="p" cid="c06019001.1"/>and their inheritance was in the midst of the inheritance of the people of Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="q" cid="c06019002.1"/>And they had for their inheritance Beersheba, Sheba, Moladah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019003"/>
    <verse num="3">Hazar-shual, Balah, Ezem,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019004"/>
    <verse num="4">Eltolad, Bethul, Hormah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019005"/>
    <verse num="5">Ziklag, Beth-marcaboth, Hazar-susah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019006"/>
    <verse num="6">Beth-lebaoth, and Sharuhen&emdash;thirteen cities with their villages;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019007"/>
    <verse num="7">Ain, Rimmon, Ether, and Ashan&emdash;four cities with their villages,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019008"/>
    <verse num="8">together with all the villages around these cities as far as Baalath-beer, Ramah of the Negeb. This was the inheritance of the tribe of the people of Simeon according to their clans.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="r" cid="c06019009.1"/>The inheritance of the people of Simeon formed part of the territory of the people of Judah. Because the portion of the people of Judah was too large for them, the people of Simeon obtained an inheritance in the midst of their inheritance.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019010"/>
    <heading>The Inheritance for Zebulun</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">The third lot came up for the people of Zebulun, according to their clans. And the territory of their inheritance reached as far as Sarid.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019011"/>
    <verse num="11">Then their boundary goes up <crossref let="s" cid="c06019011.1"/>westward and on to Mareal and touches Dabbesheth, then the brook that is east of <crossref let="t" cid="c06019011.2"/>Jokneam.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019012"/>
    <verse num="12">From Sarid it goes in the other direction eastward toward the sunrise to the boundary of Chisloth-tabor. From there it goes to Daberath, then up to Japhia.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019013"/>
    <verse num="13">From there it passes along on the east toward the sunrise to Gath-hepher, to Eth-kazin, and going on to Rimmon it bends toward Neah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019014"/>
    <verse num="14">then on the north the boundary turns about to Hannathon, and it ends at the Valley of Iphtahel;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019015"/>
    <verse num="15">and Kattath, Nahalal, <crossref let="u" cid="c06019015.1"/>Shimron, Idalah, and Bethlehem&emdash;twelve cities with their villages.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019016"/>
    <verse num="16">This is the inheritance of the people of Zebulun, according to their clans&emdash;these cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019017"/>
    <heading>The Inheritance for Issachar</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17">The fourth lot came out for Issachar, for the people of Issachar, according to their clans.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019018"/>
    <verse num="18">Their territory included Jezreel, Chesulloth, <crossref let="v" cid="c06019018.1"/>Shunem,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019019"/>
    <verse num="19">Hapharaim, Shion, Anaharath,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019020"/>
    <verse num="20">Rabbith, Kishion, Ebez,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019021"/>
    <verse num="21">Remeth, En-gannim, En-haddah, Beth-pazzez.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019022"/>
    <verse num="22">The boundary also touches Tabor, Shahazumah, and Beth-shemesh, and its boundary ends at the Jordan&emdash;sixteen cities with their villages.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019023"/>
    <verse num="23">This is the inheritance of the tribe of the people of Issachar, according to their clans&emdash;the cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019024"/>
    <heading>The Inheritance for Asher</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24">The fifth lot came out for the tribe of the people of Asher according to their clans.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019025"/>
    <verse num="25">Their territory included Helkath, Hali, Beten, Achshaph,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019026"/>
    <verse num="26">Allammelech, Amad, and Mishal. On the west it touches <crossref let="w" cid="c06019026.1"/>Carmel and Shihor-libnath,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019027"/>
    <verse num="27">then it turns eastward, it goes to Beth-dagon, and touches Zebulun and the Valley of Iphtahel northward to Beth-emek and Neiel. Then it continues in the north to <crossref let="x" cid="c06019027.1"/>Cabul,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019028"/>
    <verse num="28">Ebron, Rehob, Hammon, Kanah, as far as <crossref let="y" cid="c06019028.1"/>Sidon the Great.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019029"/>
    <verse num="29">Then the boundary turns to Ramah, reaching to the fortified city of Tyre. Then the boundary turns to Hosah, and it ends at the sea; Mahalab,<note nid="n06019029.1"/> Achzib,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019030"/>
    <verse num="30">Ummah, Aphek and Rehob&emdash;twenty-two cities with their villages.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019031"/>
    <verse num="31">This is the inheritance of the tribe of the people of Asher according to their clans&emdash;these cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019032"/>
    <heading>The Inheritance for Naphtali</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="32">The sixth lot came out for the people of Naphtali, for the people of Naphtali, according to their clans.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019033"/>
    <verse num="33">And their boundary ran from Heleph, from <crossref let="z" cid="c06019033.1"/>the oak in Zaanannim, and Adami-nekeb, and Jabneel, as far as Lakkum, and it ended at the Jordan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019034"/>
    <verse num="34">Then the boundary turns <crossref let="a" cid="c06019034.1"/>westward to Aznoth-tabor and goes from there to Hukkok, touching Zebulun at the south and Asher on the west and Judah on the east at the Jordan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019035"/>
    <verse num="35">The fortified cities are Ziddim, Zer, Hammath, Rakkath, <crossref let="b" cid="c06019035.1"/>Chinnereth,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019036"/>
    <verse num="36">Adamah, Ramah, <crossref let="c" cid="c06019036.1"/>Hazor,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019037"/>
    <verse num="37">Kedesh, Edrei, En-hazor,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019038"/>
    <verse num="38">Yiron, Migdal-el, Horem, Beth-anath, and Beth-shemesh&emdash;nineteen cities with their villages.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019039"/>
    <verse num="39">This is the inheritance of the tribe of the people of Naphtali according to their clans&emdash;the cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019040"/>
    <heading>The Inheritance for Dan</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="40">The seventh lot came out for the tribe of the people of Dan, according to their clans.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019041"/>
    <verse num="41">And the territory of its inheritance included Zorah, Eshtaol, Ir-shemesh,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019042"/>
    <verse num="42"><crossref let="d" cid="c06019042.1"/>Shaalabbin, <crossref let="d" cid="c06019042.2"/>Aijalon, Ithlah,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019043"/>
    <verse num="43">Elon, Timnah, Ekron,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019044"/>
    <verse num="44">Eltekeh, Gibbethon, Baalath,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019045"/>
    <verse num="45">Jehud, Bene-berak, Gath-rimmon,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019046"/>
    <verse num="46">and Me-jarkon and Rakkon with the territory over against <crossref let="e" cid="c06019046.1"/>Joppa.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019047"/>
    <verse num="47">When <crossref let="f" cid="c06019047.1"/>the territory of the people of Dan was lost to them, the people of Dan went up and fought against Leshem, and after capturing it and striking it with the sword they took possession of it and settled in it, calling Leshem, Dan, after the name of Dan their ancestor.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019048"/>
    <verse num="48">This is the inheritance of the tribe of the people of Dan, according to their clans&emdash;these cities with their villages.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019049"/>
    <heading>The Inheritance for Joshua</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="49">When they had finished distributing the several territories of the land as inheritances, the people of Israel gave an inheritance among them to Joshua the son of Nun.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019050"/>
    <verse num="50">By command of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> they gave him the city that he asked, <crossref let="g" cid="c06019050.1"/>Timnath-serah in the hill country of Ephraim. And he rebuilt the city and settled in it.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06019051"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="51"><crossref let="h" cid="c06019051.1"/>These are the inheritances that Eleazar the priest and Joshua the son of Nun and the heads of the fathers&apos; houses of the tribes of the people of Israel distributed by lot <crossref let="i" cid="c06019051.2"/>at Shiloh before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, at the entrance of the tent of meeting. So they finished dividing the land.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06020001"/>
  <chapter num="20">
    <heading>The Cities of Refuge</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Then the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Joshua,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06020002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="06020002.1" from="06020002.1" to="06020006.2"/>Say to the people of Israel, <crossref let="j" cid="c06020002.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="06020002.2" from="06020002.2" to="06020006.1"/>Appoint the cities of refuge, of which I spoke to you through Moses,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06020003"/>
    <verse num="3">that the manslayer who strikes any person without intent or unknowingly may flee there. They shall be for you a refuge from the avenger of blood.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06020004"/>
    <verse num="4">He shall flee to one of these cities and shall stand <crossref let="k" cid="c06020004.1"/>at the entrance of the gate of the city and explain his case to the elders of that city. Then they shall take him into the city and give him a place, and he shall remain with them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06020005"/>
    <verse num="5">And if the avenger of blood pursues him, they shall not give up the manslayer into his hand, because he struck his neighbor unknowingly, and did not hate him in the past.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06020006"/>
    <verse num="6">And he shall remain in that city <crossref let="l" cid="c06020006.1"/>until he has stood before the congregation for judgment, until the death of him who is high priest at the time. Then the manslayer may return to his own town and his own home, to the town from which he fled.<q class="end-single" qid="06020006.1" from="06020002.2" to="06020006.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="06020006.2" from="06020002.1" to="06020006.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06020007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">So they set apart <crossref let="m" cid="c06020007.1"/>Kedesh in Galilee in the hill country of Naphtali, and <crossref let="n" cid="c06020007.2"/>Shechem in the hill country of Ephraim, and <crossref let="o" cid="c06020007.3"/>Kiriath-arba (that is, Hebron) <crossref let="p" cid="c06020007.4"/>in the hill country of Judah.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06020008"/>
    <verse num="8">And beyond the Jordan east of Jericho, they appointed <crossref let="q" cid="c06020008.1"/>Bezer in the wilderness on the tableland, from the tribe of Reuben, and <crossref let="r" cid="c06020008.2"/>Ramoth in Gilead, from the tribe of Gad, and <crossref let="s" cid="c06020008.3"/>Golan in Bashan, from the tribe of Manasseh.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06020009"/>
    <verse num="9">These were the cities designated for all the people of Israel and <crossref let="t" cid="c06020009.1"/>for the stranger sojourning among them, that anyone who killed a person without intent could flee there, so that he might not die by the hand of the avenger of blood, till he stood before the congregation.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021001"/>
  <chapter num="21">
    <heading>Cities and Pasturelands Allotted to Levi</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Then the heads of the fathers&apos; houses of the Levites came <crossref let="u" cid="c06021001.1"/>to Eleazar the priest and to Joshua the son of Nun and to the heads of the fathers&apos; houses of the tribes of the people of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021002"/>
    <verse num="2">And they said to them <crossref let="v" cid="c06021002.1"/>at Shiloh in the land of Canaan, <crossref let="w" cid="c06021002.2"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06021002.1" from="06021002.1" to="06021002.2"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded through Moses that we be given cities to dwell in, along with their pasturelands for our livestock.<q class="end-double" qid="06021002.2" from="06021002.1" to="06021002.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021003"/>
    <verse num="3">So by command of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> the people of Israel gave to the Levites the following cities and pasturelands out of their inheritance.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">The lot came out for the clans of the Kohathites. So those Levites who were descendants of Aaron the priest <crossref let="x" cid="c06021004.1"/>received by lot from the tribes of Judah, Simeon, and Benjamin, thirteen cities.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021005"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5">And the rest of the Kohathites received by lot <crossref let="y" cid="c06021005.1"/>from the clans of the tribe of Ephraim, from the tribe of Dan and the half-tribe of Manasseh, ten cities.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6">The <crossref let="z" cid="c06021006.1"/>Gershonites received by lot from the clans of the tribe of Issachar, from the tribe of Asher, from the tribe of Naphtali, and from the half-tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteen cities.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">The <crossref let="a" cid="c06021007.1"/>Merarites according to their clans received from the tribe of Reuben, the tribe of Gad, and the tribe of Zebulun, twelve cities.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">These cities and their pasturelands the people of Israel <crossref let="b" cid="c06021008.1"/>gave by lot to the Levites, <crossref let="c" cid="c06021008.2"/>as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had commanded through Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021009"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9">Out of the tribe of the people of Judah and the tribe of the people of Simeon they gave the following cities mentioned by name,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021010"/>
    <verse num="10">which went to <crossref let="d" cid="c06021010.1"/>the descendants of Aaron, one of the clans of the Kohathites who belonged to the people of Levi; since the lot fell to them first.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="e" cid="c06021011.1"/>They gave them <crossref let="f" cid="c06021011.2"/>Kiriath-arba (Arba being the father of Anak), that is Hebron, <crossref let="g" cid="c06021011.3"/>in the hill country of Judah, along with the pasturelands around it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021012"/>
    <verse num="12">But the fields of the city and its villages had been given to Caleb the son of Jephunneh as his possession.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">And to the descendants of Aaron the priest they gave Hebron, <crossref let="h" cid="c06021013.1"/>the city of refuge for the manslayer, with its pasturelands, <crossref let="i" cid="c06021013.2"/>Libnah with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021014"/>
    <verse num="14">Jattir with its pasturelands, Eshtemoa with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021015"/>
    <verse num="15">Holon with its pasturelands, Debir with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021016"/>
    <verse num="16">Ain with its pasturelands, Juttah with its pasturelands, Beth-shemesh with its pasturelands&emdash;nine cities out of these two tribes;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021017"/>
    <verse num="17">then out of the tribe of Benjamin, <crossref let="j" cid="c06021017.1"/>Gibeon with its pasturelands, Geba with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021018"/>
    <verse num="18">Anathoth with its pasturelands, and Almon with its pasturelands&emdash;four cities.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021019"/>
    <verse num="19">The cities of the descendants of Aaron, the priests, were in all thirteen cities with their pasturelands.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021020"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="k" cid="c06021020.1"/>As to the rest of the Kohathites belonging to the Kohathite clans of the Levites, the cities allotted to them were out of the tribe of Ephraim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021021"/>
    <verse num="21">To them were given Shechem, <crossref let="l" cid="c06021021.1"/>the city of refuge for the manslayer, with its pasturelands in the hill country of Ephraim, Gezer with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021022"/>
    <verse num="22">Kibzaim with its pasturelands, Beth-horon with its pasturelands&emdash;four cities;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021023"/>
    <verse num="23">and out of the tribe of Dan, Elteke with its pasturelands, Gibbethon with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021024"/>
    <verse num="24">Aijalon with its pasturelands, Gath-rimmon with its pasturelands&emdash;four cities;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021025"/>
    <verse num="25">and out of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Taanach with its pasturelands, and Gath-rimmon with its pasturelands&emdash;two cities.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021026"/>
    <verse num="26">The cities of the clans of the rest of the Kohathites were ten in all with their pasturelands.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021027"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="27"><crossref let="m" cid="c06021027.1"/>And to the Gershonites, one of the clans of the Levites, were given out of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Golan in Bashan with its pasturelands, <crossref let="l" cid="c06021027.2"/>the city of refuge for the manslayer, and Beeshterah with its pasturelands&emdash;two cities;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021028"/>
    <verse num="28">and out of the tribe of Issachar, Kishion with its pasturelands, Daberath with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021029"/>
    <verse num="29">Jarmuth with its pasturelands, En-gannim with its pasturelands&emdash;four cities;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021030"/>
    <verse num="30">and out of the tribe of Asher, Mishal with its pasturelands, Abdon with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021031"/>
    <verse num="31">Helkath with its pasturelands, and Rehob with its pasturelands&emdash;four cities;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021032"/>
    <verse num="32">and out of the tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee with its pasturelands, <crossref let="l" cid="c06021032.1"/>the city of refuge for the manslayer, Hammoth-dor with its pasturelands, and Kartan with its pasturelands&emdash;three cities.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021033"/>
    <verse num="33">The cities of the several clans of the Gershonites were in all thirteen cities with their pasturelands.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021034"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="34"><crossref let="n" cid="c06021034.1"/>And to the rest of the Levites, the Merarite clans, were given out of the tribe of Zebulun, Jokneam with its pasturelands, Kartah with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021035"/>
    <verse num="35">Dimnah with its pasturelands, Nahalal with its pasturelands&emdash;four cities;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021036"/>
    <verse num="36">and out of the tribe of Reuben, <crossref let="o" cid="c06021036.1"/>Bezer with its pasturelands, Jahaz with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021037"/>
    <verse num="37">Kedemoth with its pasturelands, and Mephaath with its pasturelands&emdash;four cities;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021038"/>
    <verse num="38">and out of the tribe of Gad, <crossref let="o" cid="c06021038.1"/>Ramoth in Gilead with its pasturelands, the city of refuge for the manslayer, <crossref let="p" cid="c06021038.2"/>Mahanaim with its pasturelands,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021039"/>
    <verse num="39"><crossref let="p" cid="c06021039.1"/>Heshbon with its pasturelands, Jazer with its pasturelands&emdash;four cities in all.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021040"/>
    <verse num="40">As for the cities of the several Merarite clans, that is, the remainder of the clans of the Levites, those allotted to them were in all twelve cities.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021041"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="41"><crossref let="q" cid="c06021041.1"/>The cities of the Levites in the midst of the possession of the people of Israel were in all forty-eight cities with their pasturelands.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021042"/>
    <verse num="42">These cities each had its pasturelands around it. So it was with all these cities.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021043"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="43"><crossref let="r" cid="c06021043.1"/>Thus the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave to Israel all the land that he swore to give to their fathers. And they took possession of it, and they settled there.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021044"/>
    <verse num="44"><crossref let="s" cid="c06021044.1"/>And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave them rest on every side just as he had sworn to their fathers. <crossref let="t" cid="c06021044.2"/>Not one of all their enemies had withstood them, for <crossref let="u" cid="c06021044.3"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had given all their enemies into their hands.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06021045"/>
    <verse num="45"><crossref let="v" cid="c06021045.1"/>Not one word of all the good promises that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had made to the house of Israel had failed; all came to pass.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022001"/>
  <chapter num="22">
    <heading>The Eastern Tribes Return Home</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">At that time Joshua summoned the Reubenites and the Gadites and the half-tribe of Manasseh,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022002"/>
    <verse num="2">and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="06022002.1" from="06022002.1" to="06022005.1"/>You have kept <crossref let="w" cid="c06022002.1"/>all that Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded you <crossref let="x" cid="c06022002.2"/>and have obeyed my voice in all that I have commanded you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022003"/>
    <verse num="3">You have not forsaken your brothers these many days, down to this day, but have been careful to keep the charge of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="y" cid="c06022004.1"/>And now the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God has given rest to your brothers, as he promised them. Therefore turn and go to your tents in the land where your possession lies, <crossref let="z" cid="c06022004.2"/>which Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> gave you on the other side of the Jordan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022005"/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="a" cid="c06022005.1"/>Only be very careful to observe the commandment and the law that Moses the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded you, <crossref let="b" cid="c06022005.2"/>to love the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God, and to walk in all his ways and to keep his commandments and to cling to him and to serve him with all your heart and with all your soul.<q class="end-double" qid="06022005.1" from="06022002.1" to="06022005.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022006"/>
    <verse num="6">So Joshua <crossref let="c" cid="c06022006.1"/>blessed them and sent them away, and they went to their tents.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7">Now to the one half of the tribe of Manasseh Moses had given a possession in Bashan, <crossref let="d" cid="c06022007.1"/>but to the other half Joshua had given a possession beside their brothers in the land west of the Jordan. And when Joshua sent them away to their homes and blessed them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022008"/>
    <verse num="8">he said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="06022008.1" from="06022008.1" to="06022008.2"/>Go back to your tents with much wealth and with very much livestock, with silver, gold, bronze, and iron, and with much clothing. <crossref let="e" cid="c06022008.1"/>Divide the spoil of your enemies with your brothers.<q class="end-double" qid="06022008.2" from="06022008.1" to="06022008.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022009"/>
    <verse num="9">So the people of Reuben and the people of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh returned home, parting from the people of Israel at Shiloh, which is in the land of Canaan, to go <crossref let="f" cid="c06022009.1"/>to the land of Gilead, their own land of which they had possessed themselves by command of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> through Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022010"/>
    <heading>The Eastern Tribes&apos; Altar of Witness</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">And when they came to the region of the Jordan that is in the land of Canaan, the people of Reuben and the people of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh built there an altar by the Jordan, an altar of imposing size.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022011"/>
    <verse num="11">And the people of Israel <crossref let="g" cid="c06022011.1"/>heard it said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06022011.1" from="06022011.1" to="06022011.2"/>Behold, the people of Reuben and the people of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh have built the altar at the frontier of the land of Canaan, in the region about the Jordan, on the side that belongs to the people of Israel.<q class="end-double" qid="06022011.2" from="06022011.1" to="06022011.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022012"/>
    <verse num="12">And when the people of Israel heard of it, <crossref let="h" cid="c06022012.1"/>the whole assembly of the people of Israel gathered at Shiloh to make war against them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">Then the people of Israel sent to the people of Reuben and the people of Gad and the half-tribe of Manasseh, in the land of Gilead, <crossref let="i" cid="c06022013.1"/>Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022014"/>
    <verse num="14">and with him ten chiefs, one from each of the tribal families of Israel, <crossref let="j" cid="c06022014.1"/>every one of them the head of a family among the clans of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022015"/>
    <verse num="15">And they came to the people of Reuben, the people of Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, in the land of Gilead, and they said to them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022016"/>
    <verse num="16"><q class="begin-double" qid="06022016.1" from="06022016.1" to="06022020.2"/>Thus says the whole congregation of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <q class="begin-single" qid="06022016.2" from="06022016.2" to="06022020.1"/>What is this breach of faith that you have committed against the God of Israel in turning away this day from following the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> by building yourselves an altar this day <crossref let="k" cid="c06022016.1"/>in rebellion against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022017"/>
    <verse num="17">Have we not had enough of <crossref let="l" cid="c06022017.1"/>the sin at Peor from which even yet we have not cleansed ourselves, and for which there came a plague upon the congregation of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022018"/>
    <verse num="18">that you too must turn away this day from following the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>? And if <crossref let="k" cid="c06022018.1"/>you too rebel against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> today then tomorrow <crossref let="m" cid="c06022018.2"/>he will be angry with the whole congregation of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022019"/>
    <verse num="19">But now, if the land of your possession is unclean, pass over into the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s land <crossref let="n" cid="c06022019.1"/>where the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s tabernacle stands, and take for yourselves a possession among us. <crossref let="o" cid="c06022019.2"/>Only do not rebel against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> or make us as rebels by building for yourselves an altar other than the altar of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="p" cid="c06022020.1"/>Did not Achan the son of Zerah break faith in the matter of the devoted things, and <crossref let="m" cid="c06022020.2"/>wrath fell upon all the congregation of Israel? And he did not perish alone for his iniquity.<q class="end-single" qid="06022020.1" from="06022016.2" to="06022020.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="06022020.2" from="06022016.1" to="06022020.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022021"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="21">Then the people of Reuben, the people of Gad, and the half-tribe of Manasseh said in answer to the heads of the families of Israel,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022022"/>
    <verse num="22"><q class="begin-double" qid="06022022.1" from="06022022.1" to="06022029.1"/>The Mighty One, <crossref let="q" cid="c06022022.1"/>God, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>! The Mighty One, God, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>! <crossref let="r" cid="c06022022.2"/>He knows; and let Israel itself know! If it was in rebellion or in breach of faith against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, do not spare us today</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022023"/>
    <verse num="23">for building an altar to turn away from following the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. Or if we did so to offer burnt offerings or grain offerings or peace offerings on it, may the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> himself <crossref let="s" cid="c06022023.1"/>take vengeance.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022024"/>
    <verse num="24">No, but we did it from fear that <crossref let="t" cid="c06022024.1"/>in time to come your children might say to our children, <q class="begin-single" qid="06022024.1" from="06022024.1" to="06022025.1"/>What have you to do with the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022025"/>
    <verse num="25">For the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has made the Jordan a boundary between us and you, you people of Reuben and people of Gad. You have no portion in the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-single" qid="06022025.1" from="06022024.1" to="06022025.1"/> So your children might make our children cease to worship the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022026"/>
    <verse num="26">Therefore we said, <q class="begin-single" qid="06022026.1" from="06022026.1" to="06022027.3"/>Let us now build an altar, not for burnt offering, nor for sacrifice,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022027"/>
    <verse num="27">but to be <crossref let="u" cid="c06022027.1"/>a witness between us and you, and between our generations after us, that we <crossref let="v" cid="c06022027.2"/>do perform the service of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in his presence with our burnt offerings and sacrifices and peace offerings, so your children will not say to our children in time to come, <q class="begin-inner-double" qid="06022027.1" from="06022027.1" to="06022027.2"/>You have no portion in the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-inner-double" qid="06022027.2" from="06022027.1" to="06022027.2"/><q class="end-single" qid="06022027.3" from="06022026.1" to="06022027.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022028"/>
    <verse num="28">And we thought, <q class="begin-single" qid="06022028.1" from="06022028.1" to="06022028.4"/>If this should be said to us or to our descendants in time to come, we should say, <q class="begin-double" qid="06022028.2" from="06022028.2" to="06022028.3"/>Behold, the copy of the altar of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, which our fathers made, not for burnt offerings, nor for sacrifice, but to be <crossref let="u" cid="c06022028.1"/>a witness between us and you.<q class="end-double" qid="06022028.3" from="06022028.2" to="06022028.3"/><q class="end-single" qid="06022028.4" from="06022028.1" to="06022028.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022029"/>
    <verse num="29">Far be it from us that we should <crossref let="w" cid="c06022029.1"/>rebel against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and turn away this day from following the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="w" cid="c06022029.2"/>by building an altar for burnt offering, grain offering, or sacrifice, other than the altar of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God that stands before his tabernacle!<q class="end-double" qid="06022029.1" from="06022022.1" to="06022029.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022030"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="30">When <crossref let="x" cid="c06022030.1"/>Phinehas the priest and the chiefs of the congregation, the heads of the families of Israel who were with him, heard the words that the people of Reuben and the people of Gad and the people of Manasseh spoke, <crossref let="y" cid="c06022030.2"/>it was good in their eyes.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022031"/>
    <verse num="31">And Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest said to the people of Reuben and the people of Gad and the people of Manasseh, <q class="begin-double" qid="06022031.1" from="06022031.1" to="06022031.2"/>Today we know that <crossref let="z" cid="c06022031.1"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is in our midst, because you have not committed this breach of faith against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. Now you have delivered the people of Israel from the hand of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="06022031.2" from="06022031.1" to="06022031.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022032"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="32">Then Phinehas the son of Eleazar the priest, and the chiefs, returned from the people of Reuben and the people of Gad <crossref let="a" cid="c06022032.1"/>in the land of Gilead to the land of Canaan, to the people of Israel, and brought back word to them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022033"/>
    <verse num="33">And the report <crossref let="b" cid="c06022033.1"/>was good in the eyes of the people of Israel. And the people of Israel <crossref let="c" cid="c06022033.2"/>blessed God and spoke no more of making war against them to destroy the land where the people of Reuben and the people of Gad were settled.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06022034"/>
    <verse num="34">The people of Reuben and the people of Gad called the altar Witness, <q class="begin-double" qid="06022034.1" from="06022034.1" to="06022034.2"/>For,<q class="end-double" qid="06022034.2" from="06022034.1" to="06022034.2"/> they said, <crossref let="d" cid="c06022034.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="06022034.3" from="06022034.3" to="06022034.4"/>it is a witness between us that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is God.<q class="end-double" qid="06022034.4" from="06022034.3" to="06022034.4"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023001"/>
  <chapter num="23">
    <heading>Joshua&apos;s Charge to Israel&apos;s Leaders</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">A long time afterward, when the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> had given <crossref let="e" cid="c06023001.1"/>rest to Israel from all their surrounding enemies, and Joshua <crossref let="f" cid="c06023001.2"/>was old and well advanced in years,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023002"/>
    <verse num="2">Joshua <crossref let="g" cid="c06023002.1"/>summoned all Israel, its elders and heads, its judges and officers, and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="06023002.1" from="06023002.1" to="06023016.1"/>I am now old and well advanced in years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023003"/>
    <verse num="3">And you have seen all that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God has done to all these nations for your sake, <crossref let="h" cid="c06023003.1"/>for it is the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God who has fought for you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023004"/>
    <verse num="4">Behold, <crossref let="i" cid="c06023004.1"/>I have allotted to you as an inheritance for your tribes those nations that remain, along with all the nations that I have already cut off, from the Jordan to the Great Sea in the west.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023005"/>
    <verse num="5">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God <crossref let="j" cid="c06023005.1"/>will push them back before you and drive them out of your sight. And you shall possess their land, <crossref let="k" cid="c06023005.2"/>just as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God promised you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023006"/>
    <verse num="6">Therefore, <crossref let="l" cid="c06023006.1"/>be very strong to keep and to do all that is written in the Book of the Law of Moses, <crossref let="m" cid="c06023006.2"/>turning aside from it neither to the right hand nor to the left,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="n" cid="c06023007.1"/>that you may not mix with these nations remaining among you <crossref let="o" cid="c06023007.2"/>or make mention of the names of their gods <crossref let="p" cid="c06023007.3"/>or swear by them or serve them or bow down to them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="q" cid="c06023008.1"/>but you shall cling to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God just as you have done to this day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="r" cid="c06023009.1"/>For the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has driven out before you great and strong nations. And as for you, <crossref let="s" cid="c06023009.2"/>no man has been able to stand before you to this day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="t" cid="c06023010.1"/>One man of you puts to flight a thousand, since it is the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God <crossref let="u" cid="c06023010.2"/>who fights for you, just as he promised you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="v" cid="c06023011.1"/>Be very careful, therefore, to love the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023012"/>
    <verse num="12">For if you turn back and cling to the remnant of these nations remaining among you <crossref let="w" cid="c06023012.1"/>and make marriages with them, so that you associate with them and they with you,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023013"/>
    <verse num="13">know for certain that <crossref let="x" cid="c06023013.1"/>the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God will no longer drive out these nations before you, <crossref let="y" cid="c06023013.2"/>but they shall be a snare and a trap for you, a whip on your sides and thorns in your eyes, until you perish from off this good ground that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God has given you.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14"><q class="continue-double" qid="06023014.1" from="06023002.1" to="06023016.1"/>And now <crossref let="z" cid="c06023014.1"/>I am about to go the way of all the earth, and you know in your hearts and souls, all of you, that <crossref let="a" cid="c06023014.2"/>not one word has failed of all the good things<note nid="n06023014.1"/> that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God promised concerning you. All have come to pass for you; not one of them has failed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023015"/>
    <verse num="15">But just as all the good things that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God promised concerning you have been fulfilled for you, so the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will bring upon you <crossref let="b" cid="c06023015.1"/>all the evil things, until he has destroyed you from off this good land that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God has given you,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06023016"/>
    <verse num="16">if you transgress the covenant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God, which he commanded you, and go and serve other gods and bow down to them. Then the anger of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will be kindled against you, and you shall perish quickly from off the good land that he has given to you.<q class="end-double" qid="06023016.1" from="06023002.1" to="06023016.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024001"/>
  <chapter num="24">
    <heading>The Covenant Renewal at Shechem</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Joshua gathered all the tribes of Israel <crossref let="c" cid="c06024001.1"/>to Shechem and <crossref let="d" cid="c06024001.2"/>summoned the elders, the heads, the judges, and the officers of Israel. And <crossref let="e" cid="c06024001.3"/>they presented themselves before God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024002"/>
    <verse num="2">And Joshua said to all the people, <q class="begin-double" qid="06024002.1" from="06024002.1" to="06024015.1"/>Thus says the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel, <q class="begin-single" qid="06024002.2" from="06024002.2" to="06024013.1"/>Long ago, <crossref let="f" cid="c06024002.1"/>your fathers lived beyond the Euphrates,<note nid="n06024002.1"/> Terah, the father of Abraham and of Nahor; and <crossref let="g" cid="c06024002.2"/>they served other gods.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024003"/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="h" cid="c06024003.1"/>Then I took your father Abraham from beyond the River<note nid="n06024003.1"/> and <crossref let="i" cid="c06024003.2"/>led him through all the land of Canaan, and made his offspring many. <crossref let="j" cid="c06024003.3"/>I gave him Isaac.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024004"/>
    <verse num="4">And to Isaac I gave <crossref let="k" cid="c06024004.1"/>Jacob and Esau. <crossref let="l" cid="c06024004.2"/>And I gave Esau the hill country of Seir to possess, <crossref let="m" cid="c06024004.3"/>but Jacob and his children went down to Egypt.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024005"/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="n" cid="c06024005.1"/>And I sent Moses and Aaron, <crossref let="o" cid="c06024005.2"/>and I plagued Egypt with what I did in the midst of it, and <crossref let="p" cid="c06024005.3"/>afterward I brought you out.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6"><q class="continue-double" qid="06024006.1" from="06024002.1" to="06024015.1"/><q class="continue-single" qid="06024006.2" from="06024002.2" to="06024013.1"/>Then <crossref let="p" cid="c06024006.1"/>I brought your fathers out of Egypt, and <crossref let="q" cid="c06024006.2"/>you came to the sea. <crossref let="r" cid="c06024006.3"/>And the Egyptians pursued your fathers with chariots and horsemen to the Red Sea.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="s" cid="c06024007.1"/>And when they cried to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="t" cid="c06024007.2"/>he put darkness between you and the Egyptians <crossref let="u" cid="c06024007.3"/>and made the sea come upon them and cover them; <crossref let="v" cid="c06024007.4"/>and your eyes saw what I did in Egypt. <crossref let="w" cid="c06024007.5"/>And you lived in the wilderness a long time.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024008"/>
    <verse num="8">Then I brought you to the land of the Amorites, who lived on the other side of the Jordan. <crossref let="x" cid="c06024008.1"/>They fought with you, and I gave them into your hand, and you took possession of their land, and I destroyed them before you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="y" cid="c06024009.1"/>Then Balak the son of Zippor, king of Moab, arose and fought against Israel. <crossref let="z" cid="c06024009.2"/>And he sent and invited Balaam the son of Beor to curse you,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="a" cid="c06024010.1"/>but I would not listen to Balaam. <crossref let="a" cid="c06024010.2"/>Indeed, he blessed you. So I delivered you out of his hand.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="b" cid="c06024011.1"/>And you went over the Jordan and came to Jericho, <crossref let="c" cid="c06024011.2"/>and the leaders of Jericho fought against you, and also <crossref let="c" cid="c06024011.3"/>the Amorites, the Perizzites, the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Girgashites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites. And I gave them into your hand.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024012"/>
    <verse num="12">And I sent <crossref let="d" cid="c06024012.1"/>the hornet before you, which drove them out before you, the two kings of the Amorites; it was <crossref let="e" cid="c06024012.2"/>not by your sword or by your bow.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024013"/>
    <verse num="13">I gave you a land on which you had not labored <crossref let="f" cid="c06024013.1"/>and cities that you had not built, and you dwell in them. You eat the fruit of vineyards and olive orchards that you did not plant.<q class="end-single" qid="06024013.1" from="06024002.2" to="06024013.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024014"/>
    <heading>Choose Whom You Will Serve</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="g" cid="c06024014.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="06024014.1" from="06024002.1" to="06024015.1"/>Now therefore fear the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and serve him in sincerity and in faithfulness. <crossref let="h" cid="c06024014.2"/>Put away the gods that your fathers served beyond the River and in Egypt, and serve the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="i" cid="c06024015.1"/>And if it is evil in your eyes to serve the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="j" cid="c06024015.2"/>choose this day whom you will serve, whether <crossref let="h" cid="c06024015.3"/>the gods your fathers served in the region beyond the River, or <crossref let="k" cid="c06024015.4"/>the gods of the Amorites in whose land you dwell. <crossref let="l" cid="c06024015.5"/>But as for me and my house, we will serve the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="06024015.1" from="06024002.1" to="06024015.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">Then the people answered, <q class="begin-double" qid="06024016.1" from="06024016.1" to="06024018.1"/>Far be it from us that we should forsake the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to serve other gods,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024017"/>
    <verse num="17">for it is the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God who brought us and our fathers up from the land of Egypt, out of the house of slavery, and who did those great signs in our sight and preserved us in all the way that we went, and among all the peoples through whom we passed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024018"/>
    <verse num="18">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> drove out before us all the peoples, the Amorites who lived in the land. Therefore we also will serve the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, for he is our God.<q class="end-double" qid="06024018.1" from="06024016.1" to="06024018.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19">But Joshua said to the people, <q class="begin-double" qid="06024019.1" from="06024019.1" to="06024020.1"/>You are not able to serve the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, for he is <crossref let="m" cid="c06024019.1"/>a holy God. He is <crossref let="n" cid="c06024019.2"/>a jealous God; <crossref let="o" cid="c06024019.3"/>he will not forgive your transgressions or your sins.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="p" cid="c06024020.1"/>If you forsake the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and serve foreign gods, then <crossref let="q" cid="c06024020.2"/>he will turn and do you harm and consume you, after having done you good.<q class="end-double" qid="06024020.1" from="06024019.1" to="06024020.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024021"/>
    <verse num="21">And the people said to Joshua, <q class="begin-double" qid="06024021.1" from="06024021.1" to="06024021.2"/>No, but we will serve the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="06024021.2" from="06024021.1" to="06024021.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024022"/>
    <verse num="22">Then Joshua said to the people, <q class="begin-double" qid="06024022.1" from="06024022.1" to="06024022.2"/>You are witnesses against yourselves that <crossref let="r" cid="c06024022.1"/>you have chosen the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, to serve him.<q class="end-double" qid="06024022.2" from="06024022.1" to="06024022.2"/> And they said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06024022.3" from="06024022.3" to="06024022.4"/>We are witnesses.<q class="end-double" qid="06024022.4" from="06024022.3" to="06024022.4"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024023"/>
    <verse num="23">He said, <q class="begin-double" qid="06024023.1" from="06024023.1" to="06024023.2"/>Then <crossref let="s" cid="c06024023.1"/>put away the foreign gods that are among you, and incline your heart to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the God of Israel.<q class="end-double" qid="06024023.2" from="06024023.1" to="06024023.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024024"/>
    <verse num="24">And the people said to Joshua, <q class="begin-double" qid="06024024.1" from="06024024.1" to="06024024.2"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> our God we will serve, and his voice we will obey.<q class="end-double" qid="06024024.2" from="06024024.1" to="06024024.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024025"/>
    <verse num="25">So Joshua <crossref let="t" cid="c06024025.1"/>made a covenant with the people that day, and put in place <crossref let="u" cid="c06024025.2"/>statutes and rules for them at Shechem.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024026"/>
    <verse num="26">And Joshua <crossref let="v" cid="c06024026.1"/>wrote these words in the Book of the Law of God. And <crossref let="w" cid="c06024026.2"/>he took a large stone and set it up there <crossref let="x" cid="c06024026.3"/>under the terebinth that was by the sanctuary of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024027"/>
    <verse num="27">And Joshua said to all the people, <q class="begin-double" qid="06024027.1" from="06024027.1" to="06024027.2"/>Behold, <crossref let="y" cid="c06024027.1"/>this stone shall be a witness against us, for <crossref let="z" cid="c06024027.2"/>it has heard all the words of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> that he spoke to us. Therefore it shall be a witness against you, lest you deal falsely with your God.<q class="end-double" qid="06024027.2" from="06024027.1" to="06024027.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024028"/>
    <verse num="28">So Joshua <crossref let="a" cid="c06024028.1"/>sent the people away, every man to his inheritance.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024029"/>
    <heading>Joshua&apos;s Death and Burial</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="b" cid="c06024029.1"/>After these things Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, died, being 110 years old.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024030"/>
    <verse num="30">And they buried him in his own inheritance at <crossref let="c" cid="c06024030.1"/>Timnath-serah, which is in the hill country of Ephraim, north of the mountain of Gaash.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024031"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="31"><crossref let="d" cid="c06024031.1"/>Israel served the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders who outlived Joshua <crossref let="e" cid="c06024031.2"/>and had known all the work that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> did for Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024032"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="32"><crossref let="f" cid="c06024032.1"/>As for the bones of Joseph, which the people of Israel brought up from Egypt, they buried them at Shechem, in the piece of land <crossref let="g" cid="c06024032.2"/>that Jacob bought from the sons of Hamor the father of Shechem for a hundred pieces of money.<note nid="n06024032.1"/> It became an inheritance of the descendants of Joseph.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v06024033"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="33">And Eleazar the son of Aaron died, and they buried him at Gibeah, the town of <crossref let="h" cid="c06024033.1"/>Phinehas his son, which had been given him in <crossref let="i" cid="c06024033.2"/>the hill country of Ephraim.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
</book>
</crossway-bible>
