<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE crossway-bible SYSTEM "schema/crossway.bibles.dtd">
<crossway-bible translation="English Standard Version" revision="2025-02-02" xmlns="http://www.crosswaybibles.org" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="schema/crossway.bibles.xsd">
<book title="Leviticus" num="3">
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001001"/>
  <chapter num="1">
    <heading>Laws for Burnt Offerings</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="a" cid="c03001001.1"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> called Moses and spoke to him <crossref let="b" cid="c03001001.2"/>from the tent of meeting, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03001002.1" from="03001002.1" to="03003017.1"/>Speak to the people of Israel and say to them, <crossref let="c" cid="c03001002.1"/>When any one of you brings an offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, you shall bring your offering of livestock from the herd or from the flock.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001003"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3"><q class="continue-double" qid="03001003.1" from="03001002.1" to="03003017.1"/>If his offering is a burnt offering from the herd, he shall offer <crossref let="d" cid="c03001003.1"/>a male without blemish. He shall bring it to the entrance of the tent of meeting, that he may be accepted before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="e" cid="c03001004.1"/>He shall lay his hand on the head of the burnt offering, and it shall be <crossref let="f" cid="c03001004.2"/>accepted for him <crossref let="g" cid="c03001004.3"/>to make atonement for him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001005"/>
    <verse num="5">Then he shall kill the bull before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and Aaron&apos;s sons the priests shall bring the blood <crossref let="h" cid="c03001005.1"/>and throw the blood against the sides of the altar that is at the entrance of the tent of meeting.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001006"/>
    <verse num="6">Then he shall flay the burnt offering and cut it into pieces,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001007"/>
    <verse num="7">and the sons of Aaron the priest shall put fire on the altar and <crossref let="i" cid="c03001007.1"/>arrange wood on the fire.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001008"/>
    <verse num="8">And Aaron&apos;s sons the priests shall arrange the pieces, the head, and the fat, on the wood that is on the fire on the altar;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001009"/>
    <verse num="9">but its entrails and its legs he shall wash with water. And the priest shall burn all of it on the altar, as <crossref let="j" cid="c03001009.1"/>a burnt offering, a food offering<note nid="n03001009.1"/> with a <crossref let="k" cid="c03001009.2"/>pleasing aroma to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10"><q class="continue-double" qid="03001010.1" from="03001002.1" to="03003017.1"/>If his gift for a burnt offering is from the flock, from the sheep or goats, he shall bring a male without blemish,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="l" cid="c03001011.1"/>and he shall kill it on the north side of the altar before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and Aaron&apos;s sons the priests shall throw its blood against the sides of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001012"/>
    <verse num="12">And he shall cut it into pieces, with its head and its fat, and the priest shall arrange them on the wood that is on the fire on the altar,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001013"/>
    <verse num="13">but the entrails and the legs he shall wash with water. And the priest shall offer all of it and burn it on the altar; it is <crossref let="j" cid="c03001013.1"/>a burnt offering, a food offering with <crossref let="k" cid="c03001013.2"/>a pleasing aroma to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14"><q class="continue-double" qid="03001014.1" from="03001002.1" to="03003017.1"/>If his offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is a burnt offering of birds, then he shall bring his offering of <crossref let="m" cid="c03001014.1"/>turtledoves or pigeons.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001015"/>
    <verse num="15">And the priest shall bring it to the altar and wring off its head and burn it on the altar. Its blood shall be drained out on the side of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001016"/>
    <verse num="16">He shall remove its crop with its contents<note nid="n03001016.1"/> and cast it <crossref let="n" cid="c03001016.1"/>beside the altar on the east side, in the place for ashes.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03001017"/>
    <verse num="17">He shall tear it open by its wings, but <crossref let="o" cid="c03001017.1"/>shall not sever it completely. And the priest shall burn it on the altar, on the wood that is on the fire. It is a burnt offering, a food offering with a pleasing aroma to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002001"/>
  <chapter num="2">
    <heading>Laws for Grain Offerings</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><q class="continue-double" qid="03002001.1" from="03001002.1" to="03003017.1"/>When anyone brings a <crossref let="p" cid="c03002001.1"/>grain offering as an offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, his offering shall be of fine flour. <crossref let="q" cid="c03002001.2"/>He shall pour oil on it and put frankincense on it</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002002"/>
    <verse num="2">and bring it to Aaron&apos;s sons the priests. And he shall take from it a handful of the fine flour and oil, with all of its frankincense, and the priest shall burn this as its <crossref let="r" cid="c03002002.1"/>memorial portion on the altar, a food <crossref let="s" cid="c03002002.2"/>offering with a pleasing aroma to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002003"/>
    <verse num="3">But the <crossref let="t" cid="c03002003.1"/>rest of the grain offering shall be for Aaron and his sons; <crossref let="u" cid="c03002003.2"/>it is a most holy part of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s food offerings.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4"><q class="continue-double" qid="03002004.1" from="03001002.1" to="03003017.1"/>When you bring a grain offering baked in the oven as an offering, it shall be <crossref let="v" cid="c03002004.1"/>unleavened loaves of fine flour mixed with oil or unleavened wafers smeared with oil.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002005"/>
    <verse num="5">And if your offering is a grain offering <crossref let="w" cid="c03002005.1"/>baked on a griddle, it shall be of fine flour unleavened, mixed with oil.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002006"/>
    <verse num="6">You shall break it in pieces and pour oil on it; it is a grain offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002007"/>
    <verse num="7">And if your offering is a grain offering cooked in a pan, it shall be made of fine flour with oil.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002008"/>
    <verse num="8">And you shall bring the grain offering that is made of these things to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and when it is presented to the priest, he shall bring it to the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002009"/>
    <verse num="9">And the priest shall take from the grain offering its memorial portion and burn this on the altar, a food <crossref let="x" cid="c03002009.1"/>offering with a <crossref let="y" cid="c03002009.2"/>pleasing aroma to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002010"/>
    <verse num="10">But the <crossref let="z" cid="c03002010.1"/>rest of the grain offering shall be for Aaron and his sons; <crossref let="z" cid="c03002010.2"/>it is a most holy part of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s food offerings.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11"><q class="continue-double" qid="03002011.1" from="03001002.1" to="03003017.1"/>No grain offering that you bring to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> shall be made with <crossref let="a" cid="c03002011.1"/>leaven, for you shall burn no leaven nor any honey as a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="b" cid="c03002012.1"/>As an offering of firstfruits you may bring them to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, but they shall not be offered on the altar for a pleasing aroma.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002013"/>
    <verse num="13">You <crossref let="c" cid="c03002013.1"/>shall season all your grain offerings with salt. You shall not let the <crossref let="d" cid="c03002013.2"/>salt of the covenant with your God be missing from your grain offering; <crossref let="e" cid="c03002013.3"/>with all your offerings you shall offer salt.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14"><q class="continue-double" qid="03002014.1" from="03001002.1" to="03003017.1"/>If you offer a grain offering of firstfruits to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, you shall offer for the grain offering of your firstfruits fresh <crossref let="f" cid="c03002014.1"/>ears, roasted with fire, crushed new grain.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002015"/>
    <verse num="15">And <crossref let="g" cid="c03002015.1"/>you shall put oil on it and lay frankincense on it; it is a grain offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03002016"/>
    <verse num="16">And the priest shall burn as its <crossref let="h" cid="c03002016.1"/>memorial portion some of the crushed grain and some of the oil with all of its frankincense; it is a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003001"/>
  <chapter num="3">
    <heading>Laws for Peace Offerings</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><q class="continue-double" qid="03003001.1" from="03001002.1" to="03003017.1"/>If his offering is <crossref let="i" cid="c03003001.1"/>a sacrifice of peace offering, if he offers an animal from the herd, male or female, <crossref let="j" cid="c03003001.2"/>he shall offer it <crossref let="k" cid="c03003001.3"/>without blemish before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003002"/>
    <verse num="2">And <crossref let="l" cid="c03003002.1"/>he shall lay his hand on the head of his offering and kill it at the entrance of the tent of meeting, and Aaron&apos;s sons the priests shall throw the blood against the sides of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003003"/>
    <verse num="3">And from the sacrifice of the peace offering, as a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, he shall offer <crossref let="m" cid="c03003003.1"/>the fat covering the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="n" cid="c03003004.1"/>and the two kidneys with the fat that is on them at the loins, and the long lobe of the liver that he shall remove with the kidneys.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003005"/>
    <verse num="5">Then Aaron&apos;s sons <crossref let="o" cid="c03003005.1"/>shall burn it on the altar on top of the burnt offering, which is on the wood on the fire; it is a food offering with a pleasing aroma to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6"><q class="continue-double" qid="03003006.1" from="03001002.1" to="03003017.1"/>If his offering for a sacrifice of peace offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is an animal from the flock, male or female, he shall offer it <crossref let="k" cid="c03003006.1"/>without blemish.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003007"/>
    <verse num="7">If he offers a lamb for his offering, then he shall offer it before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003008"/>
    <verse num="8">lay his hand on the head of his offering, and kill it in front of the tent of meeting; and Aaron&apos;s sons shall throw its blood against the sides of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003009"/>
    <verse num="9">Then from the sacrifice of the peace offering he shall offer as a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> its fat; he shall remove the whole <crossref let="p" cid="c03003009.1"/>fat tail, cut off close to the backbone, and the fat that covers the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003010"/>
    <verse num="10">and the two kidneys with the fat that is on them at the loins and the long lobe of the liver that he shall remove <crossref let="q" cid="c03003010.1"/>with the kidneys.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003011"/>
    <verse num="11">And the priest shall burn it on the altar as <crossref let="r" cid="c03003011.1"/>a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12"><q class="continue-double" qid="03003012.1" from="03001002.1" to="03003017.1"/>If his offering is a goat, then he shall offer it before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003013"/>
    <verse num="13">and lay his hand on its head and kill it in front of the tent of meeting, and the sons of Aaron shall throw its blood against the sides of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003014"/>
    <verse num="14">Then he shall offer from it, as his offering for a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the fat covering the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003015"/>
    <verse num="15">and the two kidneys with the fat that is on them at the loins and the long lobe of the liver that he shall remove <crossref let="q" cid="c03003015.1"/>with the kidneys.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003016"/>
    <verse num="16">And the priest shall burn them on the altar as a <crossref let="r" cid="c03003016.1"/>food offering with a pleasing aroma. <crossref let="s" cid="c03003016.2"/>All fat is the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03003017"/>
    <verse num="17">It shall be a statute forever throughout your generations, in all your dwelling places, that you eat neither <crossref let="s" cid="c03003017.1"/>fat nor <crossref let="t" cid="c03003017.2"/>blood.<q class="end-double" qid="03003017.1" from="03001002.1" to="03003017.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004001"/>
  <chapter num="4">
    <heading>Laws for Sin Offerings</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03004002.1" from="03004002.1" to="03005013.1"/>Speak to the people of Israel, saying, <crossref let="u" cid="c03004002.1"/>If anyone sins unintentionally<note nid="n03004002.1"/> in any of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s commandments <crossref let="v" cid="c03004002.2"/>about things not to be done, and does any one of them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004003"/>
    <verse num="3">if it is the anointed priest who <crossref let="w" cid="c03004003.1"/>sins, thus bringing guilt on the people, then he shall offer for the sin that he has committed <crossref let="x" cid="c03004003.2"/>a bull from the herd without blemish to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for a sin offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004004"/>
    <verse num="4">He shall bring the bull to the <crossref let="y" cid="c03004004.1"/>entrance of the tent of meeting before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and lay his hand on the head of the bull and kill the bull before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004005"/>
    <verse num="5">And the anointed priest <crossref let="z" cid="c03004005.1"/>shall take some of the blood of the bull and bring it into the tent of meeting,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004006"/>
    <verse num="6">and the priest shall dip his finger in the blood and <crossref let="z" cid="c03004006.1"/>sprinkle part of the blood seven times before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in front of the veil of the sanctuary.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004007"/>
    <verse num="7">And the priest <crossref let="a" cid="c03004007.1"/>shall put some of the blood on the horns of the altar of fragrant incense before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> that is in the tent of meeting, and <crossref let="b" cid="c03004007.2"/>all the rest of the blood of the bull he shall pour out at the base of the altar of burnt offering that is at the entrance of the tent of meeting.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004008"/>
    <verse num="8">And all the fat of the bull of the sin offering he shall remove from it, <crossref let="c" cid="c03004008.1"/>the fat that covers the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="d" cid="c03004009.1"/>and the two kidneys with the fat that is on them at the loins and the long lobe of the liver that he shall remove with the kidneys</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004010"/>
    <verse num="10">(just as these are taken from the ox of the sacrifice of the peace offerings); and the priest shall burn them on the altar of burnt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004011"/>
    <verse num="11">But <crossref let="e" cid="c03004011.1"/>the skin of the bull and all its flesh, with its head, its legs, its entrails, and its dung&emdash;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004012"/>
    <verse num="12">all the rest of the bull&emdash;he shall carry <crossref let="f" cid="c03004012.1"/>outside the camp to a clean place, to the ash heap, and shall <crossref let="g" cid="c03004012.2"/>burn it up on a fire of wood. On the ash heap it shall be burned up.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="h" cid="c03004013.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03004013.1" from="03004002.1" to="03005013.1"/>If the whole congregation of Israel sins unintentionally<note nid="n03004013.1"/> and <crossref let="i" cid="c03004013.2"/>the thing is hidden from the eyes of the assembly, and they do any one of the things that by the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s commandments ought not to be done, and they realize their guilt,<note nid="n03004013.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004014"/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="j" cid="c03004014.1"/>when the sin which they have committed becomes known, the assembly shall offer a bull from the herd for a sin offering and bring it in front of the tent of meeting.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004015"/>
    <verse num="15">And the elders of the congregation <crossref let="k" cid="c03004015.1"/>shall lay their hands on the head of the bull before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and the bull shall be killed before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004016"/>
    <verse num="16">Then <crossref let="l" cid="c03004016.1"/>the anointed priest shall bring some of the blood of the bull into the tent of meeting,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004017"/>
    <verse num="17">and the priest shall dip his finger in the blood and sprinkle it seven times before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in front of the veil.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004018"/>
    <verse num="18">And he shall put some of the blood on the horns of the altar that is in the tent of meeting before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and the rest of the blood he shall pour out at the base of the altar of burnt offering that is at the entrance of the tent of meeting.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004019"/>
    <verse num="19">And all its fat he shall take from it and burn on the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004020"/>
    <verse num="20">Thus shall he do with the bull. As he did <crossref let="m" cid="c03004020.1"/>with the bull of the sin offering, so shall he do with this. <crossref let="n" cid="c03004020.2"/>And the priest shall make atonement for them, and they shall be forgiven.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004021"/>
    <verse num="21">And he shall carry the bull <crossref let="f" cid="c03004021.1"/>outside the camp and burn it up as he burned the first bull; it is the sin offering for the assembly.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22"><q class="continue-double" qid="03004022.1" from="03004002.1" to="03005013.1"/>When a leader sins, <crossref let="o" cid="c03004022.1"/>doing unintentionally any one of all the things that by the commandments of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> his God ought not to be done, and realizes his guilt,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004023"/>
    <verse num="23">or <crossref let="p" cid="c03004023.1"/>the sin which he has committed is made known to him, he shall bring as his offering a goat, a male without blemish,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004024"/>
    <verse num="24">and <crossref let="q" cid="c03004024.1"/>shall lay his hand on the head of the goat and kill it in the place where they kill the burnt offering before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>; it is a sin offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004025"/>
    <verse num="25"><crossref let="r" cid="c03004025.1"/>Then the priest shall take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger and put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering and pour out the rest of its blood at the base of the altar of burnt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004026"/>
    <verse num="26">And all its fat he shall burn on the altar, like <crossref let="s" cid="c03004026.1"/>the fat of the sacrifice of peace offerings. So <crossref let="t" cid="c03004026.2"/>the priest shall make atonement for him for his sin, and he shall be forgiven.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004027"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="27"><q class="continue-double" qid="03004027.1" from="03004002.1" to="03005013.1"/>If <crossref let="u" cid="c03004027.1"/>anyone of the common people sins unintentionally in doing any one of the things that by the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s commandments ought not to be done, and realizes his guilt,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004028"/>
    <verse num="28"><crossref let="v" cid="c03004028.1"/>or the sin which he has committed is made known to him, he shall bring for his offering a goat, a female without blemish, for his sin which he has committed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004029"/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="w" cid="c03004029.1"/>And he shall lay his hand on the head of the sin offering and kill the sin offering in the place of burnt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004030"/>
    <verse num="30">And the priest shall take some of its blood with his finger and put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering and pour out all the rest of its blood at the base of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004031"/>
    <verse num="31">And <crossref let="x" cid="c03004031.1"/>all its fat he shall remove, <crossref let="y" cid="c03004031.2"/>as the fat is removed from the peace offerings, and the priest shall burn it on the altar for a <crossref let="z" cid="c03004031.3"/>pleasing aroma to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. <crossref let="a" cid="c03004031.4"/>And the priest shall make atonement for him, and he shall be forgiven.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004032"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="32"><q class="continue-double" qid="03004032.1" from="03004002.1" to="03005013.1"/>If he brings a lamb as his offering for a sin offering, he shall bring <crossref let="b" cid="c03004032.1"/>a female without blemish</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004033"/>
    <verse num="33"><crossref let="w" cid="c03004033.1"/>and lay his hand on the head of the sin offering and kill it for a sin offering in the place where they kill the burnt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004034"/>
    <verse num="34">Then the priest shall take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger and put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering and pour out all the rest of its blood at the base of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03004035"/>
    <verse num="35">And all its fat he shall remove <crossref let="c" cid="c03004035.1"/>as the fat of the lamb is removed from the sacrifice of peace offerings, and the priest shall burn it on the altar, on top of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s food offerings. <crossref let="d" cid="c03004035.2"/>And the priest shall make atonement for him for the sin which he has committed, and he shall be forgiven.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005001"/>
  <chapter num="5">
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><q class="continue-double" qid="03005001.1" from="03004002.1" to="03005013.1"/>If anyone sins in that he hears a public <crossref let="e" cid="c03005001.1"/>adjuration to testify, and though he is a witness, whether he has seen or come to know the matter, yet does not speak, he shall <crossref let="f" cid="c03005001.2"/>bear his iniquity;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005002"/>
    <verse num="2">or <crossref let="g" cid="c03005002.1"/>if anyone touches an unclean thing, whether a carcass of an unclean wild animal or a carcass of unclean livestock or a carcass of unclean swarming things, and it is hidden from him and he has become unclean, and he realizes his guilt;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005003"/>
    <verse num="3">or if he touches <crossref let="h" cid="c03005003.1"/>human uncleanness, of whatever sort the uncleanness may be with which one becomes unclean, and it is hidden from him, when he comes to know it, and realizes his guilt;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005004"/>
    <verse num="4">or if anyone utters with his lips a <crossref let="i" cid="c03005004.1"/>rash oath to do evil or to do good, any sort of rash oath that people <crossref let="j" cid="c03005004.2"/>swear, and it is hidden from him, when he comes to know it, and he realizes his guilt in any of these;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005005"/>
    <verse num="5">when he realizes his guilt in any of these and <crossref let="k" cid="c03005005.1"/>confesses the sin he has committed,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005006"/>
    <verse num="6">he shall bring to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> as his compensation<note nid="n03005006.1"/> for the sin that he has committed, a female from the flock, a lamb or a goat, for a sin offering. And the priest shall make atonement for him for his sin.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005007"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="7"><q class="continue-double" qid="03005007.1" from="03004002.1" to="03005013.1"/>But <crossref let="l" cid="c03005007.1"/>if he cannot afford a lamb, then he shall bring to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> as his compensation for the sin that he has committed two <crossref let="m" cid="c03005007.2"/>turtledoves or two pigeons,<note nid="n03005007.1"/> one for a sin offering and the other for a burnt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005008"/>
    <verse num="8">He shall bring them to the priest, who shall offer first the one for the sin offering. He shall <crossref let="n" cid="c03005008.1"/>wring its head from its neck <crossref let="n" cid="c03005008.2"/>but shall not sever it completely,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005009"/>
    <verse num="9">and he shall sprinkle some of the blood of the sin offering on the side of the altar, while <crossref let="o" cid="c03005009.1"/>the rest of the blood shall be drained out <crossref let="p" cid="c03005009.2"/>at the base of the altar; it is a sin offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005010"/>
    <verse num="10">Then he shall offer the second for a burnt offering according to the rule. <crossref let="q" cid="c03005010.1"/>And the priest shall make atonement for him for the sin that he has committed, and he shall be forgiven.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11"><q class="continue-double" qid="03005011.1" from="03004002.1" to="03005013.1"/>But if he cannot afford two turtledoves or two pigeons, then he shall bring as his offering for the sin that he has committed a <crossref let="r" cid="c03005011.1"/>tenth of an ephah<note nid="n03005011.1"/> of fine flour for a sin offering. He <crossref let="r" cid="c03005011.2"/>shall put no oil on it and shall put no frankincense on it, for it is a sin offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005012"/>
    <verse num="12">And he shall bring it to <crossref let="s" cid="c03005012.1"/>the priest, and the priest shall take a handful of it as its memorial portion and <crossref let="t" cid="c03005012.2"/>burn this on the altar, on the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s food offerings; it is a sin offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005013"/>
    <verse num="13">Thus <crossref let="q" cid="c03005013.1"/>the priest shall make atonement for him for the sin which he has committed in any one of these things, and he shall be forgiven. And the remainder<note nid="n03005013.1"/> shall be for the priest, as in the grain offering.<q class="end-double" qid="03005013.1" from="03004002.1" to="03005013.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005014"/>
    <heading>Laws for Guilt Offerings</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="u" cid="c03005015.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="03005015.1" from="03005015.1" to="03005019.1"/>If anyone commits a breach of faith and sins unintentionally in any of the holy things of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="v" cid="c03005015.2"/>he shall bring to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> as his compensation, a ram without blemish out of the flock, valued<note nid="n03005015.1"/> in silver shekels,<note nid="n03005015.2"/> according to the <crossref let="w" cid="c03005015.3"/>shekel of the sanctuary, for a guilt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005016"/>
    <verse num="16">He shall also make restitution for what he has done amiss in the holy thing and <crossref let="x" cid="c03005016.1"/>shall add a fifth to it and give it to the priest. <crossref let="q" cid="c03005016.2"/>And the priest shall make atonement for him with the ram of the guilt offering, and he shall be forgiven.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005017"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="y" cid="c03005017.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03005017.1" from="03005015.1" to="03005019.1"/>If anyone sins, doing any of the things that by the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s commandments ought not to be done, <crossref let="z" cid="c03005017.2"/>though he did not know it, then realizes his guilt, he shall bear his iniquity.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005018"/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="a" cid="c03005018.1"/>He shall bring to the priest a ram without blemish out of the flock, or its equivalent, for a guilt offering, and <crossref let="q" cid="c03005018.2"/>the priest shall make atonement for him for the mistake that he made unintentionally, and he shall be forgiven.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03005019"/>
    <verse num="19">It is a guilt offering; he has indeed incurred guilt before<note nid="n03005019.1"/> the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="03005019.1" from="03005015.1" to="03005019.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006001"/>
  <chapter num="6">
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><note nid="n03006001.1"/> The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03006002.1" from="03006002.1" to="03006007.1"/>If anyone sins and <crossref let="b" cid="c03006002.1"/>commits a breach of faith against the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> by <crossref let="c" cid="c03006002.2"/>deceiving his neighbor in <crossref let="d" cid="c03006002.3"/>a matter of deposit or security, or through robbery, or <crossref let="e" cid="c03006002.4"/>if he has oppressed his neighbor</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006003"/>
    <verse num="3">or <crossref let="f" cid="c03006003.1"/>has found something lost and lied about it, <crossref let="g" cid="c03006003.2"/>swearing falsely&emdash;in any of all the things that people do and sin thereby&emdash;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006004"/>
    <verse num="4">if he has sinned and has realized his guilt and will restore <crossref let="e" cid="c03006004.1"/>what he took by robbery or what he got by oppression or the deposit that was committed to him or the lost thing that he found</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006005"/>
    <verse num="5">or anything about which he has sworn falsely, he shall <crossref let="h" cid="c03006005.1"/>restore it in full and shall add a fifth to it, and give it to him to whom it belongs on the day he realizes his guilt.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006006"/>
    <verse num="6">And he shall bring to the priest as his compensation to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="i" cid="c03006006.1"/>a ram without blemish out of the flock, or its equivalent, for a guilt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="j" cid="c03006007.1"/>And the priest shall make atonement for him before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and he shall be forgiven for any of the things that one may do and thereby become guilty.<q class="end-double" qid="03006007.1" from="03006002.1" to="03006007.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006008"/>
    <heading>The Priests and the Offerings</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8"><note nid="n03006008.1"/> The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006009"/>
    <verse num="9"><q class="begin-double" qid="03006009.1" from="03006009.1" to="03006018.1"/>Command Aaron and his sons, saying, This is the law of the burnt offering. The burnt offering shall be on the hearth on the altar all night until the morning, and the fire of the altar shall be kept burning on it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006010"/>
    <verse num="10">And <crossref let="k" cid="c03006010.1"/>the priest shall put on his linen garment and put his linen undergarment on his body, and he shall take up the ashes to which the fire has reduced the burnt offering on the altar and put them <crossref let="l" cid="c03006010.2"/>beside the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006011"/>
    <verse num="11">Then <crossref let="m" cid="c03006011.1"/>he shall take off his garments and put on other garments and carry the ashes <crossref let="n" cid="c03006011.2"/>outside the camp to a clean place.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006012"/>
    <verse num="12">The fire on the altar shall be kept burning on it; it shall not go out. The priest shall burn wood on it every morning, and he shall arrange the burnt offering on it and shall burn on it <crossref let="o" cid="c03006012.1"/>the fat of the peace offerings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006013"/>
    <verse num="13">Fire shall be kept burning on the altar continually; it shall not go out.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14"><q class="continue-double" qid="03006014.1" from="03006009.1" to="03006018.1"/>And this is the law of <crossref let="p" cid="c03006014.1"/>the grain offering. The sons of Aaron shall offer it before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in front of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006015"/>
    <verse num="15">And one shall take from it a handful of the fine flour of the grain offering and its oil and all the frankincense that is on the grain offering and burn this as its <crossref let="q" cid="c03006015.1"/>memorial portion on the altar, a pleasing aroma to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006016"/>
    <verse num="16">And <crossref let="r" cid="c03006016.1"/>the rest of it Aaron and his sons shall eat. It shall be eaten unleavened <crossref let="s" cid="c03006016.2"/>in a holy place. In the court of the tent of meeting they shall eat it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="t" cid="c03006017.1"/>It shall not be baked with leaven. <crossref let="u" cid="c03006017.2"/>I have given it as their portion of my food offerings. <crossref let="v" cid="c03006017.3"/>It is a thing most holy, like the sin offering and the guilt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006018"/>
    <verse num="18">Every male among the children of Aaron may eat of it, as decreed forever throughout your generations, from the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s food offerings. Whatever touches them shall become holy.<q class="end-double" qid="03006018.1" from="03006009.1" to="03006018.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="w" cid="c03006020.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="03006020.1" from="03006020.1" to="03006023.1"/>This is the offering that Aaron and his sons shall offer to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> on the day when he is anointed: a <crossref let="x" cid="c03006020.2"/>tenth of an ephah<note nid="n03006020.1"/> of fine flour as a regular grain offering, half of it in the morning and half in the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006021"/>
    <verse num="21">It shall be made with oil <crossref let="y" cid="c03006021.1"/>on a griddle. You shall bring it <crossref let="z" cid="c03006021.2"/>well mixed, in baked<note nid="n03006021.1"/> pieces like a grain offering, and offer it for a pleasing aroma to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006022"/>
    <verse num="22">The priest from among Aaron&apos;s sons, who is anointed to succeed him, shall offer it to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> as decreed forever. <crossref let="a" cid="c03006022.1"/>The whole of it shall be burned.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006023"/>
    <verse num="23">Every grain offering of a priest shall be wholly burned. It shall not be eaten.<q class="end-double" qid="03006023.1" from="03006020.1" to="03006023.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006024"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006025"/>
    <verse num="25"><q class="begin-double" qid="03006025.1" from="03006025.1" to="03007021.1"/>Speak to Aaron and his sons, saying, <crossref let="b" cid="c03006025.1"/>This is the law of the sin offering. <crossref let="c" cid="c03006025.2"/>In the place where the burnt offering is killed shall the sin offering be killed before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>; <crossref let="d" cid="c03006025.3"/>it is most holy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006026"/>
    <verse num="26"><crossref let="e" cid="c03006026.1"/>The priest who offers it for sin shall eat it. <crossref let="f" cid="c03006026.2"/>In a holy place it shall be eaten, in the court of the tent of meeting.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006027"/>
    <verse num="27">Whatever touches its flesh shall be holy, and when any of its blood is splashed on a garment, you shall wash that on which it was splashed in a holy place.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006028"/>
    <verse num="28">And <crossref let="g" cid="c03006028.1"/>the earthenware vessel in which it is boiled <crossref let="h" cid="c03006028.2"/>shall be broken. But if it is boiled in a bronze vessel, that shall be scoured and rinsed in water.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006029"/>
    <verse num="29">Every male among the priests may eat of it; <crossref let="d" cid="c03006029.1"/>it is most holy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03006030"/>
    <verse num="30"><crossref let="i" cid="c03006030.1"/>But no sin offering shall be eaten from which any blood is brought into the tent of meeting to make atonement in the Holy Place; it shall be burned up with fire.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007001"/>
  <chapter num="7">
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="j" cid="c03007001.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03007001.1" from="03006025.1" to="03007021.1"/>This is the law of the <crossref let="k" cid="c03007001.2"/>guilt offering. <crossref let="l" cid="c03007001.3"/>It is most holy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="m" cid="c03007002.1"/>In the place where they kill the burnt offering they shall kill the guilt offering, and its blood shall be thrown against the sides of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007003"/>
    <verse num="3">And <crossref let="n" cid="c03007003.1"/>all its fat shall be offered, the fat tail, the fat that covers the entrails,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007004"/>
    <verse num="4">the two kidneys with the fat that is on them at the loins, and the long lobe of the liver that he shall remove <crossref let="o" cid="c03007004.1"/>with the kidneys.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007005"/>
    <verse num="5">The priest shall burn them on the altar as a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>; it is a guilt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="p" cid="c03007006.1"/>Every male among the priests may eat of it. It shall be eaten in a holy place. <crossref let="q" cid="c03007006.2"/>It is most holy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007007"/>
    <verse num="7">The <crossref let="r" cid="c03007007.1"/>guilt offering is just like the sin offering; there is one law for them. The priest who makes atonement with it shall have it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007008"/>
    <verse num="8">And the priest who offers any man&apos;s burnt offering shall have for himself the skin of the burnt offering that he has offered.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007009"/>
    <verse num="9">And <crossref let="s" cid="c03007009.1"/>every grain offering baked <crossref let="t" cid="c03007009.2"/>in the oven and all that is prepared <crossref let="u" cid="c03007009.3"/>on a pan or a griddle shall belong to the priest who offers it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007010"/>
    <verse num="10">And every grain offering, mixed with oil or dry, shall be shared equally among all the sons of Aaron.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11"><q class="continue-double" qid="03007011.1" from="03006025.1" to="03007021.1"/>And this is the law of the sacrifice of peace offerings that one may offer to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007012"/>
    <verse num="12">If he offers it for a thanksgiving, then he shall offer with the thanksgiving sacrifice <crossref let="v" cid="c03007012.1"/>unleavened loaves mixed with oil, unleavened wafers smeared with oil, and loaves of fine flour <crossref let="w" cid="c03007012.2"/>well mixed with oil.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="x" cid="c03007013.1"/>With the sacrifice of his peace offerings for thanksgiving he shall bring his offering with loaves of leavened bread.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007014"/>
    <verse num="14">And from it he shall offer one loaf from each offering, as a <crossref let="y" cid="c03007014.1"/>gift to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. <crossref let="z" cid="c03007014.2"/>It shall belong to the priest who throws the blood of the peace offerings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007015"/>
    <verse num="15">And the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offerings <crossref let="a" cid="c03007015.1"/>for thanksgiving shall be eaten on the day of his offering. He shall not leave any of it until the morning.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007016"/>
    <verse num="16">But <crossref let="b" cid="c03007016.1"/>if the sacrifice of his offering is a vow offering or a freewill offering, it shall be eaten on the day that he offers his sacrifice, and on the next day what remains of it shall be eaten.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007017"/>
    <verse num="17">But what remains of the flesh of the sacrifice on the third day shall be burned up with fire.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007018"/>
    <verse num="18">If any of the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offering is eaten on the third day, he who offers it shall not be accepted, neither shall it be credited to him. It is <crossref let="c" cid="c03007018.1"/>tainted, and he who eats of it shall bear his iniquity.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19"><q class="continue-double" qid="03007019.1" from="03006025.1" to="03007021.1"/>Flesh that touches any unclean thing shall not be eaten. It shall be burned up with fire. All who are clean may eat flesh,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007020"/>
    <verse num="20">but the person who eats of the flesh of the sacrifice of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s peace offerings <crossref let="d" cid="c03007020.1"/>while an uncleanness is on him, that person shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007021"/>
    <verse num="21">And if anyone touches an unclean thing, whether <crossref let="e" cid="c03007021.1"/>human uncleanness or an <crossref let="f" cid="c03007021.2"/>unclean beast or any <crossref let="g" cid="c03007021.3"/>unclean detestable creature, and then eats some flesh from the sacrifice of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s peace offerings, that person shall be cut off from his people.<q class="end-double" qid="03007021.1" from="03006025.1" to="03007021.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007023"/>
    <verse num="23"><q class="begin-double" qid="03007023.1" from="03007023.1" to="03007027.1"/>Speak to the people of Israel, saying, <crossref let="h" cid="c03007023.1"/>You shall eat no fat, of ox or sheep or goat.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007024"/>
    <verse num="24">The fat of an animal <crossref let="i" cid="c03007024.1"/>that dies of itself and the fat of one that is torn by beasts may be put to any other use, but on no account shall you eat it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007025"/>
    <verse num="25">For every person who eats of the fat of an animal of which a food offering may be made to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007026"/>
    <verse num="26">Moreover, <crossref let="j" cid="c03007026.1"/>you shall eat no blood whatever, whether of fowl or of animal, in any of your dwelling places.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007027"/>
    <verse num="27">Whoever eats any blood, that person shall be cut off from his people.<q class="end-double" qid="03007027.1" from="03007023.1" to="03007027.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007028"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="28">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007029"/>
    <verse num="29"><q class="begin-double" qid="03007029.1" from="03007029.1" to="03007036.1"/>Speak to the people of Israel, saying, <crossref let="k" cid="c03007029.1"/>Whoever offers the sacrifice of his peace offerings to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> shall bring his offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> from the sacrifice of his peace offerings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007030"/>
    <verse num="30"><crossref let="l" cid="c03007030.1"/>His own hands shall bring the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s food offerings. He shall bring the fat with <crossref let="m" cid="c03007030.2"/>the breast, that the breast may be waved as a wave offering before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007031"/>
    <verse num="31"><crossref let="n" cid="c03007031.1"/>The priest shall burn the fat on the altar, but <crossref let="o" cid="c03007031.2"/>the breast shall be for Aaron and his sons.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007032"/>
    <verse num="32">And <crossref let="o" cid="c03007032.1"/>the right thigh you shall give to the priest as a contribution from the sacrifice of your peace offerings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007033"/>
    <verse num="33">Whoever among the sons of Aaron offers the blood of the peace offerings and the fat shall have the right thigh for a portion.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007034"/>
    <verse num="34">For the breast that is <crossref let="o" cid="c03007034.1"/>waved and the thigh that is <crossref let="o" cid="c03007034.2"/>contributed I have taken from the people of Israel, out of the sacrifices of their peace offerings, and <crossref let="p" cid="c03007034.3"/>have given them to Aaron the priest and to his sons, as a perpetual due from the people of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007035"/>
    <verse num="35">This is the portion of Aaron and of his sons from the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s food offerings, from the day they were presented to serve as priests of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007036"/>
    <verse num="36">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded this to be given them by the people of Israel, <crossref let="q" cid="c03007036.1"/>from the day that he anointed them. It is a perpetual due throughout their generations.<q class="end-double" qid="03007036.1" from="03007029.1" to="03007036.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007037"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="37">This is the law <crossref let="r" cid="c03007037.1"/>of the burnt offering, of the grain offering, of the sin offering, <crossref let="s" cid="c03007037.2"/>of the guilt offering, <crossref let="t" cid="c03007037.3"/>of the ordination offering, and <crossref let="u" cid="c03007037.4"/>of the peace offering,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03007038"/>
    <verse num="38">which the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses on Mount Sinai, on the day that he commanded the people of Israel <crossref let="v" cid="c03007038.1"/>to bring their offerings to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, in the wilderness of Sinai.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008001"/>
  <chapter num="8">
    <heading>Consecration of Aaron and His Sons</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="w" cid="c03008001.1"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03008002.1" from="03008002.1" to="03008003.1"/>Take Aaron and his sons with him, and <crossref let="x" cid="c03008002.1"/>the garments and <crossref let="y" cid="c03008002.2"/>the anointing oil and the bull of the sin offering and the two rams and the basket of unleavened bread.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008003"/>
    <verse num="3">And assemble all the congregation at the entrance of the tent of meeting.<q class="end-double" qid="03008003.1" from="03008002.1" to="03008003.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008004"/>
    <verse num="4">And Moses did as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded him, and the congregation was assembled at the entrance of the tent of meeting.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008005"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5">And Moses said to the congregation, <crossref let="z" cid="c03008005.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="03008005.1" from="03008005.1" to="03008005.2"/>This is the thing that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has commanded to be done.<q class="end-double" qid="03008005.2" from="03008005.1" to="03008005.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008006"/>
    <verse num="6">And Moses brought Aaron and his sons and washed them with water.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008007"/>
    <verse num="7">And he put <crossref let="a" cid="c03008007.1"/>the coat on him and tied the sash around his waist and clothed him with the robe and put the ephod on him and tied the skillfully woven band of the ephod around him, binding it to him with the band.<note nid="n03008007.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008008"/>
    <verse num="8">And he placed the breastpiece on him, and <crossref let="b" cid="c03008008.1"/>in the breastpiece he put the Urim and the Thummim.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008009"/>
    <verse num="9">And he set <crossref let="a" cid="c03008009.1"/>the turban on his head, and <crossref let="c" cid="c03008009.2"/>on the turban, in front, he set the golden plate, the holy crown, as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="d" cid="c03008010.1"/>Then Moses took the anointing oil and anointed the tabernacle and all that was in it, and consecrated them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008011"/>
    <verse num="11">And he sprinkled some of it on the altar seven times, and anointed the altar and all its utensils and the basin and its stand, to consecrate them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008012"/>
    <verse num="12">And <crossref let="e" cid="c03008012.1"/>he poured some of the anointing oil on Aaron&apos;s head and anointed him to consecrate him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008013"/>
    <verse num="13">And Moses brought Aaron&apos;s sons and clothed them with coats and tied sashes around their waists and bound caps on them, as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14">Then he brought <crossref let="f" cid="c03008014.1"/>the bull of the sin offering, and Aaron and his sons <crossref let="g" cid="c03008014.2"/>laid their hands on the head of the bull of the sin offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008015"/>
    <verse num="15">And he<note nid="n03008015.1"/> killed it, and <crossref let="h" cid="c03008015.1"/>Moses took the blood, and with his finger put it on the horns of the altar around it and purified the altar and poured out the blood at the base of the altar and consecrated it to make atonement for it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008016"/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="i" cid="c03008016.1"/>And he took all the fat that was on the entrails and the long lobe of the liver and the two kidneys with their fat, and Moses burned them on the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008017"/>
    <verse num="17">But <crossref let="j" cid="c03008017.1"/>the bull and its skin and its flesh and its dung he burned up with fire outside the camp, as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="k" cid="c03008018.1"/>Then he presented the ram of the burnt offering, and Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the ram.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008019"/>
    <verse num="19">And he killed it, and Moses threw the blood against the sides of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008020"/>
    <verse num="20">He cut the ram into pieces, and Moses burned <crossref let="l" cid="c03008020.1"/>the head and the pieces and the fat.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008021"/>
    <verse num="21">He washed the entrails and the legs with water, and Moses burned the whole ram on the altar. It was a burnt offering with a pleasing aroma, a food offering for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">Then <crossref let="m" cid="c03008022.1"/>he presented the other ram, the ram of ordination, and Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the ram.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008023"/>
    <verse num="23">And he killed it, and Moses took some of its blood and <crossref let="n" cid="c03008023.1"/>put it on the lobe of Aaron&apos;s right ear and on the thumb of his right hand and on the big toe of his right foot.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008024"/>
    <verse num="24">Then he presented Aaron&apos;s sons, and Moses put some of the blood on the lobes of their right ears and on the thumbs of their right hands and on the big toes of their right feet. And Moses threw the blood against the sides of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008025"/>
    <verse num="25">Then he took the fat and the fat tail and all the fat that was on the entrails and the long lobe of the liver and the two kidneys with their fat and the right thigh,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008026"/>
    <verse num="26">and out of the basket of unleavened bread that was before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> he took one unleavened loaf and one loaf of bread with oil and one wafer and placed them on the pieces of fat and on the right thigh.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008027"/>
    <verse num="27">And he put all these in the hands of Aaron and in the hands of his sons and waved them as a wave offering before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008028"/>
    <verse num="28">Then Moses took them from their hands and burned them on the altar with the burnt offering. This was an ordination offering with a pleasing aroma, a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008029"/>
    <verse num="29">And Moses took the breast and waved it for a wave offering before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. It was Moses&apos; portion of the ram of ordination, as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008030"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="30">Then <crossref let="o" cid="c03008030.1"/>Moses took some of the anointing oil and of the blood that was on the altar and sprinkled it on Aaron and his garments, and also on his sons and his sons&apos; garments. So he consecrated Aaron and his garments, and his sons and his sons&apos; garments with him.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008031"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="31">And Moses said to Aaron and his sons, <q class="begin-double" qid="03008031.1" from="03008031.1" to="03008035.1"/>Boil the flesh at the entrance of the tent of meeting, and there eat it and the bread that is in the basket of ordination offerings, as I commanded, saying, <q class="begin-single" qid="03008031.2" from="03008031.2" to="03008031.3"/>Aaron and his sons shall eat it.<q class="end-single" qid="03008031.3" from="03008031.2" to="03008031.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008032"/>
    <verse num="32">And what remains of the flesh and the bread you shall burn up with fire.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008033"/>
    <verse num="33">And you shall not go outside the entrance of the tent of meeting for seven days, until the days of your ordination are completed, for it <crossref let="p" cid="c03008033.1"/>will take seven days to ordain you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008034"/>
    <verse num="34">As has been done today, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has commanded to be done to make atonement for you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008035"/>
    <verse num="35">At the entrance of the tent of meeting you shall remain day and night for seven days, performing what the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has <crossref let="q" cid="c03008035.1"/>charged, so that you do not die, for so I have been commanded.<q class="end-double" qid="03008035.1" from="03008031.1" to="03008035.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03008036"/>
    <verse num="36">And Aaron and his sons did all the things that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded by Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009001"/>
  <chapter num="9">
    <heading>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> Accepts Aaron&apos;s Offering</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="r" cid="c03009001.1"/>On the eighth day Moses called Aaron and his sons and the elders of Israel,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009002"/>
    <verse num="2">and he said to Aaron, <crossref let="s" cid="c03009002.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="03009002.1" from="03009002.1" to="03009004.2"/>Take for yourself a bull calf for a sin offering and <crossref let="t" cid="c03009002.2"/>a ram for a burnt offering, both without blemish, and offer them before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009003"/>
    <verse num="3">And say to the people of Israel, <crossref let="u" cid="c03009003.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="03009003.1" from="03009003.1" to="03009004.1"/>Take a male goat for a sin offering, and a calf and a lamb, both a year old without blemish, for a burnt offering,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009004"/>
    <verse num="4">and an ox and a ram for peace offerings, to sacrifice before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and <crossref let="v" cid="c03009004.1"/>a grain offering mixed with oil, for <crossref let="w" cid="c03009004.2"/>today the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> will appear to you.<q class="end-single" qid="03009004.1" from="03009003.1" to="03009004.1"/><q class="end-double" qid="03009004.2" from="03009002.1" to="03009004.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009005"/>
    <verse num="5">And they brought what Moses commanded in front of the tent of meeting, and all the congregation drew near and stood before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009006"/>
    <verse num="6">And Moses said, <q class="begin-double" qid="03009006.1" from="03009006.1" to="03009006.2"/>This is the thing that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded you to do, that the glory of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> may appear to you.<q class="end-double" qid="03009006.2" from="03009006.1" to="03009006.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009007"/>
    <verse num="7">Then Moses said to Aaron, <q class="begin-double" qid="03009007.1" from="03009007.1" to="03009007.2"/>Draw near to the altar and <crossref let="x" cid="c03009007.1"/>offer your sin offering and your burnt offering and <crossref let="y" cid="c03009007.2"/>make atonement for yourself and for the people, and bring the offering of the people and make atonement for them, as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has commanded.<q class="end-double" qid="03009007.2" from="03009007.1" to="03009007.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">So Aaron drew near to the altar and killed the calf of the sin offering, which was for himself.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="z" cid="c03009009.1"/>And the sons of Aaron presented the blood to him, and he dipped his finger in the blood and <crossref let="a" cid="c03009009.2"/>put it on the horns of the altar and poured out the blood at the base of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="b" cid="c03009010.1"/>But the fat and the kidneys and the long lobe of the liver from the sin offering he burned on the altar, <crossref let="c" cid="c03009010.2"/>as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="d" cid="c03009011.1"/>The flesh and the skin he burned up with fire outside the camp.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">Then he killed the burnt offering, and Aaron&apos;s sons handed him the blood, and he <crossref let="e" cid="c03009012.1"/>threw it against the sides of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="f" cid="c03009013.1"/>And they handed the burnt offering to him, piece by piece, and the head, and he burned them on the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009014"/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="g" cid="c03009014.1"/>And he washed the entrails and the legs and burned them with the burnt offering on the altar.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="h" cid="c03009015.1"/>Then he presented the people&apos;s offering and took the goat of the sin offering that was for the people and killed it and <crossref let="i" cid="c03009015.2"/>offered it as a sin offering, <crossref let="j" cid="c03009015.3"/>like the first one.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009016"/>
    <verse num="16">And he presented the burnt offering and offered it <crossref let="k" cid="c03009016.1"/>according to the <crossref let="l" cid="c03009016.2"/>rule.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009017"/>
    <verse num="17">And he presented the <crossref let="m" cid="c03009017.1"/>grain offering, took a handful of it, and burned it on the altar, <crossref let="n" cid="c03009017.2"/>besides the burnt offering of the morning.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18">Then he killed the ox and the ram, <crossref let="o" cid="c03009018.1"/>the sacrifice of peace offerings for the people. And Aaron&apos;s sons handed him the blood, and he threw it against the sides of the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009019"/>
    <verse num="19">But the fat pieces of the ox and of the ram, the fat tail and that which covers <crossref let="p" cid="c03009019.1"/>the entrails and the kidneys and the long lobe of the liver&emdash;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009020"/>
    <verse num="20">they put the fat pieces on the breasts, <crossref let="q" cid="c03009020.1"/>and he burned the fat pieces on the altar,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009021"/>
    <verse num="21">but the breasts and the right thigh Aaron waved <crossref let="r" cid="c03009021.1"/>for a wave offering before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, as Moses commanded.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22">Then Aaron <crossref let="s" cid="c03009022.1"/>lifted up his hands toward the people and <crossref let="t" cid="c03009022.2"/>blessed them, and he came down from offering the sin offering and the burnt offering and the peace offerings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009023"/>
    <verse num="23">And Moses and Aaron went into the tent of meeting, and when they came out they blessed the people, and <crossref let="u" cid="c03009023.1"/>the glory of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> appeared to all the people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03009024"/>
    <verse num="24">And <crossref let="v" cid="c03009024.1"/>fire came out from before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and consumed the burnt offering and the pieces of fat on the altar, and when all the people saw it, <crossref let="w" cid="c03009024.2"/>they shouted and <crossref let="x" cid="c03009024.3"/>fell on their faces.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010001"/>
  <chapter num="10">
    <heading>The Death of Nadab and Abihu</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">Now <crossref let="y" cid="c03010001.1"/>Nadab and Abihu, the sons of Aaron, <crossref let="z" cid="c03010001.2"/>each took his censer and put fire in it and laid incense on it and offered <crossref let="a" cid="c03010001.3"/>unauthorized<note nid="n03010001.1"/> fire before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, which he had not commanded them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010002"/>
    <verse num="2">And fire <crossref let="b" cid="c03010002.1"/>came out from before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and consumed them, and they died before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010003"/>
    <verse num="3">Then Moses said to Aaron, <q class="begin-double" qid="03010003.1" from="03010003.1" to="03010003.4"/>This is what the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has said: <q class="begin-single" qid="03010003.2" from="03010003.2" to="03010003.3"/>Among <crossref let="c" cid="c03010003.1"/>those who are near me <crossref let="d" cid="c03010003.2"/>I will be sanctified, and before all the people I will be glorified.<q class="end-single" qid="03010003.3" from="03010003.2" to="03010003.3"/><q class="end-double" qid="03010003.4" from="03010003.1" to="03010003.4"/> <crossref let="e" cid="c03010003.3"/>And Aaron held his peace.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010004"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4">And Moses called Mishael and Elzaphan, the sons of <crossref let="f" cid="c03010004.1"/>Uzziel the uncle of Aaron, and said to them, <q class="begin-double" qid="03010004.1" from="03010004.1" to="03010004.2"/>Come near; carry your brothers away from the front of the sanctuary and out of the camp.<q class="end-double" qid="03010004.2" from="03010004.1" to="03010004.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010005"/>
    <verse num="5">So they came near and carried them in their coats out of the camp, as Moses had said.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010006"/>
    <verse num="6">And Moses said to Aaron and to Eleazar and Ithamar his sons, <crossref let="g" cid="c03010006.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="03010006.1" from="03010006.1" to="03010007.1"/>Do not let the hair of your heads hang loose, and do not tear your clothes, lest you die, and <crossref let="h" cid="c03010006.2"/>wrath come upon all the congregation; but let your brothers, the whole house of Israel, bewail the burning that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has kindled.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="i" cid="c03010007.1"/>And do not go outside the entrance of the tent of meeting, lest you die, <crossref let="j" cid="c03010007.2"/>for the anointing oil of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is upon you.<q class="end-double" qid="03010007.1" from="03010006.1" to="03010007.1"/> And they did according to the word of Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Aaron, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="k" cid="c03010009.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="03010009.1" from="03010009.1" to="03010011.1"/>Drink no wine or strong drink, you or your sons with you, when you go into the tent of meeting, lest you die. It shall be a statute forever throughout your generations.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010010"/>
    <verse num="10">You are to <crossref let="l" cid="c03010010.1"/>distinguish between the holy and the common, and between the unclean and the clean,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010011"/>
    <verse num="11">and <crossref let="m" cid="c03010011.1"/>you are to teach the people of Israel all the statutes that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has spoken to them by Moses.<q class="end-double" qid="03010011.1" from="03010009.1" to="03010011.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010012"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="12">Moses spoke to Aaron and to Eleazar and Ithamar, his surviving sons: <q class="begin-double" qid="03010012.1" from="03010012.1" to="03010015.1"/>Take the <crossref let="n" cid="c03010012.1"/>grain offering that is left of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s food offerings, and eat it unleavened beside the altar, for <crossref let="o" cid="c03010012.2"/>it is most holy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010013"/>
    <verse num="13">You shall eat it in a holy place, because it is your due and your sons&apos; due, from the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s food offerings, for <crossref let="p" cid="c03010013.1"/>so I am commanded.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010014"/>
    <verse num="14">But the <crossref let="q" cid="c03010014.1"/>breast that is waved and the thigh that is contributed you shall eat in a clean place, you and your sons and your daughters with you, for they are given as your due and your sons&apos; due from the sacrifices of the peace offerings of the people of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="r" cid="c03010015.1"/>The thigh that is contributed and the breast that is waved they shall bring with the food offerings of the fat pieces to wave for a wave offering before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and it shall be yours and your sons&apos; with you as a due forever, as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has commanded.<q class="end-double" qid="03010015.1" from="03010012.1" to="03010015.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">Now Moses diligently inquired about <crossref let="s" cid="c03010016.1"/>the goat of the sin offering, and behold, it was burned up! And he was angry with Eleazar and Ithamar, the surviving sons of Aaron, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="t" cid="c03010017.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="03010017.1" from="03010017.1" to="03010018.1"/>Why have you not eaten the sin offering in the place of the sanctuary, since <crossref let="o" cid="c03010017.2"/>it is a thing most holy and has been given to you that you may bear the iniquity of the congregation, to make atonement for them before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>?</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010018"/>
    <verse num="18">Behold, <crossref let="u" cid="c03010018.1"/>its blood was not brought into the inner part of the sanctuary. You certainly ought to have eaten it in the sanctuary, <crossref let="v" cid="c03010018.2"/>as I commanded.<q class="end-double" qid="03010018.1" from="03010017.1" to="03010018.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010019"/>
    <verse num="19">And Aaron said to Moses, <q class="begin-double" qid="03010019.1" from="03010019.1" to="03010019.2"/>Behold, <crossref let="w" cid="c03010019.1"/>today they have offered their sin offering and their burnt offering before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and yet such things as these have happened to me! If I had eaten the sin offering today, <crossref let="x" cid="c03010019.2"/>would the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> have approved?<q class="end-double" qid="03010019.2" from="03010019.1" to="03010019.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03010020"/>
    <verse num="20">And when Moses heard that, he approved.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011001"/>
  <chapter num="11">
    <heading>Clean and Unclean Animals</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying to them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03011002.1" from="03011002.1" to="03011045.1"/>Speak to the people of Israel, saying, <crossref let="y" cid="c03011002.1"/>These are the living things that you may eat among all the animals that are on the earth.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011003"/>
    <verse num="3">Whatever parts the hoof and is cloven-footed and chews the cud, among the animals, you may eat.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011004"/>
    <verse num="4">Nevertheless, among those that chew the cud or part the hoof, you shall not eat these: The camel, because it chews the cud but does not part the hoof, is unclean to you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011005"/>
    <verse num="5">And the <crossref let="z" cid="c03011005.1"/>rock badger, because it chews the cud but does not part the hoof, is unclean to you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011006"/>
    <verse num="6">And the hare, because it chews the cud but does not part the hoof, is unclean to you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011007"/>
    <verse num="7">And the pig, because it parts the hoof and is cloven-footed but does not chew the cud, <crossref let="a" cid="c03011007.1"/>is unclean to you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011008"/>
    <verse num="8">You shall not eat any of their flesh, and you shall not touch their carcasses; they are unclean to you.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011009"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9"><q class="continue-double" qid="03011009.1" from="03011002.1" to="03011045.1"/>These you may eat, of all that are in the waters. Everything in the waters that has fins and scales, whether in the seas or in the rivers, you may eat.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011010"/>
    <verse num="10">But anything in the seas or the rivers that does not have fins and scales, of the swarming creatures in the waters and of the living creatures that are in the waters, is <crossref let="b" cid="c03011010.1"/>detestable to you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011011"/>
    <verse num="11">You shall regard them as detestable; you shall not eat any of their flesh, and you shall detest their carcasses.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011012"/>
    <verse num="12">Everything in the waters that does not have fins and scales is detestable to you.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13"><q class="continue-double" qid="03011013.1" from="03011002.1" to="03011045.1"/>And these you shall detest among the birds;<note nid="n03011013.1"/> they shall not be eaten; they are <crossref let="b" cid="c03011013.1"/>detestable: <crossref let="c" cid="c03011013.2"/>the eagle,<note nid="n03011013.2"/> the bearded vulture, the black vulture,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011014"/>
    <verse num="14">the kite, <crossref let="d" cid="c03011014.1"/>the falcon of any kind,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011015"/>
    <verse num="15">every raven of any kind,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011016"/>
    <verse num="16">the ostrich, the nighthawk, the sea gull, the <crossref let="e" cid="c03011016.1"/>hawk of any kind,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011017"/>
    <verse num="17">the <crossref let="f" cid="c03011017.1"/>little owl, the cormorant, the <crossref let="g" cid="c03011017.2"/>short-eared owl,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011018"/>
    <verse num="18">the barn owl, the <crossref let="h" cid="c03011018.1"/>tawny owl, the carrion vulture,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011019"/>
    <verse num="19">the stork, the heron of any kind, the hoopoe, and <crossref let="i" cid="c03011019.1"/>the bat.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011020"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20"><q class="continue-double" qid="03011020.1" from="03011002.1" to="03011045.1"/>All winged insects that go on all fours are detestable to you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011021"/>
    <verse num="21">Yet among the winged insects that go on all fours you may eat those that have jointed legs above their feet, with which to hop on the ground.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011022"/>
    <verse num="22">Of them you may eat: <crossref let="j" cid="c03011022.1"/>the locust of any kind, the bald locust of any kind, the cricket of any kind, and the grasshopper of any kind.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011023"/>
    <verse num="23">But all other winged insects that have four feet are detestable to you.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011024"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24"><q class="continue-double" qid="03011024.1" from="03011002.1" to="03011045.1"/>And by these you shall become unclean. Whoever touches their carcass shall be unclean until the evening,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011025"/>
    <verse num="25">and whoever carries any part of their carcass <crossref let="k" cid="c03011025.1"/>shall wash his clothes and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011026"/>
    <verse num="26">Every animal that parts the hoof but is not cloven-footed or does not chew the cud is unclean to you. Everyone who touches them shall be unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011027"/>
    <verse num="27">And all that walk on their paws, among the animals that go on all fours, are unclean to you. Whoever touches their carcass shall be unclean until the evening,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011028"/>
    <verse num="28">and he who carries their carcass <crossref let="k" cid="c03011028.1"/>shall wash his clothes and be unclean until the evening; they are unclean to you.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011029"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29"><q class="continue-double" qid="03011029.1" from="03011002.1" to="03011045.1"/>And these are unclean to you among the swarming things that swarm on the ground: the mole rat, <crossref let="l" cid="c03011029.1"/>the mouse, the great lizard of any kind,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011030"/>
    <verse num="30">the gecko, the monitor lizard, the lizard, the sand lizard, and the chameleon.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011031"/>
    <verse num="31">These are unclean to you among all that swarm. Whoever touches them when they are dead shall be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011032"/>
    <verse num="32">And anything on which any of them falls when they are dead shall be unclean, whether it is an article of wood or a garment or a skin or a sack, any article that is used for any purpose. <crossref let="m" cid="c03011032.1"/>It must be put into water, and it shall be unclean until the evening; then it shall be clean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011033"/>
    <verse num="33">And if any of them falls into any earthenware vessel, all that is in it shall be unclean, and you <crossref let="n" cid="c03011033.1"/>shall break it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011034"/>
    <verse num="34">Any food in it that could be eaten, on which water comes, shall be unclean. And all drink that could be drunk from every such vessel shall be unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011035"/>
    <verse num="35">And everything on which any part of their carcass falls shall be unclean. Whether oven or stove, it shall be broken in pieces. They are unclean and shall remain unclean for you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011036"/>
    <verse num="36">Nevertheless, a spring or a cistern holding water shall be clean, but whoever touches a carcass in them shall be unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011037"/>
    <verse num="37">And if any part of their carcass falls upon any seed grain that is to be sown, it is clean,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011038"/>
    <verse num="38">but if water is put on the seed and any part of their carcass falls on it, it is unclean to you.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011039"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="39"><q class="continue-double" qid="03011039.1" from="03011002.1" to="03011045.1"/>And if any animal which you may eat dies, whoever touches its carcass shall be unclean until the evening,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011040"/>
    <verse num="40">and <crossref let="o" cid="c03011040.1"/>whoever eats of its carcass shall wash his clothes and be unclean until the evening. And whoever carries the carcass shall wash his clothes and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011041"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="41"><crossref let="p" cid="c03011041.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03011041.1" from="03011002.1" to="03011045.1"/>Every swarming thing that swarms on the ground is detestable; it shall not be eaten.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011042"/>
    <verse num="42">Whatever goes on its belly, and whatever goes on all fours, or whatever has many feet, any swarming thing that swarms on the ground, you shall not eat, for they are detestable.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011043"/>
    <verse num="43"><crossref let="q" cid="c03011043.1"/>You shall not make yourselves detestable with any swarming thing that swarms, and you shall not defile yourselves with them, and become unclean through them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011044"/>
    <verse num="44">For I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God. Consecrate yourselves therefore, and <crossref let="r" cid="c03011044.1"/>be holy, for I am holy. <crossref let="q" cid="c03011044.2"/>You shall not defile yourselves with any swarming thing that crawls on the ground.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011045"/>
    <verse num="45"><crossref let="s" cid="c03011045.1"/>For I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> who brought you up out of the land of Egypt to be your God. <crossref let="r" cid="c03011045.2"/>You shall therefore be holy, for I am holy.<q class="end-double" qid="03011045.1" from="03011002.1" to="03011045.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011046"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="46">This is the law about beast and bird and every living creature that moves through the waters and every creature that swarms on the ground,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03011047"/>
    <verse num="47"><crossref let="t" cid="c03011047.1"/>to make a distinction between the unclean and the clean and between the living creature that may be eaten and the living creature that may not be eaten.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03012001"/>
  <chapter num="12">
    <heading>Purification After Childbirth</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03012002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03012002.1" from="03012002.1" to="03012008.1"/>Speak to the people of Israel, saying, If a woman conceives and bears a male child, then <crossref let="u" cid="c03012002.1"/>she shall be unclean seven days. <crossref let="v" cid="c03012002.2"/>As at the time of her menstruation, she shall be unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03012003"/>
    <verse num="3">And on the <crossref let="w" cid="c03012003.1"/>eighth day the flesh of his foreskin shall be circumcised.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03012004"/>
    <verse num="4">Then she shall continue for thirty-three days in the blood of her purifying. She shall not touch anything holy, nor come into the sanctuary, until the days of her purifying are completed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03012005"/>
    <verse num="5">But if she bears a female child, then she shall be unclean two weeks, as in her menstruation. And she shall continue in the blood of her purifying for sixty-six days.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03012006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="u" cid="c03012006.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03012006.1" from="03012002.1" to="03012008.1"/>And when the days of her purifying are completed, whether for a son or for a daughter, she shall bring to the priest at the entrance of the tent of meeting a lamb a year old for a burnt offering, and a pigeon or a turtledove for a sin offering,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03012007"/>
    <verse num="7">and he shall offer it before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and make atonement for her. Then she shall be clean from the flow of her blood. This is the law for her who bears a child, either male or female.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03012008"/>
    <verse num="8">And if she cannot afford a lamb, then she shall take <crossref let="x" cid="c03012008.1"/>two turtledoves or two pigeons,<note nid="n03012008.1"/> <crossref let="y" cid="c03012008.2"/>one for a burnt offering and the other for a sin offering. <crossref let="z" cid="c03012008.3"/>And the priest shall make atonement for her, and she shall be clean.<q class="end-double" qid="03012008.1" from="03012002.1" to="03012008.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013001"/>
  <chapter num="13">
    <heading>Laws About Leprosy</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03013002.1" from="03013002.1" to="03013058.1"/>When a person has on the skin of his body a <crossref let="a" cid="c03013002.1"/>swelling or an eruption or a spot, and it turns into a case of leprous<note nid="n03013002.1"/> disease on the skin of his body, <crossref let="b" cid="c03013002.2"/>then he shall be brought to Aaron the priest or to one of his sons the priests,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013003"/>
    <verse num="3">and the priest shall examine the diseased area on the skin of his body. And if the hair in the diseased area has turned white and the disease appears to be deeper than the skin of his body, it is a case of leprous disease. When the priest has examined him, he shall pronounce him unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013004"/>
    <verse num="4">But if the spot is white in the skin of his body and appears no deeper than the skin, and the hair in it has not turned white, <crossref let="c" cid="c03013004.1"/>the priest shall shut up the diseased person for seven days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013005"/>
    <verse num="5">And the priest shall examine him on the seventh day, and if in his eyes the disease is checked and the disease has not spread in the skin, then the <crossref let="c" cid="c03013005.1"/>priest shall shut him up for another seven days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013006"/>
    <verse num="6">And the priest shall examine him again on the seventh day, and if the diseased area has faded and the disease has not spread in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean; it is only an eruption. And <crossref let="d" cid="c03013006.1"/>he shall wash his clothes and be clean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013007"/>
    <verse num="7">But if the eruption spreads in the skin, after he has shown himself to the priest for his cleansing, he shall appear again before the priest.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013008"/>
    <verse num="8">And the priest shall look, and if the eruption has spread in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean; it is a leprous disease.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013009"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9"><q class="continue-double" qid="03013009.1" from="03013002.1" to="03013058.1"/>When a man is afflicted with a leprous disease, he shall be brought to the priest,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013010"/>
    <verse num="10">and the priest shall look. And if there is a <crossref let="e" cid="c03013010.1"/>white swelling in the skin that has turned the hair white, and there is raw flesh in the swelling,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013011"/>
    <verse num="11">it is a chronic leprous disease in the skin of his body, and the priest shall pronounce him unclean. <crossref let="f" cid="c03013011.1"/>He shall not shut him up, for he is unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013012"/>
    <verse num="12">And if the leprous disease breaks out in the skin, so that the leprous disease covers all the skin of the diseased person from head to foot, so far as the priest can see,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013013"/>
    <verse num="13">then the priest shall look, and if the leprous disease has covered all his body, he shall pronounce him clean of the disease; it has all turned white, and he is clean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013014"/>
    <verse num="14">But when raw flesh appears on him, he shall be unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013015"/>
    <verse num="15">And the priest shall examine the raw flesh and pronounce him unclean. Raw flesh is unclean, for it is a leprous disease.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013016"/>
    <verse num="16">But if the raw flesh recovers and turns white again, then he shall come to the priest,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013017"/>
    <verse num="17">and the priest shall examine him, and if the disease has turned white, then the priest shall pronounce the diseased person clean; he is clean.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18"><q class="continue-double" qid="03013018.1" from="03013002.1" to="03013058.1"/>If there is in the skin of one&apos;s body a <crossref let="g" cid="c03013018.1"/>boil and it heals,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013019"/>
    <verse num="19">and in the place of the boil there comes a white swelling or a <crossref let="h" cid="c03013019.1"/>reddish-white spot, then it shall be shown to the priest.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013020"/>
    <verse num="20">And the priest shall look, and if it appears deeper than the skin and its hair has turned white, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is a case of leprous disease that has broken out in the boil.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013021"/>
    <verse num="21">But if the priest examines it and there is no white hair in it and it is not deeper than the skin, but has faded, then the priest shall shut him up seven days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013022"/>
    <verse num="22">And if it spreads in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean; it is a disease.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013023"/>
    <verse num="23">But <crossref let="i" cid="c03013023.1"/>if the spot remains in one place and does not spread, it is the scar of the boil, and the priest shall pronounce him clean.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013024"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24"><q class="continue-double" qid="03013024.1" from="03013002.1" to="03013058.1"/>Or, when the body has a burn on its skin and the raw flesh of the burn becomes a spot, <crossref let="j" cid="c03013024.1"/>reddish-white or white,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013025"/>
    <verse num="25">the priest shall examine it, and if the hair in the spot has turned white and it appears deeper than the skin, then it is a leprous disease. It has broken out in the burn, and the priest shall pronounce him unclean; it is a case of leprous disease.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013026"/>
    <verse num="26">But if the priest examines it and there is no white hair in the spot and it is no deeper than the skin, but has faded, the priest shall shut him up seven days,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013027"/>
    <verse num="27">and the priest shall examine him the seventh day. If it is spreading in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean; it is a case of leprous disease.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013028"/>
    <verse num="28">But if the spot remains <crossref let="k" cid="c03013028.1"/>in one place and does not spread in the skin, but has faded, it is a swelling from the burn, and the priest shall pronounce him clean, for it is the scar of the burn.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013029"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29"><q class="continue-double" qid="03013029.1" from="03013002.1" to="03013058.1"/>When a man or woman has a disease on the head or the beard,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013030"/>
    <verse num="30">the priest shall examine the disease. And if it appears deeper than the skin, and the hair in it is yellow and thin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is an itch, a leprous disease of the head or the beard.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013031"/>
    <verse num="31">And if the priest examines the itching disease and it appears no deeper than the skin and there is no black hair in it, then the priest shall shut up the person with the itching disease for seven days,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013032"/>
    <verse num="32">and on the seventh day the priest shall examine the disease. If the itch has not spread, and there is in it no yellow hair, and the itch appears to be no deeper than the skin,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013033"/>
    <verse num="33">then he shall shave himself, but the itch he shall not shave; and the priest shall shut up the person with the itching disease for another seven days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013034"/>
    <verse num="34">And on the seventh day the priest shall examine the itch, and if the itch has not spread in the skin and it appears to be no deeper than the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean. And <crossref let="l" cid="c03013034.1"/>he shall wash his clothes and be clean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013035"/>
    <verse num="35">But if the itch spreads in the skin after his cleansing,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013036"/>
    <verse num="36">then the priest shall examine him, and if the itch has spread in the skin, the priest need not seek for the yellow hair; he is unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013037"/>
    <verse num="37">But if in his eyes the itch is unchanged and black hair has grown in it, the itch is healed and he is clean, and the priest shall pronounce him clean.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013038"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="38"><q class="continue-double" qid="03013038.1" from="03013002.1" to="03013058.1"/>When a man or a woman has spots on the skin of the body, white spots,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013039"/>
    <verse num="39">the priest shall look, and if the spots on the skin of the body are of a dull white, it is leukoderma that has broken out in the skin; he is clean.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013040"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="40"><q class="continue-double" qid="03013040.1" from="03013002.1" to="03013058.1"/>If a man&apos;s hair falls out from his head, he is bald; he is clean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013041"/>
    <verse num="41">And if a man&apos;s hair falls out from his forehead, he has baldness of the forehead; he is clean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013042"/>
    <verse num="42">But if there is on the bald head or the bald forehead a reddish-white diseased area, it is a leprous disease breaking out on his bald head or his bald forehead.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013043"/>
    <verse num="43">Then the priest shall examine him, and if the diseased swelling is reddish-white on his bald head or on his bald forehead, like the appearance of leprous disease in the skin of the body,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013044"/>
    <verse num="44">he is a leprous man, he is unclean. The priest must pronounce him unclean; his disease is on his head.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013045"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="45"><q class="continue-double" qid="03013045.1" from="03013002.1" to="03013058.1"/>The leprous person who has the disease shall wear torn clothes and <crossref let="m" cid="c03013045.1"/>let the hair of his head hang loose, and he shall <crossref let="n" cid="c03013045.2"/>cover his upper lip<note nid="n03013045.1"/> and cry out, <crossref let="o" cid="c03013045.3"/><q class="begin-single" qid="03013045.2" from="03013045.2" to="03013045.3"/>Unclean, unclean.<q class="end-single" qid="03013045.3" from="03013045.2" to="03013045.3"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013046"/>
    <verse num="46">He shall remain unclean as long as he has the disease. He is unclean. He shall live alone. His dwelling shall be <crossref let="p" cid="c03013046.1"/>outside the camp.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013047"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="47"><q class="continue-double" qid="03013047.1" from="03013002.1" to="03013058.1"/>When there is a case of leprous disease in a <crossref let="q" cid="c03013047.1"/>garment, whether a woolen or a linen garment,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013048"/>
    <verse num="48">in warp or woof of linen or wool, or in a skin or in anything made of skin,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013049"/>
    <verse num="49">if the disease is greenish or reddish in the garment, or in the skin or in the warp or the woof or in any article made of skin, it is a case of leprous disease, and it shall be shown to the priest.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013050"/>
    <verse num="50">And the priest shall examine the disease and shut up that which has the disease for seven days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013051"/>
    <verse num="51">Then he shall examine the disease on the seventh day. If the disease has spread in the garment, in the warp or the woof, or in the skin, whatever be the use of the skin, the disease is a <crossref let="r" cid="c03013051.1"/>persistent leprous disease; it is unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013052"/>
    <verse num="52">And he shall burn the garment, or the warp or the woof, the wool or the linen, or any article made of skin that is diseased, for it is a persistent leprous disease. It shall be burned in the fire.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013053"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="53"><q class="continue-double" qid="03013053.1" from="03013002.1" to="03013058.1"/>And if the priest examines, and if the disease has not spread in the garment, in the warp or the woof or in any article made of skin,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013054"/>
    <verse num="54">then the priest shall command that they wash the thing in which is the disease, and he shall shut it up for another seven days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013055"/>
    <verse num="55">And the priest shall examine the diseased thing after it has been washed. And if the appearance of the diseased area has not changed, though the disease has not spread, it is unclean. You shall burn it in the fire, whether the rot is on the back or on the front.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013056"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="56"><q class="continue-double" qid="03013056.1" from="03013002.1" to="03013058.1"/>But if the priest examines, and if the diseased area has faded after it has been washed, he shall tear it out of the garment or the skin or the warp or the woof.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013057"/>
    <verse num="57">Then if it appears again in the garment, in the warp or the woof, or in any article made of skin, it is spreading. You shall burn with fire whatever has the disease.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013058"/>
    <verse num="58">But the garment, or the warp or the woof, or any article made of skin from which the disease departs when you have washed it, shall then be washed a second time, and be clean.<q class="end-double" qid="03013058.1" from="03013002.1" to="03013058.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03013059"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="59">This is the law for a case of leprous disease in a garment of wool or linen, either in the warp or the woof, or in any article made of skin, to determine whether it is clean or unclean.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014001"/>
  <chapter num="14">
    <heading>Laws for Cleansing Lepers</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03014002.1" from="03014002.1" to="03014032.1"/>This shall be the law of the leprous person for the day of his cleansing. <crossref let="s" cid="c03014002.1"/>He shall be brought to the priest,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014003"/>
    <verse num="3">and the priest shall go <crossref let="t" cid="c03014003.1"/>out of the camp, and the priest shall look. Then, if the case of leprous disease is healed in the leprous person,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014004"/>
    <verse num="4">the priest shall command them to take for him who is to be cleansed two live<note nid="n03014004.1"/> clean birds and <crossref let="u" cid="c03014004.1"/>cedarwood and <crossref let="v" cid="c03014004.2"/>scarlet yarn and <crossref let="w" cid="c03014004.3"/>hyssop.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014005"/>
    <verse num="5">And the priest shall command them to kill one of the birds in an earthenware vessel over fresh<note nid="n03014005.1"/> water.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014006"/>
    <verse num="6">He shall take the live bird with the cedarwood and the scarlet yarn and the hyssop, and dip them and the live bird in the blood of the bird that was killed over the fresh water.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014007"/>
    <verse num="7">And he shall <crossref let="x" cid="c03014007.1"/>sprinkle it <crossref let="y" cid="c03014007.2"/>seven times on him who is to be cleansed of the leprous disease. Then he shall pronounce him clean and shall <crossref let="z" cid="c03014007.3"/>let the living bird go <crossref let="a" cid="c03014007.4"/>into the open field.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014008"/>
    <verse num="8">And he who is to be cleansed <crossref let="b" cid="c03014008.1"/>shall wash his clothes and shave off all his hair and bathe himself in water, and he shall be clean. And after that he may come into the camp, but <crossref let="c" cid="c03014008.2"/>live outside his tent seven days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014009"/>
    <verse num="9">And <crossref let="d" cid="c03014009.1"/>on the seventh day he shall shave off all his hair from his head, his beard, and his eyebrows. He shall shave off all his hair, and then he <crossref let="b" cid="c03014009.2"/>shall wash his clothes and bathe his body in water, and he shall be clean.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10"><q class="continue-double" qid="03014010.1" from="03014002.1" to="03014032.1"/>And on the eighth day he <crossref let="e" cid="c03014010.1"/>shall take two male lambs without blemish, and one ewe lamb a year old without blemish, and a <crossref let="f" cid="c03014010.2"/>grain offering of three tenths of an ephah<note nid="n03014010.1"/> of fine flour mixed with oil, and one log<note nid="n03014010.2"/> of oil.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014011"/>
    <verse num="11">And the priest who cleanses him shall set the man who is to be cleansed and these things before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, at the entrance of the tent of meeting.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014012"/>
    <verse num="12">And the priest shall take one of the male lambs and <crossref let="g" cid="c03014012.1"/>offer it for a guilt offering, along with the log of oil, and <crossref let="h" cid="c03014012.2"/>wave them for a wave offering before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014013"/>
    <verse num="13">And he shall kill the lamb <crossref let="i" cid="c03014013.1"/>in the place where they kill the sin offering and the burnt offering, in the place of the sanctuary. For <crossref let="j" cid="c03014013.2"/>the guilt offering, like the sin offering, belongs to the priest; <crossref let="k" cid="c03014013.3"/>it is most holy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014014"/>
    <verse num="14">The priest shall take some of the blood of the guilt offering, and the priest shall put it <crossref let="l" cid="c03014014.1"/>on the lobe of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed and on the thumb of his right hand and on the big toe of his right foot.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014015"/>
    <verse num="15">Then the priest shall take some of the log of oil and pour it into the palm of his own left hand</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014016"/>
    <verse num="16">and dip his right finger in the oil that is in his left hand and sprinkle some oil with his finger seven times before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014017"/>
    <verse num="17">And some of the oil that remains in his hand the priest shall put on the lobe of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed and on the thumb of his right hand and on the big toe of his right foot, on top of the blood of the guilt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014018"/>
    <verse num="18">And the rest of the oil that is in the priest&apos;s hand he shall put on the head of him who is to be cleansed. <crossref let="m" cid="c03014018.1"/>Then the priest shall make atonement for him before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014019"/>
    <verse num="19">The priest shall offer the sin offering, to make atonement for him who is to be cleansed from his uncleanness. And afterward he shall kill the burnt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014020"/>
    <verse num="20">And the priest shall offer the burnt offering and the <crossref let="f" cid="c03014020.1"/>grain offering on the altar. <crossref let="m" cid="c03014020.2"/>Thus the priest shall make atonement for him, and he shall be clean.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014021"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="21"><q class="continue-double" qid="03014021.1" from="03014002.1" to="03014032.1"/>But <crossref let="n" cid="c03014021.1"/>if he is poor and cannot afford so much, then he shall take one male lamb for a guilt offering <crossref let="h" cid="c03014021.2"/>to be waved, to make atonement for him, and a tenth of an ephah of fine flour mixed with oil for a grain offering, and a log of oil;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014022"/>
    <verse num="22"><crossref let="o" cid="c03014022.1"/>also two turtledoves or two pigeons, whichever he can afford. The one shall be a sin offering and the other a burnt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014023"/>
    <verse num="23"><crossref let="p" cid="c03014023.1"/>And on the eighth day he shall bring them for his cleansing to the priest, to the entrance of the tent of meeting, before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014024"/>
    <verse num="24"><crossref let="q" cid="c03014024.1"/>And the priest shall take the lamb of the guilt offering and the log of oil, and the priest shall wave them for a wave offering before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014025"/>
    <verse num="25">And he shall kill the lamb of the guilt offering. <crossref let="r" cid="c03014025.1"/>And the priest shall take some of the blood of the guilt offering and put it on the lobe of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, and on the thumb of his right hand and on the big toe of his right foot.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014026"/>
    <verse num="26">And the priest shall pour some of the oil into the palm of his own left hand,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014027"/>
    <verse num="27">and shall sprinkle with his right finger some of the oil that is in his left hand seven times before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014028"/>
    <verse num="28">And the priest shall put some of the oil that is in his hand on the lobe of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed and on the thumb of his right hand and on the big toe of his right foot, in the place where the blood of the guilt offering was put.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014029"/>
    <verse num="29">And the rest of the oil that is in the priest&apos;s hand he shall put on the head of him who is to be cleansed, to make atonement for him before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014030"/>
    <verse num="30">And he shall offer, of the <crossref let="s" cid="c03014030.1"/>turtledoves or pigeons, whichever he can afford,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014031"/>
    <verse num="31">one<note nid="n03014031.1"/> for a sin offering and the other for a burnt offering, along with a grain offering. <crossref let="m" cid="c03014031.1"/>And the priest shall make atonement before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for him who is being cleansed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014032"/>
    <verse num="32">This is the law for him in whom is a case of leprous disease, who cannot afford <crossref let="t" cid="c03014032.1"/>the offerings for his cleansing.<q class="end-double" qid="03014032.1" from="03014002.1" to="03014032.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014033"/>
    <heading>Laws for Cleansing Houses</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="33">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014034"/>
    <verse num="34"><q class="begin-double" qid="03014034.1" from="03014034.1" to="03014053.1"/>When you come into the land of Canaan, which I give you <crossref let="u" cid="c03014034.1"/>for a possession, and I put a case of leprous disease in a house in the land of your possession,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014035"/>
    <verse num="35">then he who owns the house shall come and tell the priest, <q class="begin-single" qid="03014035.1" from="03014035.1" to="03014035.2"/>There seems to me to be some case of <crossref let="v" cid="c03014035.1"/>disease in my house.<q class="end-single" qid="03014035.2" from="03014035.1" to="03014035.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014036"/>
    <verse num="36">Then the priest shall command that they empty the house before the priest goes to examine the disease, lest all that is in the house be declared unclean. And afterward the priest shall go in to see the house.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014037"/>
    <verse num="37">And he shall examine the disease. And if the disease is in the walls of the house with greenish or reddish spots, and if it appears to be deeper than the surface,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014038"/>
    <verse num="38">then the priest shall go out of the house to the door of the house and shut up the house seven days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014039"/>
    <verse num="39">And the priest shall come again on the seventh day, and look. If the disease has spread in the walls of the house,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014040"/>
    <verse num="40">then the priest shall command that they take out the stones in which is the disease and throw them into an unclean place outside the city.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014041"/>
    <verse num="41">And he shall have the inside of the house scraped all around, and the plaster that they scrape off they shall pour out in an unclean place outside the city.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014042"/>
    <verse num="42">Then they shall take other stones and put them in the place of those stones, and he shall take other plaster and plaster the house.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014043"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="43"><q class="continue-double" qid="03014043.1" from="03014034.1" to="03014053.1"/>If the disease breaks out again in the house, after he has taken out the stones and scraped the house and plastered it,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014044"/>
    <verse num="44">then the priest shall go and look. And if the disease has spread in the house, it is a <crossref let="w" cid="c03014044.1"/>persistent leprous disease in the house; it is unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014045"/>
    <verse num="45">And he shall break down the house, its stones and timber and all the plaster of the house, and he shall carry them out of the city to an unclean place.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014046"/>
    <verse num="46">Moreover, whoever enters the house while it is shut up shall be unclean until the evening,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014047"/>
    <verse num="47">and whoever sleeps in the house <crossref let="x" cid="c03014047.1"/>shall wash his clothes, and whoever eats in the house shall wash his clothes.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014048"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="48"><q class="continue-double" qid="03014048.1" from="03014034.1" to="03014053.1"/>But if the priest comes and looks, and if the disease has not spread in the house after the house was plastered, then the priest shall pronounce the house clean, for the disease is healed.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014049"/>
    <verse num="49">And for the <crossref let="y" cid="c03014049.1"/>cleansing of the house he shall take <crossref let="z" cid="c03014049.2"/>two small birds, with cedarwood and scarlet yarn and hyssop,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014050"/>
    <verse num="50">and shall kill one of the birds in an earthenware vessel over fresh water</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014051"/>
    <verse num="51">and shall take the cedarwood and the hyssop and the scarlet yarn, along with the live bird, and dip them in the blood of the bird that was killed and in the fresh water and sprinkle the house seven times.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014052"/>
    <verse num="52">Thus he shall cleanse the house with the blood of the bird and with the fresh water and with the live bird and with the cedarwood and hyssop and scarlet yarn.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014053"/>
    <verse num="53">And he shall let the live bird go out of the city <crossref let="a" cid="c03014053.1"/>into the open country. So he shall <crossref let="b" cid="c03014053.2"/>make atonement for the house, and it shall be clean.<q class="end-double" qid="03014053.1" from="03014034.1" to="03014053.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014054"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="54">This is the law for any case of leprous disease: for <crossref let="c" cid="c03014054.1"/>an itch,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014055"/>
    <verse num="55">for <crossref let="d" cid="c03014055.1"/>leprous disease in a garment or in <crossref let="e" cid="c03014055.2"/>a house,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014056"/>
    <verse num="56">and <crossref let="f" cid="c03014056.1"/>for a swelling or an eruption or a spot,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03014057"/>
    <verse num="57">to <crossref let="g" cid="c03014057.1"/>show when it is unclean and when it is clean. This is the law for leprous disease.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015001"/>
  <chapter num="15">
    <heading>Laws About Bodily Discharges</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03015002.1" from="03015002.1" to="03015031.2"/>Speak to the people of Israel and say to them, <crossref let="h" cid="c03015002.1"/>When any man has a discharge from his body,<note nid="n03015002.1"/> his discharge is unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015003"/>
    <verse num="3">And this is the law of his uncleanness for a discharge: whether his body runs with his discharge, or his body is blocked up by his discharge, it is his uncleanness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015004"/>
    <verse num="4">Every bed on which the one with the discharge lies shall be unclean, and everything on which he sits shall be unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015005"/>
    <verse num="5">And anyone who touches his bed <crossref let="i" cid="c03015005.1"/>shall wash his clothes and <crossref let="j" cid="c03015005.2"/>bathe himself in water and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015006"/>
    <verse num="6">And whoever sits on anything on which the one with the discharge has sat shall wash his clothes and bathe himself in water and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015007"/>
    <verse num="7">And whoever touches the body of the one with the discharge shall wash his clothes and bathe himself in water and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015008"/>
    <verse num="8">And if the one with the discharge spits on someone who is clean, then he shall wash his clothes and bathe himself in water and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015009"/>
    <verse num="9">And any saddle on which the one with the discharge rides shall be unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015010"/>
    <verse num="10">And whoever touches anything that was under him shall be unclean until the evening. And whoever carries such things shall wash his clothes and bathe himself in water and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015011"/>
    <verse num="11">Anyone whom the one with the discharge touches without having rinsed his hands in water shall wash his clothes and bathe himself in water and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015012"/>
    <verse num="12">And an <crossref let="k" cid="c03015012.1"/>earthenware vessel that the one with the discharge touches shall be broken, and every vessel of wood shall be rinsed in water.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13"><q class="continue-double" qid="03015013.1" from="03015002.1" to="03015031.2"/>And when the one with a discharge is cleansed of his discharge, then <crossref let="l" cid="c03015013.1"/>he shall count for himself seven days for his cleansing, and wash his clothes. And he shall bathe his body in fresh water and shall be clean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015014"/>
    <verse num="14">And on the eighth day he shall take two <crossref let="m" cid="c03015014.1"/>turtledoves or two pigeons and come before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to the entrance of the tent of meeting and give them to the priest.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015015"/>
    <verse num="15">And the priest shall use them, <crossref let="n" cid="c03015015.1"/>one for a sin offering and the other for a burnt offering. <crossref let="o" cid="c03015015.2"/>And the priest shall make atonement for him before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for his discharge.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="p" cid="c03015016.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03015016.1" from="03015002.1" to="03015031.2"/>If a man has an emission of semen, he shall bathe his whole body in water and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015017"/>
    <verse num="17">And every garment and every skin on which the semen comes shall be washed with water and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015018"/>
    <verse num="18">If a man lies with a woman and has an emission of semen, both of them shall bathe themselves in water and <crossref let="q" cid="c03015018.1"/>be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19"><q class="continue-double" qid="03015019.1" from="03015002.1" to="03015031.2"/>When a woman has a discharge, and the discharge in her body is blood, she shall be in her menstrual impurity for seven days, and whoever touches her shall be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="r" cid="c03015020.1"/>And everything on which she lies during her menstrual impurity shall be unclean. Everything also on which she sits shall be unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015021"/>
    <verse num="21">And whoever touches her bed shall wash his clothes and bathe himself in water and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015022"/>
    <verse num="22">And whoever touches anything on which she sits shall wash his clothes and bathe himself in water and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015023"/>
    <verse num="23">Whether it is the bed or anything on which she sits, when he touches it he shall be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015024"/>
    <verse num="24">And <crossref let="s" cid="c03015024.1"/>if any man lies with her and her menstrual impurity comes upon him, he shall be unclean seven days, and every bed on which he lies shall be unclean.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015025"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="25"><q class="continue-double" qid="03015025.1" from="03015002.1" to="03015031.2"/>If <crossref let="t" cid="c03015025.1"/>a woman has a discharge of blood for many days, not at the time of her menstrual impurity, or if she has a discharge beyond the time of her impurity, all the days of the discharge she shall continue in uncleanness. As in the days of her impurity, she shall be unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015026"/>
    <verse num="26">Every bed on which she lies, all the days of her discharge, shall be to her as the bed of her impurity. And everything on which she sits shall be unclean, as in the uncleanness of her menstrual impurity.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015027"/>
    <verse num="27">And whoever touches these things shall be unclean, and shall wash his clothes and bathe himself in water and be unclean until the evening.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015028"/>
    <verse num="28">But <crossref let="u" cid="c03015028.1"/>if she is cleansed of her discharge, she shall count for herself seven days, and after that she shall be clean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015029"/>
    <verse num="29">And on the eighth day she shall take two <crossref let="v" cid="c03015029.1"/>turtledoves or two pigeons and bring them to the priest, to the entrance of the tent of meeting.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015030"/>
    <verse num="30">And the priest shall use one for a sin offering and the other for a burnt offering. And the priest shall make atonement for her before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for her unclean discharge.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015031"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="31"><q class="continue-double" qid="03015031.1" from="03015002.1" to="03015031.2"/>Thus you shall keep the people of Israel separate from their uncleanness, lest they die in their uncleanness by <crossref let="w" cid="c03015031.1"/>defiling my tabernacle that is in their midst.<q class="end-double" qid="03015031.2" from="03015002.1" to="03015031.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015032"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="32">This is the law <crossref let="x" cid="c03015032.1"/>for him who has a discharge and <crossref let="y" cid="c03015032.2"/>for him who has an emission of semen, becoming unclean thereby;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03015033"/>
    <verse num="33"><crossref let="z" cid="c03015033.1"/>also for her who is unwell with her menstrual impurity, that is, for anyone, <crossref let="x" cid="c03015033.2"/>male or <crossref let="a" cid="c03015033.3"/>female, who has a discharge, and for the <crossref let="b" cid="c03015033.4"/>man who lies with a woman who is unclean.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016001"/>
  <chapter num="16">
    <heading>The Day of Atonement</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses after <crossref let="c" cid="c03016001.1"/>the death of the two sons of Aaron, when they drew near before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and died,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016002"/>
    <verse num="2">and the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Moses, <q class="begin-double" qid="03016002.1" from="03016002.1" to="03016034.1"/>Tell Aaron your brother not to <crossref let="d" cid="c03016002.1"/>come at any time into the Holy Place inside the veil, before the mercy seat that is on the ark, so that he may not die. For <crossref let="e" cid="c03016002.2"/>I will appear in the cloud over the mercy seat.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016003"/>
    <verse num="3">But in this way Aaron shall come into the Holy Place: <crossref let="f" cid="c03016003.1"/>with a bull from the herd for a sin offering and <crossref let="g" cid="c03016003.2"/>a ram for a burnt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016004"/>
    <verse num="4">He shall put on <crossref let="h" cid="c03016004.1"/>the holy linen coat and shall have the linen undergarment on his body, and he shall tie the linen sash around his waist, and wear the linen turban; these are the holy garments. <crossref let="i" cid="c03016004.2"/>He shall bathe his body in water and then put them on.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016005"/>
    <verse num="5">And he shall take from <crossref let="j" cid="c03016005.1"/>the congregation of the people of Israel two male goats for a sin offering, and one ram for a burnt offering.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6"><q class="continue-double" qid="03016006.1" from="03016002.1" to="03016034.1"/>Aaron shall <crossref let="k" cid="c03016006.1"/>offer the bull as a sin offering for himself and shall <crossref let="l" cid="c03016006.2"/>make atonement for himself and for his house.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016007"/>
    <verse num="7">Then he shall take the two goats and set them before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> at the entrance of the tent of meeting.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016008"/>
    <verse num="8">And Aaron shall cast lots over the two goats, one lot for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and the other lot for <crossref let="m" cid="c03016008.1"/>Azazel.<note nid="n03016008.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016009"/>
    <verse num="9">And Aaron shall present the goat on which the lot fell for the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and use it as a sin offering,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016010"/>
    <verse num="10">but the goat on which the lot fell for <crossref let="m" cid="c03016010.1"/>Azazel shall be presented alive before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> to make atonement over it, that it may be sent away into the wilderness to <crossref let="m" cid="c03016010.2"/>Azazel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11"><q class="continue-double" qid="03016011.1" from="03016002.1" to="03016034.1"/>Aaron shall present <crossref let="k" cid="c03016011.1"/>the bull as a sin offering for himself, and shall make atonement for himself and for his house. He shall kill the bull as a sin offering for himself.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016012"/>
    <verse num="12">And he shall take <crossref let="n" cid="c03016012.1"/>a censer full of coals of fire from the altar before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and two handfuls of sweet incense beaten small, and he shall bring it inside the veil</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="o" cid="c03016013.1"/>and put the incense on the fire before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, that the cloud of the incense may cover <crossref let="p" cid="c03016013.2"/>the mercy seat that is over the testimony, so that he does not die.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016014"/>
    <verse num="14">And <crossref let="q" cid="c03016014.1"/>he shall take some of the blood of the bull and sprinkle it with his finger on the front of the mercy seat on the east side, and in front of the mercy seat he shall sprinkle some of the blood with his finger seven times.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="r" cid="c03016015.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03016015.1" from="03016002.1" to="03016034.1"/>Then he shall kill the goat of the sin offering that is for the people and bring its blood <crossref let="s" cid="c03016015.2"/>inside the veil and do with its blood as he did with the blood of the bull, sprinkling it over the mercy seat and in front of the mercy seat.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016016"/>
    <verse num="16">Thus he shall <crossref let="t" cid="c03016016.1"/>make atonement for the Holy Place, because of the uncleannesses of the people of Israel and because of their transgressions, all their sins. And so he shall do for the tent of meeting, which dwells with them in the midst of their uncleannesses.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="u" cid="c03016017.1"/>No one may be in the tent of meeting from the time he enters to make atonement in the Holy Place until he comes out and has made atonement for himself and for his house and for all the assembly of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016018"/>
    <verse num="18">Then he shall go out to the altar that is <crossref let="v" cid="c03016018.1"/>before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> and <crossref let="w" cid="c03016018.2"/>make atonement for it, and shall take some of the blood of the bull and some of the blood of the goat, and put it on the horns of the altar all around.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016019"/>
    <verse num="19">And he shall sprinkle some of the blood on it with his finger seven times, and cleanse it and consecrate it from the uncleannesses of the people of Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016020"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20"><q class="continue-double" qid="03016020.1" from="03016002.1" to="03016034.1"/>And when he has made an end of <crossref let="x" cid="c03016020.1"/>atoning for the Holy Place and the tent of meeting and the altar, he shall present the live goat.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016021"/>
    <verse num="21">And Aaron shall lay both his hands on the head of the live goat, and confess over it all the iniquities of the people of Israel, and all their transgressions, all their sins. And he shall <crossref let="y" cid="c03016021.1"/>put them on the head of the goat and send it away into the wilderness by the hand of a man who is in readiness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016022"/>
    <verse num="22">The goat shall <crossref let="z" cid="c03016022.1"/>bear all their iniquities on itself to a remote area, and <crossref let="a" cid="c03016022.2"/>he shall let the goat go free in the wilderness.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016023"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="23"><q class="continue-double" qid="03016023.1" from="03016002.1" to="03016034.1"/>Then Aaron shall come into the tent of meeting and <crossref let="b" cid="c03016023.1"/>shall take off the linen garments that he put on when he went into the Holy Place and shall leave them there.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016024"/>
    <verse num="24">And he shall bathe his body in water in a holy place and put on his garments and come out and <crossref let="c" cid="c03016024.1"/>offer his burnt offering and the burnt offering of the people and make atonement for himself and for the people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016025"/>
    <verse num="25">And <crossref let="d" cid="c03016025.1"/>the fat of the sin offering he shall burn on the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016026"/>
    <verse num="26">And he who lets the goat go to <crossref let="e" cid="c03016026.1"/>Azazel shall wash his clothes and <crossref let="f" cid="c03016026.2"/>bathe his body in water, and afterward he may come into the camp.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016027"/>
    <verse num="27"><crossref let="g" cid="c03016027.1"/>And the bull for the sin offering and the goat for the sin offering, whose blood was brought in to make atonement in the Holy Place, shall be carried outside the camp. Their skin and their flesh and their dung shall be burned up with fire.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016028"/>
    <verse num="28">And he who burns them shall wash his clothes and bathe his body in water, and afterward he may come into the camp.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016029"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29"><q class="continue-double" qid="03016029.1" from="03016002.1" to="03016034.1"/>And it shall be a statute to you forever that <crossref let="h" cid="c03016029.1"/>in the seventh month, on the tenth day of the month, you shall <crossref let="i" cid="c03016029.2"/>afflict yourselves<note nid="n03016029.1"/> and shall do no work, either <crossref let="j" cid="c03016029.3"/>the native or the stranger who sojourns among you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016030"/>
    <verse num="30">For on this day shall atonement be made for you <crossref let="k" cid="c03016030.1"/>to cleanse you. You shall be clean before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> from all your sins.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016031"/>
    <verse num="31"><crossref let="l" cid="c03016031.1"/>It is a Sabbath of solemn rest to you, and you shall <crossref let="i" cid="c03016031.2"/>afflict yourselves; it is a statute forever.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016032"/>
    <verse num="32"><crossref let="m" cid="c03016032.1"/>And the priest who is anointed and <crossref let="n" cid="c03016032.2"/>consecrated as priest in his father&apos;s place <crossref let="o" cid="c03016032.3"/>shall make atonement, wearing the holy linen garments.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016033"/>
    <verse num="33">He shall make atonement for <crossref let="p" cid="c03016033.1"/>the holy sanctuary, and he shall make atonement for the tent of meeting and for <crossref let="q" cid="c03016033.2"/>the altar, and he shall make atonement for <crossref let="r" cid="c03016033.3"/>the priests and for <crossref let="s" cid="c03016033.4"/>all the people of the assembly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03016034"/>
    <verse num="34">And this shall be a statute forever for you, that atonement may be made for the people of Israel <crossref let="t" cid="c03016034.1"/>once in the year because of all their sins.<q class="end-double" qid="03016034.1" from="03016002.1" to="03016034.1"/> And Aaron<note nid="n03016034.1"/> did as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017001"/>
  <chapter num="17">
    <heading>The Place of Sacrifice</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03017002.1" from="03017002.1" to="03017016.1"/>Speak to Aaron and his sons and to all the people of Israel and say to them, This is the thing that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> has commanded.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017003"/>
    <verse num="3">If any one of the house of Israel <crossref let="u" cid="c03017003.1"/>kills an ox or a lamb or a goat in the camp, or kills it outside the camp,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017004"/>
    <verse num="4">and <crossref let="v" cid="c03017004.1"/>does not bring it to the entrance of the tent of meeting to offer it as a gift to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in front of the tabernacle of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, bloodguilt shall be imputed to that man. He has shed blood, and that man <crossref let="w" cid="c03017004.2"/>shall be cut off from among his people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017005"/>
    <verse num="5">This is to the end that the people of Israel may bring their sacrifices that they sacrifice <crossref let="x" cid="c03017005.1"/>in the open field, that they may bring them to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, to the priest at the entrance of the tent of meeting, and sacrifice them <crossref let="y" cid="c03017005.2"/>as sacrifices of peace offerings to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017006"/>
    <verse num="6">And the priest shall <crossref let="y" cid="c03017006.1"/>throw the blood on the altar of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> at the entrance of the tent of meeting and burn the fat <crossref let="z" cid="c03017006.2"/>for a pleasing aroma to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017007"/>
    <verse num="7">So they shall no more sacrifice their sacrifices to goat demons, after whom they <crossref let="a" cid="c03017007.1"/>whore. This shall be a statute forever for them throughout their generations.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017008"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8"><q class="continue-double" qid="03017008.1" from="03017002.1" to="03017016.1"/>And you shall say to them, Any one of the house of Israel, or of the strangers who sojourn among them, who <crossref let="b" cid="c03017008.1"/>offers a burnt offering or sacrifice</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017009"/>
    <verse num="9">and <crossref let="c" cid="c03017009.1"/>does not bring it to the entrance of the tent of meeting to offer it to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, <crossref let="w" cid="c03017009.2"/>that man shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017010"/>
    <heading>Laws Against Eating Blood</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10"><q class="continue-double" qid="03017010.1" from="03017002.1" to="03017016.1"/>If any one of the house of Israel or of the strangers who sojourn among them <crossref let="d" cid="c03017010.1"/>eats any blood, I will <crossref let="e" cid="c03017010.2"/>set my face against that person who eats blood and will cut him off from among his people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="f" cid="c03017011.1"/>For the life of the flesh is in the blood, and I have given it for you on the altar <crossref let="g" cid="c03017011.2"/>to make atonement for your souls, <crossref let="h" cid="c03017011.3"/>for it is the blood that makes atonement by the life.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017012"/>
    <verse num="12">Therefore I have said to the people of Israel, No person among you shall eat blood, neither shall any stranger who sojourns among you eat blood.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13"><q class="continue-double" qid="03017013.1" from="03017002.1" to="03017016.1"/>Any one also of the people of Israel, or of the strangers who sojourn among them, who takes in hunting any beast or bird that may be eaten shall <crossref let="i" cid="c03017013.1"/>pour out its blood and <crossref let="j" cid="c03017013.2"/>cover it with earth.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017014"/>
    <verse num="14">For the life of every creature<note nid="n03017014.1"/> is its <crossref let="k" cid="c03017014.1"/>blood: its blood is its life.<note nid="n03017014.2"/> Therefore I have said to the people of Israel, You shall not eat the blood of any creature, for the life of every creature is its blood. Whoever eats it shall be cut off.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="l" cid="c03017015.1"/>And every person who eats what dies of itself or what is torn by beasts, <crossref let="m" cid="c03017015.2"/>whether he is a native or a sojourner, <crossref let="n" cid="c03017015.3"/>shall wash his clothes and <crossref let="o" cid="c03017015.4"/>bathe himself in water and be unclean until the evening; then he shall be clean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03017016"/>
    <verse num="16">But if he does not wash them or bathe his flesh, <crossref let="p" cid="c03017016.1"/>he shall bear his iniquity.<q class="end-double" qid="03017016.1" from="03017002.1" to="03017016.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018001"/>
  <chapter num="18">
    <heading>Unlawful Sexual Relations</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03018002.1" from="03018002.1" to="03018030.1"/>Speak to the people of Israel and say to them, <crossref let="q" cid="c03018002.1"/>I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018003"/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="r" cid="c03018003.1"/>You shall not do as they do in the land of Egypt, where you lived, and <crossref let="s" cid="c03018003.2"/>you shall not do as they do in the land of Canaan, to which I am bringing you. You shall not walk in their statutes.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="t" cid="c03018004.1"/>You shall follow my rules<note nid="n03018004.1"/> and keep my statutes and walk in them. <crossref let="q" cid="c03018004.2"/>I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018005"/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="t" cid="c03018005.1"/>You shall therefore keep my statutes and my rules; <crossref let="u" cid="c03018005.2"/>if a person does them, he shall live by them: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6"><q class="continue-double" qid="03018006.1" from="03018002.1" to="03018030.1"/>None of you shall approach any one of his close relatives to uncover nakedness. I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="v" cid="c03018007.1"/>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father, which is the nakedness of your mother; she is your mother, you shall not uncover her nakedness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="w" cid="c03018008.1"/>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father&apos;s wife; it is your father&apos;s nakedness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="x" cid="c03018009.1"/>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your sister, your father&apos;s daughter or your mother&apos;s daughter, whether brought up in the family or in another home.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018010"/>
    <verse num="10">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your son&apos;s daughter or of your daughter&apos;s daughter, for their nakedness is your own nakedness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018011"/>
    <verse num="11">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father&apos;s wife&apos;s daughter, brought up in your father&apos;s family, since she is your sister.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018012"/>
    <verse num="12">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father&apos;s sister; she is your father&apos;s relative.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018013"/>
    <verse num="13">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your mother&apos;s sister, for she is your mother&apos;s relative.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018014"/>
    <verse num="14">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father&apos;s brother, that is, you shall not approach his wife; she is your aunt.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="y" cid="c03018015.1"/>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your daughter-in-law; she is your son&apos;s wife, you shall not uncover her nakedness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018016"/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="z" cid="c03018016.1"/>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your brother&apos;s wife; it is your brother&apos;s nakedness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018017"/>
    <verse num="17">You shall not uncover the nakedness of a woman and of her daughter, and you shall not take her son&apos;s daughter or her daughter&apos;s daughter to uncover her nakedness; they are relatives; it is depravity.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018018"/>
    <verse num="18">And you shall not take a woman as a <crossref let="a" cid="c03018018.1"/>rival wife to her sister, uncovering her nakedness <crossref let="b" cid="c03018018.2"/>while her sister is still alive.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018019"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="c" cid="c03018019.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03018019.1" from="03018002.1" to="03018030.1"/>You shall not approach a woman to uncover her nakedness while she is in her menstrual uncleanness.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="d" cid="c03018020.1"/>And you shall not lie sexually with your neighbor&apos;s wife and so make yourself unclean with her.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018021"/>
    <verse num="21">You shall not give any of your children to <crossref let="e" cid="c03018021.1"/>offer them<note nid="n03018021.1"/> to <crossref let="f" cid="c03018021.2"/>Molech, and so <crossref let="g" cid="c03018021.3"/>profane the name of your God: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018022"/>
    <verse num="22"><crossref let="h" cid="c03018022.1"/>You shall not lie with a male as with a woman; it is an abomination.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018023"/>
    <verse num="23"><crossref let="i" cid="c03018023.1"/>And you shall not lie with any animal and so make yourself unclean with it, neither shall any woman give herself to an animal to lie with it: it is <crossref let="j" cid="c03018023.2"/>perversion.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018024"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="24"><crossref let="k" cid="c03018024.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03018024.1" from="03018002.1" to="03018030.1"/>Do not make yourselves unclean by any of these things, <crossref let="l" cid="c03018024.2"/>for by all these the nations I am driving out before you have become unclean,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018025"/>
    <verse num="25">and the <crossref let="m" cid="c03018025.1"/>land became unclean, so that I punished its iniquity, and the land <crossref let="n" cid="c03018025.2"/>vomited out its inhabitants.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018026"/>
    <verse num="26">But <crossref let="o" cid="c03018026.1"/>you shall keep my statutes and my rules and do none of these abominations, either the <crossref let="p" cid="c03018026.2"/>native or the stranger who sojourns among you</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018027"/>
    <verse num="27">(for the people of the land, who were before you, did all of these abominations, so that the land became unclean),</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018028"/>
    <verse num="28">lest the land vomit you out when you make it unclean, as it vomited out the nation that was before you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018029"/>
    <verse num="29">For everyone who does any of these abominations, the persons who do them shall be cut off from among their people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03018030"/>
    <verse num="30"><crossref let="q" cid="c03018030.1"/>So keep my charge never to practice <crossref let="r" cid="c03018030.2"/>any of these abominable customs that were practiced before you, and never to make yourselves unclean by them: <crossref let="s" cid="c03018030.3"/>I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.<q class="end-double" qid="03018030.1" from="03018002.1" to="03018030.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019001"/>
  <chapter num="19">
    <heading>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> Is Holy</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03019002.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>Speak to all the congregation of the people of Israel and say to them, <crossref let="t" cid="c03019002.1"/>You shall be holy, for I the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God am holy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019003"/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="u" cid="c03019003.1"/>Every one of you shall revere his mother and his father, and <crossref let="v" cid="c03019003.2"/>you shall keep my Sabbaths: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019004"/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="w" cid="c03019004.1"/>Do not turn to idols <crossref let="x" cid="c03019004.2"/>or make for yourselves any gods of cast metal: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019005"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="y" cid="c03019005.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019005.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>When you offer a sacrifice of peace offerings to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, you shall offer it so <crossref let="z" cid="c03019005.2"/>that you may be accepted.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019006"/>
    <verse num="6">It shall be eaten the same day you offer it or on the day after, and anything left over until the third day shall be burned up with fire.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019007"/>
    <verse num="7">If it is eaten at all on the third day, it is <crossref let="a" cid="c03019007.1"/>tainted; it will not be accepted,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019008"/>
    <verse num="8">and everyone who eats it shall <crossref let="b" cid="c03019008.1"/>bear his iniquity, because <crossref let="c" cid="c03019008.2"/>he has profaned what is holy to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, and that person shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019009"/>
    <heading>Love Your Neighbor as Yourself</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="d" cid="c03019009.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019009.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>When you reap the harvest of your land, you shall not reap your field right up to its edge, neither shall you gather the gleanings after your harvest.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019010"/>
    <verse num="10">And you shall not strip your vineyard bare, neither shall you gather the fallen grapes of your vineyard. You shall leave them for the poor and for the sojourner: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019011"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="e" cid="c03019011.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019011.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>You shall not steal; <crossref let="f" cid="c03019011.2"/>you shall not deal falsely; you shall not lie to one another.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="g" cid="c03019012.1"/>You shall not swear by my name falsely, and so <crossref let="h" cid="c03019012.2"/>profane the name of your God: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="i" cid="c03019013.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019013.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>You shall not oppress your neighbor or rob him. <crossref let="j" cid="c03019013.2"/>The wages of a hired worker shall not remain with you all night until the morning.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019014"/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="k" cid="c03019014.1"/>You shall not curse the deaf or put a stumbling block before the blind, but you shall <crossref let="l" cid="c03019014.2"/>fear your God: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019015"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="m" cid="c03019015.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019015.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>You shall do no injustice in court. You shall not be partial to the poor or defer to the great, but in righteousness shall you judge your neighbor.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019016"/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="n" cid="c03019016.1"/>You shall not go around as a slanderer among your people, and you shall not <crossref let="o" cid="c03019016.2"/>stand up against the life<note nid="n03019016.1"/> of your neighbor: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019017"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="p" cid="c03019017.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019017.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>You shall not hate your brother in your heart, but <crossref let="q" cid="c03019017.2"/>you shall reason frankly with your neighbor, lest you <crossref let="r" cid="c03019017.3"/>incur sin because of him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019018"/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="s" cid="c03019018.1"/>You shall not take vengeance or bear a grudge against the sons of your own people, but <crossref let="t" cid="c03019018.2"/>you shall love your neighbor as yourself: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019019"/>
    <heading>You Shall Keep My Statutes</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="u" cid="c03019019.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019019.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>You shall keep my statutes. You shall not let your cattle breed with a different kind. <crossref let="v" cid="c03019019.2"/>You shall not sow your field with two kinds of seed, nor shall you wear a garment of cloth made of two kinds of material.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019020"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="20"><q class="continue-double" qid="03019020.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>If a man lies sexually with a woman who is a slave, assigned to another man and not yet ransomed or given her freedom, a distinction shall be made. They shall not be put to death, because she was not free;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019021"/>
    <verse num="21">but <crossref let="w" cid="c03019021.1"/>he shall bring his compensation to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, to the entrance of the tent of meeting, a ram for a guilt offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019022"/>
    <verse num="22">And the priest shall make atonement for him with the ram of the guilt offering before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for his sin that he has committed, and he shall be forgiven for the sin that he has committed.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019023"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="23"><q class="continue-double" qid="03019023.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>When you come into the land and plant any kind of tree for food, then you shall regard its fruit as forbidden.<note nid="n03019023.1"/> Three years it shall be forbidden to you; it must not be eaten.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019024"/>
    <verse num="24">And in the fourth year all its fruit shall be holy, an offering of praise to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019025"/>
    <verse num="25">But in the fifth year you may eat of its fruit, to increase its yield for you: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019026"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="26"><crossref let="x" cid="c03019026.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019026.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>You shall not eat any flesh with the blood in it. <crossref let="y" cid="c03019026.2"/>You shall not interpret omens or <crossref let="z" cid="c03019026.3"/>tell fortunes.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019027"/>
    <verse num="27"><crossref let="a" cid="c03019027.1"/>You shall not round off the hair on your temples or mar the edges of your beard.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019028"/>
    <verse num="28">You shall not make any <crossref let="b" cid="c03019028.1"/>cuts on your body for the dead or tattoo yourselves: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019029"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="c" cid="c03019029.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019029.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>Do not profane your daughter by making her a prostitute, lest the land fall into prostitution and the land become full of depravity.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019030"/>
    <verse num="30"><crossref let="d" cid="c03019030.1"/>You shall keep my Sabbaths and <crossref let="e" cid="c03019030.2"/>reverence my sanctuary: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019031"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="31"><crossref let="f" cid="c03019031.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019031.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>Do not turn to mediums or necromancers; do not seek them out, and so make yourselves unclean by them: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019032"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="32"><crossref let="g" cid="c03019032.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019032.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>You shall stand up before the gray head and honor the face of an old man, and you shall <crossref let="h" cid="c03019032.2"/>fear your God: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019033"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="33"><crossref let="i" cid="c03019033.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019033.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>When a stranger sojourns with you in your land, you shall not do him wrong.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019034"/>
    <verse num="34"><crossref let="j" cid="c03019034.1"/>You shall treat the stranger who sojourns with you as the native among you, and <crossref let="k" cid="c03019034.2"/>you shall love him as yourself, for you were strangers in the land of Egypt: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019035"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="35"><crossref let="l" cid="c03019035.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03019035.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/>You shall do no wrong in judgment, in measures of length or weight or quantity.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019036"/>
    <verse num="36"><crossref let="m" cid="c03019036.1"/>You shall have just balances, just weights, a just ephah, and a just hin:<note nid="n03019036.1"/> I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03019037"/>
    <verse num="37">And <crossref let="n" cid="c03019037.1"/>you shall observe all my statutes and all my rules, and do them: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="03019037.1" from="03019002.1" to="03019037.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020001"/>
  <chapter num="20">
    <heading>Punishment for Child Sacrifice</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03020002.1" from="03020002.1" to="03020027.2"/>Say to the people of Israel, <crossref let="o" cid="c03020002.1"/>Any one of the people of Israel or of the strangers who sojourn in Israel who gives any of his children to Molech shall surely be put to death. The people of the land shall stone him with stones.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020003"/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="p" cid="c03020003.1"/>I myself will set my face against that man and will cut him off from among his people, because he has given one of his children to Molech, to make my sanctuary <crossref let="q" cid="c03020003.2"/>unclean and <crossref let="r" cid="c03020003.3"/>to profane my holy name.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020004"/>
    <verse num="4">And if the people of the land do at all close their eyes to that man when he gives one of his children to Molech, and do not <crossref let="s" cid="c03020004.1"/>put him to death,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020005"/>
    <verse num="5">then I will set my face against that man and against his clan and will cut them off from among their people, him and all who follow him in <crossref let="t" cid="c03020005.1"/>whoring after Molech.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020006"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="6"><q class="continue-double" qid="03020006.1" from="03020002.1" to="03020027.2"/>If <crossref let="u" cid="c03020006.1"/>a person turns to mediums and necromancers, whoring after them, <crossref let="v" cid="c03020006.2"/>I will set my face against that person and will cut him off from among his people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="w" cid="c03020007.1"/>Consecrate yourselves, therefore, and be holy, for I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="x" cid="c03020008.1"/>Keep my statutes and do them; <crossref let="y" cid="c03020008.2"/>I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> who sanctifies you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020009"/>
    <verse num="9">For <crossref let="z" cid="c03020009.1"/>anyone who curses his father or his mother shall surely be put to death; he has cursed his father or his mother; <crossref let="a" cid="c03020009.2"/>his blood is upon him.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020010"/>
    <heading>Punishments for Sexual Immorality</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10"><q class="continue-double" qid="03020010.1" from="03020002.1" to="03020027.2"/>If a <crossref let="b" cid="c03020010.1"/>man commits adultery with the wife of<note nid="n03020010.1"/> his neighbor, both the adulterer and the adulteress shall surely be put to death.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="c" cid="c03020011.1"/>If a man lies with his father&apos;s wife, he has uncovered his father&apos;s nakedness; both of them shall surely be put to death; their blood is upon them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="d" cid="c03020012.1"/>If a man lies with his daughter-in-law, both of them shall surely be put to death; they have committed <crossref let="e" cid="c03020012.2"/>perversion; their blood is upon them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="f" cid="c03020013.1"/>If a man lies with a male as with a woman, both of them have committed an abomination; they shall surely be put to death; their blood is upon them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020014"/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="g" cid="c03020014.1"/>If a man takes a woman and her mother also, it is depravity; he and they shall be burned with fire, that there may be no depravity among you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="h" cid="c03020015.1"/>If a man lies with an animal, he shall surely be put to death, and you shall kill the animal.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020016"/>
    <verse num="16"><crossref let="h" cid="c03020016.1"/>If a woman approaches any animal and lies with it, you shall kill the woman and the animal; they shall surely be put to death; their blood is upon them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020017"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="i" cid="c03020017.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03020017.1" from="03020002.1" to="03020027.2"/>If a man takes his sister, a daughter of his father or a daughter of his mother, and sees her nakedness, and she sees his nakedness, it is a disgrace, and they shall be cut off in the sight of the children of their people. He has uncovered his sister&apos;s nakedness, and he shall bear his iniquity.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020018"/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="j" cid="c03020018.1"/>If a man lies with a woman during her menstrual period and uncovers her nakedness, he has made naked her fountain, and she has uncovered the fountain of her blood. Both of them shall be cut off from among their people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020019"/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="k" cid="c03020019.1"/>You shall not uncover the nakedness of your mother&apos;s sister or of your father&apos;s sister, for that is to make naked <crossref let="l" cid="c03020019.2"/>one&apos;s relative; they shall bear their iniquity.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="m" cid="c03020020.1"/>If a man lies with his uncle&apos;s wife, he has uncovered his uncle&apos;s nakedness; they shall bear their sin; they shall die childless.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020021"/>
    <verse num="21"><crossref let="n" cid="c03020021.1"/>If a man takes his brother&apos;s wife, it is impurity.<note nid="n03020021.1"/> He has uncovered his brother&apos;s nakedness; they shall be childless.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020022"/>
    <heading>You Shall Be Holy</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22"><crossref let="o" cid="c03020022.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03020022.1" from="03020002.1" to="03020027.2"/>You shall therefore keep all my statutes and all my rules and do them, that the land where I am bringing you to live may not <crossref let="p" cid="c03020022.2"/>vomit you out.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020023"/>
    <verse num="23"><crossref let="q" cid="c03020023.1"/>And you shall not walk in the customs of the nation that I am driving out before you, for they did all these things, and therefore I detested them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020024"/>
    <verse num="24">But <crossref let="r" cid="c03020024.1"/>I have said to you, <q class="begin-single" qid="03020024.1" from="03020024.1" to="03020024.2"/>You shall inherit their land, and I will give it to you to possess, a land <crossref let="s" cid="c03020024.2"/>flowing with milk and honey.<q class="end-single" qid="03020024.2" from="03020024.1" to="03020024.2"/> I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God, <crossref let="t" cid="c03020024.3"/>who has separated you from the peoples.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020025"/>
    <verse num="25"><crossref let="u" cid="c03020025.1"/>You shall therefore separate the clean beast from the unclean, and the unclean bird from the clean. You shall not make yourselves detestable by beast or by bird or by anything with which the ground crawls, which I have set apart for you to hold unclean.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020026"/>
    <verse num="26"><crossref let="v" cid="c03020026.1"/>You shall be holy to me, <crossref let="w" cid="c03020026.2"/>for I the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> am holy and have separated you from the peoples, that you should be mine.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03020027"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="27"><crossref let="x" cid="c03020027.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03020027.1" from="03020002.1" to="03020027.2"/>A man or a woman who is a medium or a necromancer shall surely be put to death. They shall be <crossref let="y" cid="c03020027.2"/>stoned with stones; <crossref let="z" cid="c03020027.3"/>their blood shall be upon them.<q class="end-double" qid="03020027.2" from="03020002.1" to="03020027.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021001"/>
  <chapter num="21">
    <heading>Holiness and the Priests</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> said to Moses, <q class="begin-double" qid="03021001.1" from="03021001.1" to="03021015.1"/>Speak to the priests, the sons of Aaron, and say to them, <crossref let="a" cid="c03021001.1"/>No one shall make himself unclean for the dead among his people,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021002"/>
    <verse num="2">except for his closest relatives, his mother, his father, his son, his daughter, his brother,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021003"/>
    <verse num="3">or his virgin sister (who is near to him because she has had no husband; for her he may make himself unclean).</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021004"/>
    <verse num="4">He shall not make himself unclean as a husband among his people and so profane himself.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021005"/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="b" cid="c03021005.1"/>They shall not make bald patches on their heads, nor shave off the edges of their beards, nor make any cuts on their body.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021006"/>
    <verse num="6">They shall be holy to their God and <crossref let="c" cid="c03021006.1"/>not profane the name of their God. For they offer the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s food offerings, <crossref let="d" cid="c03021006.2"/>the bread of their God; therefore they shall be holy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="e" cid="c03021007.1"/>They shall not marry a prostitute or a woman who has been defiled, neither shall they marry a woman <crossref let="f" cid="c03021007.2"/>divorced from her husband, for the priest is holy to his God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021008"/>
    <verse num="8">You shall sanctify him, for he offers the bread of your God. He shall be holy to you, for <crossref let="g" cid="c03021008.1"/>I, the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, who sanctify you, <crossref let="h" cid="c03021008.2"/>am holy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021009"/>
    <verse num="9">And the daughter of any priest, if she profanes herself by whoring, profanes her father; <crossref let="i" cid="c03021009.1"/>she shall be burned with fire.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="j" cid="c03021010.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03021010.1" from="03021001.1" to="03021015.1"/>The priest who is chief among his brothers, on whose head the anointing oil is poured and who has been consecrated to wear the garments, <crossref let="k" cid="c03021010.2"/>shall not let the hair of his head hang loose nor tear his clothes.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021011"/>
    <verse num="11">He shall not <crossref let="l" cid="c03021011.1"/>go in to any dead bodies nor make himself unclean, even for his father or for his mother.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="m" cid="c03021012.1"/>He shall not go out of the sanctuary, lest he <crossref let="n" cid="c03021012.2"/>profane the sanctuary of his God, for the <crossref let="o" cid="c03021012.3"/>consecration of the anointing oil of his God is on him: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021013"/>
    <verse num="13">And he shall take a wife in her virginity.<note nid="n03021013.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021014"/>
    <verse num="14">A widow, <crossref let="p" cid="c03021014.1"/>or a divorced woman, or a woman who has been defiled, or a prostitute, these he shall not marry. But he shall take as his wife a virgin<note nid="n03021014.1"/> of his own people,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021015"/>
    <verse num="15">that he may not profane his offspring among his people, for <crossref let="g" cid="c03021015.1"/>I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> who sanctifies him.<q class="end-double" qid="03021015.1" from="03021001.1" to="03021015.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021017"/>
    <verse num="17"><q class="begin-double" qid="03021017.1" from="03021017.1" to="03021023.1"/>Speak to Aaron, saying, None of your offspring throughout their generations who has a blemish may <crossref let="q" cid="c03021017.1"/>approach to offer the bread of his God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021018"/>
    <verse num="18">For no one who has a blemish shall draw near, a man <crossref let="r" cid="c03021018.1"/>blind or lame, or one who has a mutilated face <crossref let="s" cid="c03021018.2"/>or a limb too long,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021019"/>
    <verse num="19">or a man who has an injured foot or an injured hand,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021020"/>
    <verse num="20">or a hunchback or a dwarf or a man with a <crossref let="r" cid="c03021020.1"/>defect in his sight or an itching disease or scabs or <crossref let="t" cid="c03021020.2"/>crushed testicles.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021021"/>
    <verse num="21">No man of the offspring of Aaron the priest who has a blemish shall come near to <crossref let="u" cid="c03021021.1"/>offer the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s food offerings; since he has a blemish, he shall not come near to offer the bread of his God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021022"/>
    <verse num="22">He may eat the bread of his God, both of <crossref let="v" cid="c03021022.1"/>the most holy and of the <crossref let="w" cid="c03021022.2"/>holy things,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021023"/>
    <verse num="23">but he shall not go through the veil or approach the altar, because he has a blemish, that he may not <crossref let="x" cid="c03021023.1"/>profane my sanctuaries,<note nid="n03021023.1"/> <crossref let="y" cid="c03021023.2"/>for I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> who sanctifies them.<q class="end-double" qid="03021023.1" from="03021017.1" to="03021023.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03021024"/>
    <verse num="24">So Moses spoke to Aaron and to his sons and to all the people of Israel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022001"/>
  <chapter num="22">
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03022002.1" from="03022002.1" to="03022016.1"/>Speak to Aaron and his sons so that they <crossref let="z" cid="c03022002.1"/>abstain from the holy things of the people of Israel, which they <crossref let="a" cid="c03022002.2"/>dedicate to me, so that they do not <crossref let="b" cid="c03022002.3"/>profane my holy name: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022003"/>
    <verse num="3">Say to them, <q class="begin-single" qid="03022003.1" from="03022003.1" to="03022008.1"/>If any one of all your offspring throughout your generations approaches the holy things that the people of Israel dedicate to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, while <crossref let="c" cid="c03022003.1"/>he has an uncleanness, that person shall be cut off from my presence: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022004"/>
    <verse num="4">None of the offspring of Aaron who has a leprous disease or a <crossref let="d" cid="c03022004.1"/>discharge may eat of the holy things <crossref let="e" cid="c03022004.2"/>until he is clean. <crossref let="f" cid="c03022004.3"/>Whoever touches anything that is unclean through contact with the dead or <crossref let="g" cid="c03022004.4"/>a man who has had an emission of semen,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022005"/>
    <verse num="5">and <crossref let="h" cid="c03022005.1"/>whoever touches a swarming thing by which he may be made unclean or <crossref let="i" cid="c03022005.2"/>a person from whom he may take uncleanness, whatever his uncleanness may be&emdash;</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022006"/>
    <verse num="6">the person who touches such a thing shall be unclean until the evening and shall not eat of the holy things unless he has <crossref let="j" cid="c03022006.1"/>bathed his body in water.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022007"/>
    <verse num="7">When the sun goes down he shall be clean, and afterward he may eat of the holy things, because <crossref let="k" cid="c03022007.1"/>they are his food.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="l" cid="c03022008.1"/>He shall not eat what dies of itself or is torn by beasts, and so make himself unclean by it: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-single" qid="03022008.1" from="03022003.1" to="03022008.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022009"/>
    <verse num="9">They shall therefore keep my charge, <crossref let="m" cid="c03022009.1"/>lest they bear sin for it and die thereby when they profane it: <crossref let="n" cid="c03022009.2"/>I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> who sanctifies them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022010"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="o" cid="c03022010.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03022010.1" from="03022002.1" to="03022016.1"/>A lay person shall not eat of a holy thing; no foreign guest of the priest or hired worker shall eat of a holy thing,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022011"/>
    <verse num="11">but if a priest buys a slave<note nid="n03022011.1"/> as his property for money, the slave<note nid="n03022011.2"/> may eat of it, and <crossref let="p" cid="c03022011.1"/>anyone born in his house may eat of his food.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022012"/>
    <verse num="12">If a priest&apos;s daughter marries a layman, she shall not eat of the contribution of the holy things.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022013"/>
    <verse num="13">But if a priest&apos;s daughter is widowed or divorced and has no child and <crossref let="q" cid="c03022013.1"/>returns to her father&apos;s house, <crossref let="r" cid="c03022013.2"/>as in her youth, she may eat of her father&apos;s food; yet no lay person shall eat of it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022014"/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="s" cid="c03022014.1"/>And if anyone eats of a holy thing unintentionally, he shall add <crossref let="t" cid="c03022014.2"/>the fifth of its value to it and give the holy thing to the priest.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022015"/>
    <verse num="15">They <crossref let="u" cid="c03022015.1"/>shall not profane the holy things of the people of Israel, which they contribute to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022016"/>
    <verse num="16">and so cause them <crossref let="m" cid="c03022016.1"/>to bear iniquity and guilt, by eating their holy things: <crossref let="n" cid="c03022016.2"/>for I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> who sanctifies them.<q class="end-double" qid="03022016.1" from="03022002.1" to="03022016.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022017"/>
    <heading>Acceptable Offerings</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022018"/>
    <verse num="18"><q class="begin-double" qid="03022018.1" from="03022018.1" to="03022025.1"/>Speak to Aaron and his sons and all the people of Israel and say to them, <crossref let="v" cid="c03022018.1"/>When any one of the house of Israel or of the sojourners in Israel presents a burnt offering as his offering, for any of their vows or freewill offerings that they offer to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022019"/>
    <verse num="19">if it is to be accepted for you it shall be a <crossref let="w" cid="c03022019.1"/>male without blemish, of the bulls or the sheep or the goats.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022020"/>
    <verse num="20"><crossref let="x" cid="c03022020.1"/>You shall not offer anything that has a blemish, for it will not be acceptable for you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022021"/>
    <verse num="21">And when anyone <crossref let="y" cid="c03022021.1"/>offers a sacrifice of peace offerings to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> <crossref let="z" cid="c03022021.2"/>to fulfill a vow or as a freewill offering from the herd or from the flock, to be accepted it must be perfect; there shall be no blemish in it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022022"/>
    <verse num="22">Animals <crossref let="a" cid="c03022022.1"/>blind or disabled or mutilated or having a discharge or <crossref let="b" cid="c03022022.2"/>an itch or scabs you shall not offer to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> or give them to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> as a food <crossref let="c" cid="c03022022.3"/>offering on the altar.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022023"/>
    <verse num="23">You may present a bull or a lamb that has a part <crossref let="d" cid="c03022023.1"/>too long or too short for a freewill offering, but for a vow offering it cannot be accepted.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022024"/>
    <verse num="24">Any animal that has its testicles bruised or crushed or torn or cut you shall not offer to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>; you shall not do it within your land,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022025"/>
    <verse num="25">neither shall you offer as <crossref let="e" cid="c03022025.1"/>the bread of your God any such animals gotten from a foreigner. Since there is a <crossref let="f" cid="c03022025.2"/>blemish in them, because of their mutilation, they will not be accepted for you.<q class="end-double" qid="03022025.1" from="03022018.1" to="03022025.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022026"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="26">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022027"/>
    <verse num="27"><crossref let="g" cid="c03022027.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="03022027.1" from="03022027.1" to="03022033.1"/>When an ox or sheep or goat is born, it shall remain seven days with its mother, and from the eighth day on it shall be acceptable as a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022028"/>
    <verse num="28">But you shall not kill an ox or a sheep <crossref let="h" cid="c03022028.1"/>and her young in one day.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022029"/>
    <verse num="29">And when you sacrifice a <crossref let="i" cid="c03022029.1"/>sacrifice of thanksgiving to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, you shall sacrifice it so that you may be accepted.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022030"/>
    <verse num="30">It shall be eaten on the same day; <crossref let="j" cid="c03022030.1"/>you shall leave none of it until morning: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022031"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="31"><crossref let="k" cid="c03022031.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03022031.1" from="03022027.1" to="03022033.1"/>So you shall keep my commandments and do them: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022032"/>
    <verse num="32"><crossref let="l" cid="c03022032.1"/>And you shall not profane my holy name, that <crossref let="m" cid="c03022032.2"/>I may be sanctified among the people of Israel. <crossref let="n" cid="c03022032.3"/>I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> who sanctifies you,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03022033"/>
    <verse num="33">who brought you out of the land of Egypt <crossref let="o" cid="c03022033.1"/>to be your God: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="03022033.1" from="03022027.1" to="03022033.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023001"/>
  <chapter num="23">
    <heading>Feasts of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span></heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03023002.1" from="03023002.1" to="03023008.1"/>Speak to the people of Israel and say to them, <crossref let="p" cid="c03023002.1"/>These are the appointed feasts of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> that you shall <crossref let="q" cid="c03023002.2"/>proclaim as <crossref let="r" cid="c03023002.3"/>holy convocations; they are my appointed feasts.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023003"/>
    <heading>The Sabbath</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="s" cid="c03023003.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03023003.1" from="03023002.1" to="03023008.1"/>Six days shall work be done, but on the seventh day is a Sabbath of solemn rest, a holy convocation. You shall do no work. It is a Sabbath to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> in all your dwelling places.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023004"/>
    <heading>The Passover</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="4"><crossref let="p" cid="c03023004.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03023004.1" from="03023002.1" to="03023008.1"/>These are the appointed feasts of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the <crossref let="t" cid="c03023004.2"/>holy convocations, which you shall proclaim at the time appointed for them.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023005"/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="u" cid="c03023005.1"/>In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month at twilight,<note nid="n03023005.1"/> is the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s Passover.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023006"/>
    <verse num="6">And on the fifteenth day of the same month is the Feast of Unleavened Bread to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>; for seven days you shall eat unleavened bread.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023007"/>
    <verse num="7"><crossref let="v" cid="c03023007.1"/>On the first day you shall have a holy convocation; you shall not do any ordinary work.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023008"/>
    <verse num="8">But you shall present a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for seven days. On the seventh day is a holy convocation; you shall not do any ordinary work.<q class="end-double" qid="03023008.1" from="03023002.1" to="03023008.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023009"/>
    <heading>The Feast of Firstfruits</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023010"/>
    <verse num="10"><q class="begin-double" qid="03023010.1" from="03023010.1" to="03023022.2"/>Speak to the people of Israel and say to them, <crossref let="w" cid="c03023010.1"/>When you come into the land that I give you and reap its harvest, you shall bring the sheaf of <crossref let="x" cid="c03023010.2"/>the firstfruits of your harvest to the priest,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023011"/>
    <verse num="11">and he shall <crossref let="y" cid="c03023011.1"/>wave the sheaf before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, so that you may be accepted. On the day after the Sabbath the priest shall wave it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023012"/>
    <verse num="12">And on the day when you <crossref let="y" cid="c03023012.1"/>wave the sheaf, you shall offer a <crossref let="z" cid="c03023012.2"/>male lamb a year old without blemish as a burnt offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="a" cid="c03023013.1"/>And the grain offering with it shall be two tenths of an ephah<note nid="n03023013.1"/> of fine flour mixed with oil, a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> with a pleasing aroma, <crossref let="b" cid="c03023013.2"/>and the drink offering with it shall be of wine, a fourth of a hin.<note nid="n03023013.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023014"/>
    <verse num="14">And you shall eat neither bread nor grain <crossref let="c" cid="c03023014.1"/>parched or <crossref let="c" cid="c03023014.2"/>fresh until this same day, until you have brought the offering of your God: it is a statute forever throughout your generations in all your dwellings.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023015"/>
    <heading>The Feast of Weeks</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="d" cid="c03023015.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03023015.1" from="03023010.1" to="03023022.2"/>You shall count seven full weeks from the day after the Sabbath, from the day that you brought the sheaf of the <crossref let="y" cid="c03023015.2"/>wave offering.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023016"/>
    <verse num="16">You shall count <crossref let="e" cid="c03023016.1"/>fifty days to the day after the seventh Sabbath. Then you shall present a grain offering of <crossref let="f" cid="c03023016.2"/>new grain to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023017"/>
    <verse num="17">You shall bring from your dwelling places two loaves of bread to be waved, made of two tenths of an ephah. They shall be of fine flour, and they shall be baked with leaven, as <crossref let="g" cid="c03023017.1"/>firstfruits to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023018"/>
    <verse num="18">And you shall present with the bread seven lambs a year old without blemish, and one bull from the herd and two rams. They shall be a burnt offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, with their grain offering and their drink offerings, a food offering with a pleasing aroma to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023019"/>
    <verse num="19">And you shall offer one <crossref let="h" cid="c03023019.1"/>male goat for a sin offering, and two male lambs a year old as a sacrifice of <crossref let="i" cid="c03023019.2"/>peace offerings.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023020"/>
    <verse num="20">And the priest shall <crossref let="y" cid="c03023020.1"/>wave them with the bread of the firstfruits as a wave offering before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, with the two lambs. <crossref let="j" cid="c03023020.2"/>They shall be holy to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for the priest.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023021"/>
    <verse num="21">And you shall make a proclamation on the same day. You shall hold a holy convocation. You shall not do any ordinary work. It is a statute forever in all your dwelling places throughout your generations.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023022"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="22"><q class="continue-double" qid="03023022.1" from="03023010.1" to="03023022.2"/>And <crossref let="k" cid="c03023022.1"/>when you reap the harvest of your land, you shall not reap your field right up to its edge, nor shall you gather the gleanings after your harvest. You shall leave them for the poor and for the sojourner: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.<q class="end-double" qid="03023022.2" from="03023010.1" to="03023022.2"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023023"/>
    <heading>The Feast of Trumpets</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="23">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023024"/>
    <verse num="24"><q class="begin-double" qid="03023024.1" from="03023024.1" to="03023025.1"/>Speak to the people of Israel, saying, In <crossref let="l" cid="c03023024.1"/>the seventh month, on the first day of the month, you shall observe a day of solemn rest, <crossref let="m" cid="c03023024.2"/>a memorial proclaimed with blast of trumpets, a holy convocation.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023025"/>
    <verse num="25">You shall not do any ordinary work, and you shall present a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="03023025.1" from="03023024.1" to="03023025.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023026"/>
    <heading>The Day of Atonement</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="26">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023027"/>
    <verse num="27"><q class="begin-double" qid="03023027.1" from="03023027.1" to="03023032.1"/>Now <crossref let="n" cid="c03023027.1"/>on the tenth day of this seventh month is the Day of Atonement. It shall be for you a time of holy convocation, and you shall afflict yourselves<note nid="n03023027.1"/> and present a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023028"/>
    <verse num="28">And you shall not do any work on that very day, for it is a Day of Atonement, to make atonement for you before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023029"/>
    <verse num="29">For whoever is not afflicted<note nid="n03023029.1"/> on that very day <crossref let="o" cid="c03023029.1"/>shall be cut off from his people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023030"/>
    <verse num="30">And whoever does any work on that very day, that person I will destroy from among his people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023031"/>
    <verse num="31">You shall not do any work. It is a statute forever throughout your generations in all your dwelling places.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023032"/>
    <verse num="32">It shall be to you a Sabbath of solemn rest, and you shall afflict yourselves. On the ninth day of the month beginning at evening, from evening to evening shall you keep your Sabbath.<q class="end-double" qid="03023032.1" from="03023027.1" to="03023032.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023033"/>
    <heading>The Feast of Booths</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="33">And the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023034"/>
    <verse num="34"><q class="begin-double" qid="03023034.1" from="03023034.1" to="03023043.1"/>Speak to the people of Israel, saying, <crossref let="p" cid="c03023034.1"/>On the fifteenth day of this seventh month and for seven days is the Feast of Booths<note nid="n03023034.1"/> to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023035"/>
    <verse num="35">On the first day shall be a holy convocation; you shall not do any ordinary work.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023036"/>
    <verse num="36">For seven days you shall present food offerings to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. <crossref let="q" cid="c03023036.1"/>On the eighth day you shall hold a holy convocation and present a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. It is a <crossref let="r" cid="c03023036.2"/>solemn assembly; you shall not do any ordinary work.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023037"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="37"><crossref let="s" cid="c03023037.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03023037.1" from="03023034.1" to="03023043.1"/>These are the appointed feasts of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, which you shall proclaim as times of holy convocation, for presenting to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> food offerings, burnt offerings and grain offerings, sacrifices and drink offerings, each on its proper day,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023038"/>
    <verse num="38"><crossref let="t" cid="c03023038.1"/>besides the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s Sabbaths and besides your gifts and besides all your vow offerings and besides all your freewill offerings, which you give to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023039"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="39"><q class="continue-double" qid="03023039.1" from="03023034.1" to="03023043.1"/>On the fifteenth day of the seventh month, when you have <crossref let="u" cid="c03023039.1"/>gathered in the produce of the land, you shall celebrate the feast of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> seven days. On the first day shall be a solemn rest, and on the eighth day shall be a solemn rest.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023040"/>
    <verse num="40">And <crossref let="v" cid="c03023040.1"/>you shall take on the first day the fruit of splendid trees, branches of palm trees and boughs of leafy trees and willows of the brook, and <crossref let="w" cid="c03023040.2"/>you shall rejoice before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God seven days.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023041"/>
    <verse num="41"><crossref let="x" cid="c03023041.1"/>You shall celebrate it as a feast to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> for seven days in the year. It is a statute forever throughout your generations; you shall celebrate it in the seventh month.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023042"/>
    <verse num="42"><crossref let="y" cid="c03023042.1"/>You shall dwell in booths for seven days. All native Israelites shall dwell in booths,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023043"/>
    <verse num="43">that <crossref let="z" cid="c03023043.1"/>your generations may know that I made the people of Israel dwell in booths when I brought them out of the land of Egypt: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.<q class="end-double" qid="03023043.1" from="03023034.1" to="03023043.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03023044"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="44">Thus Moses <crossref let="a" cid="c03023044.1"/>declared to the people of Israel the appointed feasts of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024001"/>
  <chapter num="24">
    <heading>The Lamps</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="b" cid="c03024001.1"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03024002.1" from="03024002.1" to="03024009.1"/>Command the people of Israel to bring you pure oil from beaten olives for the lamp, that a light may be kept burning regularly.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024003"/>
    <verse num="3">Outside the veil of the testimony, in the tent of meeting, Aaron shall arrange it from evening to morning before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> regularly. It shall be a statute forever throughout your generations.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024004"/>
    <verse num="4">He shall arrange the lamps on the <crossref let="c" cid="c03024004.1"/>lampstand of pure gold<note nid="n03024004.1"/> before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> regularly.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024005"/>
    <heading>Bread for the Tabernacle</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="5"><q class="continue-double" qid="03024005.1" from="03024002.1" to="03024009.1"/>You shall take fine flour and bake twelve <crossref let="d" cid="c03024005.1"/>loaves from it; two tenths of an ephah<note nid="n03024005.1"/> shall be in each loaf.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024006"/>
    <verse num="6">And you shall set them in two piles, six in a pile, <crossref let="e" cid="c03024006.1"/>on the table of pure gold<note nid="n03024006.1"/> before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024007"/>
    <verse num="7">And you shall put pure frankincense on each pile, that it may go with the bread as a memorial portion as a food offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="f" cid="c03024008.1"/>Every Sabbath day Aaron shall arrange it before the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> regularly; it is from the people of Israel as a covenant forever.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024009"/>
    <verse num="9">And <crossref let="g" cid="c03024009.1"/>it shall be for Aaron and his sons, and <crossref let="h" cid="c03024009.2"/>they shall eat it in a holy place, since it is for him a most holy portion out of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s food offerings, a perpetual due.<q class="end-double" qid="03024009.1" from="03024002.1" to="03024009.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024010"/>
    <heading>Punishment for Blasphemy</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="10">Now an Israelite woman&apos;s son, whose father was an Egyptian, went out among the people of Israel. And the Israelite woman&apos;s son and a man of Israel fought in the camp,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024011"/>
    <verse num="11">and the Israelite woman&apos;s son <crossref let="i" cid="c03024011.1"/>blasphemed the <crossref let="j" cid="c03024011.2"/>Name, and cursed. Then they <crossref let="k" cid="c03024011.3"/>brought him to Moses. His mother&apos;s name was Shelomith, the daughter of Dibri, of the tribe of Dan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024012"/>
    <verse num="12">And <crossref let="l" cid="c03024012.1"/>they put him in custody, <crossref let="m" cid="c03024012.2"/>till the will of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> should be clear to them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13">Then the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024014"/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="n" cid="c03024014.1"/><q class="begin-double" qid="03024014.1" from="03024014.1" to="03024022.1"/>Bring out of the camp the one who cursed, and let all who heard him <crossref let="o" cid="c03024014.2"/>lay their hands on his head, and let all the congregation stone him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024015"/>
    <verse num="15">And speak to the people of Israel, saying, Whoever curses his God shall <crossref let="p" cid="c03024015.1"/>bear his sin.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024016"/>
    <verse num="16">Whoever <crossref let="q" cid="c03024016.1"/>blasphemes the name of the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> shall surely be put to death. All the congregation shall stone him. The sojourner as well as the native, when he blasphemes the Name, shall be put to death.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024017"/>
    <heading>An Eye for an Eye</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="r" cid="c03024017.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03024017.1" from="03024014.1" to="03024022.1"/>Whoever takes a human life shall surely be put to death.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024018"/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="s" cid="c03024018.1"/>Whoever takes an animal&apos;s life shall make it good, life for life.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024019"/>
    <verse num="19">If anyone injures his neighbor, <crossref let="t" cid="c03024019.1"/>as he has done it shall be done to him,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024020"/>
    <verse num="20">fracture for fracture, eye for eye, tooth for tooth; whatever injury he has given a person shall be given to him.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024021"/>
    <verse num="21"><crossref let="s" cid="c03024021.1"/>Whoever kills an animal shall make it good, <crossref let="r" cid="c03024021.2"/>and whoever kills a person shall be put to death.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024022"/>
    <verse num="22">You shall have the <crossref let="u" cid="c03024022.1"/>same rule for the sojourner and for the native, for I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.<q class="end-double" qid="03024022.1" from="03024014.1" to="03024022.1"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03024023"/>
    <verse num="23">So Moses spoke to the people of Israel, and <crossref let="v" cid="c03024023.1"/>they brought out of the camp the one who had cursed and stoned him with stones. Thus the people of Israel did as the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025001"/>
  <chapter num="25">
    <heading>The Sabbath Year</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><crossref let="w" cid="c03025001.1"/>The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses on Mount Sinai, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03025002.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>Speak to the people of Israel and say to them, When you come into <crossref let="x" cid="c03025002.1"/>the land that I give you, the land shall keep a Sabbath to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025003"/>
    <verse num="3">For six years you shall sow your field, and for six years you shall prune your vineyard and gather in its fruits,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025004"/>
    <verse num="4">but in the seventh year there shall be a Sabbath of solemn rest for the land, a Sabbath to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>. You shall not sow your field or prune your vineyard.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025005"/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="y" cid="c03025005.1"/>You shall not reap what grows of itself in your harvest, or gather the grapes of your undressed vine. It shall be a year of solemn rest for the land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025006"/>
    <verse num="6">The Sabbath of the land<note nid="n03025006.1"/> shall provide food for you, for yourself and for your male and female slaves<note nid="n03025006.2"/> and for your hired worker and the sojourner who lives with you,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025007"/>
    <verse num="7">and for your cattle and for the wild animals that are in your land: <crossref let="z" cid="c03025007.1"/>all its yield shall be for food.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025008"/>
    <heading>The Year of Jubilee</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="8"><q class="continue-double" qid="03025008.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>You shall count seven weeks<note nid="n03025008.1"/> of years, seven times seven years, so that the time of the seven weeks of years shall give you forty-nine years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025009"/>
    <verse num="9">Then you shall sound <crossref let="a" cid="c03025009.1"/>the loud trumpet on the tenth day of the seventh month. <crossref let="b" cid="c03025009.2"/>On the Day of Atonement you shall sound the trumpet throughout all your land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025010"/>
    <verse num="10">And you shall consecrate the fiftieth year, and <crossref let="c" cid="c03025010.1"/>proclaim liberty throughout the land to all its inhabitants. It shall be a jubilee for you, when each of you shall return to his property and each of <crossref let="d" cid="c03025010.2"/>you shall return to his clan.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025011"/>
    <verse num="11">That fiftieth year shall be a jubilee for you; in it <crossref let="e" cid="c03025011.1"/>you shall neither sow nor reap <crossref let="y" cid="c03025011.2"/>what grows of itself nor gather the grapes from the undressed vines.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025012"/>
    <verse num="12">For it is a jubilee. It shall be holy to you. <crossref let="f" cid="c03025012.1"/>You may eat the produce of the field.<note nid="n03025012.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025013"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="d" cid="c03025013.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03025013.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>In this year of jubilee each of you shall return to his property.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025014"/>
    <verse num="14">And if you make a sale to your neighbor or buy from your neighbor, <crossref let="g" cid="c03025014.1"/>you shall not wrong one another.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="h" cid="c03025015.1"/>You shall pay your neighbor according to the number of years after the jubilee, and he shall sell to you according to the number of years for crops.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025016"/>
    <verse num="16">If the years are many, you shall increase the price, and if the years are few, you shall reduce the price, for it is the number of the crops that he is selling to you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025017"/>
    <verse num="17"><crossref let="i" cid="c03025017.1"/>You shall not wrong one another, but you shall fear your God, for I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025018"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="18"><crossref let="j" cid="c03025018.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03025018.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>Therefore you shall do my statutes and keep my rules and perform them, and then <crossref let="k" cid="c03025018.2"/>you will dwell in the land securely.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025019"/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="l" cid="c03025019.1"/>The land will yield its fruit, and <crossref let="m" cid="c03025019.2"/>you will eat your fill <crossref let="k" cid="c03025019.3"/>and dwell in it securely.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025020"/>
    <verse num="20">And if you say, <crossref let="n" cid="c03025020.1"/><q class="begin-single" qid="03025020.1" from="03025020.1" to="03025020.2"/>What shall we eat in the seventh year, if <crossref let="o" cid="c03025020.2"/>we may not sow or gather in our crop?<q class="end-single" qid="03025020.2" from="03025020.1" to="03025020.2"/></verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025021"/>
    <verse num="21">I will <crossref let="p" cid="c03025021.1"/>command my blessing on you in the sixth year, so that it will produce a crop sufficient for three years.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025022"/>
    <verse num="22"><crossref let="q" cid="c03025022.1"/>When you sow in the eighth year, you will be eating some of <crossref let="r" cid="c03025022.2"/>the old crop; you shall eat the old until the ninth year, when its crop arrives.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025023"/>
    <heading>Redemption of Property</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="23"><q class="continue-double" qid="03025023.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>The land shall not be sold in perpetuity, for <crossref let="s" cid="c03025023.1"/>the land is mine. For you are strangers and sojourners with me.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025024"/>
    <verse num="24">And in all the country you possess, you shall allow a redemption of the land.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025025"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="25"><q class="continue-double" qid="03025025.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>If your brother becomes poor and sells part of his property, <crossref let="t" cid="c03025025.1"/>then his nearest redeemer shall come and redeem what his brother has sold.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025026"/>
    <verse num="26">If a man has no one to redeem it and then himself becomes prosperous and finds sufficient means to redeem it,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025027"/>
    <verse num="27">let <crossref let="u" cid="c03025027.1"/>him calculate the years since he sold it and pay back the balance to the man to whom he sold it, and then return to his property.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025028"/>
    <verse num="28">But if he does not have sufficient means to recover it, then what he sold shall remain in the hand of the buyer until the year of jubilee. In the jubilee it shall <crossref let="v" cid="c03025028.1"/>be released, and <crossref let="w" cid="c03025028.2"/>he shall return to his property.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025029"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="29"><q class="continue-double" qid="03025029.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>If a man sells a dwelling house in a walled city, he may redeem it within a year of its sale. For a full year he shall have the right of redemption.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025030"/>
    <verse num="30">If it is not redeemed within a full year, then the house in the walled city shall belong in perpetuity to the buyer, throughout his generations; <crossref let="v" cid="c03025030.1"/>it shall not be released in the jubilee.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025031"/>
    <verse num="31">But the houses of the villages that have no wall around them shall be classified with the fields of the land. They may be redeemed, and <crossref let="v" cid="c03025031.1"/>they shall be released in the jubilee.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025032"/>
    <verse num="32">As for <crossref let="x" cid="c03025032.1"/>the cities of the Levites, the Levites may redeem at any time the houses in the cities they possess.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025033"/>
    <verse num="33">And if one of the Levites exercises his right of redemption, then the house that was sold in a city they possess shall be released in the jubilee. For the houses in the cities of the Levites are their possession among the people of Israel.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025034"/>
    <verse num="34">But the fields <crossref let="y" cid="c03025034.1"/>of pastureland belonging to their cities may not be sold, for that is their possession forever.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025035"/>
    <heading>Kindness for Poor Brothers</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="35"><q class="continue-double" qid="03025035.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>If your brother becomes poor and cannot maintain himself with you, <crossref let="z" cid="c03025035.1"/>you shall support him as though he were a stranger and a sojourner, and he shall live with you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025036"/>
    <verse num="36"><crossref let="a" cid="c03025036.1"/>Take no interest from him or profit, but <crossref let="b" cid="c03025036.2"/>fear your God, that your brother may live beside you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025037"/>
    <verse num="37"><crossref let="a" cid="c03025037.1"/>You shall not lend him your money at interest, nor give him your food for profit.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025038"/>
    <verse num="38"><crossref let="c" cid="c03025038.1"/>I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt to give you the land of Canaan, and to be your God.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025039"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="39"><crossref let="d" cid="c03025039.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03025039.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>If your brother becomes poor beside you and sells himself to you, you shall not make him serve as a slave:</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025040"/>
    <verse num="40">he shall be with you as a hired worker and as a sojourner. He shall serve with you until the year of the jubilee.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025041"/>
    <verse num="41"><crossref let="v" cid="c03025041.1"/>Then he shall go out from you, <crossref let="e" cid="c03025041.2"/>he and his children with him, and go back to his own clan and return <crossref let="f" cid="c03025041.3"/>to the possession of his fathers.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025042"/>
    <verse num="42">For they are <crossref let="g" cid="c03025042.1"/>my servants,<note nid="n03025042.1"/> whom I brought out of the land of Egypt; they shall not be sold as slaves.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025043"/>
    <verse num="43"><crossref let="h" cid="c03025043.1"/>You shall not rule over him <crossref let="i" cid="c03025043.2"/>ruthlessly but <crossref let="j" cid="c03025043.3"/>shall fear your God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025044"/>
    <verse num="44">As for your male and female slaves whom you may have: you may buy male and female slaves from among the nations that are around you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025045"/>
    <verse num="45"><crossref let="k" cid="c03025045.1"/>You may also buy from among the strangers who sojourn with you and their clans that are with you, who have been born in your land, and they may be your property.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025046"/>
    <verse num="46">You may bequeath them to your sons after you to inherit as a possession forever. You may make slaves of them, but over your brothers the people of Israel <crossref let="l" cid="c03025046.1"/>you shall not rule, one over another ruthlessly.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025047"/>
    <heading>Redeeming a Poor Man</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="47"><q class="continue-double" qid="03025047.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>If a stranger or sojourner with you becomes rich, and <crossref let="m" cid="c03025047.1"/>your brother beside him becomes poor and sells himself to the stranger or sojourner with you or to a member of the stranger&apos;s clan,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025048"/>
    <verse num="48">then after he is sold he may be redeemed. One of his brothers may redeem him,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025049"/>
    <verse num="49">or his uncle or his cousin may <crossref let="n" cid="c03025049.1"/>redeem him, or a close relative from his clan may redeem him. Or if he <crossref let="o" cid="c03025049.2"/>grows rich he may redeem himself.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025050"/>
    <verse num="50">He shall calculate with his buyer from the year when he sold himself to him until the year of jubilee, and the price of his sale shall vary with the number of years. The time he was with his owner shall be <crossref let="p" cid="c03025050.1"/>rated as the time of a hired worker.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025051"/>
    <verse num="51">If there are still many years left, he shall pay proportionately for his redemption some of his sale price.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025052"/>
    <verse num="52">If there remain but a few years until the year of jubilee, he shall calculate and pay for his redemption in proportion to his years of service.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025053"/>
    <verse num="53">He shall treat him as a worker hired year by year. <crossref let="l" cid="c03025053.1"/>He shall not rule ruthlessly over him in your sight.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025054"/>
    <verse num="54">And if he is not redeemed by these means, then <crossref let="q" cid="c03025054.1"/>he and his children with him shall be released in the year of jubilee.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03025055"/>
    <verse num="55">For it is <crossref let="r" cid="c03025055.1"/>to me that the people of Israel are servants.<note nid="n03025055.1"/> They are my servants whom I brought out of the land of Egypt: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026001"/>
  <chapter num="26">
    <heading>Blessings for Obedience</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1"><q class="continue-double" qid="03026001.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>You shall not make <crossref let="s" cid="c03026001.1"/>idols for yourselves or erect an <crossref let="t" cid="c03026001.2"/>image or <crossref let="u" cid="c03026001.3"/>pillar, and you shall not set up a <crossref let="v" cid="c03026001.4"/>figured stone in your land to bow down to it, for I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026002"/>
    <verse num="2"><crossref let="w" cid="c03026002.1"/>You shall keep my Sabbaths and reverence my sanctuary: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026003"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="3"><crossref let="x" cid="c03026003.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03026003.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>If you walk in my statutes and observe my commandments and do them,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026004"/>
    <verse num="4">then <crossref let="y" cid="c03026004.1"/>I will give you your rains in their season, and the land shall yield its increase, and the trees of the field shall yield their fruit.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026005"/>
    <verse num="5"><crossref let="z" cid="c03026005.1"/>Your threshing shall last to the time of the grape harvest, and the grape harvest shall last to the time for sowing. And <crossref let="a" cid="c03026005.2"/>you shall eat your bread to the full and <crossref let="b" cid="c03026005.3"/>dwell in your land securely.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026006"/>
    <verse num="6"><crossref let="c" cid="c03026006.1"/>I will give peace in the land, and <crossref let="d" cid="c03026006.2"/>you shall lie down, and none shall make you afraid. And <crossref let="e" cid="c03026006.3"/>I will remove harmful beasts from the land, <crossref let="f" cid="c03026006.4"/>and the sword shall not go through your land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026007"/>
    <verse num="7">You shall chase your enemies, and they shall fall before you by the sword.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026008"/>
    <verse num="8"><crossref let="g" cid="c03026008.1"/>Five of you shall chase a hundred, and a hundred of you shall chase ten thousand, and your enemies shall fall before you by the sword.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026009"/>
    <verse num="9"><crossref let="h" cid="c03026009.1"/>I will turn to you and <crossref let="i" cid="c03026009.2"/>make you fruitful and multiply you and will confirm my covenant with you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026010"/>
    <verse num="10">You shall eat <crossref let="j" cid="c03026010.1"/>old store long kept, and you shall clear out the old to make way for the new.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026011"/>
    <verse num="11"><crossref let="k" cid="c03026011.1"/>I will make my dwelling<note nid="n03026011.1"/> among you, and my soul shall not abhor you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026012"/>
    <verse num="12"><crossref let="l" cid="c03026012.1"/>And I <crossref let="m" cid="c03026012.2"/>will walk among you and will be your God, and you shall be my people.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="n" cid="c03026013.1"/>I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt, that you should not be their slaves. <crossref let="o" cid="c03026013.2"/>And I have broken the bars of your yoke and made you walk erect.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026014"/>
    <heading>Punishment for Disobedience</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14"><crossref let="p" cid="c03026014.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03026014.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>But if you will not listen to me and will not do all these commandments,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026015"/>
    <verse num="15">if you spurn my statutes, and if your soul abhors my rules, so that you will not do all my commandments, but <crossref let="q" cid="c03026015.1"/>break my covenant,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026016"/>
    <verse num="16">then I will do this to you: I will visit you with panic, with <crossref let="r" cid="c03026016.1"/>wasting disease and fever that consume the eyes and make the heart ache. And <crossref let="s" cid="c03026016.2"/>you shall sow your seed in vain, for your enemies shall eat it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026017"/>
    <verse num="17">I will <crossref let="t" cid="c03026017.1"/>set my face against you, and <crossref let="u" cid="c03026017.2"/>you shall be struck down before your enemies. <crossref let="v" cid="c03026017.3"/>Those who hate you shall rule over you, and <crossref let="w" cid="c03026017.4"/>you shall flee when none pursues you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026018"/>
    <verse num="18">And if in spite of this you will not listen to me, then I will discipline you again <crossref let="x" cid="c03026018.1"/>sevenfold for your sins,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026019"/>
    <verse num="19">and I will break <crossref let="y" cid="c03026019.1"/>the pride of your power, and I <crossref let="z" cid="c03026019.2"/>will make your heavens like iron and your earth like bronze.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026020"/>
    <verse num="20">And <crossref let="a" cid="c03026020.1"/>your strength shall be spent in vain, for <crossref let="b" cid="c03026020.2"/>your land shall not yield its increase, and the trees of the land shall not yield their fruit.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026021"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="21"><crossref let="c" cid="c03026021.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03026021.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>Then if you walk contrary to me and will not listen to me, I will continue striking you, sevenfold for your sins.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026022"/>
    <verse num="22">And <crossref let="d" cid="c03026022.1"/>I will let loose the wild beasts against you, which shall bereave you of your children and destroy your livestock and make you few in number, so that <crossref let="e" cid="c03026022.2"/>your roads shall be deserted.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026023"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="23"><q class="continue-double" qid="03026023.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>And <crossref let="f" cid="c03026023.1"/>if by this discipline you are not turned to me <crossref let="c" cid="c03026023.2"/>but walk contrary to me,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026024"/>
    <verse num="24"><crossref let="g" cid="c03026024.1"/>then I also will walk contrary to you, and I myself will strike you sevenfold for your sins.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026025"/>
    <verse num="25">And <crossref let="h" cid="c03026025.1"/>I will bring a sword upon you, that shall execute vengeance for the covenant. And if you gather within your cities, <crossref let="i" cid="c03026025.2"/>I will send pestilence among you, and you shall be delivered into the hand of the enemy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026026"/>
    <verse num="26"><crossref let="j" cid="c03026026.1"/>When I break your supply<note nid="n03026026.1"/> of bread, ten women shall bake your bread in a single oven and shall dole out your bread again by weight, and <crossref let="k" cid="c03026026.2"/>you shall eat and not be satisfied.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026027"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="27"><q class="continue-double" qid="03026027.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>But <crossref let="l" cid="c03026027.1"/>if in spite of this you will not listen to me, but walk contrary to me,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026028"/>
    <verse num="28">then I will walk contrary to you <crossref let="m" cid="c03026028.1"/>in fury, and I myself will discipline you <crossref let="x" cid="c03026028.2"/>sevenfold for your sins.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026029"/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="n" cid="c03026029.1"/>You shall eat the flesh of your sons, and you shall eat the flesh of your daughters.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026030"/>
    <verse num="30">And <crossref let="o" cid="c03026030.1"/>I will destroy your high places and cut down your incense altars and <crossref let="p" cid="c03026030.2"/>cast your dead bodies upon the dead bodies of your idols, and my soul will abhor you.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026031"/>
    <verse num="31">And I will <crossref let="q" cid="c03026031.1"/>lay your cities waste and will <crossref let="r" cid="c03026031.2"/>make your sanctuaries desolate, and <crossref let="s" cid="c03026031.3"/>I will not smell your pleasing aromas.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026032"/>
    <verse num="32">And <crossref let="t" cid="c03026032.1"/>I myself will devastate the land, so that your enemies who settle in it shall be <crossref let="u" cid="c03026032.2"/>appalled at it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026033"/>
    <verse num="33">And <crossref let="v" cid="c03026033.1"/>I will scatter you among the nations, and I will unsheathe the sword after you, and your land shall be a desolation, and your cities shall be a waste.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026034"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="34"><crossref let="w" cid="c03026034.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03026034.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>Then the land shall enjoy<note nid="n03026034.1"/> its Sabbaths as long as it lies desolate, while you are in your enemies&apos; land; then the land shall rest, and enjoy its Sabbaths.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026035"/>
    <verse num="35">As long as it lies desolate it shall have rest, the rest that it did not have on your Sabbaths when you were dwelling in it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026036"/>
    <verse num="36">And as for those of you who are left, <crossref let="x" cid="c03026036.1"/>I will send faintness into their hearts in the lands of their enemies. The <crossref let="y" cid="c03026036.2"/>sound of a <crossref let="z" cid="c03026036.3"/>driven leaf shall put them to flight, and they shall flee as one flees from the sword, and they shall fall when none pursues.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026037"/>
    <verse num="37">They shall stumble over one another, as if to escape a sword, though none pursues. And <crossref let="a" cid="c03026037.1"/>you shall have no power to stand before your enemies.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026038"/>
    <verse num="38">And you shall perish among the nations, and the land of your enemies shall eat you up.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026039"/>
    <verse num="39">And those of you who are left shall <crossref let="b" cid="c03026039.1"/>rot away in your enemies&apos; lands because of their iniquity, and also because of the iniquities of their fathers they shall rot away like them.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026040"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="40"><q class="continue-double" qid="03026040.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/>But if <crossref let="c" cid="c03026040.1"/>they confess their iniquity and the iniquity of their fathers in their treachery that they <crossref let="d" cid="c03026040.2"/>committed against me, and also in walking contrary to me,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026041"/>
    <verse num="41">so that I walked contrary to them and brought them into the land of their enemies&emdash;if then their <crossref let="e" cid="c03026041.1"/>uncircumcised heart is <crossref let="f" cid="c03026041.2"/>humbled and they make amends for their iniquity,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026042"/>
    <verse num="42">then I will <crossref let="g" cid="c03026042.1"/>remember my covenant with Jacob, and I will remember my covenant with Isaac and my covenant with Abraham, and I will <crossref let="h" cid="c03026042.2"/>remember the land.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026043"/>
    <verse num="43">But <crossref let="w" cid="c03026043.1"/>the land shall be abandoned by them and enjoy its Sabbaths while it lies desolate without them, and they shall make amends for their iniquity, because they spurned my rules and their soul abhorred my statutes.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026044"/>
    <verse num="44">Yet for all that, when they are in the land of their enemies, <crossref let="i" cid="c03026044.1"/>I will not spurn them, neither will I abhor them so as to destroy them utterly and <crossref let="j" cid="c03026044.2"/>break my covenant with them, for I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> their God.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026045"/>
    <verse num="45">But I will for their sake remember the covenant with their forefathers, <crossref let="k" cid="c03026045.1"/>whom I brought out of the land of Egypt <crossref let="l" cid="c03026045.2"/>in the sight of the nations, that I might be their God: I am the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.<q class="end-double" qid="03026045.1" from="03025002.1" to="03026045.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03026046"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="46"><crossref let="m" cid="c03026046.1"/>These are the statutes and rules and laws that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> made between himself and the people of Israel through Moses <crossref let="n" cid="c03026046.2"/>on Mount Sinai.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
  <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027001"/>
  <chapter num="27">
    <heading>Laws About Vows</heading>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="1">The <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> spoke to Moses, saying,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027002"/>
    <verse num="2"><q class="begin-double" qid="03027002.1" from="03027002.1" to="03027033.1"/>Speak to the people of Israel and say to them, If anyone <crossref let="o" cid="c03027002.1"/>makes a special vow to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> involving the valuation of persons,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027003"/>
    <verse num="3">then the valuation of a male from twenty years old up to sixty years old shall be fifty shekels<note nid="n03027003.1"/> of silver, according to the <crossref let="p" cid="c03027003.1"/>shekel of the sanctuary.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027004"/>
    <verse num="4">If the person is a female, the valuation shall be thirty shekels.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027005"/>
    <verse num="5">If the person is from five years old up to twenty years old, the valuation shall be for a male twenty shekels, and for a female ten shekels.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027006"/>
    <verse num="6">If the person is from a month old up to five years old, the valuation shall be for a male five shekels of silver, and for a female the valuation shall be three shekels of silver.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027007"/>
    <verse num="7">And if the person is sixty years old or over, then the valuation for a male shall be fifteen shekels, and for a female ten shekels.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027008"/>
    <verse num="8">And if someone is too poor to pay the valuation, then he shall be made to stand before the priest, and the priest shall value him; the priest shall value him according to what the vower can afford.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027009"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="9"><q class="continue-double" qid="03027009.1" from="03027002.1" to="03027033.1"/>If the vow<note nid="n03027009.1"/> is an animal that may be offered as an offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, all of it that he gives to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> is holy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027010"/>
    <verse num="10"><crossref let="q" cid="c03027010.1"/>He shall not exchange it or make a substitute for it, good for bad, or bad for good; and if he does in fact substitute one animal for another, then both it and the substitute shall be holy.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027011"/>
    <verse num="11">And if it is any unclean animal that may not be offered as an offering to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, then he shall stand the animal before the priest,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027012"/>
    <verse num="12">and the priest shall value it as either good or bad; as the priest values it, so it shall be.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027013"/>
    <verse num="13"><crossref let="r" cid="c03027013.1"/>But if he wishes to redeem it, he shall add a <crossref let="s" cid="c03027013.2"/>fifth to the valuation.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027014"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="14"><q class="continue-double" qid="03027014.1" from="03027002.1" to="03027033.1"/>When a man dedicates his house as a holy gift to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, the priest shall value it as either good or bad; as the priest values it, so it shall stand.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027015"/>
    <verse num="15"><crossref let="t" cid="c03027015.1"/>And if the donor wishes to redeem his house, he shall add a <crossref let="s" cid="c03027015.2"/>fifth to the valuation price, and it shall be his.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027016"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="16"><q class="continue-double" qid="03027016.1" from="03027002.1" to="03027033.1"/>If a man dedicates to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> part of the land that is his possession, then the valuation shall be in proportion to its seed. A homer<note nid="n03027016.1"/> of barley seed shall be valued at fifty shekels of silver.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027017"/>
    <verse num="17">If he dedicates his field from the year of jubilee, the valuation shall stand,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027018"/>
    <verse num="18">but if he dedicates his field after the jubilee, then the priest shall <crossref let="u" cid="c03027018.1"/>calculate the price according to the years that remain until the year of jubilee, and a deduction shall be made from the valuation.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027019"/>
    <verse num="19"><crossref let="v" cid="c03027019.1"/>And if he who dedicates the field wishes to redeem it, then he shall add a <crossref let="s" cid="c03027019.2"/>fifth to its valuation price, and it shall remain his.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027020"/>
    <verse num="20">But if he does not wish to redeem the field, or if he has sold the field to another man, it shall not be redeemed anymore.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027021"/>
    <verse num="21">But the field, <crossref let="w" cid="c03027021.1"/>when it is released in the jubilee, shall be a holy gift to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, like a field that has been <crossref let="x" cid="c03027021.2"/>devoted. The priest shall be in <crossref let="y" cid="c03027021.3"/>possession of it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027022"/>
    <verse num="22">If he dedicates to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> a field that he has bought, <crossref let="z" cid="c03027022.1"/>which is not a part of his possession,</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027023"/>
    <verse num="23"><crossref let="a" cid="c03027023.1"/>then the priest shall calculate the amount of the valuation for it up to the year of jubilee, and the man shall give the valuation on that day as a holy gift to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027024"/>
    <verse num="24"><crossref let="b" cid="c03027024.1"/>In the year of jubilee the field shall return to him from whom it was bought, to whom the land belongs as a possession.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027025"/>
    <verse num="25">Every valuation shall be according to <crossref let="c" cid="c03027025.1"/>the shekel of the sanctuary: <crossref let="d" cid="c03027025.2"/>twenty gerahs<note nid="n03027025.1"/> shall make a shekel.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027026"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="26"><q class="continue-double" qid="03027026.1" from="03027002.1" to="03027033.1"/>But a <crossref let="e" cid="c03027026.1"/>firstborn of animals, which as a firstborn belongs to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, no man may dedicate; whether ox or sheep, it is the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027027"/>
    <verse num="27">And if it is an unclean animal, then he shall buy it back at the valuation, <crossref let="f" cid="c03027027.1"/>and add a fifth to it; or, if it is not redeemed, it shall be sold at the valuation.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027028"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="28"><q class="continue-double" qid="03027028.1" from="03027002.1" to="03027033.1"/>But <crossref let="g" cid="c03027028.1"/>no devoted thing that a man devotes to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>, of anything that he has, whether man or beast, or of his inherited field, shall be sold or redeemed; every devoted thing is most holy to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027029"/>
    <verse num="29"><crossref let="h" cid="c03027029.1"/>No one devoted, who is to be devoted for destruction<note nid="n03027029.1"/> from mankind, shall be ransomed; he shall surely be put to death.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027030"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="30"><crossref let="i" cid="c03027030.1"/><q class="continue-double" qid="03027030.1" from="03027002.1" to="03027033.1"/>Every tithe of the land, whether of the seed of the land or of the fruit of the trees, is the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>&apos;s; it is holy to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027031"/>
    <verse num="31">If a man wishes to redeem some of his tithe, he shall add a fifth to it.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027032"/>
    <verse num="32">And every tithe of herds and flocks, every tenth animal of all that <crossref let="j" cid="c03027032.1"/>pass under the herdsman&apos;s staff, shall be holy to the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span>.</verse>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027033"/>
    <verse num="33">One shall not differentiate between good or bad, <crossref let="k" cid="c03027033.1"/>neither shall he make a substitute for it; and if he does substitute for it, then both it and the substitute shall be holy; it shall not be redeemed.<q class="end-double" qid="03027033.1" from="03027002.1" to="03027033.1"/></verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
    <marker class="begin-verse" mid="v03027034"/>
    <begin-paragraph/>
    <verse num="34"><crossref let="l" cid="c03027034.1"/>These are the commandments that the <span class="divine-name">Lord</span> commanded Moses for the people of Israel <crossref let="m" cid="c03027034.2"/>on Mount Sinai.</verse>
    <end-paragraph/>
  </chapter>
</book>
</crossway-bible>
